Thank you.
Hello, everyone.
Alright, so it is 515.
So I guess I'll just get started then.
I'll wait for people to come in but I'll kind of give a quick introduction for them. So, for those of you who don't know me which I'm assuming is everyone.
I, my name is Liam, and I did this class.
Last year, and also took this class in 2018.
So, yeah, it's the new experience for me to give this lecture to a room full of unfamiliar faces because last time I gave it, I knew all of the students because I was 13.
We'll see how this goes.
Um, yeah, I guess I'll just jump right in. So, first to start out, who here has taken a machine learning course at Penn so I would say, sis 525 19 count.
Okay.
Solid amount of hands.
Who's taken a class that has featured machine learning in some capacity. So say like 530 or 521 or courses like that. Okay, few more hands but that still does mean that about half of the class didn't raise their hand for either who's done a project
that involves machine learning in any capacity at all.
Like, either personal otherwise senior design, okay even more hands. Okay, so
a majority of you have at least some tangential experience with machine learning.
So, today's lecture might be a bit review, but I'm hoping to give, you know, I'm hoping to have this lecture have a little bit of something for everyone.
So,
first to start off, I already kind of introduced myself please excuse the incredibly old headshot.
So I'm a second year PhD student in the computer science department here. I also went here for undergrad. So, conv and robo.
Anyone, computer engineering or robotics.
And so my current research focuses on large language models. So if you've heard of GPT three.
That's really what we work with nowadays and it'll be. And then also last summer I did a lot of work in speech processing and translation over at Roblox, working closely with Morgan McGuire who is a good friend of the class.
And yeah, cool.
So, what are we going to cover today. So today I'm going to talk about the sort of basic introduction to what a neural network is what it does, how it works.
I'm going to talk about gradient descent. And then I'm going to give an overview of a lot of different like machine learning jargon and terminology, then go into general improvements that we've made to neural networks architecture, and then applications to tasks that you might find interesting in GPU programming.
I think it's really important for me to start out this lecture and talk about the goals here, because I'm not trying to like teach a whole machine learning course in like one lecture.
What I'm trying to do is to give you enough familiarity with machine learning, so that you're not as intimidated to attempt it for a final project.
So last year we kind of piloted this whole giving a couple of machine learning lectures to this class in the hopes that we would do some final projects and it turns out that we had two really successful teams doing machine learning projects in CUDA in WebGPU.
I don't know if Shazon has mentioned those two projects, but I will definitely be plugging them in this talk, partially because I thought they were really great and also partially because I advised them.
But yeah, so after this lecture, you should be fairly familiar with some of the machine learning jargon.
And I want to give you a basic understanding of how to improve model performance, what things that you can tweak to get better performance on machine learning models.
And then hopefully by the end, you'll have a good idea of how you would apply machine learning to common tasks.
Worth noting, though, that this lecture will be very fast because the background experience of the people in this lecture vary very widely.
And I kind of want to have this lecture be educational for even the people that have taken a machine learning class before.
So if you've really never looked at any machine learning whatsoever, the first half of this lecture might be really fast for you.
Feel free to ask as many questions as you need. Also, I will link some resources or at least send resources to the teams that can link for the people that really want to follow along better.
OK. Cool. So what is a neural network?
So when we start thinking about machine learning, it's important to think about kind of what tasks machine learning is solving, and I think that that better contextualizes it.
If any people have seen the 3Blue1Brown series on machine learning, this first half of the talk steals very heavily from that really good video series.
I highly recommend watching it instead of listening very closely to my retelling of his video series.
I actually told the students the last time I gave this lecture to watch that first before coming to class so I can just review it quickly.
But yeah, so I'm going to basically retread a lot of the things that he talks about in his videos.
In any case, so we want to accomplish the task, given a handwritten digit, classify what number it is.
The way that we're going to represent the input is by a vector of length 784, where each index in the vector corresponds to a pixel value.
So black pixels are coded as 0 and white pixels are coded as 1.
And, you know, up here the image is shown as a matrix, but you can basically take that and extend it to be a giant column vector, and that's what we're going to think of it as.
Okay, so here's a neural network that does this task.
Treating this as a black box, what we're doing is we're taking an image, we're feeding it into the neural network,
and we expect to get out a vector of size k, where k is the number of classes that we have to choose from.
And we would assume that the class, the correct class, in this case 9, is the one that has the highest activation on the output neuron.
So for people who have machine learning experience, what are all these lines and circles? Anyone?
Like in this diagram.
Yeah, exactly. Right, so the circles are the nodes, some people call them neurons, if they want to really, like, belabor the brain metaphor.
And then the connections between the nodes are the weights.
To be more specific, actually really quickly, I really like this visualization.
Pass in an image, propagates the network, the weights connect all of the nodes, they light up different nodes, and then we get the output as the proper class.
Anyway, okay, so what are these connections?
The connections are weights.
What a layer does is it takes a weighted sum of every single input,
and then the output neuron is, like I said, the weighted sum of all of the inputs.
So down here, weight 1 times input 1 plus weight 2 times input 2, so on and so forth.
And each input is connected to every output, and every output is connected to every input, thus the fully connected.
So this is, I'm going to be describing a fully connected layer.
So we do this for every single output neuron.
And so if I had, let's say, k output neurons and n input neurons, how many different weights do I have here?
Correct.
What was that?
k to the n?
Go ahead.
n times k.
Yeah.
Sorry.
Yeah, so n times k total weights.
So there would be n weights for every k output.
We have k outputs.
Perfect.
Cool.
So importantly, if we just did this weighted sum and then had the outputs sum weighted sum over and over and over again,
you can actually just decompose that into a gigantic weighted sum.
So we have to add a nonlinear function for each one of these layers, or else us doing multiple layers doesn't actually make any sense.
This is the function that we're going to be using for now.
I'll talk a bit more about the choice of activation function.
But for now, you can think of this function as taking an input that can vary from negative infinity to positive infinity, and then kind of clamping it to 0 and 1.
So the equation for one neuron is this weighted sum, and then you do this sigmoid function on top of the weighted sum.
And that's all it is.
There's actually an extra term in here that I haven't talked about so far, and this is called the bias term.
What do people know about bias term?
What is it doing here?
I kind of have it already in the slide.
So if you have a bias term, this means that the activation, the neuron, will only activate meaningfully when the sum is above a certain value, if the bias term is negative.
And so this means that we can scale our neuron activations independently of our input parameters.
So, okay, this is an equation for one specific neuron.
We have a weighted sum of all the inputs for one specific neuron, because each W is individual value.
But how would we write an equation for an entire layer at once?
Can we even do that?
How would you use a vector exactly?
Yeah, it's very similar.
So it's a good observation.
So this is very similar to a dot product.
We have the, if you consider the weights as a row vector and activations as a column vector, if you dot product at this, that would be this.
And so you have the same activations.
So these A's would be, let's say, our input, right?
But we have a different set of weights for every single output.
So how do we take one column vector and dot product it with multiple row vectors?
How do you take one column vector, let's say the A's, and dot product them with multiple different sets of weights?
Because we have a different set of weights for every single output neuron.
Yeah, exactly.
So you do matrix multiply.
So we can make this into a matrix equation to give us an equation for an entire layer.
So writing this capital W as a matrix of row vectors that contain weights, the equation for an entire output layer is sigmoid, which is element-wise sigmoid, of weight times x plus b.
So what are the dimensions of all of these?
What is the dimension of W, dimension of x?
Let's say that we have n input neurons and then k output neurons, right?
So x would be a column vector of size what?
N.
And then b, sorry, our W would be a matrix of size what?
N by k.
And then b would be a vector of?
Yes, k.
And then sigmoid does this on that final vector.
So you have a 1 by k vector after doing Wx plus b and you do sigmoid on that.
And then that's the whole layer.
Cool.
All right.
So what parameters of this equation are learned by the network or we expect them to be learned by the network?
Exactly, right.
And so the total number of learned parameters is n times k, which we were talking about.
That's the amount of weights, and then plus another k for the bias terms.
Cool.
What is the function?
Yeah, sure.
Let me go back.
What this function is, it's 1 over 1 plus e to the minus x.
So that's just being applied to every single element in the vector.
And the reason why we're applying it is because we have to have some nonlinear function after each layer.
Because if we didn't, then if you had two layers in a row, so like in linear algebra,
if you apply a matrix, and then you apply another matrix, and you apply another matrix,
all of that can be written as just one matrix.
So we don't get any more modeling power if we continue to just apply linear layers over and over again.
Because what we're essentially doing is applying one linear layer.
And so if we put nonlinearities in between, then you can actually get more power out of it.
Is this sigmoid the activation function?
Correct.
Like, it could also be linear?
Exactly.
Yeah, I'll talk about it later on.
Yeah, absolutely.
Okay.
Any other questions about linear layers?
Especially about this equation.
This equation will be featured in like tons of slides from this point forward.
So, okay, cool.
We have this nice animation.
Okay, so a neural network, zooming back out again at a high level,
is a function that is parameterized by a ton of weights and biases.
So in this case, 13,000 weights and biases for a two-layer network.
And it takes in a ton of different inputs.
So it's a function of 784 variables.
And then you apply all of the parameters, and then you get some output vector
that corresponds to the class that you want.
But how do we learn the weights and biases, right?
I've kind of skipped over the most important part.
Okay, so let's talk about gradient descent.
So imagine hypothetically that we had some function, c of x,
that told us for a specific input to the neural network
how bad the neural network is doing at that input.
We'd like to find the minima of this function,
because then we can make our neural network minimally bad.
If we found the minima, we know the values of the weights and biases
that makes the network minimally bad for a specific input x.
Cool.
One possible such function is mean squared error.
So if we have the output of our neural network,
and we have the true output, so let's say for this image,
the true output would be a fully activated 3D neuron and nothing else.
We take the difference of these two outputs and then square them.
We don't want sign difference, because then you get into the realm
of negative and positive, and that would cancel out.
And so we would want squared difference.
So that's one possible such function.
There are a bunch of different functions we could choose,
but this seems like a reasonable choice,
because it's just how far away are you.
You could, but absolute value turns out to be harder to learn,
because the distance between two vectors,
if you're using squared distance, it's like Euclidean distance,
whereas absolute value, it's like Manhattan distance.
But yeah, no, that's a good point.
And people actually do use that.
It's a root mean squared error, and that's also a common function,
which is square root of...
Any other questions?
This function choice might seem arbitrary,
but I'll talk about it a bit more in the future.
So what would be, again, just to make sure that everyone's on the same page,
what would be the inputs of our function, of the cost function?
The function that tells us how bad our neural network is for a given input.
We have the input, right, x.
But what else?
Yeah, the correct answer, exactly.
Anything else?
What's the function parameterized by?
Yeah, the weights and the biases.
So the total, writing the function out properly would be like
cost function of C, sorry, C of x, y,
which would be the correct answer, let's say,
and then weights and biases.
So this is a really unwieldy function.
It's gigantic, and the number of parameters means that this function
is like 13,000 input variables, basically.
And we're trying to find the minimum value of this function,
which is a very difficult task.
So I've kind of already preempted myself,
but why can't we just sort of set the derivative of this function
equal to zero and solve for the minimum?
It seems like a totally reasonable thing to attempt, right?
You know, we want to find all of the weights and biases
that make the function a minimum,
so we just take the partial with respect to every single one
of the 13,000 weights and biases, set them all to zero,
and then solve for those values.
Well, it turns out that this function is not a linear function,
and so unless you have a nice algorithm to solve 13,000
simultaneous equations, this is generally not feasible.
And even if it was feasible, you don't really want to solve
that equation for a specific input x,
because then your neural network would be very good at classifying one x.
You want to solve it for the set of all x's,
which makes this even harder,
because you want to find some average solution.
So you can see why people don't just actually solve
for the closed form of this.
So what can we do instead of solving for closed form?
So an easier method is if we have some value for our function,
for the weights and biases that we have,
and we take the derivative of that function,
and we step the weights and biases in the direction of that derivative.
So let's say we have some step size parameter eta.
Eventually, if we keep taking steps,
we will converge to some minimum value of this function,
and this is called gradient descent.
Obviously, in this diagram, it's only two dimensions,
so there's no gradient.
It's just the derivative, but obviously,
our function is not two-dimensional.
It's just for ease of visualization.
So I have a couple of questions on this slide.
So why would the step size parameter not be learned by the function?
Why do we have to supply this?
Yes.
Yeah, I mean, so I would say the reason,
the real reason why we can't learn the step size parameter
is because very similar to what you said,
like if we tried to learn the step size parameter,
how would we go about learning with gradient descent?
But the step size parameter is part of gradient descent, right?
You can't learn the parameters of gradient descent with gradient descent, right?
But yeah, and eventually, we're converged to the minimum,
but is that, okay, this is a very obvious answer to this question, right?
This function can have a ton of minima.
There's no guarantee at all that it's convex.
It's definitely not.
And so, yeah, there's no guarantee that there's a global minimum.
This is obviously very important for machine learning.
It means that training the same network with the same data
multiple times with different initializations
means that you're going to get different accuracies.
It's just how it works.
Okay.
So it's a nice visualization.
You can imagine these balls being initialized.
Sorry, hold on.
Starting on the curve would be some point
where you have a certain amount of weights.
And we start taking gradient descent,
and all of these balls sort of step in the direction of the gradient
and roll down to the local minimum.
How much of ML is just like tuning the guess at C?
We like not to think about that.
No, there's, I mean, it's obviously,
you're not supposed to tune your random seeds
or tune your initialization.
You're supposed to develop techniques that,
regardless of the initialization or seed,
on average get you better performance than other people.
But you can definitely cheat it a bit
where if you get a very specifically very good random seed.
Exactly, yeah.
So that's to prevent, especially when you have,
let's say if you're submitting to some leaderboard
for a very specific task,
like they'll hold the test data themselves
to make sure that you can't specifically tune
the initializations and the parameters
so that you get really high accuracy by cheating.
I mean, if you, hypothetically,
you had population size data,
tuning the random seed would give you the optimal results.
It would, but it's really unsatisfying.
And I think the only scenario where you would do that
is if you're in a machine learning class
and you're trying to get extra credit
from a position on a leaderboard.
Other than that, yeah.
But that is true.
Okay.
Any other questions?
Okay, cool.
So moving to the multivariable case,
we've talked about the 2D function.
The derivative for multivariable functions
is called the gradient.
And the gradient is the direction of the steepest increase.
So the negative gradient would be the direction
of the steepest decrease.
And so to update our weights,
we take the weight matrix at time step n plus one
as equal to the weight matrix at time step n
minus our step size parameter
times this upside down delta is the symbol for a gradient.
And then C is our cost function.
And we have our input.
The correct answer why is implicit here for some reason.
But yes, we have input and then the weight matrix.
Note here, I'm actually not writing the bias term explicitly
because technically speaking,
you can consider the bias term
as just another column in the matrix
if you just add another column to your input vector
and give that value zero.
So sometimes I will swap between
considering everything as one big weight matrix
and separating out the weight and the bias terms.
I'll let you guys know when I'm swapping between those.
But yes, this is just to make the equation pretty.
Okay, cool.
And this is another very nice visualization.
So the gradient as a vector is going to have one value
for each weight slash bias in the entire network.
And the value of the gradient is going to tell you
what small changes to that weight will do to the output.
So if we have a value of a gradient that's like 3.2,
that means that small changes to that weight
will have a large effect on the output loss or cost.
But a gradient value of 0.1 means that
small changes to that weight
really won't affect the output much at all.
And so you can imagine that this is going to give you
like basically importance values
for all of your weights for a specific input.
Like if I went to classify the image for three
and I had a really high gradient on one of these,
that means that changing that will really change
how correct I was
for predicting that specific input, image three.
Okay, cool.
So a few conceptual questions.
So I've already asked this input question.
I don't know why I have this again on here.
I forgot, I guess I asked it earlier.
But does the cost function change based on the input x
and should it?
Definitely, right?
So our cost function changes completely
based on the given input image.
But if we're trying to learn a network
that can classify any image,
yeah, we would love it if the cost function
was just a general cost function
that applied to the set of all possible images,
like the distribution of all possible handwritten digits.
So we did not have to deal with any specific image.
Obviously, that's infeasible to actually calculate,
but we'll get into ways that you can approximate
values of that cost function
and then optimize that one instead of any one particular one.
Another thing, when we calculate the gradient
with respect to the weights and biases,
are we actually calculating the full gradient
of this function or not?
I see people shaking their heads.
What would the full gradient of the function look like?
Yeah.
So if I had a function that depended on three variables,
x, y, z, the gradient would involve the partial
with respect to each of those three variables.
So that would be the full gradient of the function.
But this function depends on the variables
that we throw in, so the weights, the input.
But when we're calculating the gradient for gradient descent,
what are we not calculating?
We calculate the partial with respect to all of the weights
and all of the biases,
but we're not calculating partial with respect to what?
Yeah.
So why would it be nonsensical to calculate the gradient
with respect to the input points and step in that direction?
Anyone else?
Yeah, exactly. You can't change the input image.
It'd be nice if our image was not the way it is, but it is.
The gradient with respect to the image would tell you
how you could change the image such that your network
did better at it.
That's not the direction we want to go.
We want to change our network such that it's better
at the image.
Cool.
I skipped the last question because I think we talked about it a bit.
All right, so let's actually go ahead and calculate the gradient.
Let's manually do it.
As you can see, we have our gradient upwards delta c,
and then each of the values in the gradient
is the partial of c, which is the cost function,
with respect to a parameter.
So this is d weight 1 would be the weight of the first layer,
and then db1 would be the bias of the first layer,
and so on and so forth for all of the layers.
People call this backpropagation because you get some sort of value
at the end of your neural network, which is the cost,
and then you calculate the derivatives by going backwards
from the cost.
It's really just calculus. It's just the derivative chain rule.
I'm going to go through it for two layers.
Bear with me for this.
Okay, so here are the three equations that are involved
in going through the very last layer of a network.
This one, which is the weight times a,
aka the activation of the previous layer, note l minus 1,
and then the bias term.
So we have weights times activation plus bias.
The derivative of this with respect to the weights
is just the activation of the previous layer.
Everybody's okay with that? Yeah.
This term is activations equals the output of this equation
put into the sigmoid function.
So the actual activation of your neuron is not just the output
of weights times activation plus bias, but it's actually
weight activation plus bias put into sigmoid,
and the derivative of this is just the derivative of sigmoid,
which it turns out is very easy to do.
And then finally, we had the mean squared error function.
So our cost is the activation minus the true value y squared,
and the derivative of this is just 2 times a minus y.
And so computing the derivative with respect to the weights
of a specific layer is you just multiply.
So you have the activation times derivative of sigmoid
times 2 activation minus y.
Done. Easy.
And you can do this over and over and over again
and just keep going backwards.
So go ahead.
Sure, sure. Go for it.
Why is the derivative of ZL just the activation?
Why is the derivative with respect to ZL just the activations?
Sorry, can you say that again?
Basically, could you just explain a bit further why the first line?
Oh, this first line. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, sure.
So what we're doing is we're taking derivative with respect
to this weight, right?
And so since we have activation times weight,
the derivative of like, you know, if it makes it easier,
we can think of weight as just like x.
And if you have a times x, the derivative of a times x is a.
Everyone clear?
On Wednesday, I'm going to do this with matrices and vectors.
So just get ready.
This is with one input.
So I'm leaving all the other stuff out.
Okay.
Cool.
And so like I was saying earlier,
you can just keep going backwards with this.
And so the chain rule, you can just do over and over again.
So the derivative with respect to the weights on the L minus one layer
is just, you know, all of these terms cancel out, right?
We have derivative with respect to activations,
which is then inputs,
which is then activations of the previous layer,
which is then inputs to the previous layer,
which then are determined by the weights.
However, this is actually wrong.
So this equation is not correct at all.
Can anyone tell me why this equation is actually wrong?
It's kind of subtle though.
There's like a slight complication with this.
Okay.
So not quite, but.
We don't need to take into consideration the weight of the first layer
because we basically will get there by the time we calculate the derivative
with respect to that layer, right?
Like basically you can consider the inputs to the L minus one,
L minus one layer as constant,
and then just sort of use this to calculate how much weight
you're going to get by the time you calculate the derivative with respect to
that layer, right?
As constant,
and then just sort of use this to calculate how much changes to that affect
the output and changes to that do not depend on the previous layers.
So no, it's not that either.
So the, the,
the subtlety here is that since every single neuron is connected to every
single output neuron,
that means that in order to calculate how one neuron affects the neurons
further down in the network,
you actually have to take the derivative with respect to all of the different
neurons in the next layer,
and then sum them all up to get the value for how one neuron affects the next
layers, right?
So just to quickly chuck this up,
the actual derivative is the sum across all of the different activations.
So an easier way rather than looking at this equation,
because this is very hard to parse,
easier way to think about it is for each weight that contributes some amount to
a given neuron.
So we have to take the partial with respect to each of the weights.
And for every neuron, there are K output weights.
And so you do have to sum up across all of the different output neurons,
but this is the only complication.
And then you can just keep doing this over and over and over again and back
propagating.
Cool.
All right.
So this is the most densely difficult thing to think about in this lecture.
The rest is going to be kind of smooth sailing,
but I think it's important to just sort of demystify that this is like basic
calculus.
And we can do this in more detail on Wednesday and slash implementing it in
more detail and watch how it's implemented in CUDA,
because as I'm sure you guys can tell, this is embarrassingly parallel.
We can compute all of these in parallel, sum them all up and yeah.
Cool.
All right.
So traditional gradient descent takes one step for every pass through the
entirety of the training data.
The reason for that is, again,
we don't want to optimize the function for one specific input.
We want to optimize the function for a given set of training data.
So what we do is we get the loss function or we get the, sorry,
we get the gradient for every single item in our training data set.
And then we average all of those gradients together.
And then we take a step in the direction of that average gradient.
And in some senses,
that's like taking a step in the direction of the real cost function,
not a cost function for any one specific image.
Does that make sense?
There's a really important distinction.
Yeah, absolutely, Ken.
And I will talk about that when I get to that sort of improvements to basic
neural networks, but that's called an annealing schedule.
And yeah, like almost everyone does that.
Does everyone understand the fact that gradient descent tends to take,
or the traditional gradient descent takes one step for every pass to the
entire training data.
We don't want to take a step for a specific input.
We want to take a step over the whole training data.
The problem is that this is actually super duper slow because we have to pass
through the entirety of our training data to take one optimization step.
So to approximate that, we actually do take one step per input example.
And we just hope that like in expectation,
that's going to end up being the same as taking one step for every average
gradient.
So here, this very low res diagram,
the purple is what happens when you take one step per input image.
And then the blue is what happens when you take one step per the entirety of
the training data.
And this sort of like the contour line plot is some imagining of like some
perfect cost function that doesn't depend on input.
So the nickname for this gradient descent is called stochastic gradient
descent.
There's nothing stochastic about this.
It just looks very random when you take a step per every individual input
image.
But yeah, it's a really, really bad thing.
With GPUs though, we can do like mini batch stochastic gradient descent,
where we basically just take a step for 32 images in parallel.
So we compute the gradient for 32 different images in parallel,
and then we can average them and take a step in that direction.
And so that's much, much, much better.
But still, this is how neural networks are actually trained.
We take mini batch stochastic gradient descent.
Okay.
Any questions?
Sweet.
Okay.
A lot of text.
I'll just read it.
Neural network is linear layers, WX plus B.
The cost or loss function tells us how bad our network is doing,
given a specific X, W, and B.
The weights and biases of a network are learned from our data by minimizing
through gradient descent.
Gradient descent is a process by which we randomly initialize weights and
biases,
and then iteratively update them by taking a fixed size step in the
direction of the negative gradient.
And then we calculate the gradient through back propagation,
which is just applying the chain rule.
And then we use mini batch stochastic gradient descent.
Cool.
All right.
So let's get to some jargon.
So activation function, I've mentioned this already,
but this is the nonlinear function that we apply in between layers.
This can be any nonlinear function.
The cost function or the loss function is what I was saying.
It's the function that tells us how bad our neural network is doing.
This also can be any function.
Some function choices make more sense than others.
The input representation is how we represent our input as a vector.
So in the case of an image,
we have the pixels corresponding to black or white,
but in more complicated things like language,
that's not always obvious how you represent your input as a vector,
but you need to in order to pass it into a neural network.
The parameters are the trainable numbers in a neural network,
aka the weights and biases.
And the architecture is how all of them are connected.
Finally,
optimization method is what variant of gradient descent do you use?
So do you use normal gradient descent, stochastic gradient descent?
Do you use with an annealing schedule?
Do you use an adaptive learning rate? All this stuff.
The hyper parameters are the parameters that are not learned.
And the initialization is what you start with,
the starting weight and bias.
This is just jargon so that if I say one of these words later on,
people don't get confused.
All right.
Finally,
traditionally when we use machine learning,
we like to split up our data into three different sets.
So the training set is the images that we actually do gradient descent on.
The development set is the set of data that we use to tune our hyper parameter.
So in the case of learning rate,
which learning rate gives us the best accuracy,
we can look at the accuracy on the development set of data.
And that's how we can decide what the best learning rate is.
And this usually involves just manually retraining the entire network over and
over and over and over again with different values of the hyper parameters.
Because again,
there's no way to learn a parameter that's involved in gradient descent.
And then finally we have the test data.
And it's important to split up development and test data because you don't want to
actually over optimize to a specific set of test data because you're kind of
cheating. Similar to the question from earlier.
Like if you tune your initialization variables and you're learning rate to a
specific set of data,
you're not really going to be able to generalize to new sets of data.
Or I should say the accuracy on that set of data isn't representative of the
accuracy on other sets of data. And then finally overfitting,
which is if you fully train a neural network to full convergence,
like you just do gradient descent over and over and over again until there's
never any more updates. They're all zero.
The network is powerful enough that it will just memorize the training data and
it loses the ability to generalize.
This is a very common phenomenon when you have a model that has way more
parameters than your function really necessitates and neural networks tend to.
The way to fix this is just stop early.
Stop when you have good accuracy on your validation set.
All of the things that I've talked about is the state of machine learning in
the 1990s.
We can make a lot of improvements to these.
Let's take neural networks into the 21st century.
The task that I've been talking about so far,
the recognizing handwritten digits is a famous task in machine learning and
the data set of handwritten digits is called MNIST.
Don't ask what the acronym stands for, I forget.
And it was released in 1998 and a three layer neural network with all of the
things that we just talked about. So stochastic gradient descent,
learning rate, all this stuff, got about 97% accuracy.
And I think someone can correct me if I'm wrong,
but this is one of the first occasions where a neural network got really,
really good accuracy and it was shown that it would be practical to actually
use. Nowadays,
the accuracy of the best networks on MNIST are so
good that it's almost meaningless to compare between each other.
Almost every network is 99.7%.
But what's the difference? What got us that last 3%?
99.7% is basically perfect,
given that some of the images in MNIST kind of look like this.
I don't know if you could consider that having a label of eight or that
having a label of four. I think 99.7% is good enough.
So what changed?
So I would say the biggest difference between older neural networks and
newer neural networks is depth.
So when people say deep learning,
all they're doing is doing machine learning, but with more layers.
So there's nothing fundamentally different about deep learning versus
machine learning. It's just machine learning, but bigger.
This is very, very expensive.
Just to remind us, the amount of learnable parameters in a given layer is
n times k. And so you keep adding layers on,
that's another factor of n times k. And for large n and large k,
obviously n times k is huge. But this is made possible by GPUs.
This is totally infeasible to train on the CPU,
but with the advent of GPUs and with people getting better at
parallelizing and having a lot more ability to do things in parallel,
we've been able to train deeper and deeper networks and therefore the
accuracy goes up. And importantly,
while deep learning theory is still incredibly young,
we know that depth improves performance in almost every scenario,
and we don't really know why.
There are theories on why.
This one is an image from a 2019 paper that describes the double descent
phenomenon, where after a certain amount of parameters,
if you add more, instead of overfitting,
those parameters seem to generalize on top of other parameters that have
overfit. Very hand wavy.
Someone that is more involved with actual theory of scale and machine
learning can talk better about this.
But the consensus is that depth works very well, but it is expensive.
We currently do not know the limits of how well depth works.
Like if every single task is just improvable by adding more layers.
Okay. The next improvement, besides just scaling,
is in the loss function.
So earlier we were talking about mean squared error as a loss function.
Changing the loss function, obviously,
can drastically alter what is learned because it is literally what we back
propagate.
The value of the loss function determines every single update we make to all
of the weights.
So instead of using mean squared error or alternative root mean squared
error, is there a better loss function for classification in particular?
So reminder that in the case of MNIST,
our output is a vector of size K, where K is the number of classes.
Man.
It is weird. The last time I gave this lecture, it also thunderstormed like
this in the middle of the lecture.
It is a sign.
So each class in the output vector gets a score based on the output of the
final layer.
However, let's take a hypothetical.
Let's say that our neural network predicted zero for every class and then
for three predicted like 10.
But the true answer is zero for every class, but at three, a value of one.
What would our loss be for that example?
Sure, sure.
So let's say our neural network output a vector that instead of containing
like in this example, we have like 0.43, 0.28, whatnot.
Let's say that it was very confident that the image was three, so much so
that it gave three, the index corresponding to class three, a weight of
five, and every other class, a weight of zero.
However, the true answer gave the weight for class three one and
everything else zero.
What would mean squared error give us as a loss?
Yeah, it would give you a really big value because we predicted five
instead of one.
This seems wrong.
If the network is 100% confident and gave all of its weight to the right
class, that should be zero loss.
It got it perfectly correct.
So how do we incorporate this intuition into our loss function?
What we can do, exactly.
Normalize it, but then also normalize it in log space.
Exactly.
So if we put the output scores through this softmax function, which is
normalizing it, but in log space, then we can turn any output into a
probability distribution.
So the highest value gets given the highest probability, and it scales
logarithmically with respect to how large your output is with respect to
all of the other things in the vector.
Absolutely.
Yep.
Cool.
So in our example from earlier, if we had five to the correct class, after
we put it through softmax, that should be one, and therefore we would get
zero mean squared error after putting it through softmax.
Okay.
However, now we're going to do something a little bit more complicated.
We're going to do something a little bit more complicated.
However, now we're comparing two probability distributions with each
other.
So our true distribution is zero and one in the correct class, and the
actual distribution that we get from our network is the softmax
distribution.
When we're comparing two distributions, does it make sense to use mean
squared error?
Put a different way.
Is a change in probability of 89% to 99% the same as a change in
probability of 59% to 69%, or should it be?
No, right?
Like, it should be much more important to go from 89% to 99%, or much more
difficult, I shouldn't say.
You should get a much higher loss if you guess 89% for a 99% than if you
guess 59% for a 69%.
So is there a mathematical concept that compares how different two
probability distributions are?
.