and stuff we can talk about.
This meeting is being recorded.
Hey.
So if I do an Intel talk or an NVIDIA talk,
if I was going to do that, now I haven't done an NVIDIA talk,
there's usually some kind of legal disclaimer in there.
We don't always have to give it.
Sometimes we give it in the back.
This is a personal legal disclaimer.
This talk represents knowledge and the sole opinions of me.
Don't represent NVIDIA or Intel Corporation in the slides
other than the stuff I've done that's public,
all that kind of stuff.
So sorry about the legal disclaimer.
This, as soon as you guys get jobs
and in any one of these companies,
this legality thing actually comes to play.
So it is a little bit of a career thing to be aware of.
Anyway, like I said, I just left Intel
the beginning of this month.
I had kind of a broad set of responsibilities,
effectively the general manager of anything
to do with professional visualization, ray tracing,
particularly on the software side.
But the team at the time that I had actually
helped and were significant in the design,
in the whole new Intel GPU line coming out, ARC.
And let's see, which ones am I allowed to say?
ARC.
And they announced one called Flex.
And there's another one to be announced.
But its code name is Ponte Vecchio, and that is public.
And that's going as an HPC device that's sort of,
if you know what an A100 is from NVIDIA,
it's the thing for that.
All those devices have ray tracing hardware.
And myself and my team together helped design the ray tracing
hardware.
And then that's being utilized both for real-time gaming ray
tracing, but also for professional rendering,
like Embree and OpenImageDenoise.
And I was the leader for rendering toolkit,
which had all those products.
Enough about Intel, because I'm not there anymore.
And then now, as Shazan said, I've just started.
And I'm bootstrapping.
And we can talk about what's even, you guys can ask me,
what's it like to switch companies?
Because it's a relatively big deal.
And yeah, so I've started that.
HPC is high-performance computing,
if you haven't heard that.
Supercomputing, high-performance computing.
And that's where the climate change stuff.
We'll talk a little bit more about that.
Enough of the legal upfront stuff.
I kind of have a legacy.
So you see the black and white pictures?
They're really black and white pictures.
These are my parents.
This is my father.
They're passed away.
But my father was one of the pioneers
across the country in what we call cable TV.
Now you call it Verizon Fios.
It's fiber optic, all that stuff.
But my dad was one of the world's leading engineers
in delivering pixels to your home.
So there's kind of a DNA.
I'm the closest one in the family.
I'm the youngest one in the family.
And I'm the one who kind of ended up
pursuing a digital career where visual computing was there.
My dad graduated from Moore School of Engineering in 1949.
So don't please add any of that up and figure it out.
I'm the youngest, so I was born when he was 80.
So anyway, my daughter, class of 06, Sarah Jeffers.
I did not go here.
I went to LaSalle University.
So I'm still a Philadelphian.
My son-in-law, who's married to my daughter, in 05.
And my daughter-in-law, who's married to my son,
graduated from Penn in 10.
And then my mother, during the war,
actually was one of the early females who came to Penn.
She ended up only staying for a two-year stint
before the world got crazy enough
that she didn't complete her degree, but my dad did.
So pixels and pen go together.
I'm kind of a legacy, because I'm a legacy sandwich.
My daughter went here, and my father went there.
But anyway, love University of Pennsylvania.
I'm very aware of the campus, even though I'm late today.
I also am a huge Philadelphia Phillies and Eagles
and everything fan, so I run it.
OK, more about some of the stuff
that I have done and have been involved in.
This is a little bit of a one-page snapshot
of bits and pieces of my career, some of the interesting things.
If you look up in the middle, where it says,
do I have a little pointer?
Yes, the horizontal button.
Oh, wait.
That should be the one with the window.
That guy, that guy.
OK.
So as Shazan said, I live in the Philadelphia area.
I grew up in Flowertown.
If anybody heard of Chestnut Hill, it is the next town over.
It's the closest you can be without being in Philadelphia.
So I went to Springfield High School there.
Grew up in Flowertown.
I mentioned my parents.
They lived in Flowertown my whole life,
all my brothers and sisters' whole life.
They were there for many, many years.
I now live in Yardley, Pennsylvania,
beautiful river town.
Feel free to visit it if you like Bucks County.
That's where it is.
But this is actually not my house,
but it's what's called Lake Afton, which
is really a pond in my house.
So anyway, Philadelphia, born, bred, continue.
Actually, two of my children and their families
also live in Yardley, so we're very close there.
Some cool stuff.
Why did I put up a football game?
Oh, wait.
It's not even the Eagles.
Is it the Eagles?
No, it's not the Eagles.
I worked on the technology behind this line here,
the first down line.
So any football fans who are watching the first down line
or whatever, I actually have a patent
on key parts of that technology.
Was really fun and great to work on.
Also, if you watch the Phillies game tonight
and look behind to the left of the batter,
you occasionally see they do a different thing.
And there's a green screen there.
But when the batter comes up, there's
an advertisement or something there.
Exact same technology.
Back in the day, I sat in a little truck
outside the Phillies game and ran the system
that did all that stuff.
So very interesting technology.
A lot of people, particularly American sports fans,
where it's mostly used, it's also
used sometimes in Olympic swimming
when they put the flags on the pit.
All this virtual technology derives.
And the patent, it says my name on it.
Everything I've done has been in a group setting.
I'm not some magic person or brilliant or whatever.
It's all about collaboration.
And that's something to keep in mind
as you continue your work.
And I know Shazam was talking to me about two and three person
projects.
That's actually a perfect thing to think about.
Let's see.
Shortly after the first down line,
we come down here, these funky little cameras.
Webcams are gone, pretty much.
They're built into your machines.
Obviously, we're using a camera up there.
But before webcams are in the machines,
there was various clever designs.
And the key thing that I worked on, actually,
a little less that camera.
This was to get cool looking cameras in people's hands.
This thing called Click Video Messenger.
It's Zoom 15, 18 years ago.
That's what it was.
Another thing to consider as you're in your careers
is, is the market ready for your technology?
You might be able to do it, but is the market ready?
And often, you don't know.
Was the market ready for an iPhone?
Apparently, it was, because they took off pretty quick.
But it really wasn't until the COVID pandemic and some stuff
before, like the FaceTime and everything,
where personal video conferencing.
And then it became so ubiquitous that personal video
conferencing became business video conferencing,
all with the use of tools and the internet and everything.
We had lots of challenges then, like internet bandwidth
and stuff that we saw.
Those challenges don't really exist anymore
in the world of gigabit capability.
So anyway, I did work on that, so pixels in the video realm.
And then, oh, whoops.
And as Shazan said, there's two of the four books
that I wrote jointly with James Reinders.
I actually have a text message from James.
He wanted to talk to me today.
But I didn't get a chance.
Back in the day, he mentioned an early stint at Intel,
Intel DVI technology.
That stands for Digital Video Interactive, not
the old display technology.
But that was in and around digital video,
kind of a precursor here.
I said this was the Xeon Phi time frame.
In between all that, I worked at a company in Newtown
called Seng Labs.
And they were actually pretty much the first, quote,
GPU country, company in the world, in the United States.
They glommed on.
And I joined them a significant way.
I didn't start it up or anything.
I joined them from Intel and actually worked
on DirectX 1.0, in fact, a little
hint is for cool thing that you stumble on in your career.
I was the first person ever to get a DirectX graphics driver
actually running with a graphics channel in prototype form.
So that was a cool thing.
And then down here, after the Xeon Phi time, I took over.
And this was mostly about high performance
computing and compute.
This was bringing those things together,
compute with ray tracing, video, things like that.
And one, I forgot to mention, a lot of people
aren't really aware that I was on a team that
won a technical Emmy award for downline technology.
That was a general award of multiple companies
and multiple people.
And then my team, with my support,
got for Embree, which hopefully you've heard of,
if you're into ray tracing at all,
got a 2020 Technical Achievement Award from the Academy
of Motion Pictures.
And this all stems from Intel 1API rendering toolkit,
which until October was something that I led
and was responsible for.
OK.
Just to glom on that, what happens when you navigate
your career and you accidentally,
or as a little kid would say, by purpose or on purpose,
get to do some cool things?
So DreamWorks has used Embree in their renderer Moonray.
So all the How to Train Your Dragon's movie,
any DreamWorks movie, television show that uses ray tracing
uses the technology that my team did.
And we built it hand-in-hand with DreamWorks.
And very cool, they just announced at SIGGRAPH
that they're open sourcing the whole package, Moonray.
So they'll be kind of a really, I'm not saying Blender
is not a real production, but Blender
is kind of used somewhere between hobbyist
and professional.
There's been movies like Next Gen done with Blender.
I'm not saying anything's bad.
But Moonray has literally put out Blockbuster.
Blockbuster movie set will be going open source soon.
Visual effects on top of it, the Marvel movies,
things like that.
The other cool thing that I like about renderers,
because I also like this about high-performance computing,
is they like naming their renderers.
So Moonray was the name for DreamWorks renderer.
Freak is the name for Framestore's renderer.
You may not have heard much about Framestore,
but they're one of the top special effects companies.
And obviously, they've done a lot in the Spider-Man, Marvel
movies.
Other cool movies using the technology,
The Lens from Animal Logic has been possibly
the longest Embree customer there is.
They took something called Embree 1.3,
and integrated it into Glimpse and all the Lego movies
and stuff like that.
V-Ray is another renderer rendering bolt-on.
You can bolt it on to RenderMan.
You can bolt it on to Arnold.
Utilize it in various ways.
And these are just some of the movies.
Actually, I pulled an old slide to make sure
that I was legally doing something new.
So these are 2017 and 2018 designed movies,
as well as this well-known Nintendo
that was completely crafted from V-Ray.
Again, partners.
We're enabling partners, giving them technology,
and really cool technology to get them performance
and capability that basically they
don't have to design themselves.
And the other thing, and Jason mentioned it,
is open source.
Everything that I've worked on most recently
has been open source.
We'll see how that goes.
If I can interrupt you, do you have a favorite movie,
a favorite incident you remember,
anything where you were like, oh, I go in,
or your team goes in and changes the game for the studios?
That is a fantastic question, and the answer is I don't know.
Why is my answer I don't know?
Does anyone know why my answer is I don't know?
Because the intellectual property of the movie
is the 3D models.
So they don't give them to us.
They would send us a problem outside.
We knew it was a movie.
One of the teams that we worked mostly with us,
like we knew they were working on a movie.
We knew they had to finish it in three weeks.
And they would go, I ran into problem X,
or I'd like Embry to extend this so we don't
have to do it or whatever.
And that is Illumination.
So Sing, Sing 2, Secret Life of Pets, The Minions,
all that stuff.
We probably got an email connection with them weekly.
And they're working on two or three movies.
The Grinch, all that kind.
The Grinch was the first movie that they really
fully integrated that one.
But the answer is we never know until after the movie's out.
So we don't have that cool factor when we're doing it.
Yes?
So are you allowed to say it was a Mario movie?
No.
The answer is, one, I'm not allowed.
And two, I don't know anything about it.
It's the same thing.
We know they're using it.
So the only thing I would have been
able to say, which I can't say because of Intel
confidentiality, which I'm still responsible for,
is I could say, hey, they were trying
to do this kind of motion blur with this element
or whatever, or they were, hair and fur is a huge,
continues to be a huge compute problem.
But it is the thing that really adds
that natural, realistic feel.
They really want the hair to flow,
like hair and everything else.
And then motion blur and hair and all these other things
come into play.
But the bottom line is, no, I can't tell you
about the Mario movie.
I can't tell you almost about any movie,
not because of NDA, although that's part of it,
is they don't tell us.
They don't tell us what movie it is.
There is one movie that I'll bring it up in a,
actually, I'll bring it up in a second
that I believe I can mention because they said it out loud
at SIGGRAPH.
But it's kind of a cool movie from Pixar
that's going to come out.
And interestingly, Pixar is the most constrained organization
on the planet, which you can understand that.
They have really, really cool technology.
Actually, here it is.
So this is not a Pixar movie, but this is RenderMan.
And this is RenderMan.
This is kind of the last technology thing
I and my team at Intel were deeply involved in
was integrating what's called the volume kernel library.
And in graphics, in film graphics in general,
what's called volume rendering is growing leaps and bounds,
a really important thing.
Does everyone know what volume rendering is?
Do you have a sense of what it is?
And if people don't like that.
I think most of you have done at least a volumetric render,
right?
Some form like Perlin noise, those kind of things?
Yeah.
Probably on a much smaller scale.
Of course, small scale.
But basically, your 3D environment
is truly in a 3D box.
It's not described as a 3D location and then an object.
It's actually typically amorphous,
like fire, smoke, things that don't make sense
to boil down into triangles.
Actually, the pixels and their color and their transparency
are kind of explained in a true 3D space.
And that's the volume.
And then you shoot rays through it.
And there you may do things like multi-hit.
Hit one, hit one, hit one, where normally you
do single hit and bounce on geometry.
So Embree is a geometric tool kit or tool.
Open volume kernel library is the Embree for volumes.
And the reason I brought up Pixar
is Pixar is working on a movie called Elementals.
And the characters are all volumetric.
Fire is one of the characters.
So that's the reason I know about it
and why I can mention it, because volume rendering is
going to be a huge part of the rendering of that movie.
I'm going to now switch gears a little.
Movies are cool.
It's been great.
You asked me a bunch of exciting, exciting photos I did.
Oh, OK.
We'll cut that.
And let's show them.
Oh, I see.
I see.
This guy.
What happened?
Do this.
Shouldn't be able to charge that whole thing.
Because I think it's good.
OK.
OK, we're back.
Switch gears a little bit, because I
think this is a GPU programming course.
It's not necessarily a full-blown graphics course.
Obviously, visual computing is involved.
But one, the area I'm going into,
but an area that has really been exciting for me
to get involved in is supercomputing,
scientific visualization, scientific computing
to get to the visualization.
And I have had the benefit of doing things like working
and meeting Stephen Hawking.
And now he has passed away a few years ago.
Actually, was invited and attended
his memorial ceremony.
And I continue to work with that team.
So I'm going to just see if I can make this move.
A neutron star is created by a massive star collapsing
in on itself.
It is estimated to be sort of the size of our sun,
compressed down to just the size of a city, like Rome.
The spiraling dance of these two massive objects
dramatically stirred up space-time
and simulated a very specific pattern of gravitational waves
that the LICO detectors picked up.
So that's a brief segment.
That last little part where the split screen was here,
this you saw Intel Osprey under there.
That was actually a simulation.
Everything else was like dialed up.
The first part and everything was done by an artist,
just doing it.
But that was mathematically correct.
And the thing on the right of two neutron or dark matter
stars hitting each other.
And they know that that happens because they detected it
on the LIGO detector, which in 2015, 2016
was a Nobel Prize winner.
And then the Hawking team and scientists around the world,
it's a two-sided thing.
They attempt to simulate the cosmological and Einstein
gravitational capability, visualize it,
make sure that's used in three different ways,
the visualization.
One is to just, is my code working?
Is it doing something interesting?
So debugging.
And then they use it to detect the science
and interesting artifacts.
Once they validate that it seems to work,
then they're looking at the gravitational waves.
And then they can communicate to the LIGO people
and say, if it works the way we think,
you change your detector to do this.
So it's pretty cool.
Other, again, we've worked with hundreds,
but these are the pretty cool.
This is a thing we've done with NASA Ames.
This is computational fluid dynamics,
a code they call LAVA, is generating this.
They're doing particle volume rendering here.
And NASA does more than just shoot things into space.
They analyze aircraft, all sorts of things like that.
That's what's going on here.
They're showing how a landing gear impacts
and the data flows around it.
And again, there's compute code.
Eventually, there is code.
But cool stuff you get to work on
if you work in high-performance computing.
And it's not necessarily all about science or cosmology
or space.
This is Bentley.
Now, I don't think any of us are going to go out and buy one,
but it represents a high-end car brand.
And the concept here is to think about Bentley
is it's all about customer service for them.
It's also, they have almost no dealerships.
They have one dealership in London.
Now, you can think, well, if you can afford one,
you'll just fly there and do it.
That's not what people do.
They order Bentleys online.
That's what they do.
So they want to, we're working with us
to provide the utmost in photo-real experiences.
So this is a tool that we created with Bentley.
And as you can see, you can pop cars in and out.
You see, actually, some of the Monte Carlo.
The denoisers wasn't on.
In this case, this is convergence.
It's not with Open Image Denoise.
We have a later version that has the denoiser in there.
But it's not great on a projected screen.
It's a little better on the monitor here.
But you see how the realism of ray tracing
can come into play.
By the way, just so you know, no GPU was harmed in this.
This is all CPU.
This is all CPU-based rendering.
So be aware that CPUs are still pretty good at stuff
and usable.
And from an Intel perspective, which is public,
they're looking at platform computing.
But so is NVIDIA.
NVIDIA's coming out with CPUs.
Anyway, this just gives you a sense of the type of things
we could do.
This is actually three to four years old now.
Again, I reached back in the archives.
So I didn't have stuff.
We've done more with Bentley and everything.
And we're mapping all this stuff for who
were Intel with us to use our GPUs that were coming out.
Jim, I think Shobham, one of my PAs, has a question.
Yes.
Oh, I like your shirt.
I didn't see that.
This is a thin GPU, right?
Did you buy one of these thin GPUs?
This one, yeah.
This one was done, this setup was
done with eight nodes of dual socket.
Again, though, of an age of about four years.
And I'll talk about that a little bit.
So that's the cool stuff.
Let's see if I can move on.
There we go.
Guess what?
The rest of the presentation looked like this.
So I gave you all the cool stuff up front.
And now we're just talking about the GPUs.
And now we're just going to talk, OK?
And talk a little bit about, what's
it really like to try to craft that stuff?
What do you have to, what should you be aware of?
What should you know?
What considerations are there when writing and deploying
code?
Because everything I showed you pretty much was a product,
was deployable.
So the first thing is, I wasn't here necessarily
to impress you how great I am.
I'm not that great.
I had a combination of opportunities
and grabbed those opportunities when
I could to work with some of the top people in the world.
And some of it was grabbing.
And some of it was them asking and just getting yourself
in a position to do that.
So maybe you're somewhat impressed.
I'm really, really cool.
That's what everyone tells me.
But what does it have to do with this?
And the answer is, none of it would
work without real, concentrated, deep software engineering
capability.
So I've coined this little three-word thing
that I try to keep in mind and try
to keep the teams that I work with in mind
and my partners in mind.
Quality, fidelity, and performance.
None of those products, if we didn't have all three
of those, I wouldn't be here today.
I wouldn't be able to talk to you
about Hawking or DreamWorks or any of that cool stuff
because that's the key thing to get things in people's hands,
to take your ideas, your knowledge, your coding.
You need to keep this in mind as you enter the workforce.
There's a continuum, of course.
My career, I would say I've been focused on products.
I've been focused on things that people
will touch in some form or fashion.
Millions of moviegoers, millions of television folks.
Now, it's also touching the thousands
of people running the TV show and everything as well.
But I have seen my own code go south watching TV.
Seen the first airline fly off the screen.
Stuff like that.
You don't want that to happen.
You usually, I'll mention something
in a second about the TV thing, which
was one of the best pieces of advice I got.
And made me feel better, I'll tell you in a second.
But quality, fidelity, performance.
If you take anything away from this talk today,
keep that in mind as you do your work.
It's a little less rigorous here, I'm not sure.
You're probably not going to fail if you have a bug, right?
But that mindset can really make a huge difference
in how you're perceived as an individual,
how your team is perceived, and the usage in the marketplace.
So what I call product software engineering practices
are critical.
You can go by the books.
I'm sure you've seen the books in software engineering
and been taught things.
The key for me is to pick the things that
map to the job at hand.
There's not just one way to do agile.
There's not just one way to do software engineering.
You apply it to the circumstances that you're in.
That's something that you learn as you go.
It's perfectly good to fall back on do this, do this, do this,
do this checklist, all that stuff.
That's perfectly fine, but we'll
come across something that we'll get at in a second.
But if you have proprietary license software,
there's a thought, or has been a traditional thought,
oh my god, that has to be by far the best quality,
because people are paying for it and everything.
And that's true, OK?
But open source software is no free lunch.
To me, it actually is a slightly higher bar, potentially,
than proprietary software.
With proprietary software, you get the opportunity
to do some crazy workaround to get it out.
You can hide your dirty laundry.
Open source is open, right?
So the practices fit both things.
There's no free lunch.
Open source, which many of you will be involved in,
because it's so prevalent now and growing,
you really need to consider that.
Like I say, your personal ability and the company
reputation is fully exposed.
A line of code that has a security problem that's
completely obvious, all that stuff is there.
I don't mention security in this talk,
and I probably should have, because the security practices
around both proprietary and open source software
are a important and critical factor.
So you will immediately, in any company,
you go in, particularly a large, publicly traded
company, be prepared for two weeks of security training.
Now, I don't want to discourage you
from doing pet projects and this cool stuff and everything.
Just make sure you're crystal clear that it's a toy,
or I didn't do everything you're supposed to do, whatever.
Just be open about what you're doing
if you want to get feedback.
But it's better to follow some form of practices
than just throw it against the wall,
would be my recommendation.
Because maybe you really have a brilliant idea.
It's just like, you go, ah, it's a pain in the butt for me.
Every time I do this, I have to build that, build that,
build that.
I created a tool to do it.
You go, well, maybe other people could use it.
Oh, no, if that thing goes viral,
either you've got to pull it, which people don't like,
or you're committed to supporting it.
So just be aware that code quality and usages,
think about the software engineering practices
as you go do it.
Again, not trying to block you from anything.
But if you're in a company and you're developing open source,
that's aligned with a product, you will have higher bars.
And I will tell you that Intel, I haven't found out
what NVIDIA does, but I can tell because of all the training
I've gotten already in two days, the open source
had three or four more bars to get through, committees
and reviews and all this stuff.
And did you do this?
Did you do that?
Is there a security review?
So just be aware of that.
And if and only if you want to pick one of the above,
you basically don't have a usable thing unless it has quality.
It's pretty obvious.
However, I really put them together
as three equal partners in developing software.
I'll talk about each one.
Jim, if I can interrupt you first
to pick on the open source software part.
You've really seen the industry grow.
You were there when Linux came about.
You've seen Microsoft in its we hate Linux kind of fashion.
And now they've very much adopted Linux
and adopted open source.
Yes.
So maybe if you can just share your thoughts
on how open source has evolved and become industry standard
essentially and how if you're building a product that
is an industry standard that people want you to open source
it and maybe some advice to a student.
So a lot of the projects we do in the class,
I ask them to put on GitHub to be like, hey,
you don't have to package this and send it to your interview.
It's already there.
Exactly.
So maybe just your thoughts on that.
Please don't say, hey, Jim said I
don't have to do all that GitHub crap.
No, you should do what is on there.
Yeah, I mean, what I think is the good news
is it's become a virtuous cycle.
I think when it first came out, it had shareware
and you had to write a $5 check or whatever.
And you want to reward the people who put out
tools and capabilities.
At the same time where there was like,
is this somebody in their garage at midnight
who will never answer, the whole support infrastructure
had become probably the thing that would slow it down.
But through the community and open source,
there are so many tools like GitHub, GitLab,
that provide the software engineering capability
that you can utilize.
And I'm going to be blunt with you.
I don't think anyone in this room wants to be,
you want to be the best.
You want to be the best, write the highest quality code.
That's what your desire is.
So you migrate towards those tools
that allow you to do that and sustain your code
and all that kind of thing.
And it's just grown because then the community comes in.
I view open sources, there's a couple
of facets to open source.
And what's interesting is, as I would say,
my Intel team that was doing open source
was kind of a little bit far to the right,
like in one end of open source.
And those facets are, it's a community code in everybody.
Everybody and anybody can contribute to it.
And there is enough infrastructure.
And there is Alina's tour holds or somebody watching over
and not letting bad stuff get in and everything.
And those projects go really, really, really well.
And of course, the huge benefit for companies
is a lot of those things are solving problems
that are just a pain in the butt.
They're just, they're cool things,
they're tools and everything else.
But then the company can incorporate that,
even if they have proprietary code or their secret sauce,
as you will.
The things that aren't secret sauce, they can just,
they don't need to work on.
They have a built-in army to go help it.
And they can submit it.
Or the other thing is, is they have a measure of control.
If it breaks, they can go fix it.
They're not counting on this proprietary library,
this, that, the other thing.
So the virtuous cycle occurred.
It kind of, in the beginning, it was a cool thing,
a little bit of spaghetti against the wall.
Then people realizing they could do it.
And now it's a business.
There's a business reason to do it.
You don't have to write that code or deal with that code
so much.
At the same time, you still have to scan the code.
You still have to do all sorts of stuff.
They have, at Intel, they have whitelists and blacklists.
Things that have security problems, can't use them.
Write it yourself.
There's all this kind of stuff.
But the virtuous cycle and that openness,
it's a little bit self-monitoring.
Because you don't want to be called out
for bad code, everything else.
So you do concentrate it.
So that's it.
By the way, the other side of the coin that my team did
is we were a team who wrote code on behalf of Intel.
That was Intel production code that
happened to be open source.
While we accepted contributions, they were more than curated.
They were either solicited or solicited by the other side.
And then we would take control and commit
to supporting code from third party sources and everything.
That person never had to do it again.
If they were willing to commit, they would do it.
So 95% of the code in the stuff we did
was written by Intel, written by the Intel team.
How that benefited people like DreamWorks and everything
was, if Intel made a business decision
to stop working on that code, they still had access.
They could make that.
So it was good for Intel in their arena to do it.
But me, my team, we were so oriented
towards quality, fidelity, and performance
that we wanted to maintain that control.
And so that's the two sides of the coin.
No, that was beautiful.
To your last point, in the industry,
that's essentially called supplier risk.
Essentially, if you're depending on a software or service
where you agree to pay x amount of dollars, let's take Penn.
As you entered university, you agreed to pay a certain amount
for your tuition.
If Penn suddenly went, oh, you need to pay 2x now,
that's a risk you're taking on.
So having open source and at least open source available,
even if the company decides to pull it out,
you still have the ability to take it over
and build it in-house.
So it reduces supplier risk.
Yeah, I think the other thing, which
I think the focus of engineers and everything
is not necessarily unless you aspire to open your own business
or do your own thing is what I don't think has happened
is there's not one settled business
model for open source.
There are companies that just do open source.
There's a company called Kitware that had them on the thing.
Everything they do is open source,
but they're a contracting firm.
So they take in feature requests from the government
and everything, and they've built a model around that.
And then the question is, is how sustainable that?
That gives sort of an up and down sustainability
of the business.
Red Hat's another one.
They package it, they add value, and then
they craft a support license.
That's still a struggle in the industry.
The cool thing is it's pretty open to how
you might achieve that.
So anyway, that's that.
Let's make my go quicker.
It's not working very well.
Maybe I beat on it too much.
Get your laptop turned off.
I turned it off.
I'm sorry.
So quality, you've probably all heard of CI,
continuous integration, Agile techniques.
I'm not going to give you the whole book on Agile
as I just said.
What I have encountered and think
works in most circumstances.
And it'll work with often with you'll
use open source tools to build proprietary code as well
as open source.
So the continuous integration things I've seen, Jenkins,
there's a bunch of open source and a few other things.
My experience, though, is they all need to be customized.
It depends on what you're building,
why you're building it, who your users are,
how it's distributed, and what your mechanism is.
So that's why I say homegrown scripting.
It's kind of you're probably going to have both.
You're going to do that.
You're going to use a thing, again,
from Kitware called CMake to script
how you do various things.
But the concept of continuous integration, you make a change
and fully test everything.
One is easy to say and extremely hard to achieve.
And you're always one of those things
that you're reaching higher to do it.
But your software engineering practices
should always consider an automated continuous
integration.
JIRA, you'll encounter.
JIRA seems to be the one of the day now for bug and task
tracking.
I, in my mind, separate the two, but you don't have to.
But you really should think about the task
you're going to do, estimate it.
All that is real world stuff you'll
encounter when you enter a company.
You will have to spend not inordinate but not
minimal amount of time just tracking what you do.
So it's more of a career pointing out.
You're going to be an engineer.
Be aware.
You're going to have to write down what you're doing.
And somebody is going to either want to monitor it.
The best engineers I've found like to do it
because they monitor themselves.
And they don't care if anybody else is monitoring it.
It helps them focus on what they're doing.
So tasks and bug trackers will be critical to any job
you take.
Probably, if I can add, probably one
of the most underrated skills, especially for new grads
coming out, is how do you prioritize?
How do you prioritize without your manager telling you
what the priority is?
And if you can solve that, you're
going up the ladder very quickly.
That is a great, great point.
Independence, I'm actually going to bring it up later
in a different way.
And it may look like it's counterintuitive.
But crafting an independence in yourself in everyday tasks
will be extremely useful to you and your manager.
And the minimum is never get in a,
I don't know what to do next.
That's probably, it's OK.
It happens.
But if you've got a plan for the next month,
and this is kind of where Agile comes in.
My team did roughly a combination
of monthly and quarterly planning.
So this tiered planning, what do I
want to achieve in a quarter?
What do I want to achieve this month?
Many teams do want to do this thing called sprints.
We didn't do it.
It didn't work for us.
Sprints weren't a thing that was good.
I'm not saying.
I would say probably 80%, 75% of companies do sprints.
That's what I meant by you have to take the Agile
as a bunch of tools, a bunch of screwdrivers and things,
and do it.
So one, keep that in mind.
The thing that I think is most important
that I've seen work the best is what I call here
incremental test-driven development.
In simple terms, write the test before you write the code.
Not the other way around.
You can benefit from that by modularizing or consolidating.
Just do a little thing, and test back and forth.
And even if you're pressured, you feel like, oh,
I've got to write a boatload of code.
101% of the time, you'll be slower doing it that way
than if you do test-driven development.
And you'll have less what's called technical debt.
Technical debt is the combination
of your code and the number of bugs you introduced into it.
And so you want to avoid technical debt.
And where Agile is, I'll get you in a second,
where some of the Agile books and everything
are completely correct.
It is roughly a 10x cost for every stage that you go out.
Yes, sir.
So last year, as part of the speaker
we brought in for the game design club,
we spoke with a programmer named Val.
And this is not necessarily like test cases,
but he says the way that he codes is he writes it all out.
And then he sets a debug point on all of them.
He never runs the code directly to see how it goes.
He just goes from breakpoint to breakpoint to breakpoint.
He calls it Zen programming.
Is that applicable?
So what I would say is we're all humans.
So that's a form of test-driven development.
He just went against my recommendation
in the sense of writing all the code.
Except he didn't really, because he put a debug point in,
and he focused on the code quality and situation
at every breakpoint.
So I actually think we're in violent agreement with him
in one sense.
But everybody, or there are certainly
10 to 20 classes of programmers.
And you do have to consider the one size doesn't fit all,
in most cases, in engineering.
That was what he became comfortable with over time.
So he's giving you a technique to do what I said.
His sensibility and his ability to think, think out loud,
whatever, I think fits the model.
My brain and a number of the people
I found most successful on my team
did this incremental methodology.
One of the other things to be aware of,
which makes a difference, is where is this thing going
to run?
Because I will tell you, GPU tools,
they're getting better and better.
But they are not nearly as robust as CPU tools.
CPU has all these counters and everything else.
And if you go deep in the architecture,
there's 350 debug things that don't
impact the running of the code.
But they know how many caches happen,
and all this other stuff.
GPUs are just different animals.
It's not that it's bad or good.
It's how long they've been in the market, all this stuff.
So those things, the architecture makes a difference.
I'll talk about that a little bit in a second.
This is pretty standard stuff.
Just final, and I think Shazan kind of mentioned this
in passing, in a different way.
He goes, oh, just put your code out there.
They'll look at it.
I'm sure it compiles and everything.
The reason he said that is because this part
of the product process is non-trivial.
You've done everything.
Think perfectly, everything else.
You get to the point where you want to give it
to somebody in an easy-to-install manner,
everything falls apart if you don't do that right.
So there are jobs, extremely important jobs,
in build, release, and deploy.
People whose whole lives are being experts in that.
So one, I don't want to discourage you
from being experts in that.
Actually, if you have this knowledge,
if you have all this, you're more and more
valuable to your company.
But just keep this in mind as you go to the marketplace.
We want to do cool eyeball.
I mean, I will, complete honesty, horrible at this,
me, personally.
I just didn't want to do it.
Hire somebody else to do that, whatever.
It wasn't, I just couldn't get that sensibility.
So I put these people on a pedestal.
So just consider that.
It's not some mundane thing.
They are really making sure that the product
quality in the customer's hands, that that first experience
of using your code isn't horrible,
because 95% of the time, there won't be a second experience.
So just keep that in mind.
Otherwise, think about test-driven development,
this whole concept of you get quality
to build it in incrementally.
Fidelity.
Fidelity means two things to me, particularly
with a group like this.
Typically, fidelity means image fidelity.
It means, and we use it fairly regularly in ray tracing.
If you either have a photograph or the ideal image
that you sat around and generated
with the world's simplest but most perfect ray
tracer over 100 hours, if you're now
going to do it in 1 30th of a second or 1 60th of a second,
what's the fidelity?
What's at first ground true?
That's really important.
It's very important when there's techniques
involved that involve AI.
They're inserting pixels in based on some neural network
that may or may not be good, may or may not
be good in a circumstance, that kind of thing.
How many edge cases can it deal with?
And obviously, any kind of antialiasing,
even with rasterization and things like that.
So that's a kind of fidelity.
Did somebody have to say something?
OK.
The other fidelity you find in compute
is mathematical fidelity, is precision.
What is the right precision for the job you're doing?
Because the lower the precision, the higher the performance.
But it's kind of a quality metric, but it's not.
You can have a precision bug and have instructions
run perfectly.
So just be aware of your result accuracy for the end user.
In high-performance computing, I will tell you
that for physics simulations, the stuff I was showing you,
the NASA, everything else, the minimum
is FP64 or 64-bit floating point.
Most people have, there was a mode back in the day
in Intel chips that was 80-bits.
Most people can survive.
It's really this difference between FP32 and FP64
where things leap around.
Most graphics devices are FP32 and perfectly fine.
But year after year for our libraries,
we've always got a company say, when
am I going to be able to flick on double precision?
And it turns out, in that whole quality and workflow
and everything, it's not just flicking a bit.
You've got to do all sorts of stuff to do it.
So be aware.
And then, of course, you see many more low-precision
methodologies out there, particularly
in machine learning.
They're fantastic.
This is twice as fast as this, twice as fast.
This is a little bit faster.
And FP16 is a little bit more precision.
It depends on the use case.
But just be aware that mathematical precision
in computers is something you will encounter in your career,
especially if you do software engineering and GPU programming.
And in that case, think in advance
how you're going to go back to the quality part.
While fidelity is not quite the same,
you need to think about how are you
going to validate whether our situation works.
And then performance, this is where the magic happens.
And it's also where your product wins or loses in the marketplace.
So it's great to have a brilliant algorithm.
It's great to have a really cool idea.
As soon as you put that idea out in open source or whatever form,
you write a paper about it or whatever,
someone's going to help you, particularly
if you didn't really think about performance
and the platform it's going to run on.
And in some cases, again, harkening back to my Intel,
we ran on every platform on the planet.
We ran on supercomputers.
The only thing we didn't really run on were these guys.
Anything that had more than passing compute capability,
we had to handle the precision, the quality, the performance,
and maximize the performance on those.
So again, be aware of these various things.
This is where you delve into computer architecture
a little bit.
And it's not absolutely necessary,
but if you're a GPU programming class,
you have to have a sense of that architecture.
What's a thread?
What's a warp?
What's a vector?
How many vectors am I using?
Is it in ray tracing?
Is it coherent?
Is it incoherent?
How's the data go together?
It all will impact it.
So I'm not going to beat this up,
but within six months on any job you take,
particularly if you expose yourself as a GPU performance
programmer, you will have to unassemble the code
and look at the instructions and figure out what's going on.
And something to realize, compilers, debuggers,
they're software too.
And despite everything I said about quality,
I never said that I have this structure
that I would lead the team with, but I never
said our stuff didn't have any bugs.
So just be aware that compilers and debuggers are software too.
And they themselves, you sometimes
have to rule out that the compiler generated bad code.
Doesn't happen super often.
It depends on a lot of factors.
But in particular, with a new, so hey,
I joined NVIDIA this week, and they're
all excited about the 4090 RTXs and everything.
That thing's new.
Got a new core architecture called Hopper.
It may be fantastic.
They may have not a single bug in their CUDA compiler,
but I'd be surprised if they didn't.
So I'm not saying it's the first thing you do.
It tends to be the last thing you do.
But don't forget that the compiler can do bad things,
or the compiler can be blocking you from performance.
And sometimes, and this is really what comes out,
know enough about this stuff.
Read what you can.
Play around and use debuggers to look at the code.
Enough to say, do I understand these instructions enough
to know that this calculation, I add two floating point numbers,
that if you think about it, are vectors.
So you're actually adding 64 numbers to 64 numbers,
whatever it is, or eight, what have you.
If that thing generated what's called scalar instructions,
which is just an add, whatever, and not a vector add,
or whatever, you go like, why the heck did it do that?
And you may be able to rewrite your code,
or look into it so the compiler catches that.
And that's actually a very typical thing for performance.
You actually don't write an assembly.
You can go into what's called intrinsics or assembly
language, that's last resort.
Understand the compiler enough to do it.
And if you can't do that, submit a bug report.
So that's performance.
It's really about the architecture
and mapping your data to the cache hierarchies
and all those things.
And GPUs and CPUs are very different in that area.
And then finally, that's not the end of performance.
This gentleman over there with the pen or the pixel
marker asked me about, oh, that thing
wasn't on one computer.
It was on multiple computers.
Yes, but very often, you attempt to run on multiple computers,
and it runs slower than one computer.
So distributed performance is the next thing.
It's a thing you're likely to encounter.
The more stuff goes in the cloud,
the more stuff that goes in the data center,
the more stuff that is a combination of edge and data
center, all that interaction and the data
structures and the methodology bring a whole new layer
of challenges in there.
So just be aware of performance of multiple platforms.
If you're not aware, the connectivity
that you'll most encounter, pretty obvious,
internet connectivity.
You guys probably deal with that all the time,
remote logins and stuff like that,
or attempting to have multiple disparate computers.
Ethernet locally sometimes is the other one.
And then in high-performance computing,
it's so important that they build their own networking
products.
NVIDIA owns a company called Melanos, which
is one of the leaders in this.
And this is operating, heading towards speed of light,
maybe 1 10th to 1 5th, the memory speeds.
But it can be the bottleneck.
It also is very, very high speed.
So just be aware that there are tools that
do this and everything.
But there's this new level of complexity beyond that.
So there's this multi-tier.
But just a key takeaway from all these aspects are,
I didn't mention it too much, but obviously,
your algorithm implementation is most likely
will be the place where you find the low-hanging fruit
in performance.
You can get pretty far with that.
Then consider the, I say XPU, I mean CPU, GPU,
any compute device.
Think about the architecture that you're mapping to.
And then number three, when you encounter it,
if you're at a company that's involved
in high-performance computing or cloud computing,
like at Google, then you might get involved in computing.
So just keep that in mind.
We'll stop for a minute and a break.
I see people going like this, which is fine.
I know it's the evening.
And this isn't as exciting a topic
as all the questions you have.
No, I just wanted to thank you for telling us
all about quality, fidelity, performance,
and open source device.
Melody is still also in engineering for a company.
I had an interview with DreamWorks.
And I asked them this question, why
did you make Moonway open source?
And then they bounced the question back to me.
And although I had points, now I have more.
So it's a thumbs up.
And usually, whenever we are interviewing,
and then we say that, oh, I have more experience,
and I would like to go for a higher experience job,
then there's this noun called bar rate.
And quality, fidelity, performance,
if we actually know about this, then we can name that.
Thank you so much.
I look forward.
Thank you.
I moved through my career and jumped to various places,
or jumped at the things I was offered sometimes.
The high performance computing thing actually
completely came out of left field.
Somebody made a bet on me, which is nice.
They said, we want to hire you.
Here's another twist, which I'll go into.
A big company like Intel, NVIDIA, and everything,
AMD, all those great companies.
From a business standpoint, the hardest thing
for a manager at these companies is to get one hit.
Believe it or not, you have 5,500 people working
on the hopper thing.
You can just take one more.
The reverse of that is, once they get it,
they want to place the person right away.
There's this mix of things.
So just be aware of that.
If you have a legitimate job interview, everything else,
you're going through the process.
It's a real quick fix.
It's a real quick fix, and it's a real quick fix.
And it's a real quick fix, and it's a real quick fix.
It's a real quid pro quo.
I'll talk about that in a second.
But the bottom line is, it's fun and rewarding.
That's why we do it.
It has become, congratulations, different
when I entered the marketplace.
It was actually semi-unusual.
Or it wasn't such a huge thing.
Engineers were important, everything else.
Software and computers were just a part of it.
Computers were useful, important,
but not like it is today.
As much as I just said getting one headcount
is hard and everything, particularly
in the constrained environment we have right now,
you're still desperately needed.
You'll all get jobs.
And that's because it is critical to solve
these problems.
We can't throw enough people at these problems.
If engineering is your career goal,
just be aware of this quality, fidelity, and performance.
Your user base could be five world-class climate
scientists.
That's it.
They're the only people you're trying to satisfy,
or their peers or whatever.
But they're trying to save the planet.
If you give false information, bad fidelity, whatever,
they're counting on you.
They're counting on you guys to do it right.
They're not going to assume you're wrong.
So a targeted thing could be as critical as something
that a million people are going to see.
A game.
And nothing's wrong with games.
They make us feel better.
They make us have fun.
It's important to have fun, by the way.
I'm not going to talk a lot about fun.
It's fun.
Make sure you're having fun wherever you go.
If there's not an element of fun in it, get the hell out.
Make sure that you're having some form of fun,
and make sure you have a life.
Seriously.
If your manager doesn't let you have a life,
that's the wrong manager.
So you can change the world with software.
OK, now, how much time do I have?
I'm going.
I mean, the class time is long, but you can take your time.
OK, I talk a lot.
I'm known for talking a lot, even though I try to tell you
to boil things down.
I'm going to talk now about the three major companies
and their software requirements.
So note this.
I am not saying one is better than the other
or representing them right now.
What I call the incumbents, they're obviously,
you have Imagination Technologies, a bunch of other.
Obviously, with the metaverse, and you've
got companies like Cesium, great companies like that.
There's all sorts of cool stuff going on.
But from my purview where I am, the distributors
most of the computing technology are NVIDIA, Intel, and AMD.
And then we can argue how Mac fits in there.
As you see, I'm a Mac user, so they're in there as well.
But let's just talk about these as GPU and CPU development
environments.
OK, so NVIDIA, I didn't pick them first for any reason
other than it was how fast I could type.
CUDA stands for Compute Unified Device Architecture.
I call that their direct GPU programming layer.
They have this newer thing that came out.
I'm in the Omniverse group, although I haven't figured out
why I'm in the Omniverse group, but I'm in the Omniverse group.
And that's a software platform for workflows, data
interchange.
In the parlance at various companies,
this would be called a solution, where
you apply software, hardware platforms to one or more
capabilities or solutions.
I'm not going to delve much into Omniverse.
These are kind of the things that are happening.
But Omniverse is more of a workflow
that supports both developers and end-user workflows.
It's pretty cool.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE MEMBER 2 We have Rev coming to talk on the forum.
Oh, you do?
OK.
Rev is not my boss.
He's my boss's boss.
So don't tell him I said anything bad.
So Intel.
I know a fair amount about this, what it is,
but I've up-leveled it.
So Intel's CUDA, and they would hate that I just said that,
but the programming environment and concept
is called SYCL, which is the Chrono Standard.
You also will hear the term DPC++,
which stands for Data Parallel C++.
That is Intel's product implementation
of the SYCL code.
Incorporate SYCL, adds extensions,
all that kind of stuff.
The whole concept is architecture agnostic direct
programming.
So will SYCL and oneAPI solve the problem you said?
I don't know.
You guys will have to pursue that.
That's what Intel is pursuing.
I'll talk about why they're pursuing it in a second.
The other thing, when you hear oneAPI,
everybody has heard of oneAPI?
Sometimes those two things are used interchangeably.
This is where I can actually tell you, and it's not insider,
it's just confusing.
This is the closest thing.
It's a compilation environment, CUDA's compilation environment.
Let's you write a piece of code that runs on a part,
runs on a processor.
oneAPI is two things.
oneAPI is an open industry specification led by Intel,
but they have, in a Chronos-like manner,
gathered a bunch of people.
And they are truly trying to make it vendor agnostic,
open source, single source code environment
that runs everywhere.
That's their goal.
And then B is anywhere you see Intel
registered trademark oneAPI, that's
the equivalent of data parallel C++ in the case.
This is the embodiment in an Intel,
they often call it a toolkit or SDK.
That is Intel's version that, for sure,
has been tested, hopefully well, with Intel hardware components.
They'll come out first on Intel hardware components, usually.
There's one case on my team where it went the other way.
But potentially other vendors.
How that potentially other vendors happen
is a whole mix of things.
From the community, there's community folks doing it.
Intel just bought a company that was
supposed to be a community company that Intel bought from.
Nothing's wrong with that, either way.
But the Uber goal is, from an Intel perspective,
is one source code runs everywhere.
And then AMD has HIP, Heterogeneous Interface
for Portability.
That's their direct GPU programming layer.
As best as I can tell, because I haven't been at AMD,
it is a very CUDA-like method where you can go do HIP, CUDA.
There's probably translators, all sorts of stuff.
There's actually a conversion tool
that SYCL has from CUDA, as well.
And that's an interesting dynamic,
which I'll talk about in a second.
Anyway, you have HIP.
And then you have ROCM, which is the one API-ish-like thing
that's not really one API.
So it's different.
But the concept is the open platform.
So what you see happening is AMD and Intel
are heavily leaning to what they call open.
And I'll talk about NVIDIA in a second,
because it doesn't mean that NVIDIA is not open.
But that is the position.
The positioning of these guys is open.
At the same time, AMD is trying to carve its own path.
And we'll see how that all goes.
And that's what I mean by this isn't
going to be solved this year.
And as you guys get out there, you're
going to hopefully help figure out
what the right thing to do is.
And it's confusing.
And there's economics involved, and products,
and everything else.
But conceptually, that's what it is.
OK, so this is from an NVIDIA, I'm
calling it an outside-in viewpoint,
from a public technologist who's
looking at NVIDIA's concept, and what they're doing,
and why they're doing what they're doing,
is the CUDA is compute unified device architecture.
The key to understand from an NVIDIA standpoint
is the unified.
This is James Rinder's calling.
He is the co-author on the books I wrote.
But I won't answer James.
I'll call him later and tell him I was talking to you guys.
He also is the primary evangelist for OneAPI.
Still a friend.
The key to understand the unified,
and where NVIDIA is coming from with CUDA,
and why they don't, in my mind, and again, this
is not an insider, this is an outsider view,
why they don't even, they rarely address it.
They don't talk about OneAPI.
They don't talk about him.
They don't talk about any of that stuff.
They don't really try to position themselves that way.
The fundamental thing is the compilers, and the software,
and the interfaces, and everything
are what's called co-designed with the hardware.
Performance.
Quality and performance is what's in their mind together.
So you go back to the thing I said.
Fidelity is kind of in there too,
but that's a little bit of a performance-first viewpoint
for the market.
It is serving them in that if they have the best, or easiest,
or most performing development environment,
then people like you guys say, I got to buy an NVIDIA device
because I get my things done with that.
Nothing's wrong with that.
That's market marketing.
Others call it proprietary because it only
runs on NVIDIA hardware.
runs on NVIDIA, but it only runs on NVIDIA by design
because the software teams and the hardware teams
sit down together and do it.
Intel, AMD aspire to do that, but it's not clear to me.
And it's there.
It's discussed on both companies.
I'm not telling you anything inside.
But their emphasis, all the way from the CEO, Jensen,
is the unified design delivers the best
combination of quality and performance to the marketplace,
and that's what you're going to deliver to change the world.
So is it proprietary?
At the same time, it's complex.
So we go back to, we might have a really crazy work
in there because the hardware does this, that,
and they don't want to expose it.
They do better with the marketplace that they don't.
So these are all challenges, decisions
that are legitimate market and customer-based decisions.
So while competitors call it proprietary,
it appears to me it's about quality and performance
and the notion of co-design.
By the way, everybody, who's heard of exascale?
You know what exascale means?
Anybody?
So exascale is the eras of supercomputing
are based on how many floating, double precision,
remember I mentioned?
Double precision floating point calculations.
The top 5 to 10 supercomputers and some of the waterfalls.
So we are transitioning from what's
called the petascale era.
So if you know what a petabyte is, petascale means,
what is that?
A terascale is a trillion floating point ops,
and then you have peta, which is the next power of 3,
add power of 3.
Exascale is the next power of 3.
It's a quadrillion floating point operations per second,
and a machine that's an exascale machine does that.
Why did I bring up exascale?
Is the concept of exascale is to get these computers delivering
that capability, and to some extent,
each one of these computers, while it
uses tons of open source software, everything else,
they are a targeted architecture with those interconnects,
everything else.
So in a weird way, as long as the tools exist,
like CUDA, they're going to go for performance.
The other point is I joined the industry just about 12,
14 years ago, and they said we will only
get to exascale if we co-design with AMD, Nvidia,
a broader level of co-design.
But the concept of co-design software and hardware
is not something invented or anything else.
It is a known methodology that gets you where you want to go.
So that's where Nvidia is coming from.
So a quick point on what you said earlier
about it being proprietary.
Probably the easiest example of it
is if you've ever seen your driver updates for Nvidia,
and it has, ooh, Spider-Man came out.
We have an optimization for Spider-Man.
And whatever the new holiday game is going to come out,
you guys know better than I do.
They're going to have an optimization for that.
And they can do it because it's proprietary.
And the driver will sit in.
So anyway, the bottom line is it's always two-sided.
Be aware of that.
OK, Intel.
Intel wants to help you solve, I believe,
the problem you talked to me about,
Intel and a little bit of AMD.
This comes from the concept that while all you
guys are going to be valuable to your company,
you're a cost sink for the most part.
It depends on what company you're at.
It's not necessarily true.
You could come in and amplify the software sales
with the stuff and everything.
But you come in.
You're a resource.
Yes, you're delivering stuff.
But they care about what's called ROI,
return on investment.
And you guys are an investment for myself.
I'm a cost sink, too.
So the whole point is if you have three GPU environments,
like I just said, rule of thumb is
it's three times as costly to support a market product.
Now, you can pick and choose.
You can pick two.
You can support later.
You dance around all this stuff.
But the concept that Intel's going with
is that's a big problem.
No one's ever solved it.
NVIDIA doesn't seem to want to solve it.
But the marketplace is at, we believe the marketplace
is asking for it.
And in fact, they are.
It's a way to be a good citizen in the marketplace
as well as drive a preference for Intel
because Intel is doing this and cares about the market
and everything else.
And on the other hand is to keep Intel in the market.
It is competitive.
Intel and NVIDIA, everybody has been impacted
by the economics that have happened lately.
But Intel's being impacted by AMD and other things.
So it's a competitive environment.
It's intended to provide a market-worthy capability that
says Intel thinks about customers first, which
is not a bad thing.
But their argument or the sub-argument
to what they're doing is you'll have to write less code.
And it goes back to the open source thing we talked about.
More open source code will just work.
It will work everywhere if you choose this paradigm.
And so they're offering that up and driving it.
And that's related.
It's one code base to run everywhere.
And the other twist, we talked about it a little bit,
is the CPUs are changing as well.
Mac has their own CPUs.
AMD is still IA, but trying to insert their special sauce
in there.
NVIDIA is coming out with a CPU, which I'm personally
very excited about.
It probably will be a big part of my job
to make that thing go.
But there's architecture twists.
So now, not only are the GPUs three of them,
there's three, four, or five CPU things.
And now you have an infinite number
of back ends you need and all that kind of stuff.
Maybe not infinite, but 10s and 20s of them.
So the bottom line is, that's the vision
that Intel's going with.
It's a good vision.
My concern, go ahead.
It's not bad when it does.
Why is it called SIGL?
Is it stand for something?
The CL stands for OpenCL, because the original back end,
the way they were going to get portability was through OpenCL.
And I forget.
So anyway, the CL stands for OpenCL, Compute Language.
And then I don't know what the SY stands for.
That's actually a good question.
We should talk about that.
I worked briefly with the back end workforce.
Yeah, it's not something that jumps out at you, but yeah.
But its original form was a compiler
that could target LLVM, OpenCL, and a bunch of other code
generating back ends to target this one code base thing.
Intel's goal is to accelerate the adoption and all
that kind of stuff, and going with that as a methodology.
That's extensible.
So one code base to run on all, rule of the law,
hear the Lord of the Rings person like I am.
But the whole idea is to reduce dev time and company software
costs is the main argument.
One code base, all that stuff I talked about, CI, everything.
Technically, you should be able to pick one platform
and test it all in it, assume it runs on other platforms.
Obviously, I don't recommend that.
You would run it everywhere.
And then the perspective is, CUDA's been out there,
I don't know, 15, 20 years, and has
gone through a lot of the pains and ecosystem
enabling and multiple generations of product
and everything.
And SYCL's about three to four years old.
Or I'm sorry, one API and how it's utilized.
And so it's not completely there yet.
It's not necessarily they won't go faster.
It might be ready in three years.
And I'm not saying it's not ready necessarily now,
but I do believe logic dictates that you'll
run into more compiler problems, like I was saying,
some performance problems.
And performance portability will be,
what we call performance portability,
will be the potential knock on SYCL.
OK, it runs everywhere, but it only runs really great on Intel
would be the thing to look out for.
Intel will say, no, we want it to run great everywhere.
But NVIDIA and AMD will probably have to join in and make it
work.
And now you have NVIDIA, am I going
to invest in this thing when CUDA runs great
and all this stuff?
But that's the concept, an open standard, open market.
It's good if it's the whole notion of open source.
You think of Intel, to an extent AMD is doubling down on that.
I'll tell you, I haven't followed AMD a whole lot.
They are a smaller player in CPUs and GPUs,
but they're an aggressive player.
And they've done a really great job the last five years.
The advantages they have, I would call it the drafter
advantage.
They appear to focus on drafting off the others
and having a good market and having good ROI and capabilities
off of Intel and NVIDIA's considered necessary ecosystem
investment.
The ecosystem is getting open source,
so AMD can kind of draft off of that stuff
and also pick and choose certain markets
they can go into, avoid others, and target performance benefits
for everything.
Again, nothing wrong with that.
It's a great business model.
They're doing very well.
And they are beating Intel and NVIDIA more often
in the last five years than they have with this model.
Lisa Souther has been their CEO through this
and doing a really good job.
They have some very good business models.
They have a lot of people in the management
doing a really good job.
They have some very exciting things.
You know I took a new job.
I did talk to AMD.
And I wouldn't necessarily not join them for any reason.
But I do view them as a little bit more of a drafter who
does targeted innovation.
And like I said, they're a strong competitor.
They're steadily growing market share,
which is what you want as a company.
They're growing market share.
They're not losing market share.
And they're not just maintaining market share.
So they are building up.
And there's a thing called crossing the chasm.
And they're heading towards that where
they may be able to leap and suddenly become a leader.
That's what an NVIDIA and an Intel need to look out for.
I see that OneAPI and Rockham have similar goals.
Again, AMD has the advantage of if they don't mess things up
too much, OneAPI will run great on their parts anyway.
And Rockham can be something they spearhead
into specific markets.
Real quick thoughts on pursuing a job.
We already were talking a little bit about the interview.
My perspective after all these years,
when I was entering the market, I
couldn't have given a crap about company culture.
And it wasn't really that thing.
I'm just telling you it's extremely important.
Keep that in mind.
What does the company stand for?
How do they operate between each other?
Are they really invested in inclusion, which
most companies are these days?
But you need to hear it from them.
You need to understand that.
So don't diminish what a company culture means.
Some companies, NVIDIA and Intel, write it down.
Some companies don't, but they have a sense of what it is.
In the interview process, see if they volunteer
what their culture is, which is great.
If they don't, try to discern it through various ways,
ultimately just saying, how would you
characterize the company culture?
Just ask the question.
Again, to me, you should be wary if they can't describe it.
And of course, you want to do the classic.
You're almost certainly going to interview with three to six
people, or in a team setting or whatever.
Make sure three or four people say the same thing,
or at least similar things.
Then you know the company actually has a culture.
If they're making it up as they go, it still might be OK.
It might be nascent or whatever.
But I found in my career, I'll be completely blunt with you.
I joined NVIDIA, once I was talking to people,
NVIDIA's culture, not the job, not the salary, not all that.
It was NVIDIA's culture, how the folks I spoke to,
more senior people in my case, but they
were adamant about what it meant.
And they all corroborated everything.
So it was important to me at this stage in my career.
And I would say, when I was younger,
I kind of ignored it until I went to a company
with a heavy culture.
And I loved it.
So think about that.
Make sure they do have a mission and goal.
Again, doesn't have to be written down.
It is different than culture.
Culture is, how do we operate as a company?
What are we for?
What do we stand for?
And what is the team and organization?
It's OK in a big company to have different cultures
across organizations.
Sometimes you have two layers of culture.
That's all OK.
Just make sure there's a culture you understand
what you're getting into.
The mission statement has to be exciting.
It has to be an objective that you align with,
or it should be.
Again, and they sometimes morph, but at least consider it.
The other thing is, are you being
hired to be a cog in the wheel?
We have 75 tasks to get done this year.
We know we're going to have 150 next.
Go do all those tasks.
Or is there a balance to, well, if I'm doing my task,
what if I realize it's not the right thing to do?
Or there's a better way to do it.
That is the other side.
Obviously, like a research organization,
that's their whole goal, is to be creative and everything.
And that's OK.
That's cool.
It's actually OK to be a cog in the wheel.
It depends on you.
It depends on where you are in your career.
Just banging stuff out and getting out
of the market and contributing can be very rewarding.
So I'm not telling you it's bad.
I'm just telling you be aware of what you're getting into.
And if your desire is to primarily move
in this direction, think about it.
That's all.
However, there will be times you might want to come out
and do this, or Jim says, that's great.
I'm just telling you, being a cog in the wheel
and delivering stuff, you can rise happily in a company
if you do that.
So that's good.
And then this is very similar.
Are you interested in the company, the product, the team,
money?
All those can be important at different times
in your career.
It is not bad to want the money.
It is not bad.
It just depends on where you are, what you do.
I will just say it depends on your personal circumstances
and everything else, student loans up the wazoo, whatever
you need the money.
That's all cool.
Just be aware that you consciously
made the decision to go there.
And then you may end up being cog in a wheel,
and it may be great for that stage of your career.
So this is not a one size fits all.
And then the other thing I can't stress more than anything
is tell the truth.
Don't stretch it.
You'll be much more respected if they say,
have you ever heard of Exascale?
No.
Just say it, right?
Or even better, no, but could you tell me what it is?
Oh, oh, I heard of it in a different context, whatever.
That's all the truth.
But be yourself and be truthful.
The last thing you want to do is go or have
a manager thinking something, and it
doesn't align with everybody.
So it's pretty simple.
And then the last one is, which you guys are doing an OK job,
but not a great job today, ask questions.
Actually, your questions are probably
as important as your answers in a job interview situation.
So again, you don't have to be a guru about the company.
You don't have to go through every product they
have and everything else.
Learn enough about the company and listen closely
to questions they're asking you, whatever,
and ask some intuitive questions.
However, be truthful.
If you are out of questions, don't make it up.
OK?
That's good.
So as I interview a lot for Cesium,
I think the last two points on identify what you want to do
and then identify what you're in for,
you don't always have to be completely honest about it
with me as an interviewer, but at least
be honest with yourself about what you're doing.
At a minimum, yeah.
So that's the main thing.
The ask questions part, as I'm interviewing,
I'm like, if and when I look for a job,
I need three interviews just to ask my own questions.
It's kind of like that.
And if somebody comes into the interview
and they ask one question, I'm like,
are you really interested in this job?
I would probably expect that.
Exactly.
And you can always go.
You can be in the deepest, how many GPU programs
have you written and whatever, and do you
understand this part and everything?
And then you answer them and everything,
and then the person goes, well, I've done my questions.
Ask them a culture question.
Even though they're all technical the whole time,
you can ask a question or something
that's on your mind, what they said.
You can completely change it because this person likely
is going to be sitting next to you in three weeks coding
and designing and doing stuff that's important.
So make sure you ask those questions.
Jim does have a question.
Yes.
I go to you when you're asking a question.
Not just for the sake of it, but you
mentioned that we should, of course,
find out about the company that we are interested in.
And would you, or also, do you suggest
that we should be prepared of things
that we should specifically know before trying to draw,
especially role-specific?
Because I've also realized that you
might know about the company, but the team
or specific role that you're interviewing for,
it's not necessarily the same.
Like you said, in the culture, it
was within the company.
How do you, do you have a session?
How do you find out about these things?
Apart from directly doing the interview, before that, maybe?
There is a really, the bottom line,
I'm going to throw it, what I said right back to you.
Ask questions about what the job and the role was.
Throw email or the recruiter.
Interestingly, depends on how big the company is.
I mean, the recruiter probably has no clue.
And at Intel, the recruiter wouldn't even
know how to answer your question.
So they'll put it to the hiring manager or someone like that.
And one, it's OK that you don't know.
It's a failure.
It's a potential gap, not failure, gap
in how the job was presented to you.
That's a gap on the company side,
which actually doesn't look good for the company.
So if you're, obviously, every last thing,
am I going to write a program with I++ in it?
That's different.
But a software engineering role in a networking organization
with the goal of optimizing X, Y, Z,
that should be somewhat clear.
If they left a gap there, ask them before you go in.
Yeah, and one thing I always recommend,
especially if you guys come up to me and talk to me and say,
I have an interview coming up.
Do you have tips?
The first thing I'm going to ask is,
do you know who you're interviewing with
and what their role is?
And if you don't know, you better email the HR
when they ask you what time slots are you available at.
Ask them who you're interviewing with and what they do.
The Google machine.
And then you can do whatever Google search you want.
Exactly, exactly.
Use the Google machine, the Google button, or whatever.
LinkedIn, all that stuff.
But yeah, basically, gap in knowledge, ask.
And in fact, it's pretty much what
I say once you're on the job, right?
Don't, it is OK.
You are new.
They could have done a great job of telling you what the job is.
You still don't know what it is.
You don't know what it is, and it could change in three months
because of industry movement, whatever.
That's why you need to consider the culture and everything
else.
By the time you land in the job, the job you interviewed
might be gone.
In fact, I'd say it's 33% to 50% chance these days
that that's actually likely.
If you're here and you're graduating in May or whatever,
you actually might get hired in January, February, whatever.
Could go longer, but what have you.
But if there's a gap of more than three months,
you might have a different manager.
There's all sorts of stuff happening.
So that's part of the reason you interview the company.
Think about if the job, hey, job on the team I was with before.
You're going to get to work with film companies on movies
or supporting them and everything,
and then something changes, a need, whatever.
Hey, we need you to work on the Argonne Exascale computer.
And it depends on what your skill set is and everything,
but that just may become the most important thing.
So it's more important to think about it
from a career perspective.
I'm going to be here three years, five years.
I'm going to keep track of what I want to do.
That will change as you grow.
But bottom line is I cannot stress enough.
Don't be afraid to do it.
Don't sit around for two hours, four hours,
pounding on some problem that you're not convinced
you know what you're supposed to do.
Ask your peer.
You may not want to ask your peer.
By the way, I have it up here.
The other thing is, one, don't be afraid to talk to people.
Watch your emails when they come.
You'll be put on email groups all sorts of different ways.
All sorts of stuff.
Somebody you didn't interview with, never heard of, whatever,
says something that you worked on in one of your classes.
You never thought you would even see that it was there.
Just go, hey, I worked on this.
Just email them.
The bottom line is the majority of co-workers at any level
want you to succeed if you've been hired.
They reserve the right to say, holy crap,
I'm delivering product X. I'm the one on the ball
here for three weeks, whatever.
They almost always will say, let's catch up after that.
If they're a real jerk, they just won't get back to you
or whatever.
But that's going to be so low.
So one, lack of happening.
The majority of people want you to succeed.
They're good people at every company.
So the biggest thing you don't want, and by the way,
your manager might be a jerk.
Just be aware of that.
He may have a great team, though.
He may be distracted.
He may whatever.
He or she, I'm sorry.
They could be the greatest mentor you have.
You're going to have to sense that.
More than likely, if they sign the document that
says we're going to hire you, they're
interested in your success as well.
But the bottom line is, one, don't stick with one mentor,
two or three.
There's one right here.
There's actually a new one right here.
And oops.
And yeah, that one, there's questions.
But remember, larger companies will have some more resources
for you.
They're also harder to navigate.
So I can say network, network, network.
I don't know who to talk to.
There's 120,000 people here, right?
But it will work itself out, right?
And then a key thing is, again, in particular a larger company,
but really any company, if they're worth their while,
they're going to have a quarterly, monthly, whatever
group you're in.
There'll be something broader that
goes around the company's mission and everything.
Listen, if you didn't get the whole story,
and you probably didn't of the mission statement
or the culture or whatever, you're
going to discern it there.
And you then get to participate more and more,
and either get more in or go, holy crap, I shouldn't be here.
But you're probably going to make the right choice.
It's pretty somewhat intuitive.
And then just remember, every company
tries to maximize ROI.
And it's something you don't think a lot about as a
graduating student or whatever.
These guys have all the money in the world.
I mentioned it before about the headcount and everything.
And on tighter times, it's very tight, like one person stuff.
Other times, they might go ahead and hire 100 people.
So it does depend.
But try to understand, I'd say, within a year.
You don't have to understand day one.
Within a year, where do you fit in the company's notion of ROI?
Let's see if we can figure that out.
It may not matter.
But then what that does, it drives
you to have the company's best interest at heart
while you want the company to have your best interest
at heart.
And it becomes a virtuous cycle.
So just try to see what you want.
And with that, I'm done.
I'm open to any other questions.
Thank you.
I'll just add a thought on ROI before I hand it over
to the students.
ROI may not always be money.
Oh, yeah.
At a company like Cesium, we want to grow the platform first.
Money may come second.
At a different company, where open source is very important,
like, let's say, Red Hat or Kitware
or companies like that, building the community
and getting your answer to the question first
is super important and things like that.
So again, you want to understand what the ROI is as well
and what makes your manager successful
and what makes your manager's manager successful
and things like that as well.
That's a fantastic point.
And that's the reason it's called ROI and not
profit or whatever.
It is a slightly more amorphous thing,
although occasionally your manager, most likely,
eventually you, if you're a manager,
you actually might have to calculate the ROI in a number.
Like, we spend $10 million on this group in salary
and benefits and everything else.
And here, the interesting thing is, what's the numerator?
Is the numerator money?
Is the numerator developers?
Is the numerator?
And then how does it relate?
So anyway, the bottom line is, are they happy?
Are you contributing?
And how does that vote for the future?
So other questions, anybody?
Thank you for your attention as well.
I know it's a little bit boring sometimes.
Yeah.
So you talked a little bit about what
to do during interviews and what to do once you're on the job.
But how about actually getting interviews?
Because that tends to be a struggle sometimes at all.
When you don't get an interview, you don't get a response,
or you get rejected, you don't necessarily
get any feedback, so you don't really
know where you're going wrong.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah, that's a tough one.
Not that tough, though.
I think if you, you know, I'll say probably a few bad things
or good things.
You're going to have a degree from the university.
That's OK.
That's pretty good.
Just sorry, that's the way it works.
You know, so you have that as a start.
If you're seeing those bumps in the road,
I would say it's likely that you're going too far,
that you're actually looking for interviews for jobs
that you may be loosely qualified for.
So be careful about the blanket, the notion of a, oh,
I know C++, and there's 10 other things in here
that I kind of know.
It goes back to knowing yourself a little bit.
And so I think there's that.
Know the market situation.
I will tell you the market situation
is briefly tough right now.
And then the other thing is, it sort of
relates to the market situation, is you have a sense of urgency
and the company has a malleable sense of urgency.
So it's really interesting.
I will tell you the other thing.
Sorry, I'm sort of drifting off your time.
But the bottom line is, I will tell you something.
This is from an Intel manager perspective,
I believe, that is very similar at any larger corporation.
When they say minimum qualifications, they mean it.
If the job says minimum qualification
and it's four things, don't apply
if you don't have four things.
The recruiter, who I just told you probably doesn't know much,
will remove you before the manager even sees you.
It's a waste of your time.
So make sure that you can speak to the minimum qualifications
confidently.
Don't apply if it doesn't fit.
So I think that's ultimately the fact.
If it's a well-structured company
and a well-structured staffing thing,
if you hit the minimum qualifications,
then you should apply.
And you should consider how you address what they
call a plus or additional.
But if the minimum qualification is
a PhD in computer graphics, don't do it.
You're actually in a little way, and the recruiter
may not screen you out.
And then the manager goes, why don't you screen this person?
So there's a little bit of mechanical stuff
with that thing.
The other thing I want to say, though,
is see if you notice when you're interviewing.
Try to have a sense of what I would call in the big flips.
And that is when they go from interviewing you
to figuring out how they can land you.
It is almost instantaneous, typically.
Or sometimes it's the second interview process or whatever.
Sometimes it's not.
Sometimes they have, you know, there's
all sorts of ways of doing this.
But in this market for engineers,
I think what I've seen in my behavior
was there's just a moment where I go, oh, they
nailed everything.
And just one, be careful to oversell yourself.
Check it.
But now that's another point to show you have job interest.
That's when you start asking culture questions
and things like, if you haven't done it yet, it's OK to do it.
But see if you can learn that skill of the bit flipping.
I think, Jim, if I can add, because I do this all
the time, and I'm realizing, as you say,
the person you're interviewing with,
whether it's a technical manager at HR,
they go from telling you about something
to selling you on something.
I think that's like, it's not always obvious.
But if you notice it in their form,
that's when you can notice it.
Yeah.
I mean, you don't have to go crazy when that happens.
And you could be wrong.
It could be the person's personality,
particularly if it's HR or something like that.
They may just have a thing.
But in particular, if the hiring manager goes into,
they'll sell you from the beginning.
They're going to assume it'll work out,
and you're navigating.
But there's a point at which they're there in that.
Just keep that in mind, because you have a little bit of power
at that point.
Because going back to everything I said,
the reality in the background, in the back office
and everything is, if they don't place somebody
in a reasonable period of time, it'll go away.
The recruiters will start emailing.
Is this thing still a legitimate job?
Whatever.
I had a very, for a while, and it's become better.
It became better towards the end.
But four or five years ago, I was there like, hey, recruiter,
just be aware.
I may not get even close to a resume for someone
who meets the minimum qualifications for nine months.
It's a little bit different now.
But for what I was hiring and what I needed to do and get
done, I could not hire what we euphemistically
call a boat anchor.
A unicorn.
Somebody who you invest in, who brings zero ROI,
or negative ROI, as they say.
So it depends on the circumstances.
They may be hiring cogs in the wheel.
And if you have a minimum thing, that's fine.
But it depends on the circumstance.
But just note, at a minimum, feel good
that somebody loves you.
It still may not work out.
At the same time, though, when they flip that bit,
now you begin to become the decider.
In the end, you're the decider.
That's the beauty of the job thing.
It's a pain in the butt.
It's stressful, all this other stuff.
What do I do?
But eventually, you're in control.
A offer comes, one or more companies,
and you decide whether you want to do this or not.
And they'll usually be begging you to land it.
And part of it is simply mechanical.
They see the value in what you have
and want to get you on board as quickly as possible.
Still, make sure you do what's right for you.
The right company and the right organization, I don't know.
You're getting married the day after you graduate,
or you've promised your family you're
going to go on a four-week thing or whatever.
And they say, no, we want you to do it.
If they say no, that's almost certainly not
the company for you, right?
Again, but if you're in a money situation or whatever,
and you just want to get something in.
So it's relative.
But anyway, I would just, that's the final piece of advice.
And that really comes down to be yourself in a way.
Don't beg them for the job.
And don't try to say anything to get the job.
That actually is very easily detectable.
And it's just not well-received by the team.
You are going to become part of a team,
whether you call it a cog or whether you
call it an important aspect of the team.
And they want you to succeed.
Like I said, they don't want you to start off
on the wrong foot, so.
OK?
Anybody else?
Yes?
I was just interested in their perspective on Agile,
specifically for graphics development.
Since I think most graphics apps have a much slower release
schedule.
Or I don't know, if you're making a movie,
you don't even care about the code.
You just output the movie.
So I was wondering how that works,
or kind of goes against Agile, or when you might
use it more in waterfall approach.
I've sort of come to feel that waterfall is the one.
I think that's a general agreement in the wider
industry.
Yeah, yeah.
So maybe I'll call it traditional waterfall.
There are, I would say, unfortunately,
a lot of software engineering organizations
that call what they're doing Agile,
and it's actually waterfall, which is really frustrating.
But I am not aware in my, I'm starting off
the waterfall list that I learned about Agile
and everything.
And so I'll sort of go back to what I said.
Agile is a tool bag.
It's a lot of people, in my experience,
a lot of people want to Agile, think of it
as an actual process.
You do this.
You have stand-up meetings.
And I've come to the conclusion that there's
nothing wrong with that process in the right circumstance.
Probably web design probably fits the classic Agile.
Or now it's called classic.
It's doing user stories, and da-da-da-da-da, all that stuff.
Something like web design probably benefits from it.
And by the way, there's a crap load of web designers, right?
So it may, from a standpoint of how many projects
are the full blown Agile with 90% of the processes,
I mean, 50% or more, whatever.
To your question, though, in graphics and GPU
and performance programming and everything else,
I think you want to select the Agile processes that
map to how you deliver to users, what the user base is,
what their concerns are.
And as much as I like Agile and just
threw waterfall under the bus, my inkling in that thing
is to use the least amount of Agile tools that you can.
Don't get caught up in it.
And that's where I really come down to the tools
that I have found work best in a graphics or a performance
or a compute.
Where the performance is the deliverable
is a feature backlog, a prioritized feature
or capability backlog, if you will.
So you always should have a backlog of things
you want to do prioritized.
And then somewhere between monthly and quarterly,
I think, and you were kind of addressing it with,
I mean, some projects are yearly with graphics drivers.
My guess is internally, though, they're monthly or quarterly.
But the beauty of Agile, and the other thing
I like about Agile is it's ready to ship.
But for market reasons, you can choose not to ship it,
whatever that market reason is.
So I like the readiness of your code
there, but the test-driven development.
So I think the backlog, test-driven development,
and automated testing.
I'm going to tell you something that I probably
shouldn't tell you.
So I don't know how much recording is going on.
I didn't have the memorizing quality, fidelity, everything.
That's what Jim's about.
Jim, as a technical manager, I didn't
have a validation engineer on my team.
I didn't have a person who was responsible for Agile.
They were computers.
Now, I did have what I call build, release, and CI
development engineers.
They were putting the tools in place,
make sure they were robust, make sure they weren't failing,
all that stuff.
But test-driven development supported
by extensive automation, well-written automation,
quality, fidelity, performance in the automation part
is, to me, the key to ultimately delivering quality
where, at a minimum, the obvious and the majority of edge cases
never are encountered by an end user.
Most of our end users were either
trying to do something we hadn't implemented yet and thought,
well, this must work, or whatever.
And we're getting maybe not wrong answers.
We're getting weird stuff.
We're going, why doesn't this work?
We tell you in the release notes it doesn't work.
That kind of thing.
But anyway, that's from a graphics standpoint
and performance programming standpoint.
I think the judicious use of the backlog.
And I have another footnote.
Do people like my philosophies?
You guys like them?
There's one other.
It just occurred to me, a philosophy
that I expelled that caused a number of people
who maybe would listen to my thing about Agile.
But would say, OK, we sort of do Agile,
but there's so many problems with that.
There's another philosophy that's around the backlog.
And you guys, everybody know what a LIFO and a FIFO is?
Right?
Most features, particularly the most compelling features
that you have not yet implemented
should generally be done in a LIFO, not a FIFO.
Which means the last idea that just came in
from a combination of a customer, a receiver,
and everything, that idea or feature request or capability
is very likely the highest priority one
that you should consider.
And that's why I talk about a backlog and a prioritized
backlog.
That almost always has more market knowledge.
Right?
It's collective market knowledge comes in.
Customer, multiple customer, whatever, say,
if you only did this, my job would be easier.
The majority of software organizations I've seen
do LIFO.
OK?
We lock it down for a year, OK?
And they are not Agile enough to do LIFO unless it literally
is life or death.
Like, if I don't get this, you lose a billion dollars
in sales, right?
Then that will trouble everything.
But my experience, and I've said this very, very often,
and got shot down a million times,
as I always said, the last thing is probably the most important.
And certain managers say, yeah, yeah, you're right, but.
And I'm like, why are you saying but?
We're structured to do this.
Let's do it.
Yeah, but you promised feature Y in August.
Feature Y is not important anymore.
Or you could get into a bigger organization, product
management, all these other people get involved.
And they go, yeah, we lose $100 million here, and da, da, da.
And you start getting into this contest.
But to me, from a mid- to long-term standpoint,
or even a near-term standpoint, if everybody goes, oh my god,
I wish I had thought of this, that last feature really
needs to be considered.
So that's just another twist on the three letters.
Feature LIFO is, to me, the true agile.
It actually is the driver of true agile processes.
And if you have a FIFO process, you'd
have all sorts of agile processes.
But the FIFO receiving, the receiving process
that turns into a FIFO, is heading towards waterfall.
And again, there's all sorts of arguments.
You can have discussions and everything.
It's about the window of time, like I said.
But typically, we would lock down
on a month or a quarterly basis.
I'll go with about 33% of the time.
The thing we started with on my team,
we ended up developing a portion of it, shelving it.
And if we had time, we would do that.
We would squeeze it in.
Now, we had the option of not doing that.
It would depend on timing and everything.
But I did follow that.
I said, shelve it.
Bring it back later.
Can we get it done?
Let's go all out and do that.
So I did try to follow my own thing.
But again, it really depends on the agile flow that you have.
Just to add to what you said, from a creative perspective,
where software is not involved, like the movie industries
where you might be doing animation and stuff,
you probably want to read Creativity, Inc.
It's a book by Ed Kastner, and it
details Pixar's work culture in that.
I don't think he ever calls it agile,
but there are certainly principles of it.
So Creativity, Inc. by Ed Kastner.
Really good book.
Yep.
Great question, though.
Do you have any thoughts on job hopping?
Or once a good time, job hopping?
Not now.
Who would ever do that?
I don't have a ton of thoughts.
I think it realistically, I probably waited too long.
That's always the hindsight.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's true.
It's always the hindsight.
I think it really, again, for me,
and this depends on where you are in your career, to me,
by the time I'm at this stage of my career,
the actual culture and what I can actually
impact in the world is most important to me.
And so it is kind of individual.
It is kind of career-oriented.
I would avoid doing it early.
So I think a reasonable situation, particularly
earlier, the bottom line is the likelihood I've seen
is as earlier in your career, you
would do it a little bit more until you settle in,
because you need that experience.
You need to gain some wisdom, if that's the right word,
or gain some experience.
And yeah, your first job, you are going
to kind of dive in head first.
As much as I gave you all this advice,
it's not going to apply every time or whatever.
So in a technology situation, yeah, I
think three to five years would make sense to a hiring manager.
But if you do do it, if you do, or when you do it,
I should say, not if, your obvious question, why now?
So in a weird way, I would refrain
from calling it job hopping.
I would say it would be career planning.
And so if you kind of get rid of that notion
that it's a job hop for the sake of job hopping,
make it a career decision that could,
just like the movies or whatever,
could be you didn't get that promo,
or you didn't get that internal job, or whatever.
There could be a straw, as you will,
if broke the camel's back, or a feeling that maybe there's
something more you could do out there.
So it's more like have a reasonable reason for doing it,
and then be honest with yourself,
and be as honest as you can be with the employer.
There may be things you can't be honest about,
like, I don't know, something that
would detract from the prior company or whatever that
doesn't look good on you anyway.
And so you do have to be careful.
There are things at a company that you cannot
reveal to your next company, and they
may have to do with people and processes.
That's why I just told you, it's a little bit shaky
that I said I had no validation people.
But it's pretty well known.
I think I said that publicly anyway, and nobody stopped me.
But yeah, make it a career decision.
Make sure that there's an element of that.
Could be I need to move back home,
or I need to move to California, or whatever it is.
Could be a perfectly good reason.
You're not job hopping.
You're life hopping, or life doing it.
But the bottom line is every interviewer, every person,
from the technical person to somebody
you're going to work with, they're going to squeeze in,
why are you leaving your current job?
Just make sure you have a good answer to that,
a good, honest answer to that.
If your resume says you've been changing jobs clockwork
18 months, I'm not hiring you.
It's kind of like that.
I think Rev was here last year.
He did a virtual lecture.
He said at NVIDIA, I don't know if it's true for all of NVIDIA
or just personal opinion, but he said
it takes any new person, regardless
of a new grad or a senior person,
two years to add value to the company.
And if you're not going to stay for two years,
why am I investing my time in you?
That's pretty normal.
One depends on the person and how aligned they are.
Sometimes you get, I happened to hire a perfect person
for Intel, and they were contributing in four weeks.
But they've worked on our technology.
That's one of the beauties of open source,
is if they touched our technology or whatever,
they were able to contribute.
But the average is the fastest people are 12 months.
And the average person, not through their own fault,
but just through the complexity of the company
and the strategies and all that stuff,
you can know all the mission statement and everything.
I just was going through.
I had, what, an hour, new employee orientation
at a high level about what NVIDIA does.
And my brain was ready to explode.
And I'm coming from the largest computational company
in the world and have a pretty good sense of what Intel does.
So anyway, the bottom line is Shizan's right.
Somewhere around the third hop within two years each
will begin to be questioned.
If it's family issues or move, that's
a little bit more explainable as long as they're real.
So don't take it I'm giving you an excuse to say.
And the bottom line is, if by nature
it happened for a good reason, you
just have to be honest about it and maybe be upfront about it.
This is your third hop.
Look, let's get the elephant out of the room.
They'll respect you a ton for that.
One last question before we get going.
I just wanted to ask about why you switched over
from Intel to NVIDIA.
Was there something new?
Yeah, you're not supposed to take my advice
and turn it around.
Was there anything new and interesting
that you were given an opportunity to work on
that you couldn't work on without Intel?
Let me try to answer this delicately.
When you're a more technical senior person than Intel,
I had an interesting dual role as what's
called a senior principal engineer as well
as a senior director.
Actually, NVIDIA would let me do that.
I think for the students here, because they
don't know all the titles and the dynamics,
I think what you're trying to say
is you were both a very senior engineer in your own right,
but you were also people manager.
That is correct.
And I also was a visitor.
So I was a technical leader.
If you're at Intel, to the point,
there's a title called principal engineer, senior principal
engineer, Intel fellow.
The interesting twist with that is
you're not promoted by the company or your manager.
You're promoted by your peers, which is
different than a lot of companies.
So it turns out that peers felt strong enough
about my technical ability to get me a senior principal
engineer.
As a senior director, you're usually
right under the next step as a vice president,
which is the same at NVIDIA.
My next step would be vice president there,
which, of course, it's narrow.
Anyway, to answer your question, I got concerned.
Sort of answer it the same way I told you
what I liked about NVIDIA.
I was concerned that the Intel culture I was used to
didn't go away, but was degrading, was degraded.
I tried in my role to enable it to come back better and work
on that.
I felt that was part of my role.
But I ran into enough challenges.
And at the stage in my career where
I want to do what I said, which is things that actually
impact a large amount of human beings on the planet,
one more time, one last time, if you will.
I am at the towards the end of my career.
But certainly, I don't plan to hop in two years.
But the bottom line is the culture
that NVIDIA presented when I started talking to them
versus the challenges, I'll say, in the traditional Intel
culture, which were understandable.
But in this stage of my career with the time I have left,
I wanted to spend less time trying to figure out
how to fix or recover the Intel culture, which
I think will recover.
NVIDIA seemed, at least so far, to be really committed
to what they're doing.
So their mission statement and their cultural values
is what attracted me.
And it wasn't that easy because I had, I would say,
I actually verbally said, two and a half to three years ago,
I had the best job in the industry.
But that, and then the other thing NVIDIA did
was be honest with me.
And they said, you can't do everything you were doing.
So they said to James Osborne, what do you want to do?
We're going to hire you no matter what.
What would you like to do?
You can be a leader in ray tracing.
You can do this, do this.
So I chose the high-performance computing as the thing
I could do.
And the beauty is, if that doesn't work out,
I'll go do ray tracing or other stuff.
And I'll get to utilize all those skills.
But yeah, the bottom line was, for me
in this stage of my career, the tide, if you will,
or the tide of Intel for me and the position I was in
and the structure and organization they had,
which makes way more difference to a leader, manager, director
level person, the actual environment you're in
and the willingness to allow you to achieve stuff
in the environment makes a huge difference to how much fun
you're having.
And so the bottom line is, I stopped having as much fun
as I liked.
And the rivers flow preventing me
from doing great things was there.
And NVIDIA said, come on over.
We're going to let you do great things.
Good question.
I saw you had a question.
So maybe knock off if there's a quick answer.
Yeah.
There's never a quick answer.
Just something that keeps, I feel
I keep getting at that during all my interviews.
So it feels like sometimes the interviewer is trying to,
is expecting a very specific word for something.
And he's trying to lead you to it.
I feel like I end up explaining everything around it
and not catch that word.
And then when the interviewer points out that word,
I'm like, of course.
I mean, I knew about it.
That's what I meant.
I knew everything about this.
You know what?
I'll say that was a good interviewer, actually,
is what I'll say.
You felt frustrated, but the interviewer
didn't give up on you.
Now, maybe you didn't get the job.
Maybe you're waiting.
Maybe you think that wasn't a big deal or whatever.
I definitely felt that way.
Yeah.
That may have been.
It's usually a collective set of probably miscommunication.
So the issue is a miscommunication
with the wrong, right person, whatever it is, human beings.
Was your interview virtual?
Yes, it was.
I was trying to make sure that I'm asking enough questions
so that I'm trying to get to the answer.
I guess that's the reason.
I've done tons of virtual interviews.
And unfortunately, the lack of direct body language
and you trying to talk to me if I was up on that screen
would be very different than me walking right up
like I'm doing now, right?
So that is a challenge for interviewers and interviewees.
And the lack of that literally 3D,
this goes back to some of the things
that I personally said, whatever it is,
and the whole notion of the metaverse and everything
is people like realism better than they like a flat screen
or whatever.
And that is true.
And your ability to fully communicate with,
even if you're gesturing and everything, whatever it is,
they don't see your torso move.
They don't sense all that stuff.
And so communication is not terrible.
It's 10% diminished, that 10% diminished difference.
So I would simply chalk it up to you're a skilled person.
You're going to do great.
You will have bumps in the road in communication,
personally or not personally, because you're still
a little bit harder virtually, to be honest.
And I applaud the interviewer for drawing it or attempting
to draw it out of you.
At the same time, if you literally said what it was
and you didn't connect the dictionary term to it,
I wasn't there.
So it really would depend on body language and stuff.
But it's a little bit unfair.
But life and interviews are not fair.
And so don't worry about it.
Let it go.
You're going to do great.
I can tell.
So just be confident.
Be honest.
I don't know what word you're going for.
I'm sorry.
And obviously, if they're poking at you,
you don't want to turn them off either.
You don't want to just say, no, I'm not going to answer it.
But just say, hey, we didn't have the right communication
style with each other.
It is what it is.
And unfortunately, you can't talk to the 100 people
you're going to work with at the company.
You're talking to the three of us.
Hopefully, that helps.
So this was great.
Thank you, everybody, for your attention.
And really great to meet you all.
I didn't get it.
I actually pulled this together relatively quickly.
I guess you couldn't tell that.
Right there.
So on Twitter, I am at Jim Jeffers 3D.
I actually changed that recently because I wanted a new name,
because mine was so associated with Intel.
And then so I'm Jim Jeffers 3D there.
I typically go by Jim, but tons of people
connect with me as James L. Jeffers.
And that is what my LinkedIn is.
So linkedin.com slash in slash James L. Jeffers
is another way to contact and communicate with me.
And I really appreciate all your questions and your attention.
And good luck with everything, and if you
think I can help you.
One other advertisement, through a totally different means,
I will be back next Wednesday at the local SIGGRAPH
undergraduate run chapter to either redo or tweak this talk.
So you don't necessarily have to go.
But if you're part of the local UPenn driven SIGGRAPH chapter,
I've been invited to speak there through a totally different
connection, mostly an open source connection in that case.
So it just was a coincidence.
But anyway, feel free to stop on by and say hi.
And again, great to meet you all.
Just before I say thanks, a quick show of hands.
How many of you have job offers from Inverdeer?
So your future colleagues.
How many might have job offers from Inverdeer?
I only wanted to check future colleagues of yours.
Yeah.
I don't know what I'm doing right now, to be truly honest.
So even somebody as long term in everything I've done,
I've got my year or two that I've got to put under my belt.
Hopefully, I'm at least contributing.
Maybe not making an ROI in the next three months or so.
Maybe after the holidays and to Q1.
But yeah, feel free to reach out if I
can connect you with the right people, the right interest.
I'll show you info on our class board
so that anybody who has interview advice
or wants to reach out for a reference.
Say hi.
I will do my best.
Interestingly, I am not the only Intel person
who has joined Inverdeer in the last three years,
including four from my own team, left,
as much as I've been to come to stay.
And other people, and of course, I
have a sort of an industry presence.
But I'll try to help you any way I can.
I do happen to be, from what I can tell,
highly related to what they call an Inverdeer dev tech.
That is not the people who make the actual products.
It is the Inverdeer engineering team
that works with third party companies and customers
to enable CUDA, enable Omniverse, enable that stuff.
It's a pretty cool but customer facing job.
Sometimes they like you to have a little more experience,
but sometimes it's in a team atmosphere.
So while I actually know quite well
the leader of ray tracing named Steve Parker
and several people in that org, yeah, to the extent I can,
I will at least help you connect the dots.
And like I said, anything I do, a question
you forgot to ask or something occurs to you
and you think I can help, book up with me on LinkedIn
or whatever and direct message me or something.
All right.
With that, thank you, Jim.
Thank you for your time.
Thanks, everyone.
Thank you.