Hi everyone. Welcome to the class today. Unfortunately, I'm not able to be there in person because
I've had some emergency travel come up. So what I'm going to do is I'm going to record
this lecture and we'll watch it in the class. You know, the TAs will host this.
The kind of the happy mistake here is that this lecture makes for a really good recording
because it's very theoretical. We don't necessarily discuss CUDA and stuff in this lecture. What
we're going to be doing is looking at the history of how CPU architecture worked and
how that has influenced how GPUs work. And we're kind of going to build our own CIS 565
GPU in this lecture. So let's take a look at how all of it plays together.
Starting off with a couple of acknowledgments. And then so this wall of GPU history that
was done at Microsoft, I came across this, I believe on either Twitter or LinkedIn. And
it really showed how graphics cards have evolved. To the left is everything in the 90s. And
what's in focus closest to the camera is GPUs in 2008. And you can see the 8400 GS from
NVIDIA kind of highlighted there. And that's really where CUDA started. That was one of
the first CUDA GPUs. And we've seen the evolution since about how GPUs have grown. So it gives
you a sense of GPUs are not just modern technology. They've come a very, very long way. And have
been inspired from many generations of architecture and redesign.
So a couple of things to look at first. So GPUs and CPUs, the performance, the compute
performance at least, is measured in what is known as flops. Floating point operations
per second. So this is essentially what you're measuring as the amount of multiplication
and addition operations that you can do in the GPU. So this is calculated using how many
gigaflops or teraflops we have, at least today. Back in the day, it would have been megaflops.
Before that, it would have probably been just flops or kiloflops. So modern day GPUs certainly
operate in the teraflop range. Supercomputers operate in the petaflops, if not the exaflops.
So one of Intel's big goals is to make an exaflop supercomputer. So that's essentially
10 to the power of 18 gigaflops per second. Which is absolutely incredible. The amount
of compute power at our fingertips would be incredible. So let's take a look at some modern
hardware and how many teraflops they have. So the slides are a couple of years older,
so you may not see the most modern Intel, NVIDIA, AMD hardware, but it's still representative of
of what the trends are essentially. So an AMD Ryzen 9 3900X was one and a half teraflops,
an Intel i9 9900K, which was top of the line CPU about two generations ago, was 1.22 teraflops.
An NVIDIA GPU, again, a couple of years old, an RTX GPU was 16.32 teraflops. That's almost
10 to 12 times about what the Intel and AMD CPUs are producing. Again, remember that this is in
terms of compute performance. If you take the standard work that CPUs do in terms of running
the operating system and stuff, you're not going to be able to get that same performance. But if
you do algorithms that are really driven for parallel computing, then you're going to be able
to maximize all the gigaflops, both on the CPU and the GPU, but you're going to see a bigger gain
on the GPU. Similarly, this kind of scaling is happening on system monochip hardware as well. So
whether it's the Tegra, the Jetsons, or the Drive PX that NVIDIA is building, we are seeing the
same kind of scaling happening where GPUs are able to provide a lot more compute performance.
While I don't have it in these slides, I'm pretty sure that's the same with
Apple's ARM architectures where they have the CPU and the GPU on the same chip.
You're going to see the same numbers and the same trends on there too.
So if you look at the way these trends are happening, you can see that there's been
an explosion since around 2008, 2011, when GPUs really started taking off compared to the CPU.
You can see how single precision and double precision performance for Intel CPUs are in
the blue. And then with NVIDIA GPUs, it's just keeping rising up. Of course, the data here
probably ends around 2016, but even then the trends have certainly continued to expand there.
And on the theoretical bandwidth side, you can still see how the bandwidth rate is increasing as
well. With CPUs, we are seeing DDR4, DDR5 kind of memories coming into play on the CPU side,
but GPUs are already on DDR5, DDR5 high bandwidth, stacking multiple memory vertically. And all of
those things are giving GPUs really high bandwidth as well. And with PCIe expanding. So PCIe4 is
kind of standard now, PCIe5 we'll probably see in the next year or two, and PCIe6 is essentially
getting standardized as we speak. So those are essentially, with each generation are doubling
the amount of bandwidth you get from copying data from CPU to the GPU. So what that means is if you
had a PCIe3 bus between the CPU and the GPU, that would have given you somewhere around 16
gigabytes per second of overall bandwidth to copy your CPU data to the GPU. Whereas with PCIe4,
you essentially double that bandwidth. So now you can copy CPU to GPU faster, which means the
overhead of using GPUs for improving your compute is becoming lower and lower every day.
So Flops is great, but we also have to put it into context. One of the main things that we have
to think about is power and heat limits. We can't be, especially in today's world, we have to be
conscious of how much energy we are using in terms of the hardware we run and what algorithms we are
running on that hardware. Single core performance, if you measure it, has kind of been, while the
number is increasing, it's kind of been slowing down given how power and heat limits are changing.
You have an ultra ultra thin laptop that needs heat dissipation, you're probably getting a slower
clock rate on your CPU. So just examples like that. And then GPUs also, we are starting to see
how the die size or how big your chips are, how much power they use, what it costs, especially
over the last couple of years, has really changed the dynamic of what the cost benefit analysis of
GPU performance also is. The other thing to think about is how this works in mobile.
When you have a mobile phone and a battery installed, that's when performance for what
becomes really important, where optimizing it for saving battery and doing proper compute and
using it efficiently becomes really, really important. So let's take a look at what are
the major components of a CPU, more in theoretical terms, but essentially understanding how a CPU is
divided, what are the considerations that go into making a CPU? And this kind of gets into
computer architecture class, but we'll try to keep it brief and at a high level,
but essentially all leading into how GPUs are developed.
So in a lightly threaded desktop application, some of the most common ones are Vim, which is
my favorite editor. LS is essentially the list of files commands on Linux. What you're going to see
is a lot of these commands and operations are likely threaded. They likely have a lot of branches
and they access a lot of memory. So these are some numbers that were run by Warren Semple back in the
day about how much memory access, how many branches, and how much actual compute these
kind of commands are doing. So if you look at this, vector instructions, which is kind of the
instructions that GPUs are really good at, is 1% or less than 1% of the overall compute.
And that's really interesting because what that says is the job of running a command on the CPU
is not necessarily always about the highest performance. It's also about how do you manage
all the branching, memory access, and other things that you have to do.
So a simple CPU core probably at its fundamental looks something like this. You have five stages,
which are fetch, decode, execute, memory, and write back. For anybody who's done
compute architecture, this probably looks very familiar to you. And what happens is all of these
steps occur in one clock period. So once the clock updates, you're going to get all of these
instructions happening at once. So just to go over a quick overview of what each of these means,
fetch is fetching the next instruction that is to be executed. So this can be an add, a multiply,
a read operation, a write operation. So those are all fetches. Decode is taking the assembly
and decoding it into an actual instruction that the hardware can understand. Execute is actually
executing that instruction. Memory is writing that result into a register. And then write back
is anything that needs to go back and then get then to the program counter for the next iteration.
Essentially, what this simple architecture shows is really bad utilization,
where you have all of this running for one command in one clock cycle. Until this
entire thing finishes for one command, you cannot update the clock cycle. So it gives really bad
clock utilization, essentially. So one of the solutions to this is kind of breaking this apart,
where you break the pipeline into different segments. So you have a memory segment,
a register file, an ALU segment, a data and memory segment, and a register file segment.
And what this allows you to do is have instruction level parallelism. So each part of this pipeline
can be executing a different instruction at a different clock cycle. So if something is in the
data mem cycle, there can be another instruction that's in the ALU part, and another instruction
that's in a reg file part. So this essentially gives you pipelining, where as soon as one
instruction is done, everything moves to the next step. So what this provides is essentially
an instruction level parallelism that significantly improves the clock speed.
It reduces how much time any instruction is waiting. So at all times, you can have multiple
instructions running at once. It does, however, increase latency. So sometimes if instructions
are taking too long to execute, something's going to be waiting before it can get executed.
It also increases the number of transistors and gates you need, and it also increases your chip
size, because now you have different control structures in place, and now you need to
dedicate transistors to those control structures. The other thing that this can cause is an issue
with dependent instructions. So what happens if an instruction that's getting executed depends on
an instruction that may happen before, or may have happened a lot earlier? How do you take care
of that? That's one thing. The other thing is branches. While it's all good that we can execute
multiple instructions in line, what is the next instruction depends on an Intel's condition,
where you have to pick which branch you want to execute. So that makes a lot of difference here.
So to give you some sense of how many stages there are, Intel Core 2 CPU had 14 stages back
in the day. So I'm talking a long time ago. A Pentium 4 had 20 stages, and modern architectures
probably have somewhere in between that. So essentially, this kind of pipelining, and I'm
showing a very simple version of it here, is what allows for very, very high clock cycles these days.
So now if we take a look at branches, and how they might execute, we don't know what instructions
will execute after the branch, until the branch is executed. So you don't know which instruction
is next, until you actually hit the if-else part, or if-equals part. So J equals is that equal
checking on the loop. So we could either stall it, and not execute any instructions until that
branch is executed, or we can speculate, and try to decide which one is likely to execute.
And then if something fails, then we just throw all of that information away and start again.
So a very common way of thinking about this is, if you have a for loop that's going from
0 to 100, 100 times, the branch prediction is going to go one way, where it's going to be like,
OK, continue for loop, continue for loop, increment, continue for loop. But on the 100th iteration,
it's going to fail. But if you're trying to optimize our performance on a CPU, it's better to
predict correctly 100 times, and fail once, than it is to wait and stall every single time for 100
times. So that's kind of what we get here, because of branch prediction.
So modern day CPUs are actually very, very good at this. Most of the time, you get 90% accuracy.
This is helped by both compilers and hardware level logic. This improves performance,
as well as energy efficiency. However, the downside is that now the chips are bigger.
You're dedicating more and more transistors into being better hardware branch predictors.
So now, the efficiency of compute per transistor is probably decreased. It also probably increases
the fetch stage latency, because now you're in different branch predictors, and you're trying
to do different things. And then, lastly, is security concerns. A few of you may have been
either probably in your freshman year, or a little before that, when Spectre and Meltdown
were the talk of the town about how, at the very core hardware level, these issues existed,
where they could provide hackers the ability to get in by reading memory that they shouldn't have
access to. And how that happened is essentially because of branch prediction, where at the
hardware level, the chips were executing instructions that were kind of in the future.
That is, they were executing instructions based on branch prediction, assuming that they would
just throw away the results later on. But what that allowed potential hackers or security loopholes is
you could write a branch prediction that went one way all the time. And then, when the CPU trusted
it enough, then you tried to access bad memory through it. So of course, I'm doing a very bad
job of explaining the core part of the security. I'm not necessarily a security person. But
essentially, that's what led to the hardware level issues, and weren't fixed by any operating system.
Intel actually had to build it into the new chip so that these kind of issues didn't happen
in the future. So looking at memory hierarchies, so some of this we've discussed in the class from
a CUDA perspective. But let's look at it from the CPU perspective as well. Essentially, the
philosophy is, as the memory gets larger, it also gets slower. So in rough numbers, if you had SRAM,
which is our L1, L2, L3 cache on the CPU, you're going to have very, very fast bandwidth because
it's literally located near the CPU. But you're going to get very, very small size. Even modern
CPUs have somewhere between 1 to 20 megabytes of L1, L2, L3 cache. Now from there, if you go into
DRAM, which is your regular 16 GB, 32 GB memory that you have in your laptop, that's going to be
somewhere between 15 to 40, depending on whether you have DDR3, DDR4, et cetera. So you get more
memory, almost 1,000 times more memory, but you're also reducing how fast you can access it.
And then from there, if you keep increasing a flash or a solid state drive, even NVMe,
NVMe is slightly faster, but not reflected here, you're going to get significantly more sizes where
it's anywhere from 256 GB these days to four terabytes. And your speed is probably going to be
in the hundreds of megabytes if you're on a regular SSD. And if you have an NVMe that's running over
PCI, then you're probably getting into the one terabyte or, sorry, one gigabyte or up to four
gigabytes per second. And finally, if you're on a traditional spinning hard disk, which are still
very, very much used these days, you're going to get somewhere in the low 100 megabytes per second
read and write speed. So essentially the larger you get, the more time you're spending on actually
trying to find where the memory exists. That's where the latency happens. It's not in actually
reading the memory, but it's in the memory bus about how the actual physical architecture,
how fast can it read the memory. And it's also in finding where the memory exists. So if you're
building up a cache and stuff, you're going to access it faster. If you don't have that cache,
you actually need to physically spin this in the case of hard disks, it's going to be a lot slower.
So in the case of caching, what we are essentially doing is keeping the most important data as close
as we need. So that the most frequently accessed data is the fastest to get. So what we are
essentially doing is exploiting temporal locality, which is if your data is likely to be used again.
So for example, again, if we go back to the for loop example, if you're doing the same operations
over and over, it's best to cache those results. And then you're also doing spatial locality.
Again, using that for loop example, if you're trying to add two arrays, the CPU and the compiler
can predict that after index I, the next iteration is going to access I plus one and the next
iteration is going to access I plus two and so on. So what it can do is predictably, it can fetch all
of that continuous memory into a cache and store it. So now you don't have to copy it each time
into the cache. So taking a look at the cache hierarchy, what you're going to see is something
like this, where L1 is the actual instruction and data caches. So in CUDA, this would essentially be
the same as registers. L2 would be unified cache and L3 would be slightly bigger unified
cache, but probably distributed across the cores. And then away from the chip itself,
you get main memory and of course, hard disk drives.
So let's take a look at what some CPU architectures actually look like. So this is
an actual image of an Intel CPU conceptually. Now, you can probably identify some parts and
others, but let's see what it actually breaks up into. If you have any predictions, put that
in your mind so that when I go to the next screenshot, let's compare about how it comes out.
So this is how the chip actually breaks up. You have this huge L3 cache here and that's where
you know how CPUs and GPUs are different. You have about six to eight cores here,
depending on how many they're going to enable. And then you have a lot of IO controllers and
memory controllers along with them. So what I want to really highlight here is the ratio of
the transistors that are dedicated to compute, which is the core parts, and the amount of
transistors dedicated to memory and memory controllers. So it's a huge percentage. So
only about 25% of the time is just in the L3 cache.
And once we go a little further, I'm going to show you how it looks on GPUs.
So this is on a more modern CPU, so it's an i9-9900. Again, we're going to see something
very similar here, where you have a lot of this dedicated to CPU cores and a lot of it in the L3
caches. And then you have some transistors dedicated to GPU and media. The reason it's
written GPU and media because a lot of the transistors here are also dedicated to things
like video decoding and video editing and those kinds of things. So those are built on a hardware
as well. So now let's see how we can go about improving the pipeline that we had. So we spoke
about how you can add different stages to the pipeline so that you can exploit instruction
level parallelism. But there's another type of parallelism that we can extract, which is
scalar or super scalar in the way, where you're not just doing the same pipeline,
but you're making two pipelines that derive from the same instruction register. So now,
if you have one pipeline that's running in the top half, you can have another one
running in the bottom half. So this way, you're increasing the pipeline width, essentially.
So this can get into something like scheduling and reordering. So let's take this example.
We have four registers here, or four instructions, sorry. XOR, add, subtract, and add increment.
Notice that add is dependent on XOR. So it's called read after write. So essentially,
the XOR always needs to happen before the add here. So XOR R1 plus R2, you get R3. And then
the result of R3 is used in the add. Subtraction and add i are dependent. So they are read after
write again. So subtraction R5 minus R2, you get R3. And then R3 is read here.
And finally, XOR and sub. So this XOR and this sub are not dependent at all, but they're write
after write. So depending on what order you do them in, you could potentially be getting into
race conditions. But they are not necessarily dependent on each other. So let's see how we
can optimize this. So how about we change this so that we are using a few more registers.
So consider this. So XOR, P1 and P2 goes into P6. And P6 is still used in the add operation,
and you get P6, P4 into P7. So XOR and add are still dependent. But for subtract, we change it.
We do P5 and P2, again, same as before. But we now write it into P8. Instead of writing into
the same register as the XOR result, we write it into a new register. And then that register gets
used in add i. So you can have P8, 1 into P9. So now what we are essentially doing is XOR and sub
can execute in parallel. And then add and add i can execute in parallel. So the first two instructions
and the second two instructions are completely independent of each other.
So that's essentially what is called out of order execution, where you're giving the CPU
and the compiler permission to reorder the instructions based on the order that you're
providing. So that's why it's always important, even in CUDA, to have memory operations and
compute operations kind of next to each other so that the GPU can optimize them if needed.
So this workflow is kind of the way that reordering happens. And there's a reorder
buffer to keep track of status of the in-flight instructions, because we can't just freehand
modify things as we want. We actually have to keep track of the results and which instructions
have executed and which have not. So that also drives into having an actual issue queue and a
scheduler, which chooses the next instruction. So it needs to have some smarts about how it
predicts which operations are dependent and independent and picking the next instruction
to put on the schedule. So on the CPU, now going from CPU from one pipeline into actually
parallelizing the CPU, we've covered instruction-level parallelism, where you can have
superscalar and out of order. And then you can have data-level parallelism. So that's vectors,
and we'll get to that on the next slide. And finally, we'll have thread-level parallelism. So
you'll have simultaneous multi-threading, which we are all very used to in modern-day CPUs. And we
also get multi-core. That's essentially what Intel and AMD have thrived on more recently.
So let's take a look at vector. So if you take a look at this for loop, what we see is this is
going from int i equals 0, i less than n, i plus plus. And it's doing the same operation over and
over. If you imagine this in an assembly language, what you're going to see is something like
execute the for loop, or execute the assignment, execute the condition, execute the statement,
execute the increment, execute the condition, then you execute the statement again,
then increment, then condition, and then the statement again. So these three steps
kind of keep repeating each other. But what if you were able to take advantage of something
that we've spoken about in GPU land, essentially? And that's SIMD. So single instruction,
multiple data. So what if you changed your for loop to be something like this, where you increment
by 4, but you add more instructions explicitly? So now you know that this n is not maybe a multiple
of 4, or you're not going to have invalid memory accesses. So now you can explicitly write these
instructions, as shown in red, so that you're doing more compute and less condition checking.
So now it can execute faster without the overhead of that increment and checks for every single
for loop iteration. So that essentially allows us to have more ALU computation,
and also needs more memory, but eventually makes our performance faster.
So some examples of vector instructions in modern architectures are SSE2, where you have four white
packed floats and packed integer instructions. So these are essentially things like operating
on VEC4s and VEC3s that can be really optimized, because you're not doing it as a vector operation.
AVX is the modern version of SSE2. So now you can do eight white packed floats and
integer instructions. And that's in the more modern Intel and AMD hardware.
So that's about vector instructions, where you are essentially taking
the same instruction, but multiple data, and executing it within the same clock cycle.
And then we have thread level parallelism, where you can have, in your program, you can define
multiple threads and what they should do. And this is more on the software level. So it's more
controlled by the developers and the programmers who are writing the code. So we have to manage
about how, which instructions they execute, what the algorithms are, and stuff like that.
And then on simultaneous multi-threading, these instructions can be issued from multiple threads,
and they require a partitioning of the reorder buffer. So you have different parts of the reorder
buffer working on different threads. And what they allow you to do is not necessarily duplicate the
hardware, but they take up more cache and execution resources, because now they have
to track different things from different threads simultaneously. So while it reduces single-threaded
performance, it can really improve multi-threaded performance because of that additional hardware
that's there to optimize it. And finally, on multicore, what we are seeing is, especially
since AMD's Threadripper CPUs came out, there's a huge increase in the number of cores that the
hardware companies are putting into the CPUs. So for example, Intel's latest architecture,
they come with that big little architecture where they have, let's say, four to six
efficient CPUs. So these are CPUs that are going to run under low performance loads,
but be really amazing with battery life. So essentially, performance per watt is really,
really good. And then you have four to six big cores where the performance is really good,
but you don't care as much about how much power you're consuming. So for example,
in gaming workloads or high-performance computing workloads, it's going to take the same thing that
you were doing. It's going to realize quickly, oh, my program needs to run on the higher performance
CPUs. So it's going to take that, move it from the efficient cores onto the high-performance cores,
and that's going to use up more battery life, but you'll get your results faster as well.
So in these cores, what you're essentially getting is full cores, duplicating the
hardware essentially, and no resource sharing other than the L3 cache at most points. It's
easier to take advantage of that in Mozilla because you can essentially copy-paste each core,
any number of times on the chip, as long as you can control the chip size.
What you decrease or don't get so much off is the utilization because you have all of this
independent cores now. They can't always talk to each other in the most efficient way,
so you get a little bit less utilization. So concluding the CPU part, so CPUs are essentially
optimized for sequential programming, and of course, a little bit for multi-threaded programming,
but they're essentially programmed for multi-threaded versions of sequential programming,
where you have pipelines, branch predictions, superscalar, out-of-order execution, lots of
human-controlled workflows essentially. And to reduce that execution time, we are increasing
the clock speed and trying to increase the utilization. Memory is always a problem because
you're going to have different levels of cache and different levels of memory, but always that bus
width and the speed is going to be a limitation to how much parallelism and compute we can extract
from that. So for modern-day architectures, modern-day CPUs, you're going to get anywhere
from 4 to 12 to 16, maybe 32 threads on the highest-end architectures, but how do you get to
32,000 threads or 64,000 threads that modern-day GPUs are able to execute? So let's take a look at
that. So essentially, going back to this chart from before, we are asking, how did this happen?
How are we going from, in 2005 and 2007, GPUs and CPUs being relatively close to each other
in terms of performance to this huge gap that we see today? So let's take a look at what kind of
workloads GPUs handle, both in terms of algorithms and their use cases, to make this kind of
scaling possible. So the first and very common use case is, of course,
rendering of triangles and pixels. Very, very popular. You have millions of triangles and
you're generally applying the same operation to them, the same world coordinate transformations,
the same normal maps and other things. So again, single instruction, multiple data really applies.
For pixels and fragments, rendering things on the screen, again, if you have your rasterization
algorithm, it's going to be very similar for all the pixels. If you're applying different filters,
different shaders, that's going to have, again, those single instructions, but you're applying
them to many, many, many pixels at the same time. So very, very parallel workloads.
So let's take a look at how GPUs have essentially evolved in rendering triangles and vertices
since the early days of gaming. So one of the first and biggest computer games was,
of course, Wolfenstein 3D and then Doom 1, both by id Software. This was all software rendering.
There was nothing like a GPU back then. It was all very, very primitive CPUs. And using
software code to make sure that we are able to render the right things at the right time.
So for Wolf 3D, it's all a 2.5D game. There's no actual 3D here. There's no ceiling or floor,
if you notice. It's all gray. There's no height changes. It's all on the same floor.
There's no rolling walls. There's no lighting. It's all flat shading. And the other thing you'll
notice, which you may or may not have until today, is the enemies, the agents that you kill,
are always facing you. They're never facing away from you. So that's why things like raycasting
and pre-computed texture coordinates work in this game. Of course, with Doom 1, now you had
this built on the BSP tree by Bruce Naylor. You have texture maps on all the surfaces,
including the floor and the ceiling. You have lighting, so you can see how the light from the
top is showing on the floor. You have different floors, so you can go up and down. You have
rolling walls. So you can see even within the span of a year of how the game evolved.
And if you want to read more about its software and how the early days of gaming really evolved
and how they came up with these algorithms, I'd recommend you read the book called Masters of
Doom. It's an amazing book, especially if you love gaming. You get a lot of history of
its software and other games. And I definitely recommend it.
So why GPU? So we are definitely seeing the workloads that are amassing parallel,
both in terms of data parallelism as well as pipeline parallelism. And there are also CPUs
and GPUs being different chips and being asynchronous to each other. They can also
execute in parallel. However, not everything is improved by making GPUs software programmable.
So when we are programming CUDA cores, they're essentially software programmable cores
where you can write code to execute on them. There is still space on our chips for hardware level
fixed function hardware, essentially, as it's called. So these are for texture filtering,
therefore rasterization, where you can change the states and change the different parameters that
are fed into these algorithms. But you can't necessarily program the algorithm. You can't
program the fixed function units of these fixed function hardware, essentially. So that's why
you're still going to have some compute that's fixed function and has dedicated transistors that
are not programmable. But they provide significant performance improvements without necessarily
giving access to the whole algorithm or to the user. And then beyond graphics, you get a lot of
different things we can do. We've already looked at matrix multiply in the first classes. You can
do cloud simulation, high simulation, particle systems. Nowadays, you can do machine learning and
computer vision and other things. So GPUs are used for a lot more than just graphics and simulation.
So let's start now building what I call the CIS 565 GPU. And in reality, it's the beyond
programmable shading course GPU from SIGGRAPH 2011. But let's say we are building the 565 GPU
inspired by that. So here's a very simple shader. Those of you who've done CIS 460, 461 should be
very familiar with this. The specific code that's here is not very important. What I want to share
is that this code applies to millions of pixels at the same time. So let's say you have a 4K
screen that is 3840 by 2160, you get probably about 8 million pixels, somewhere around that.
So these same operations, literally these four lines of code are being applied to 8 million pixels
at the same time. So now you can see how this kind of becomes similar to a kernel that we write
in CUDA where you have, let's say your matrix, and you're doing the same operations for the
entire matrix. So let's see how this works. The first thing we have to do is take the shader and
compile it into assembly language, something that the GPU can understand. And the input to that
is going to be one unshaded fragment or a pixel. And then the output is going to be,
after applying all the operations, you're going to get a shaded fragment. It's going to be colored
or it's going to have transparency and other things. But essentially, that's the function
where you have one pixel, you run the shader, and you get one pixel out. And to execute this,
what you're going to have is this kind of very simple ALU fetch decode and execution context.
So the fetch decode essentially gets the instruction, the ALU executes it,
and the execution context stores all the memory. So we can go through the different lines and
stuff. So line by line, it's going to execute that. So if we take a look at the CPU before
the multi-core era, so essentially in the generation of single cores, what you had was
this, you had the fetch decode, you had a small ALU unit, you had some execution context,
and you had a huge data cache. So we've seen L1, L2, L3, but of course, not all of them existed
back then. Maybe you had L1 and L2, but they were still very, very large compared to how much
compute you had, how much ALU you had. And then you had the out-of-order logic, the fancy branch
predictor, the memory prefetcher, so that you're able to do all the optimizations around a single
instruction rather than parallelize multiple instructions at the same time. So keep this in
mind. I want you to keep this kind of high-level diagram about what a single-core pre-multi-core
CPU kind of looked like and how the components were essentially divided.
So let's take this and let's start working on it, because this is essentially what they had in the
90s, right? And we want to take what they had in the 90s and build a GPU out of it. So let's
take this and change a few ideas here. So the first idea is that we want to increase transistors
count, make the chip essentially bigger so that we can add more cores to it. So rather than using
transistors to increase the branch predictors and the out-of-order execution, let's add more ALU
units essentially. So that's the first idea. And this is essentially within a core. So if you get
two cores, this is what it looks like. You have the fetch ALU at execution context,
but you have two of those now. So you can produce two fragments in parallel. Why stop at two? Let's
go to four. So now you can produce four pixels in parallel. Again, no need to stop there. Let's go to
16. Now you see how having a lot of ALUs with execution context and their own instruction
decode is essentially going to help produce multiple fragments at parallel.
But many fragments should be able to share the same instruction stream. So if I go back here,
maybe one step back, all of these units have their own fetch and decode. But what we discussed
is that all of these pixels and fragments are essentially executing the same instruction.
So we should ask ourselves, is there a need for a fetch decode for all of them to have it
independently? Or can we combine them into one? So essentially that's what this slide gets to
is instead of suggesting that we have fetch decode per ALU, why not combine a bunch of ALUs
and have one fetch decode? So let's see how that might work. So you have a simple processing core,
but let's change this a little bit. So we said we want to have fetch decode for one,
but have many ALUs, right? So that's what our idea two is. So we have one fetch decode.
In this case, eight ALUs. And then the context is now subdivided. We have eight contexts for each
of the ALUs, and then we have a shared context. What does this start looking like? Especially
the shared part of it. It starts looking like how we have blocks in CUDA, where if you think about
the threads, each thread has its own registers that are private to each, so its own context.
And then there's shared memory. So there's a shared context that all the threads can access.
So now you start getting the picture of how these things relate.
So this is idea two. Let's see how we modify the shader with this. So we can take the same
instruction from our shader, bring it into fetch decode, and all the ALUs now execute the same
instruction on different inputs, and then produce different outputs. The instructions remain the
same. The memory and the context changes. So now we have what is essentially one core,
but it has eight ALUs in it. So let's see how we can take this a step further.
How about we do 128 in parallel, where you can have taking this concept essentially where you
have eight ALUs and one core, and you make 16 cores out of them. So now you can do 16 times
eight is 128. You can do 128 fragments in parallel. So now, again, we start seeing how this is leading
up to code architectures essentially. So in terms of doing our traditional workflows of
rendering vertices, fragments, primitives, and even compute work items. I wrote OpenCL work items
but they can be certainly any form of parallel compute. You can divide these up into different
cores. Remember that within each core you want to be the same instructions,
but different cores can be executing different kinds of instructions. So that's where you can
grow the parallelism. So now, given what we designed about these GPUs here, or the GPU
cores here, where we have the 16 cores and each of them have eight ALUs, what do we do about
branches? This is kind of foreshadowing what we already spoke about in CUDA, but it's well worth
repeating it here. So let's say we have our eight ALUs within each core and we are going to execute
this shader code that has a branch in it. So the first evaluation is to check if each of those
eight cores has a true or false statement in it. And some can have true and some can have false.
And in that case, those three threads that are true are going to execute while the false
statements wait. And then the false statements are going to execute while the true one waits.
So just like we spoke about in CUDA, this is not ideal, but sometimes it may need to be done and
we should try to minimize this case. The worst-case scenario is that each core takes a different path
and now you get one-eighth the peak performance. So instead of all the ALUs executing the
same operation, you get all the ALUs executing different operations. So that's the worst-case
scenario. We don't want to do that. So simply processing, just for a clarification,
does not necessarily imply SIMD instructions. So with explicit vector instructions, so SSE AVX,
you get what is essentially vector instructions. But the second way, which is more of what the GPU
is, is KLAN instructions and hardware vectorization, where the cores essentially create
the parallelism that you need. It's kind of like what we discussed in matrix multiply, where
the for loops disappear and become implicit within the threads of the blocks we launch.
So the other thing we should discuss along with branch divergence is stalls,
which is also something we discussed in the CUDA lectures, is about how
memory is read and what happens when we wait. So what we want to do along with our course,
back to designing the GPU. So let's take our course and add an L1 cache that's small,
but super high speed, an L2 cache that's slightly larger, but slower speed, and a big L3 cache that
is shared with all of them that might be more larger, but slower than L1, L2, but still faster
than the memory. And then you have a bus between the memory and the GPU itself. And when I say
memory, it's more on the CPU side. So this bus kind of becomes the PCIe, et cetera.
So now we always have to discuss about how we reduce that latency. In the CUDA lectures,
in matrix multiply, we've seen how we should have more threads to cover that performance
essentially. So to do that, what we want to do is interleave the processing of fragments
in our building the GPU example. We want to interleave the processing of fragments
into a single core so that it avoids stalls and we get low latency essentially.
So the way to do that is to take our fragment shader and divide it into parts of groups of
threads, kind of like this is essentially where we get to the idea of warps. So if we take our warp
and have eight ALUs execute the first part until it hits a stall, we are going to make it,
what we essentially want is if this hits a stall, we want the next batch of threads to be able to
run right away with zero latency between the switch. So we get a stall, we launch the next
next group of threads. Of course, because we are executing the same instructions,
now batch two is going to hit a stall and same with batch three and batch four. But what we want
is that once batch four hits a stall, another batch should be able to run. In this case,
it would be batch one because batch one has finished its stall, it's ready to run. And as
soon as batch four hits a stall, batch one is ready to run. So in this way, what we essentially
get is instead of one starting here, stalling, becoming runnable, then runs again, and then
two instead of starting here, starts down here. Instead of doing that, we get a more
waterfall approach to it. So we are saving a lot of latency that's happening in between these stalls.
So essentially, while it may slightly increase the runtime of one group, because you see how
it becomes runnable, but it may have to wait a little bit. But the overall runtime of all of
these different warps is much faster, because now they can all execute in this waterfall model
instead of all having to execute sequentially. So now what we've changed is instead of
each core with eight ALUs executing eight fragments each, so they had eight contacts
and they were running eight fragments, now we want them to run 32 fragments on the same eight ALUs.
What do we need for that? We need more memory so that we can store all of those contacts,
and they become very, very fast to switch. So this is the change we're making now. We have
the fetch decode, we have the eight ALUs, and we make our storage much larger. But we don't
make the storage much larger by simple mechanism. What we want to do is we want to subdivide it.
So we subdivide it by this. We create these subparts to it, where each group has its own
contacts and shared memory, and now you can have different contacts and shared memory.
So when one goes out for a stall, another one is ready to switch in directly. So in this case,
you can have 18 very small contacts, you can have, in this case, 12 medium contacts,
or you can have four very large contacts with the same amount of memory. You can kind of
swap them in and out. So if we go back to something like this, what we're essentially
seeing from, let's say, coming from the CUDA perspective, is how you have this fetch decode,
you have your ALUs, which are the actual execution units, and then you have the memory
that's sitting in the SM, and what it's providing for that zero overhead switching of different warps.
So now in our example chip, what I want to do is, before I get to the math that's on the left side,
I want to show you how this relates to our CUDA architecture. So if you imagine, each of these
essentially becomes a streaming multiprocessor. So where you have each SM had its own scheduler
and instruction controller, it had many, many cores, while in our example, we may only have
eight ALUs, and SM can have 128 or 192 cores within each. So that's how many threads it can
run at the same time. And then the memory that's within each SM is essentially allowing us to
swap out those warps and blocks as needed, so that the compute of that SM is always occupied.
So that's essentially how it relates to the CUDA side of things. And that's also why
shared memory is shared only within the block and not across all the SMs, because
the shared memory is going to be living inside these memory banks that don't necessarily
communicate across the SMs. So we have SM, we have the instruction and fetch decode,
we have the memory, and that's allowing us to switch context really fast. And then we have
the ALUs and the cores, which are actually doing the instruction.
So now, if this is our CIS 565 GPUs, we have 16 cores, or in the case of CUDA,
we would call these SMs. We would have eight multiply and add units per core, so 128 total.
And we can have 16 simultaneous instruction streams, because we have 16 cores here.
And with that, if we have, let's say, four warps per core, we can have 64 concurrent,
but interleaved instruction streams. So how we have that waterfall model, if each SM can
house four contexts, so you have the four purple memory banks here, if they can each handle four,
that means we can have four contexts that can switch right away. So four times 16 is 64
concurrent instruction streams. And a total of that is 512 fragments. So you can have 64 times
eight fragments running at any given time. So overall, if you're running 512 fragments,
that leads to 256 gigaflops if your clock rate is one gigahertz.
The way to calculate this is you take 500 concurrent fragments, multiply that by
the clock cycle. In each clock cycle, you can essentially do
one floating point operation. So you multiply that, and then you multiply the clock rate.
So depending on that and how many clock cycles it needs, you'd get to 256 gigaflops.
So that's the kind of math here. So that's how we've designed our 565 GPU.
So if we compare the CPU and GPU memory architectures, on the CPU, we can have,
you know, we have different cores with ALUs. But on the GPU, we'll have very, very large cores,
but they have a lot more ALUs, and probably slightly more execution context, and some
fixed function memory as well. And then you have an L2 cache, and then you have a huge memory bus
to our GPU memory. Whereas on the CPU, you have this DDR3 RAM that's about 20 to 30 GB.
But on GPUs, this is 177 architecture. It's an old slide. It's from 2014. Modern day GPUs can
get anywhere from 600 to 700 gigabytes per second. So you get this huge bus between
the global memory and the caches on the GPU. So as a thought experiment,
if our job was to do element-wise multiplication of two vectors,
the way to do this is for each element, we are going to be doing read A, read B,
compute A times B, and store the result in C. So those four instructions with three memory
operations, 12 bytes, and GTX 480 could do 480 multiplications per clock at 1.4 gigahertz. So
you have 1.4 billion, essentially, times 480 multiplications that can happen per second.
But to make that possible, you need 7.5 terabytes of bandwidth to keep all the cores busy. Again,
this goes back to the concept of matrix multiply and how we hid latency and stuff
because of more compute. So if you wanted to get this maximum compute rate of 480 multiplies
per clock cycle, you would need 7.5 terabytes of bandwidth to keep up that. And that's practically
possible for GTX 480 had about 177 gigabytes. So that's only 2% efficiency, but it's still
eight times faster than the CPU. So even though we may or may not be using the GPU to its fullest
incredible capability because other hardware limits, it's still going to be very much faster
than the CPU. So this thought experiment where the problem is not limited by how much compute we have,
it's limited by the speed of the memory itself. And if the memory for faster, we could compute it
faster is known as a bandwidth limited problem. If the problem essentially is not with compute,
it's with how fast we can read with memory and the memory system cannot keep up,
that's what is known as a bandwidth limited problem. You can have a compute limited problem
as well where the compute can't keep up and the bandwidth is perfectly fine reading the data.
There are different algorithms that are compute limited and bandwidth limited.
So we'll certainly touch on some of those as we progress in the semester.
So ultimately, what is a GPU? We've designed this GPU for 5GPU essentially,
but at its core compared to the CPU that we did earlier, a GPU has a bunch of shader and compute
cores. It has some fixed function for texture and rasterization, but it probably has some other
things like video decoding and other things that can also use parallelism. And then you can have
a scheduler that is able to schedule tasks to all of these many, many cores at different
hardware or software levels. So that's the idea of a GPU. So now the last slide here is
essentially the summary of how we go from CPU to GPU. The first idea is that we slim down the cores,
we take out all the bulk around it and we pack it with many, many ALUs. This allows for explicit
SIMD instructions and also allows for sharing managed by the hardware. So kind of like the matrix
multiply implicitly in the hardware because we are launching so many different threads.
And the last idea is to have so much execution that the latency of stalls like memory reads and
stuff is hidden by groups of fragments, essentially in CUDA called warps, which can with zero
overhead switch in when a group of threads hits a stall and the cores need swapping out.
So those three big ideas are essentially what are the core of GPUs today. So that's it for this
lecture. Thank you for watching. And more than happy to take questions as we come up in future
classes. And certainly looking to get back to more on the parallel algorithms and performance
side of things. And the next class, which will be Wednesday, will be our project three path
tracer recitation. The entire class will be dedicated to that because it's a much longer
recitation. We like to dive deep into it. But certainly looking forward to it. The path tracer
is by far one of the favorite projects that everybody does in this class. And we really
love to see great results coming from that. So thank you for joining and I'll see you all on
Wednesday.