you
and I was mesmerized by this image because I couldn't tell what it was. It was obviously
not a photograph, but it didn't look like it was drawn. And when I read inside the article
that this thing was generated by an algorithm by a computer program, I was I was hooked.
So I was like, wow, I can create images using the same thing I've been learning for the
past few years, writing programs, something I had been wanting to do for forever, but
I have no natural talent at drawing. And I was always envious of my mother's side of
the family who are all naturally artistic. They were just born being able to draw, but
I couldn't do that. This thing I can do. So this is what I'm gonna do for the rest of
my life. So I poured myself into my Amiga once I got it, and I eventually figured out
enough math so I could write a basic sphere ray tracer. Took me a few years to get there.
And I came across this amazing newsletter. It was called the Ray Tracing Newsletter.
I don't know if Eric Haynes is on the call right now. Yeah, yeah. So he, it had his name
on it, this newsletter. I got it from this thing called a bulletin board system, a BBS.
None of you here probably know what that is, except us old timers. Before anybody had internet
access, people used to just set up their computers with a modem so that other people could dial
in and exchange information, and usually exchange pirated software. That's how we got our video
games and 3D software that I couldn't afford as a 12-year-old. So I had found this newsletter
on this one BBS, and then there was this funny-looking thing I couldn't quite make out. It was some
kind of address for where you can go get the rest of them, because this was number two
or number three. I forgot which edition of the newsletter, and I needed more. Eventually
I figured out that this funny address was for this thing called the internet. There
was an FTP site somewhere where I could go download the rest of them. So it took me a
while to go find a way onto the internet so I could go get more of these Ray Tracing Newsletters.
And over the years, using the information I could glean from the internet, which this
is the late 80s now. Nobody was on the internet. Back then, it was all just text. And if you
weren't at a university that happened to have internet or at a company, there's no
internet for you. You had to be part of the elite group who had that. But I found this
one company that had put three Sun machines that I could dial into and pay them 20 bucks
a month to get access to it. I learned how to program computer graphics and taught myself
whatever math I could kind of figure out on my own before going to college. But a lucky
thing happened for me. In 1993, the same year I turned 18 years old, I happened to be living
in Los Angeles. That's where I was born and raised. Momentous things happened that year.
First, the web was born, which created the opportunity for the internet to become huge
and ubiquitous all of a sudden. NVIDIA was born that year. That was the same year NVIDIA
was started. And Jurassic Park came out. And most of you weren't alive when that happened.
But for those of us that loved computer graphics, we didn't have many places where we could
go apply computer graphics. Pixar had just started. It had spun off from Lucasfilm. They
were doing commercials for Listerine and Lifesavers and stuff just to stay afloat.
There were a few movies that had a little bit of computer graphics. Terminator 2 had
happened, which was a pretty big deal in the computer graphics world. But Jurassic Park
was when it exploded. Once people went to the theater and saw these dinosaurs come to
life, there was no going back. We were never going to be able to do visual effects the
old way because it was just so much better, so mesmerizing that this was the future. And
quite frankly, looking back on it now, I think had Jurassic Park could not happen, I think
maybe computer graphics would not be where it is today. It would maybe be delayed another
10 years. Because at that moment, there was a market that formed around computer graphics.
All of the studios in Los Angeles needed this thing now. It was super weird. You have companies
like Disney and Sony doing basic R&D in computer science, something that you would not expect
from any content companies. Just because there were no tools available, the algorithms didn't
exist to go create the things that we wanted to do. And they were essentially hiring anyone.
Anyone who knew anything about it. And I happened to be in Los Angeles doing this stuff for
a few years, for many years, on my own. And so I wiggled my way into Warner Brothers and
then into Disney, where I got to work on things that nobody in their right mind would let
me do this day and age. I would have to come to a place like UPenn and get a proper education
before they'd even allow me into the room, let alone let me create a whole new renderer
for hair and fur and things like that. So that led me through the next few years. Shazan
mentioned I had my own company after I left Disney, where I developed a renderer. I licensed
it to all the big studios. And at the time, I thought my love, my passion was doing visual
effects or rendering particularly for visual effects for movies. But NVIDIA called me in
2001 and they really wanted to hire me. And I had heard through the grapevine, I wasn't
supposed to know this, but somebody at SIGGRAPH had told me, an intern that was at NVIDIA,
that they were working on this programmable shading thing. And I got excited about the
idea of doing what took hours, hours per frame in my world, in the offline visual effects
world, doing that in real time so that you could interact with it, potentially have the
same quality and fidelity and realism that I was aspiring to in offline in real time,
which maybe would unlock the opportunity to create something like a metaverse. Now,
I wasn't using the term metaverse. I was, I had read William Gibson's books, Neuromancer
and all those even that predates Snow Crash. And so the term, the matrix and cyberspace
and all that stuff came from these books. The idea of jacking into an internet and experiencing
that was there, that maybe this might happen. So then I'll go give it a try, work there
for a few years. It'll probably be five years or so. I thought we would all be living in
a metaverse like thing. But it's been 20 and it turns out it takes a lot longer to do this
stuff than we always think. We go set about solving really hard problems. We minimize
them to something that we can comprehend and hope to do in a normal amount of time. Then
we find it's actually much harder, but still worth doing. I think if we didn't do that
minimization thing, we would never actually venture to do anything cause it'd be too daunting.
So I spent the last 20 years, essentially working on all things related to simulating
virtual worlds. And what I learned while I've been at NVIDIA is that my true love wasn't
making visual effects and it wasn't even making entertaining images. My true love was
just computer graphics. I love everything about computer graphics and it turns out that
there are other markets for computer graphics and more important markets for computer graphics
and things that are far more exciting to me. As much as I love making movies and then working
on video games, fundamentally those are entertainment and they're nice things to do. There's nothing
wrong with it, but there's something about creating robots that are going to help us
farm sustainably and building cities and structures that eliminate the 30% of waste and building
every one of these structures we create around us, 30% of waste and energy and material that
just goes away that we could potentially solve by using computer graphics, strangely enough.
And this other thing happened about 10 years ago that was kind of unexpected. Ever since
I was a kid, I've been reading about artificial intelligence and how it's right around the
corner and the idea of neural networks have existed since the 50s. We'd been dabbling
in them. There was a resurgence of them in around the 90s, around the time I was at these
studios and it never quite materialized. So I kind of resigned myself to thinking we're
not going to have anything close to intelligence from a computer in my lifetime. The idea of
a computer being able to tell the difference between a cat and a dog reliably in an image,
that was just something that we were never going to solve. And overnight that changed.
About 10 years ago, as probably many of you know, there was the ImageNet challenge, University
of Toronto, there's a few grad students who took basically a consumer supercomputer, a
video game machine with one of our GeForce gaming cards in there. And they took this
old idea of neural nets and they applied it, took a whole bunch of data that was collected
on the internet and they fed it through this algorithm that trained another algorithm that
can tell the difference between a cat and a dog reliably. And that basically changed
everything. From here on out, all software and all of the most advanced algorithms that
humans are ever going to create are likely going to be created by a machine. We're going
to create the algorithms that create the algorithms. And the way we do that is by feeding it data.
You need to have lots and lots of data. Now we can call it data, but I prefer to call
it life experience. What you're actually doing when you're training these AIs, we're doing
the same thing we do when we train humans and creatures, what you guys are experiencing
right now, there's all this data that you're ingesting, this life experience, as I'm speaking,
as you're taking the signals that come in through your sensors and training your brain,
that's exactly the same thing that we're doing with these AI systems. But it turns out that
the AIs we want to create, the most impactful ones are ones that can perceive and understand
our world, this world around us, not video game worlds or arbitrary things inside computers,
and ones that can act upon our world, like robots or self-driving cars and things that
can do things around us here. And in order to provide them with that life experience,
we can't rely on them learning inside our world. I mean, babies, we train them in our
world, we bring them into this world, they learn how to see, they learn depth perception,
they learn how to distinguish between their mother and other people and all of those things
through experience. But we don't want these mega robots that are inside car factories
that can pick up cars and place them wherever they like to learn on the job. That would
be pretty scary for them to just keep trying things and break things until they learn.
That's how babies learn. That's fine. We kind of tolerate it when they throw things,
but we don't want our robots learning how to drive on the road. I mean, I don't even
want my children learning how to drive like that. They're sitting up there, the two of
them, but we kind of just have to deal with it. That's how it works. So what are we going
to do? How are we going to create these AIs? How are we going to give them life experience?
It turns out the answer is in what we've been doing all along in computer graphics,
because advanced computer graphics is 3D computer graphics. And most of 3D computer graphics
isn't about the image part. It's about constructing a model of the world, the world around us.
It's about creating these 3D worlds and spaces that have rules that match the rules in our
real world, the rules of physics, the physics of how light interacts with matter, Newtonian
physics, and eventually maybe all the way down to quantum physics, but we don't normally
have to deal with those kinds of effects in the things we model. But if we can synthesize
these worlds and we can simulate them quickly enough, then we have this amazing playground
where we can give birth to artificial intelligence and we can train them and we can make them
good robots, good AIs before we bring them out into the real world. They can drive for
billions of miles inside the virtual world. They can do billions and billions of hours
working in factories and doing all the things so they can really perfect that before we
bring them out here. So with that, I'm going to talk a little bit about what we call the
industrial metaverse. There's been a lot of talk about metaverse, especially since last
year when Facebook renamed themselves to meta. Probably when I say the word metaverse,
many of you are probably groaning like, oh my God, this is another cheesy talk about
how we're going to be surfing with Mark Zuckerberg or something. That's part of it. I think social
and gaming experiences are definitely going to be part of this metaverse thing that's
happening. But the way we look at it, the metaverse is essentially an extension of the
internet. When I started in the internet in 1988, the interface of the internet was just
a text prompt. It was a console. I had to go log in with a 2400 baud modem. Guys probably
don't even know what baud is, but I had one. I had a 2400 baud modem and you would get
a Unix shell and you could type some abstract arcane commands into it and get information
back out of it, which was really amazing because you were connected to some of the smartest
people in the world instantaneously. It was already awesome. Unfortunately, that interface
limited it to a very small number of people, only people who knew the special arcane commands
and how to get access to it, and I kind of lucked into it. But when the web was introduced
in 1993, the interface changed and it opened it up to many more people. We now could have
people who knew how to understand a graphical user interface, which was a huge portion of
the world, who could deal with text and images and eventually video and all the other things
we put in the web, interact with the internet. And that took it from thousands of people
that were on the internet to millions and now billions of people that can interact.
This next era we're going into, I think, is as profound a change as the transition from
text to a two-dimensional web. The switch to a 3D web, one where our primary interface
to the internet is something that is similar or even, in many cases, matching what the
real world around us feels and looks like is fundamentally going to change the way we
interact with the internet overall. And if you think about it as an extension of the
internet, you can think, well, we do all kinds of stuff on the internet. We, of course, socialize.
We play video games. We do all those things. And those are the things we're talking about
with the metaverse. But we also use it to learn. We use it to work. We use it to build
things and to design things together. We use it to do our banking and order food and do
all kinds of stuff on there. The internet is much greater than social networks and video
games. And so will the metaverse be. Once we introduce this 3D spatial overlay on top
of the internet, that's going to unlock many, many superpowers.
So today, there are already many applications that are metaverse-y. We can see in video
games, people talk about Fortnite and Roblox and all of these being metaverse-like experiences.
We can debate whether the metaverse is here yet or not. I think it's kind of moot. It's
just this spectrum that we're moving along into more 3D-ness of our internet experience.
But we can use the metaverse, this 3D overlay, for many purposes. And you're starting to
see many of them form already. People are using it for shopping for things online. You
can see what your furniture or clothes might look like. If you were to actually buy that,
how it might look on you, how it might look in the space that you're looking at. We're
really interested in all of the uses of the metaverse in industry. And I'll explain specifics
as to why. But before we can make use of all of this, we need to kind of set up the
foundation, the kind of ground rules for what the metaverse needs and has before we can
even start forming a 3D internet. Building the 2D web and the internet where it is today,
it's been almost three decades. There's a lot of work and energy and money and time
and tears that have gone into building this. Building a 3D one is going to be even harder.
Everything 3D, those of you that are studying computer graphics right now, you already know
it's really, really hard. There's a lot of math involved. There's a lot of computation.
You never have enough compute. That's the rule. I mean, there's, for rendering, what
is it? Lin's law? Is that all renders take, offline renders take the same amount of time
no matter what processor? I threw out, I forgot exactly what it was, but we always find ways
to fill up our compute with more things to do. So, what are the things that we need in
order to build this kind of 3D internet? First, we need open standards. If we go back to 1990
to 1973, when the web was born, and even further back when the internet was born with
DARPA in the seventies, every step of the way, it started with open standards. The people
who are building the bones of the internet and the web, they contributed the protocols,
the formats, the system design to the general public as standards and completely open from
the very start. This is a fundamental prerequisite for such a thing existing, because if you're
building a network, the measure of success is how many people connect to you or how many
connections you get. The only way you're going to get those connections is if everyone can
freely use the standards by which to connect. So, we need to have some fundamental basic
open standards for 3D in general. We need different kinds of computers. You guys here
are doing a lot of computer graphics work on GPUs. It's been a long time since people
have argued that you could do computer graphics solely on a CPU. They're just not fast enough
for that particular purpose. What we're trying to do now with real-time computer graphics
that are distributed across the globe with hundreds or thousands of people participating
in the same world, this is going to require a different kind of computing system, a different
network, ways of distributing the computation so that lots of the computation can be shared
from a data center, but some computation is done at the edge, right next to the user,
because latency matters so much. So, we need to build new kinds of computers. We need new
algorithms. This is where you guys come in. If you decide to continue in computer graphics
past what you're learning here, maybe you can work on some of these algorithms to accelerate
and, with as much fidelity and accuracy as possible, simulate the world around us. For
entertainment purposes, we can often cheat. We cheat with the physics of the world around
us. We just need the thing to kind of look cool, not necessarily actually behave correctly.
But for many of the uses we have for this metaverse thing that's happening, for the
industrial metaverse, it's not okay for it to just look right. It has to actually behave
correctly. And doing this in real time and even super real time is critical. If we're
going to give our AIs millions and millions of years of life, life experience, in the
time it takes us to experience a cup of coffee, then we're going to need very, very fancy
algorithms that can do this kind of accuracy quickly. Finally, there's a whole lot of AI
that's coming into play here. So, at NVIDIA, we live at the intersection of computer graphics
and artificial intelligence, high-performance computing in general. And it's mind-blowing
to me, almost like too much. Every day I see new things coming out from AI research that
is completely disruptive to everything I've known about computer graphics from the beginning.
I don't believe that AI is completely going to replace everything that we're learning
here. I think we need all these fundamentals. But the interplay between AI and traditional
computer graphics and principle simulation methods is the key to the future. There's
no way we're going to have enough computational power to simulate even small worlds like the
world we have right here with the physical accuracy that we need anytime soon. The supercomputers
we need to do this would end up being larger than the world itself or larger than the universe.
You need more atoms than the universe to simulate all the atoms that are here. So, we need some
clever tricks to approximate all that. And AI gives us that. The other thing AI is really
accelerating is the inverse of computer graphics, which is computer vision. We need a way to
build worlds that we simulate inside our simulators. How do you build such worlds? Today, we have
experts at the top game studios, the AAA game studios, or at visual effects studios, who
know how to do very specific aspects of the world building. Some people are experts at
modeling things around us. They can model the buildings, the chairs. Some people know
how to create humans or faces, and some know how to animate them and texture them. And
they spend decades becoming experts at those. There's just not enough of these people around.
There's maybe thousands, hundreds of thousands of experts in the world that could do it at
that level. And that's just not enough. If we're going to build a 3D web, if we're going
to build a metaverse, then everyone needs to be able to create within this new medium,
just like with the 2D web. None of you are around, except for Steve and Patrick and me,
when the web came about. One of the amazing things about it was, anybody could create
a web page. All you needed was a text editor. You could type up some HTML and put it up
on a web server, and you had a web page. And that's how the web became what it is today,
because everybody could participate in creating there. And that's still true today. Most of
the content on the internet is not created by a small elite group of people creating
all of that content. It's created by you guys. You put stuff up on YouTube and TikTok and
not Facebook. I think all of you are too young here for that. But all of these social networks
and sites and stuff, unfortunately, that's not possible with 3D content today. The average
person cannot create a 3D game or a 3D experience. It's just too hard. So with AI, we potentially
have the promise of tools that will allow average people to create 3D experiences and
content in the same way we can all create videos and photos and the written word today.
I mentioned open standards being critical. We have settled on one particular standard
as being the most critical at this moment in time. It's a standard called universal
scene description. It was invented by Pixar and open sourced about seven years ago. Seven
years ago. So when we saw it, we thought, this is pretty amazing. Because in the years
that I've been doing computer graphics, there have been many proposed standards that were
supposed to be the kind of universal standard to describe everything. Even in the very early
days of the web, I think it was 1994, there was VRML, VRML, right after it built based
on SGI's inventor. Yeah, it's too old for you guys to know. But it's an interesting
bit of history. There's been a bunch of formats that have been introduced. Collada, Autodesk
had FBX. But none of them had all of the right things. It needed to be open. Truly
open. It needed to be extensible. And with what we saw with USD, there was a lot more
than just the file format or the description of things. There's this notion of composing
worlds and allowing multiple people working together on different parts of the world
simultaneously and in harmony. This was essentially wisdom that Pixar had gained over the decades.
They've been creating large virtual worlds that ended up encoded in USD. The ideas that
are in USD had existed in different tools and systems they had before them. And if you
think about it, no company, no enterprise or group has been building large virtual worlds
using a heterogeneous set of tools with different disciplines, all contributing, hundreds and
hundreds of people contributing same virtual world for as long as Pixar. So they just hit
that right balance of things necessary in this format. We saw it and said, this looks
kind of like how HTML was in the early days. Insufficient for where we want it to go, but
has the basic foundation that we can add to and build on so we can eventually get there.
And so we've settled on this and it turns out many others are coming to the same conclusion
now. We were one of the early ones, the earliest to invest in it. A lot of people assume that
because it came from Pixar, that it's limited to media entertainment, but we saw it as general
enough so that it could apply to everything. So we're using it for robotics. We're using
it for AEC, architecture, engineering, construction, manufacturing, and so on and so forth. I'll
skip past that. I mentioned that we're going to need new forms of computing to power this
kind of 3D web. I can't stress that enough. It's not enough to just write algorithms anymore,
especially in this post-Moore's law world we're in. I mean, you guys are too young to
remember, but when I was a kid, I could write a program and be really lazy. And two years
later, my program ran two, three times faster. I didn't have to do anything else. It just
ran faster. And I could write my code without worrying about anything, without really worrying
about the architecture of the processor I was writing to. The good folks at Intel and
these guys making CPUs would just figure out how to take my same code and make it run faster
without me changing it. All of that changed about almost 20 years ago, the moment Intel
decided to go dual core, because that was essentially an admission that the extra transistors
that we're throwing at these processors don't just give us the automatic speed ups. You
had to now refactor your programs, your algorithms to take advantage of parallelism, which is
really hard. And so that opened up this future. This is why NVIDIA is what it is today.
We build accelerators that accelerate very specific workloads, starting with computer
graphics, but also physics simulation and AI. The future is more of that. We're going
to have more specialized types of computers that are optimal in terms of energy, in terms
of cost, in terms of computational density, that cater to different types of algorithms.
The idea that you could just write all of your software for one general purpose processor
and then go scale that up in the cloud is gone. And in the world of computer graphics
and real time computer graphics, ones where we're experiencing these worlds together,
high fidelity worlds, this is even more important. There's no way we're going to make cost effective
computing if we don't take advantage of the computing architectures that are most optimal
for this. So this problem isn't just limited to the amount of compute. It's also the amount
of data. Computer graphics, 3D worlds are essentially limitless in the hunger for data.
You can always describe something with more detail, requiring more bits of information.
So storage and bandwidth matters a lot. Latency matters a lot. If your compute is too far
away from you, you have a literal speed of light problem. If you make a motion here and
somebody on the other side of the world is going to react to your motion, then you're
limited by how fast that information can travel from here to the other side of the earth.
You add in all of the networking layers, all of the hops, and everything about the internet.
It wasn't really designed for these kinds of real-time applications. So we have to rearchitect
the internet completely so that we can distribute the compute where it needs to be. Sometimes
it's going to be close to you. It'll be on your device. Sometimes it's going to be in
a 5G tower that's not too far away. Or it'll be in a data center maybe a few cities away.
And occasionally it's going to be someplace really far away on another continent. We have
to distribute our algorithms across all of this and take advantage of the opportunities
in each location.
Maybe some of you have heard the term digital twin. That's another term that's been thrown
around a lot these days along with metaverse. There are many definitions of it. Our definition
is a pretty simple one. We already know about virtual worlds. That's what you guys are working
on here with your computer graphics. You build these virtual worlds and you simulate them.
What goes into a virtual world is these basic ingredients these days. You have rendering,
which is how things look. Essentially the simulation of how light interacts with matter
or electromagnetic waves. You don't have to limit it to the visible light spectrum.
We can simulate other types of sensors as well. General physics, how things behave inside
this world. And then AI is another fundamental ingredient for worlds because there are agents
inside these worlds that do things. And so they're the non-player characters in your
video games or maybe a robot inside your virtual factory. Those are things that would
use an AI.
But if you can create a simulator that matches the real world closely enough and you can
model that world closely enough to a real world thing, then you gain this opportunity
to link the simulator to the real world. You can take something. So in this case, we're
showing a factory. We're doing a lot of work with BMW who came to us because they have
this big problem. Every factory they create for every new car is more complex than the
previous one. Cars are getting more complex. Those machines are getting more complex. And
the machines that they build to build the machines are even more complex. There's lots
of software and lots of stuff going on in there. And the only way they can build these
factories that they invest billions of dollars in is by simulating them first to ensure that
they're good factories before they invest the billions of dollars to actually construct
it. Thousands of people working on this thing. But the nice thing about things like
factories is they're already instrumented with a lot of sensors and IoT devices and
things that can tell you information about the state of the factory. You can know what
the joint angle of every robot is inside that factory. You could potentially even know the
joint angles of the humans inside the factory with camera sensors and AI technology to get
their poses and whatnot. You know the state of every conveyor belt and machine. There's
encoders on every device. You know the temperatures and energy usage and all that stuff. So if
you can get all of that information that's happening in real time and extract it and
project it into your model in the virtual version of that, then you essentially have
a digital twin. You have the real world thing and you have a virtual version of it that's
kind of an approximation. But the two are kept in sync. So whatever is happening in
the real world, sometime very soon after it happens there, you can experience it inside
the virtual world. This gives us a few superpowers that are pretty amazing if you think about
it. The first one is teleportation. So if I can create a factory that is a reflection
of the exact state of the factory in the real world inside the virtual world, then I don't
actually have to go to that factory physically in order to experience it. I could put on
a VR headset or just look at it through my monitor like a video game, go fly into that
factory to any point and teleport around. And the state of what I'm seeing should be
the same as what's in the real world. That's essentially teleportation. And as we make
our algorithms better and better and we match the world more closely, it eventually becomes
indistinguishable. If we can render it so that it looks exactly the same, if we can
reflect the state of everything exactly the same way, then you might as well not go to
the place. You can just do that remotely. You can also travel to the past if you record
all of that state over time. So if you take the state that's streaming in in real time,
let's put it in storage, you get a rewind scrub bar. So not only can you teleport,
but you can time travel. You can go to any point in time in the past and experience it
at that moment in time. But where it gets awesome is if you have a simulator that really
does match the physics of the real world close enough so that you can predict the future.
If you can tell that the factory is likely to have a stoppage because the configuration
of the factory at that moment in time, something's going to overheat or some robots are going
to crash into each other or whatever you can predict, if you can do that well enough, then
essentially you have time travel into the future. This is where computation matters
a lot. If you can do it faster than it happens in real life, then you have the potential
to alter the actual future before the tragedy happens. And so we can travel into the future.
If you can simulate it really, really fast, then you can potentially experiment with many
possible futures. You can say, well, what if I moved around some stuff? I can change
my factory line and reconfigure it so the robots are spaced apart like this and maybe
change the speeds and feeds in there and do an optimization. Find the best possible
future to minimize energy usage, minimize waste, maximize employee safety, factory workers,
so on and so forth. And you can pick the future you like, the one that you want, and go apply
that in the real world. So these basic superpowers that the digital twins give you can be applied
to just about everything at every scale. We're already starting to do this. We're
doing it at the molecular scale. We're creating digital twins of vaccines and human cells.
So we can go do experiments using computational chemistry to try out many, many different
cures for diseases and drugs and medicines and whatnot. I mentioned the factory use case.
That one's kind of pretty obvious. We're doing it at city scales. We're working with
many, many different companies to do things like simulate radio propagation of 5G signals
throughout a city. If you have a good model of your city, and you know where the towers
are, and you know the equipment you have and the software that's driving it, radio these
days is really, really complex stuff. It's all active. There's beam forming and all kinds
of crazy, crazy stuff the towers are doing to optimize your signal, minimize latency,
and maximize bandwidth to each user. We can model all of that stuff and have efficient
placement, efficient in terms of energy, in terms of cost, in terms of maximizing potential
bandwidth and usage. And finally, at the planetary scale, we're building digital twins of the
whole Earth. I think probably most people here would agree that we have this little
climate problem thing happening, and nobody really knows what to do. There's a lot of
theories as to how we might be able to fix it. Some people just think it's impossible
to fix. There's nothing we can do. One thing that's probably clear is that whatever the
fix is, it's going to be expensive, and it's going to take a lot of time to implement.
And we probably aren't going to have multiple chances at doing that. So how do we convince
ourselves that whatever solution we go invest in, and convince enough people to invest in
the solution, to actually go invest trillions of dollars and decades into doing the right
thing? With this fog of war we have, we don't know exactly what the right solution is. The
only way is to actually build a digital twin of the Earth. If we can model climate change,
if we can model the weather and climate systems of the Earth, and we can prove to ourselves
that given historic data, we could predict the future that happened, and we can run the
simulator alongside the real world, and see if our simulator can match the future that
does actually happen, and build a computer with algorithms that does this, then we can
potentially experiment with possible futures. We can take our simulation of the Earth, and
we can try a few different experiments, or many experiments, and see which one is likely
to be the best solution. We might have a chance of convincing enough people in the world to
go invest in such a thing. We're working on that. We're actually building a supercomputer
to do this kind of climate science and climate modeling that'll predict out to 20, 30 years
at extremely high resolutions, down to the meter scale resolutions a year. Not only can
you tell what the average temperature of the Earth would be, but what will the temperature
at your house be like 20 years from now? If you can make it personal like that for
everyone, and you can convince them that it's accurate enough, that it predicted it, then
maybe we've got a chance. I'm going to play a little video here that shows some cool stuff
we've been doing in robotics with digital twins. Here's an example of a digital twin
we built of a warehouse, something that is pretty important these days, given everybody
just orders everything on the internet from Amazon, or wherever else, and there's warehouses
like this that are fulfilling all that stuff. This first one here is, yeah, there's three
different robots. The first one it's going to show is this Fraunhofer AMR robot. With
our simulation stack, which is called Omniverse, Shazan mentioned that's the thing I've been
working on for a while, we can model this robot almost exactly. We can take every part
from the original CAD design and piece it together and place it inside this virtual
world and model the physics of the AMR and every aspect of it. Same is true here with
this robotic arm. I forgot which one this is. You can see the real world on the left
side and the simulated world on the right side in the earlier portion of it. I think
I'll show you that again. They match close enough so that we can use all of the data
that's generated in simulation to train AIs for it. That was images being generated to
train its perception systems. Here's another example of a cool robot. These guys in Zurich
at ETH Zurich decided to give it wheels. Inside our simulated world, our physics was close
enough to the real world that it could completely learn how to stand on its hind legs and move
around on wheels, this quadruped, without ever trying it in the real world first. We
essentially created its brain. We trained its brain inside the virtual world and we
transferred it to the real robot and it works. You know, I don't know how to answer it directly
because I haven't looked at the stats, but you can see there's a farm of robots. The
way we usually do it with these reinforcement learning systems is we'll have hundreds or
thousands of the robots. In every iteration, you have a whole bunch of them randomly trying
kind of different things. Whichever one is the best, we take its brain and then we feed
it back into the loops for the next iteration or next batch of them. So the amount of life
experience would be the aggregate of all of the experience of each of those robots. What's
amazing about this one, we have another demo where we have it training live. So they start
with the robot. It doesn't know how to walk. It doesn't know how to do anything. And they're
holding it in place like a baby cow or something that just came to life. And they have a computer
running doing the reinforcement learning and within a minute or two, it can walk. And you
see it taking its first steps and doing everything in the virtual world and they're taking instances
of its brain and bringing it back in. So we can give it millions of hours of life experience in
in minutes. And that was all done with just one GPU on our part. One GPU because it's
extremely parallel. We can do many robots simultaneously and do all the physics for each
one. Okay. So for this section, give you a little summary. Some takeaways, if anything's going to
stick in your brain, some of these bullet points I think would be a good one. The metaverse is much
more than social networking and entertainment. If you just replace metaverse with internet
that has 3D, 3D spatial overlay, then you can see that it's obvious that it's much more than that
because the internet is much more than just socializing. Open 3D standards are a hard
requirement for the metaverse. There's really no way we're going to be creating a 3D web if we
don't have some agreement on how we describe the things inside these worlds and how we communicate
them to each other. This is extremely important. Even though in terms of research, a lot of these
things are largely solved problems, the implementation and turning them into standards
is still really hard. There's a long road ahead. And there's some excellent people in this room
working on that problem with us. We're really excited about it. We need a new computing
architecture. The types of computers that we need to build and the networks that we need to build
are going to look very different than the ones that we have today. So if you're
interested at all in the fundamentals of computing and computer engineering,
that all this might be an area that you could work towards on the actual computers themselves.
We need to have real-time and high-fidelity accurate simulations to create
the metaverse that we're hoping to create. If we only have computer graphics that just
looks cool, then it's not going to be sufficient to get those superpowers I was talking about.
The next era of computer graphics, I'm hoping, is all about actually being like the real world.
We've largely been applying computer graphics to entertainment, to visual effects, and then
video games. NVIDIA benefited from this when we were born. We were born right at that era.
But it's not sufficient for where we need to go. I think recreating the real world is far
more interesting than creating fantasy worlds in most cases, and much harder.
AIs are going to be born in the metaverse. And so the previous thing is necessary in order to
make sure our AIs don't learn the wrong rules. We don't want our self-driving cars to learn in a
Looney Tunes universe. Cartoon physics is not something we want them to assume when they're
driving on the roads with us. And we're going to need a lot of AIs to help us build the metaverse.
We have to have a lot of stuff inside the metaverse. We need cities and spaces and
buildings and parks and humans and creatures and all of these things in there. And there's no way
we're going to be able to construct each one of these things by hand. So the intersection of
artificial intelligence and computer graphics is really important. Otherwise, we're just going to
hit a hard wall. That's going to be our bottleneck. All right. So that was that one. I don't know how
much time we have left. Yeah, I've been talking for about an hour. I can talk for another five,
six hours if you guys want. I don't know if my kids up there would be happy if I could talk for
another five, six hours. You guys want to do some questions? Yes? You're nodding.
Very good question.
So from my perspective, all of them are important.
When we're building robots, they actually
have many sensors that aren't just visual.
Or they see, even their visual senses
are outside of the human visual spectrum.
We have LIDARs, and radar, and these ultrasonics.
So we're modeling all of that stuff
inside our omniverse-based simulators.
There's other sensors as well that
aren't dealing with waves.
There's haptic sensors.
So we need to model that as well.
It's really important.
That Fraunhofer robot I showed, the AMR with all the parts,
if the movement, the haptics aren't correct with that,
it can't learn correctly.
The animal robot that was standing on the wheels,
same thing.
For humans, I think the most important sense
turns out to be visual.
That's what we have the most neurons in our brain dedicated
to over all the other ones.
It's a really powerful sense.
But when we see, we're not really seeing with our eyes.
We're seeing with our brain.
Our eyes are just a way to collect
the signal coming from the world,
the electromagnetic waves.
It transforms it into an electrical signal,
and that hits our brain somewhere.
And in our brain, we're doing a rendering
of the world around us.
That's how we're actually seeing.
There's a renderer inside your brain.
And so the rendering of the visual aspects
of computer graphics is more than just the image.
It's how we kind of understand the 3D space around us.
And so I think that that's always
going to be an extremely important aspect
of the simulations we do.
But we're doing far more than simulating the visible light
spectrum.
You have any more questions?
Or maybe we'll let somebody else ask,
and then we'll wrap it around.
Yes?
Yeah.
I kind of want to ask, is this kind of analogous
to what you were talking about?
Absolutely.
So when the web was born, there were two standards
that were critical.
HTTP was one of them, and that's the transport protocol.
That's how you exchange the information.
But then there's the content itself,
the information content.
That was HTML, and still is.
We've just enhanced HTML over the years to HTML5,
and we added JavaScript, and all these other things
that unlock stuff in there.
So the standard I was talking about,
universal scene description, is analogous to HTML.
And if you look at HTML's journey from HTML1 to 5,
it took almost two decades.
HTML1 came in 1993, and I think HTML5
was finalized in 2010, almost 17 years or so
before it was finalized.
But there were many, many attempts
made at different aspects of the standard.
There's almost a Darwinian thing that
happens with these standards.
It's kind of weird we ended up with JavaScript
as being the language of the web.
I don't think anybody would have predicted that one.
Did you predict that?
I wouldn't have predicted that.
It's not a particularly good language, and whatnot.
Some people may love it.
I'm sorry if I offended anyone, but nobody
was predicting that one.
But it turned out to be fine for this purpose,
and it was better than the other things that showed up.
Microsoft had ActiveX that was proprietary and not open.
Then there was Adobe Flash, which had
a whole host of other problems.
JavaScript is open, and it could be
extended to solve all the problems,
even if it's not always in the most elegant way at first.
And so we're going to see the same thing happen
with 3D standards, and I think it's going to be built on USD.
And so where my focus is, and what my team is working on,
is extending this in the open so that we
don't have to wait 17 years to go from USD1 to USD5.
We want to do that much faster, and learn from our past.
We can see what worked and what didn't in the past,
and apply the good things, and put more energy there.
That's a really good question.
Patrick over here is at Cesium.
He's the CEO of Cesium, right?
And they've been contributing to 3D standards, 3D tiles.
And they're not a particularly big company,
but very active in this.
A new forum was formed a few months ago
called the Metaverse Standards Forum.
It was kind of an outshoot of the Kronos Group
that was OpenGL and Vulkan.
They set it up.
It's within that.
But it's not really a Kronos thing,
but Kronos helped create it.
And the president of it, Neil Trevitt,
who's the president of Kronos, works for NVIDIA too.
But there's like 2,000 companies that
have joined this thing to discuss
how we're going to do that.
Generally, the way these things work, though,
is only a small number of companies
actually do the hard work and contribute
code and engineering.
There'll be a few small companies that do that,
but the ones that have the resources to do it really
will do the most.
And so we're doing that.
We've been investing in USD.
And we foresaw this Metaverse 3D web thing
happening many years ago.
So we started hiring people specifically
to go work on that.
And we have a large team that does nothing but add to USD.
To us, it's vital.
We're a computer graphics company.
We're an AI company.
We're a computing company.
We need to have an open standard for all
of the content in the world so that we
have things to compute on, so we can justify making that spend.
Another one that's been surprising,
is not really known for open standards and stuff, is Apple.
Apple, every iPhone, every iPad, every Safari browser
natively supports USD.
You can drag and drop USD, USDZ files into it
and tumble them around.
And RealityKit, ARKit, all that stuff is built on USD.
So they're behind it.
They made some great contributions to it.
And we're seeing everybody else come in.
Epic Games, Unity, Autodesk, all the people
you would expect who would have an interest in this.
Adobe is jumping in as well.
Yes.
I could do it on the record.
I mean, off the record.
And maybe if we have some time, I'll show you a few other use
cases of this as well.
Yeah, so the question was, can I share
any examples of non-social?
Oh, you want me to give you thoughts on the social side?
Thoughts in terms of what?
The ethics of it, or?
Yeah, so the question is, what are my thoughts
on the social and gaming side of the Metaverse?
Because mostly I've been talking about the non-social side.
I'm an avid gamer.
I mean, that's one of the reasons I was at NVIDIA.
I've worked on video games at NVIDIA
for most of my career here.
And I continue to play video games.
I go home, and I've been playing a lot of Overwatch 2 lately.
And I've been playing a lot of Overwatch 2
I've been playing a lot of Overwatch 2 lately.
That's my thing.
For the first time in a long time,
my kids also are playing the same game I play.
And so we get to play together.
I think that already exists.
It's like, without us doing anything,
I think socializing and playing video games in 3D
with multiple people in the same world
and interacting with each other, that's going to happen
because it's already happened.
I know my kids have grown up in that world.
They grew up with Minecraft and Fortnite.
And they didn't play Roblox too much.
But all the other games they're playing,
and the most interesting games and the ones
that are really sticky are the ones that are multiplayer,
ones where many are socializing inside these worlds.
Much to my wife's chagrin,
I got really into World of Warcraft about 10 years ago.
I tortured her through my hardcore raiding experiences.
But I could understand how it's possible to feel
that this virtual world that I'm projecting myself into
is as real as the one that's out here.
I used to raid every night or every other night,
basically, for many hours with 20 other people.
And it's like this camaraderie and relationships and stuff
form that's not exactly the same as the ones with people
in real life, but just as intense and real to me.
So I think that part of the metaverse has already happened.
I've experienced it.
We're just going to get more and more immersive.
It's going to become even more natural.
We're not going to have to go out of our way to go enter it.
It's going to be all around us.
We're going to have glasses and eventually implants
in our brains or whatever.
We'll see how that ends up.
But it's essentially here.
What's less obvious is how these same technologies
we use for entertainment are going to make,
allow us to have tools that make the real world much
better.
And that's why I'm focusing my energies on all of that stuff
because I think it's pretty much a done deal that
will do fun stuff there.
Every time a new kind of computing thing is created,
people figure out how to make fun games from it, right?
The very first computers had games.
I think probably they had some game they
were running on the ENIAC.
May not a video game, but they created something.
They played tic-tac-toe or something on there.
But again, I think that's coming
to consumer, more social, maybe non-social things as well.
I think consumers are the hardest to please, right?
You need devices that are exquisite and delightful
for consumers.
Whereas for a worker in a factory,
that's not necessarily the case.
As long as it's useful, if a tool is useful,
you can get them to use it.
Company can mandate them using it,
and that's just part of the job.
Whereas if this thing on your head
is a little bit uncomfortable, you're
not going to want to watch TV in there.
You're going to take it off immediately.
It also has to be cheap, and it has to be easy,
and everything has to be just great.
So I think it's going to be a while
till we get there on the VR and even AR side for consumers.
But the industrial side, I think it's useful right now.
And I see it every day with Omniverse,
the platform my team has been building.
I was really surprised at the progression of companies
that adopted it early.
I imagined, because we were building on USD
and we're coming from traditional computer graphics
with games and movies, that the media entertainment
industry and gaming would be the first ones
to use Omniverse for their things.
And the next I imagined, the next bigger market
would be AEC, Architecture, Engineering, and Construction,
and especially the architecture side,
which is more visualization and looks more like the M&E side.
And then finally, I thought manufacturing
would be the last one.
Those are probably more like dinosaurs,
last to adopt the technology, but the biggest
prize in terms of a large market and the most impact
that it'll make in the world.
And the exact opposite has happened.
We've sold to maybe 100 different large enterprises
already.
Most of them are in manufacturing.
And it's completely inverted.
So it's companies like BMW, and then companies
I never even thought, I didn't even
know about, like Kroger, those supermarkets, and Lowe's.
And well, Nike kind of makes sense.
But all of these, there's the Deutsche Bahn,
the German railway system.
They all need to build digital twins of their systems,
of their products.
When we were speaking to BMW originally,
they're like, for them, it's an existential problem.
They spend tens of billions of dollars,
like $30 billion a year on their factories,
building new ones and operating their other.
That's a lot of money.
And every factory that they build
is getting harder and harder.
There's like 6,000, 7,000 people that
contribute to the design of a factory over many years.
And inevitably, when they build it,
there's a whole bunch of bugs.
Things don't work.
And they have to go rebuild things.
And that causes delays, and new costs,
and waste, which can be measured in billions of dollars.
So this technology that we're talking about,
VR, AR, all of that, they want, because they
want those 6,000 people to be working
on a virtual version of that factory years
before they actually transform the electrons into atoms,
into the real world.
And for them, putting on something
that's slightly uncomfortable or costs $1,500 or $1 million
for a supercomputer that can simulate that
is saving them billions of dollars and time to market.
And that pattern exists everywhere.
Yes.
Margin of profit is 2 to the third of 0.
The margin of profit here is 2 to the third of 0.
Do you think, like, I'm not sure if it is something
like that of a whole factory or a whole factory.
So do you think that it could be a function
that like operates off of a particular technology?
Wow.
Sounds like we've got somebody trying to figure out
which stocks to invest in right over here.
I've got to be careful what I say here.
So there were a bunch of questions there.
One is, do I believe the marginal cost of compute
and energy are going to zero?
I don't know about compute, but maybe with energy,
because we are building new energy systems,
renewable energy.
And depending on areas, I think that's
going to be a local question.
Some places where you have lots of sun or wind,
you'll have effectively free energy.
Other places, maybe not.
I don't know about that.
As far as compute goes, I don't know if the cost of compute
can ever be zero.
From what we've seen, the cost of building
the computers themselves, the chips and the processors,
that's actually only going up.
The science behind creating a modern chip at the scales
we're doing it at is staggering.
And the cost associated with that is even higher.
So I'm not sure that's going to go to zero any time soon.
If anything, we'll see.
We just passed the CHIPS Act here.
So there's going to be a lot more foundries and whatnot.
Yeah, if you if you measure it purely in terms of, you know,
the amount of arithmetic operations you can do,
yes, that each arithmetic operation becomes cheaper.
But what we've shown is we always have bigger problems
to fill that compute with.
So it's not just the cost of computing.
It's the cost of building the computer.
So it's not just the cost of building the computer.
And it's not just the cost of building the computer.
It's the cost of building the computer.
So we always have bigger problems to fill that compute with.
So it's just never enough.
And the fixed capacity of computers that we have available to us to run it
is still a finite quantity.
We saw this during the pandemic.
You couldn't buy enough computers.
Everybody needed them.
And both in terms of our devices, but also in the cloud,
there was just supply constraints to the amount of computers that are there.
So we're at a point where our demand for compute is so great,
we can't produce new computers fast enough.
So we're going to be using older computers for longer
in order to satisfy that demand.
But we'll see.
That's a hard thing to predict.
And I wouldn't base any of your stock purchases on anything I just said.
Because I don't know.
I'm an engineer.
I'm not a.
Yes.
So in terms of, you know, you mentioned phase two.
So in terms of newer technology, what about when we start talking about the quantum?
So, you know, IBM just released their newest quantum chip.
You know, there's been all this stuff about quantum entanglement and all that.
How does that, you know, where do you see that fitting in
I'm not an expert on quantum computing either,
but I tangentially know some stuff because I'm at NVIDIA and we're doing a lot there.
My understanding is even when we crack the quantum computing problem,
you're still going to need a whole bunch of conventional computers around it.
It's not sufficient to just have a quantum computer.
You need a lot of normal computers to test the data and the answers and stuff.
You need a lot of normal computers to test the data and the answers and stuff coming out of that
to make sure that you get the signal out of the noise from this thing.
Right.
And in terms of building the quantum computers,
you still need a conventional computer to verify that the thing actually even works.
So we're always going to need conventional computing
or some other kind of computing alongside that.
Also, there's just a whole bunch of problems that we solve with conventional computers today
that I don't think we have quantum algorithms or equivalents for.
So for certain things that are, you know, NP complete problems
that we can't use conventional computers for, it's probably going to be perfect for that,
but it's going to be part of your system.
We're going to have heterogeneous computers,
different types of processors, and some of them will be quantum computers
that are just part of the system.
I don't even have to do part two, but you want me to? Is that right?
I could just show some of the videos, but why don't we take one more question?
Question about what? Rendering. Yes. My favorite topic.
Okay. So the question was, a few years ago, about three years ago,
NVIDIA said that the future of real-time gaming graphics from rendering
is going to be path tracing in 2025.
35. We said that? I don't know who said that exactly,
but we just showed ReSTIR, the ReSTIR algorithm,
and some other advancements in real-time path tracing,
the spastic graph, so it looks like it's happening earlier.
I'm not sure that was said exactly, the 2035.
It also depends on how you define what real-time path tracing means.
If you talk about path tracing with the number of samples
that we typically do in an offline renderer,
like the Hyperion renderer somebody had mentioned,
or you were talking about earlier, Walt Disney animation,
or one of those, we're probably not going to do that many samples
in real-time, even by 2035, because they can afford
to have a computer run for days to render that one frame.
That's a lot of samples in very general.
However, the algorithms that we're advancing,
that we're inventing for real-time hold a lot of promise,
especially when we combine it with machine learning
or machine learning style optimizations,
and ReSTIR is one of those things.
I think, to some extent, we already have real-time path tracing today.
It's just for a subset of things that you can do.
You can't do all of the things an offline path tracer does in real-time.
If you look at the Omniverse renderer,
we have two modes inside the Omniverse renderer.
We have what we call real-time and one that's called interactive.
The real-time mode essentially breaks the rendering equation
down into the different terms, does multiple passes,
where it can do denoising on the passes separately
before it combines these terms together.
It's still path tracing,
even though it's a subset of the rendering equation,
but it can do a lot of the normal effects you would get from path tracing.
The interactive path tracer is more a traditional-style,
unidirectional path tracer,
and that one uses an AI-based denoiser to denoise,
and it's almost real-time in most cases.
On the new 4090 cards we released,
it's often actually real-time, depending on how you define real-time,
if 20, 30 frames per second is real-time for you or not.
Okay?
Okay, one more.
One more.
Really, really good question.
This is actually a good question to lead up into the next thing I'm going to show.
The question was, is Omniverse,
the platform that we're building,
primarily for industrial use,
or will it also be useful for other things?
Actually, we built it so that it's useful for all things.
In general, NVIDIA, as a company,
our product is technology.
We're a pure technology company.
You can say there's a lot of great technology companies out there,
but not all of them are pure technology companies,
and by pure I mean where your product,
your bottom, the earnings reports you have,
shows that you're making money from selling just technology.
Most of these other technology companies, they sell ads,
they sell other things, and the technology is a means to that end.
What we do is we build core tech, we build chips,
we build systems, we build system software stacks,
we build algorithms infused into libraries,
we build platforms like Omniverse,
that by themselves don't actually do that much.
It's kind of useless.
What's a computer without an application on it?
It's just technology.
But other people can then take this technology stack
and go build an application, a workflow, a solution for someone else.
Our strategy is to build special computers
that accelerate problems that are really, really hard to solve
and make it as general as possible, but not too general.
If it's too general, then it becomes a CPU,
and then it's not going to be great
at the types of problems we care to solve.
But if it's too specific, then we're too limited in our markets.
So we build all of our stacks
so that it can be applicable to as many domains as possible.
So we see Omniverse as being a technology stack
that can apply to many industries,
and fundamentally, by itself, it's actually not doing that much.
In some cases, we provide examples,
but we've designed it so others can take it
and integrate it into their systems.
So what is Omniverse, then, would be the next question.
It's essentially two things for us,
two things that we needed to solve our problems.
So years ago, when we started working on advancing AI
for robotics, for self-driving cars,
we're building our own self-driving cars,
the full stack, the computer, the brain,
everything that we then license to big car companies
like Mercedes and Jaguar, Land Rover, and so on and so forth.
We realized we needed a simulator,
and we need to do a type of simulation
that just nobody else was doing.
We needed an extremely high-fidelity simulation
that could produce everything that every sensor on our cars can see,
so all of the cameras, lidars, and radars,
and we need to do it with hardware in the loop.
So we want to take the brain of the car
and replace the sensor input connectors
with the output from our GPUs directly
so we can put this brain in a virtual reality,
and it has to run at exactly in real time,
at the same timing it would in the real world.
Otherwise, our testing of it would be invalid.
If we slowed down the simulator
and slowed down the brain of the computer,
that wouldn't be an accurate test to how it would behave in the real world.
We need to test that correctly.
And so to build this, we needed two things.
First, we need to actually build the world.
We need cities. We need roads. We need pedestrians.
We need all of the cars that are in these roads.
We need all of the material properties and the physical properties
of everything to be accurate inside this world.
We need to be able to simulate the visible light spectrum,
lidar, radar, sounds, everything inside this world,
and we need to be able to do it in real time.
And it should be arbitrarily complex and large and real time.
So to do that, we first said, well,
we need a way to aggregate all the information
that already exists in the world.
We have information from geospatial databases.
There's information about roads.
There's information about buildings that are in tools like Revit and ArcaCAD.
Designers use CAD tools to create these buildings.
Every piece of furniture has some CAD design somewhere.
How do we take all this data and put it into one thing
that we can then feed into the simulator?
That was USD, and then we built a whole bunch of stuff around it.
So if USD is our HTML, then we needed the equivalent of like a web server.
What's the HTTP and all that?
So we built that with Omniverse.
We call it Nucleus.
This is the database that the world lives in,
and then protocols to be able to interactively experience
the state of the world inside that in a live way.
Once we had that, then we need the actual simulator.
How do you run a real-time simulation of an extremely high-fidelity world?
We first actually tried to use game engines for this purpose.
We took Unreal Engine.
We have a great relationship with Epic,
and we have a huge team of engineers dedicated to optimizing Unreal Engine
and adding cool features to it.
So we said, why don't we use this?
Because basically, a game engine is a world simulator.
Let's try that.
And after a while, we found even though theoretically they're the same,
there's some really fundamental differences between a game engine
and a simulator that you need for the kinds of purposes we had.
One of them is that with a game, being physically accurate
is not only not necessary, it's often an anti-feature.
If you want to make a fun game, you're often breaking the laws of physics.
You have superpowers and magic and things like that.
A game developer has to recoup their investment,
which means they need to be able to sell their game to many gamers,
which means it has to run on many types of computers and small computers.
Game engines are designed to run on phones, on consoles,
on maybe a high-end gaming PC, but they're really optimized
for running on the lowest common denominator kind of system.
And what you'll give up when you're going to make your game run
on as many devices as possible is physical accuracy and fidelity.
You'll reduce the detail level of the worlds.
You'll cheat on all of the physics algorithms, on the rendering,
on everything to make it run everywhere possible.
But we needed to do the opposite.
We're like, we need this base level of fidelity and quality,
and we need it to be real-time. We can't sacrifice that.
So we're willing to throw more compute at it.
We can throw more GPUs and actually even more nodes.
We can have many, many computers with many GPUs all working as one,
but none of the game engines allow you to harness that computing power.
And so we tried to make the game engines actually do that,
to scale to many GPUs, many nodes, so we could drive a hardware
in the loop simulator, and we finally couldn't.
We're like, that doesn't work.
The other problem is the authoring pipelines for game engines
are designed around this pattern of having a large team of artists
hyper-optimize the content to distribute to the lowest
common denominator computer.
They make the assets run on a PlayStation, on Xbox.
They design to that.
Whereas we want the opposite of that.
We want to be able to take the highest fidelity designs and content,
the actual real-world data that we've captured,
and just simulate that, and not have to have a team of artists
do a transformation of the data into something that a game engine can take.
But we're willing to throw more compute at it to solve that problem.
So if you can scale up, you can do this.
So we built these two things, a system to aggregate the worlds
that you could then feed into any simulator, including a game engine,
because we've connected Unreal Engine, and now we're connecting Unity to it,
and maybe O3DE, the open-source one in the Linux Foundation.
But we built this special simulation stack that can scale up,
and built from the ground up a new kind of renderer.
The one I was talking about is the only pure ray-tracing real-time renderer
there is, as far as I know.
We have VR in pure ray-traced VR, something nobody else is doing.
And nobody else would, because we started developing this
back when the install base of ray-traced GPUs was zero.
Before we released our Turing generation in 2018,
we had started working on this.
And no game developer would do that, because it would be insanity
to develop software for computers that don't exist.
We can do it, because we know what computers we're building,
and it's in our interest to do that.
So we built this stack for that purpose.
And I believe one day somebody will make an awesome game on top of this.
I don't think it's going to be me, unfortunately,
because I'm too busy building other stuff.
And Jensen, my boss, won't let me.
He won't let me build a game as much as I want to go do that.
We built little gaming experiences.
We showed RacerX demo at the last keynote, if you guys check it out.
We had Marbles demo a few years back.
That was done by my group.
So you can use it for these kinds of things.
But until most of the computes in the cloud,
I don't think it makes sense to release a production game like this,
because it's going to require expensive computers that most consumers don't have.
OK, so that was a very long answer to your question.
I hope it was sufficient.
Let me show you a few examples of Omniverse.
I will try to erase this, because I know I've been babbling for a while.
So I mentioned that Omniverse is a platform, and it lets you do a lot of things.
But one of the fundamental things it does is it lets you take whatever tools you use in your domain
and combine your expertise with your tools into a singular virtual world.
That's the composition of all of the data from your other team members.
So here's an example that some of our experts internally at NVIDIA put together.
We have some architects that work for us that we hired to show what Omniverse can do.
First, you can go download Omniverse, all of you, as long as you have a fairly recent NVIDIA GPU.
You can use the rendering, even without the rendering.
You can use the connectors and Nucleus and all this other stuff without it.
Just go to, if you search for NVIDIA Omniverse, it'll come up.
What's scrolling here was our launcher, which has all the software.
It's free for individuals and students and all of that.
And if you guys wanted any of the enterprise stuff here, you guys know some people, so we can get you access.
Let's see.
Yeah, so they put together this really, really amazing workflow, this design story.
So let me talk you through some of this.
This is Revit.
It's a very popular tool with architects to build buildings.
So you can see the architects designed the bones of the building, the kind of skeleton of it.
And with our connector that we built, we have a whole bunch of connectors for all these different tools.
And now the tools makers themselves are building connectors to Omniverse.
We can bring it into Omniverse, and this is our interactive mode of the renderer I was telling you about.
So it's path tracing in near real time.
I can see him kind of moving around in there and see what it looks like and see what the floor plan and everything looks like in there.
All of the BIM data, the information about the building materials and metadata also comes through Revit.
So it's there in place.
It's not just the visuals.
And then this is SketchUp.
So an interior designer who's more comfortable with SketchUp than Revit can go design a few apartment layouts and the interiors of those apartments in there.
And because we have a SketchUp connector as well, they can quickly connect to our Nucleus server and live bring that in into Omniverse.
And here you see it with more accurate lighting.
We can simulate what those materials and lighting would actually look like in the real world for the different rooms.
All right.
And so here's another tool, Rhino, which is used in manufacturing.
But also a lot of architects like to use this along with a procedural graph-based low-code tool called Grasshopper to procedurally generate things that could end up in a building.
So here they've put together a little graph-based program to randomize the distribution of the different styles of apartments, the interiors, throughout the building.
And yeah, you can see they can choose different ratios for the different mixtures of buildings.
And at the end, we're going to see them publish it into Omniverse.
Oh, I can see here.
I don't have to crank my neck up.
Oh, did it start over? Okay.
All right.
And so here we have an asset swap.
Rhino can't handle all of the detail that SketchUp provides for the interiors.
So within Rhino, we just use blocks, like a very low-level LOD, to represent it.
But once we aggregate it into USD and Omniverse, we can switch out the blocks with the SketchUp interior data.
So within Omniverse, everything gets composed.
You can see on the left side, we have Rhino representation.
And in Omniverse, we have the interiors swapped in from SketchUp directly.
And then it could actually be placed inside the building structure.
So we're composing the whole building with the different apartment types.
All in there and seeing it all as one.
So throughout this workflow, what's amazing about this USD workflow is at any given time, you have a view of the designed world as is.
A source of truth of everything combined together.
So anyone on the team or even the customer or client can jump in, jump in in VR or AR or whatever,
and experience what the whole thing looks like together.
Usually, this is all done in isolation.
Every person working on the building is working in their own tools,
and they can only show them something in their own isolated little worlds.
USD has another great concept called variance.
So for every primitive or every object inside the scene graph, you can create multiple variants.
It's not limited to the objects or geometry.
It's any properties can be variants.
So these are all set up.
Essentially, you end up with a kind of building configurator or configurator application that's all data-driven.
The designers can just stick those variants in there.
And here they wrote a little extension in Omniverse that shows them the apartment mix with a nice little graph right in place.
All composed together.
So now you have the facade designer who's creating different facade variants in Rhino, Rhino and Grasshopper.
And they can bring all these variants into the variant creator.
They're just dragging and dropping the different ones.
And you can see the interactive path tracer up there.
With the whole scene, just switching the variants for the facades out and getting immediate response.
So the designer can see what it's going to look like with the different variants in the lighting,
in that geolocation at that moment in time.
Downstairs, there's a bar restaurant.
So this was designed mostly in Rhino as well.
And so the restaurant designer can export their restaurant.
And just with our connector, it immediately already has some materials and stuff.
As good as the CAD tool provides.
But you can go in there and replace them with the material libraries we provide.
Our open source materials based on the material definition language.
Which is a system we built and open sourced many years ago for describing physically accurate materials that are energy conserving.
And you can see I'm applying them there.
We also have an AI-based search tool we call DeepSearch.
That can search through the whole database of items that we have on our Nucleus server for objects.
So you can see I'm searching for glassware.
And it's using a natural language-based model to do the search.
You don't have to tag any of these assets or anything.
It understands them in the same way all of the recent natural language and generative AI stuff we've been seeing on images work.
So you can start assembling the scene from all the pieces.
And then we can play around with the interiors here.
So in Grasshopper, they've made a procedure for that thing at the ceiling.
I don't know what it's called.
But there's like flutes on it.
So they can change the depth and width of the flutes.
And immediately see in context with the lighting that would be accurate for that geolocation at that point in time in the year what it would look like.
So they don't have to guess at whether it's going to look good or not throughout the year and with different lighting conditions.
You can just check it immediately because our rendering is actually a simulation of how light would interact with matter.
Let's see.
Yeah, they can cycle through different variants and more of that.
And then produce some images.
And here we have another renderer called IRAE, which is a hyper-physically accurate renderer that's energy conserving.
It can do caustics, bidirectional, all of that stuff.
And so we can create an image here that is essentially the radiance or the energy level at each point on the surface.
So we can tell how much light is going to arrive at each point in the real world to deal with the cooling systems and the positioning of the windows and the angles of the windows and all of that.
So we don't fry the humans that are sitting in there.
And then for the outside, we can take another tool, 3ds Max, and connect it into this world.
We can drop some of the assets that we include with Omniverse for trees.
And you can see 3ds Max on the left side and Omniverse Create on the right.
They're both live connected into the same world.
So you can choose.
Multiple people could be working at the same time.
It's essentially like Minecraft, except you're not limited to one meter cubed voxels.
You can edit anything inside the world from any tool that has an Omniverse connection.
All right, and so now we're checking out the different facades with the trees and stuff there.
And we can bring in another tool to give us some more context.
This is Esri City Engine.
So we can create some geotypical buildings based on the actual location and place this building in context to see what it would look like properly.
So we take City Engine, generate the buildings around it, and then those export as USD as well.
And we can bring it into Omniverse and it renders much more beautifully.
With our real-time path tracing.
And that's the location we're going to place it.
And we can use Grasshopper again to do some generative AI.
Essentially, explore the space of possible angles and configurations of the building to see how it would be affected by the sun and what heating and cooling might be an issue there.
Also, put it in a wind tunnel.
Apparently, this is really important in designing cities.
Wind in many cities matters and the orientation of the building matters a lot.
So we can run a CFD simulation with the different variants of the building configuration and optimize for energy consumption and whatnot.
And we can also go experience this.
So here we have the city from City Engine.
And I think they're using SimScale for the CFD.
So it's running its simulation and then we can export the data from that to bring in the streamlines from the CFD simulator into Omniverse so you can visualize it.
You end up with an image like that, which is kind of cool.
And you can see it animated over time.
And we can take this whole system and view it using our renderer.
Let's stream those pixels to any device.
On the bottom right here, what you're seeing is a display on an iPad.
And because the iPad can track itself using ARKit, using SLAM, we can send that pose of the iPad back as a camera inside our world and do the rendering on a server, stream the rendering back to the iPad so it looks like it's a window into that world.
You can kind of place it on a tabletop.
We can do this with VR as well.
These are different waypoints.
All right. Ended there.
Anyway, this just shows in the creation of this one world for the design of a building in a city, there were many, many tools used.
And these people were all working simultaneously on different parts of the building.
But we could see the composition of all of them together.
This is invaluable.
Today, most of the things we build, they're designed in pieces and we don't get to integrate them together until it's very late.
And it's very costly to make any changes.
So we often have to be very conservative with the design decisions we make because we're not sure if the design, the aggressive thing we want to do is going to work or not.
But if you could see it in context combined with all of the elements others are bringing into the design, you could be more certain that you're making a good decision and build better things.
So here are all the different tools that were used for the different parts of creating this world.
City engine, pair of you, yeah, there's just a ton of them.
All right, so that's that for Omniverse.
I don't know how you guys want to do this.
I can go for longer if you guys want and answer a few questions.
Do a little more Q&A.
Sure.
All right, there was a question here.
Right.
So many of the connectors are bidirectional, but some are not.
It just depends on which one.
Our dream is that eventually everyone uses a USD compatible representation for their internal scene graph.
We're in this transition period where most tools are not built on top of USD.
Actually, very few are.
Basically, just Omniverse and Pixar's internal tools are built on that, which is fine because all great systems always start with legacy pieces that are actually very valuable.
There's a lot of great tools out there, and there's a reason people use them for the purpose they use them for.
We don't want to force everyone to change the tools they're already using.
So the compromise is we have to do a conversion from the internal representation of the data inside those tools to USD and back.
When we started on this many years ago, most of these companies like McNeil, who does Rhino, and Autodesk, they hadn't even heard of USD, at least for those tools.
So they didn't care about it.
But we said, we're going to go prime the pump.
We went and built connectors and did the best job we could with the APIs they provide us to do that translation back and forth, waiting for when they would finally take it over and provide a USD translation back and forth themselves.
Fortunately, that started to happen this past year.
We've been seeing not just interest, but just straight up adoption.
They're doing it themselves.
And so the more and more they support USD, the more natural that connection back and forth is going to be.
In the interim period, some tools have higher fidelity USD support than others.
And in some cases, it doesn't matter that much.
You don't necessarily need to have bidirectional connectivity with all tools.
Some tools are just sources that push stuff.
They don't need to bring much data back.
It just depends on the particular workflow.
Any other questions for somebody?
We're doing plenty of that, too.
If I showed you everything we're working on, we'll be here for a few weeks.
There's a ton of stuff online you should check out.
And every one of our GTC keynotes in the past few years, Jensen is showing kinds of Omniverse stuff.
One recurring character we've had is Toy Jensen.
Have you guys seen this?
So that's all done in Omniverse, and it's powered by the AIs that we're creating.
We have some really photorealistic humans as well.
We have a whole digital human team in my group that is trying to actually simulate humans, including everything on the inside as well,
muscles and everything about them, because we need to generate synthetic data for perception systems that involve humans.
One example is inside cars.
In the cockpit of a car, there are sensors now that detect when you're falling asleep or something wrong is going on in there.
We need data to train them.
So we're generating humans to go generate the data to go train those perception systems as we speak.
And we find that most of our customers need humans for various things.
BMW needs to put factory workers inside their digital twins and test the ergonomics of the factory.
Deutsche Bahn, who operates all of the trains in Germany, they really care a lot about the crowds on their platforms and keeping them safe.
And so they need to model what crowds behave like and train the perception systems they have for their cameras there to find behavior that's not dangerous
or that's too dangerous and go correct it, things like this.
So you can check it out.
We have a ton of talks at our GTC in our GTC On Demand videos that go into all of the stuff we're doing with humans.
I have a question.
Could you follow up on that?
Do you think at some point, people are going to have to get rid of trash at the top?
Because if you could perfectly simulate every car crashing, and the ingredients are different than mine, then you're not going to get rid of it.
I don't know if we'll completely get rid of it, because there's nothing like, you know, real-world simulator, God simulator.
We'll have to be sure at some point, but I think it'll reduce the number we do.
Simulation allows us to do much more than what you can do in the real life, just because the cost or the limitations.
There's only a certain amount of space and time we have in the real world here.
The virtual world, it's only limited by the amount of compute you have.
But something like a car crash is really, really hard to simulate.
The physics behind that is very tricky.
And as a result, trusting it, things revolving around safety, you have to be absolutely certain.
So I think you're always going to end up validating it with real-world crash tests.
But there's things you can do in a crash test in the virtual world that you can't do in the real world, because it'd be unethical.
Like, we wouldn't put a real baby in a crash.
I hope not, in a crash test simulator.
But you could do that in the virtual world.
We can put a squishy little baby in there and see what happens.
Yes?
Materials are a very, very complex subject.
And I think they end up being often oversimplified to the point that it's like this one-dimensional thing.
And just the phrasing of that, MDL versus Material X, assumes that they're both trying to do the same thing and they're somehow competing.
They're actually very different and compatible as a result.
You can think of material systems as a stack.
And what Material X does is it defines a standard set of nodes you could use to create a material graph from.
But the implementation of each node is not defined by Material X.
You have to go implement it for each target system renderer.
If it's HLSL, GLSL, OSL, and whatnot.
MDL is a material definition language that is actually hyper-focused on physical accuracy.
It doesn't define any nodes or any particular things.
So you can go implement Material X nodes with MDL.
But it can compile to many other languages like HLSL, GLSL, OSL, C++, CUDA, so on and so forth.
So you can combine the two there.
But MDL does something else.
It's constrained to physical accuracy.
So it's about energy conservation and bidirectionality in the BSDF models.
And all of this stuff is assumed in there.
It's constraining you to only do two things.
You can only do two things, really.
Define what the light transport is in your material at a given point.
And patterns that allow you to parameterize different aspects of this light transport.
That's the two things that it does.
And because it only does that and it's a language specified to that, it's not really Turing complete.
It's not a shading language where you can write any kind of program.
You can only write programs that define materials that are physically accurate.
And the compiler, as well as other systems we've built around it, could do transformations to that material
to target different types of renderers with different algorithms.
Something you couldn't do naturally from just an arbitrary shader to do various approximations and such.
So recently, we had open sourced MDL years ago.
We recently also open sourced what we call the distiller, where we can take a complex material
that's designed for an offline simulation class renderer
and distill it to an approximation for a real-time renderer like a game engine.
And that's the kind of transformation you just can't do with any other material system out there.
We have an implementation of MaterialX in Omniverse that's built on MDL.
No, it's in MDL, and we're looking to extend MDL.
It already, essentially, implicitly supports any wavelength of the electromagnetic spectrum.
So we can use it for infrared and radar and light.
Sound is a little trickier, because there's a time component in there,
and diffraction becomes a lot more important with those wavelengths.
We're adding support for that.
We want to move towards a system that's going to be able to do a lot of the same things
that we've been doing for a long time.
We're adding support for that.
We want to move towards a system for materials that's much more than just wave phenomenon.
If you look at what we've been doing in USD,
one of the first things we did was add a common description of rigid body properties,
physics properties, to it.
That's a type of material.
In rendering and computer graphics software, when we say material,
we just think about the component of a material that's about the visible light spectrum.
But what a material is, is actually all of the physics properties around that.
So we want to define all the different pieces of how you can describe a material,
then have a system where we can combine them all together.
So when you say this thing is a wood, it not only looks like it,
but it sounds like it and behaves like it when you crash things through it,
and so on and so forth.
Yes.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
Well, first off, today, if you look at how a building is designed like that,
nothing is taken care of.
It's just kind of like all the different people working on it
kind of have their best practices that they've learned over decades,
and they just fly that and wish for the best.
A few years back, I don't know if you guys remember.
Maybe it was not just a few years, like 10 years ago, so you were babies.
There were a few buildings.
There was one in London.
They called it Death Ray.
It was like this very shiny mirror-like building, but with curves,
and it literally melted a car.
Like the sun came in at just the right angle this time of the year
and turned into a magnifying glass focusing all the light
and melted this one car down,
and that's something that none of them predicted.
They just said, this curves look pretty,
and it would be cool if it's mirror-like, and that's that.
When we built our headquarters building a few years ago,
we have this really cool design, and it's inspired by computer graphics.
It's all triangles, and one of the things Jensen wanted was natural light
so we could take advantage of the fact that we're in California,
and we have natural light all the time,
so we had these skylights in there.
There's these triangles that were glass up at the top,
and the sides of the building are all glass.
We decided to simulate it.
We used this architect that's a big, world-famous architect, Gensler,
and they know what they're doing,
but we took their design and ran it through our simulator
with that heat map that we did.
We did one of those, and we found that we were going to fry our humans.
The number of skylights we had was like two or three times too many,
and they were way too big.
Also, the glass on the sides,
we had to tilt further away and put soffits
so that we had shadow coming in.
Otherwise, the people that were on the edge of the building
were going to be fried in this greenhouse right there.
There's no way to know this.
We would have found out if we hadn't run that simulation.
We would have found out after they built it.
The type of stuff you're talking about,
they don't do any of that at simulation.
I know it's very surprising,
but in most cases,
they don't even have the appropriate data pulled in together
in a form where they can simulate it.
We're trying to solve that first.
That's the first and probably biggest problem.
It's just collecting all the data in one place
in a form where it's easy to then go run these various simulations.
Any other questions?
There's two over here.
You guys choose amongst yourselves.
Yeah.
Well, like I said earlier,
our positioning,
what we do fundamentally is build technology.
We make it in such a way that others can take it
and go build those applications.
It's unlikely we're going to build a social network
or even a video game.
We build all of the core tech
and solve a lot of the really hard problems
so they can go focus on the last mile problem,
which is really, really important.
The common thing people say about AI
is you need all this data,
and we assume when we say data these days
that it's all the social data.
But actually, most of the data about the world
isn't social stuff.
There's lots of data in this room here
that has nothing to do with our social interactions.
We don't have to get into your private lives
to model these things.
In the case of, say, Deutsche Bahn,
I was talking about the train company for Germany.
They want to have typical behavior of crowds
on their platforms,
on different platforms, different times of the day,
so they can simulate the design of their platforms
and the trains, right?
We could gather tons and tons of data
from cameras that's completely anonymized,
get their poses and estimation just how they move,
move around and flow together,
that is not invasive at all.
And it's data that a social network doesn't have.
It's data that Deutsche Bahn has
because it's their platforms.
And so we can give them the technology
to go unlock that potential data stream for themselves
so they can model the thing they care about
and build a digital twin for that
and build behavior models for the humans in there
that are typical.
I think that data is more important
for most of the things I'm talking about
than arbitrary, you know, who likes what
and all the politics and crazy stuff
your uncle writes on Facebook and whatever, you know.
Yes, yes, you may.
I think Meta will be coming soon.
So, yeah.
So, before the question was that
if we have that kind of data, let's say,
how many of us have that?
Would that be usable for, like,
driving to studios, you know,
or is that just a cloud simulation
that you're talking about?
Yes, but I'm not sure you need
to capture that data as Meta to do it.
We're creating biomimetic humans,
you know, and simulating their muscles
and enough of the biophysics of the human
so we can generate the correct movement.
By the way, you can look up NVIDIA Holodeck.
It's a project we built on Unreal Engine
from years ago in VR.
We had legs back then.
You can look it up.
It's from, like, four years ago,
four or five years ago, and we had legs
because we generated it.
We created an AI model really quickly
to approximate where your legs should be
given the pose of your
given the position of your hands
with the controllers and the HMD.
We could derive it.
We could even sit down and do all this stuff.
It's all in there.
It's not that hard.
All right. You had a question.
Thank you.
Mm-hmm.
Because of the energy usage of the computers?
What potential might there be?
Yeah, the big question,
the trillion-dollar question.
Right.
The trillion-dollar question is,
can we make an accurate enough simulator
that runs fast enough to predict the world
without using
past a certain threshold of energy
that would actually accelerate the global
and we believe we can.
We actually have early indicators
that this can work.
And the trick is AI.
So if we were going to build a simulator
based on traditional principle,
first principle physics, CFD and all that
that could scale, that could be fast enough
and be at meter scale,
we wouldn't have a computer,
supercomputer that could do that
for another 20 years probably.
But modern AI is essentially
just an awesome function approximator.
That's basically
you can roughly think of AI as
you give it a whole bunch of example data
of what the inputs and outputs should be
and you end up with this neural network
that's an approximation of this function.
And in many cases,
we don't know what the function is
and that's why it's magical, right?
We're saying, I want this function
that tells me the difference
between a cat and a dog
and I just give it examples of it
and it figures out
what the function of that is.
We're essentially doing that
for all kinds of physics now,
including fluid dynamics,
which is a notoriously hard problem.
It's a chaotic system.
So the way it kind of works is
you have a principle simulator
that's wrong,
that doesn't actually predict the world,
but it roughly knows
what the basic rules of physics are.
And then we can run that
with the data that we're ingesting
from the world
with all of our sensors around the world.
We can compare the outputs
and see what's the delta.
How is it different?
And then we train an AI system
to learn that difference
to correct the function.
And if you do this with enough data
for long enough,
you don't even have to understand
all of the factors
of the real system in the world.
And you don't have to do
all of the computation
down to every water molecule
in the world.
You can kind of...
It figures out what that function is
and we can calculate it.
And so that gives us a bunch of benefits.
One is that AI and neural networks
are easily computationally scalable.
They're embarrassingly parallel.
So you can take this function
and scale it as wide as you want.
But it also turns out
it needs a far less computation
to do the same things.
Those approximators
can give you something
that's as accurate
because even our principled methods
are inaccurate.
They're missing a lot of terms
and variables
from the real world.
But we can feed real world data
along with our principled
physics simulator data
into this thing.
So by our calculations,
for far less energy
than we'll be saving,
we can go compute this.
Sure.
Well, we're still using some of those.
I mean, we use HTTPS transport
and some of the basics.
Yes, so there are.
So this is what...
The analogy breaks down a little bit
in that we want...
In the initial days of the web
and even today,
the 2D world that you have
is not really multiplayer by default.
You and I can't edit the web page
simultaneously.
We kind of have a little bit of this
with Google Docs.
We can go into a Word style doc
or a spreadsheet
and edit it at the same time
and change the state inside that.
But that's not an open protocol
of any sort.
What we wanted is essentially
that same capability,
the ability,
what you have in Google Sheets,
but for all USD data.
And so any application
that connects to the same database,
the same web server,
you can think of,
what we call Nucleus,
Omniverse Nucleus,
can live,
can subscribe to any changes
that happen to that data
and they can also publish changes.
And so we've created a protocol
and a stack that can efficiently calculate
when any one client changes something.
So if you change the color of a material
or move a few vertices
or change a transform
somewhere in the scene graph,
your side,
very quickly calculates what that changes,
transmits only that delta.
The Nucleus server applies that change
to the database
and for any other clients
that are subscribing,
transmits that change to them.
It's essentially the same thing
as what a game,
multiplayer game server is doing,
an MMO,
but those servers are constrained
to the small amount of specific states
that's relevant to the game,
the positions of people,
whether they shot their gun
or in Minecraft,
where they build a blocks
or a few specific things.
We've generalized it
so that any property in USD anywhere
that's changed
will be synchronized across all of them.
And so you get that Minecraft thing
that we're talking about.
Eventually we'll figure out
which parts of this
we should open up and make a standard.
We've done three or four iterations
on the algorithms
to generate those deltas
and transmit them.
So it wasn't ready to propose
as any kind of standard quite yet
because it just hadn't been done before
or somebody had to invent it.
And so it took us a few years
to land on the right one.
And we think we have a good solution now.
So we'll likely open up parts of that.
All right.
There's one more up there.
Yeah.
We live in the world of electrons mostly,
not in the world of atoms.
We're more than happy to connect
to any haptic device
and provide it the signals it needs
to do what it's going to do.
But we're not building haptic devices.
As new display technologies,
as haptic devices,
input devices are created,
we'll be the first ones
to take advantage of it
and simulate whatever we can
with the data that we receive
from the world
and then send signals back
to operate on the world from it.
You can think about the robots
that we're operating as haptic devices.
Right?
You can send a signal back.
You can imagine teleporting
to that factory I was talking about
in your VR headset
and moving an object
inside the virtual world
and then some robot
inside the real world
actually goes and moves it
to that position
to synchronize my edit to the world
with the real world one.
That's sort of haptic feedback.
We are indirectly working on that,
but we're going to wait
for the kinds of haptic devices
you're talking about.
They're still in their infancy.
Where you are essentially
crowdsourcing building
the entire digital world
using nodes.
I mean, that's an opinion kind of thing,
but I think, yeah, absolutely.
I think the world will build it
if you have open standards
to describe the world.
You guys are working on that stuff, right?
Then I think the world
will take advantage of it
and go crowdsource those things.
Why not?
I don't think it needs to belong
to any one company.
It doesn't.
All that information
that's in the public
belongs to the public.
The other question that I have
is more general around
any of the devices.
Sure.
All right.
So,
all the stuff I discussed
still needs to be built.
There's very little...
And it's funny.
People immediately start thinking
about things in terms of competition,
usually.
Like, we're competing with Meta
because they have a Metaverse
and Microsoft and Google
and whatever.
There's just so much
that needs to be done.
There's no reason to compete.
I think we can kind of
divide up the problem
and if we are going to be
maximally efficient here,
we should divide up that pie
and have everybody
go work on different pieces of it
and make them interop together
and work together nicely.
Otherwise, we're wasting
a lot of energy.
Some amount of competition
is good just to...
There should be a competition of ideas,
better ways to do things.
I don't think I or anyone
can predict what the most important
new startup companies
are going to be.
That's kind of the nature
of transformational computing platforms.
Computers themselves,
like I said,
they do nothing.
They're just a general purpose machine
that runs arbitrary programs.
It's going to take people
who are experts in their domains,
different areas,
to go apply that core technology
to real problems.
And so, what I would love to see
for Omniverse
and what I'm trying really hard
to push with our developer relations
and our business development people
is helping small companies
in various industries
get Omniverse expertise
so they can leverage our technology
to build solutions
for their particular place.
Because we can't go build
all of the applications
for every industry,
every tool, every simulator.
The world has to do that.
So, I'm not sure exactly
which ones they are,
but for Omniverse,
anyone that's at the intersection
of the industrial real world
and computation virtual worlds,
I think there's a lot
of opportunities here.
Every company who does anything
in the real world
is going to need to model
a digital version of it.
I'm not sure that's
a satisfying answer.
If you're looking for me
to give you a business plan for...
You know, we can talk about that later.
For everything.
No, I think that
you're always going to have
a component of the traditional
principled methods
combined with the AI methods.
You can use machine learning
to learn transcendental functions.
You can learn sine and cosine
and whatever.
Why bother?
You can just put the sine
and cosine function
right in your neural network
as a layer in there.
It doesn't make sense.
If you know the underlying
physics equations for something,
then you don't need to have it
learn all of it.
You can shape your neural net
to fit the problem
and make it more efficient
and have it learn something
much bigger than it otherwise would.
Okay.
We have a lot of students
who are probably graduating
who maybe have one
or two semesters left.
What are some key ideas,
omnivorous or otherwise,
that you can recommend
students work on
in a three to six month period
where they're taking an independent
study or otherwise
and be focusing on the problem?
So I hire a lot of
new college graduates
into my team.
A lot of PhDs
and masters
and bachelors.
All of them.
We hire them all.
The thing I care about the most,
actually,
I rarely care about the school
or the grades
or any of that.
First, I want to see passion
when I talk to a candidate.
If they seem excited about it,
like I am,
then I think there's a higher likelihood
they're going to work out in my team.
And one way that I get a signal
as to the passion
is to see projects
that they do on their own time
for their own love,
for their own passion.
It doesn't have to be perfect,
whatever the thing is,
the solution.
But the fact that
they went out and learned something
on their own
outside of what they learn
inside the classroom
and tried to solve a problem
on their own,
that means a lot.
And generally speaking,
the things you're going to do
out in the real world,
especially at a place like NVIDIA,
are going to require things
you didn't learn in school.
You didn't learn anywhere
because we're just figuring it out.
They're all new things.
We're on the cutting edge
of engineering and science and art.
And so the meta skill
of being able to learn
and teach yourself
and take advantage
of the information around you
and harness that into something
is the most important thing I look for.
And I might have a bias
because that's just kind of
how I've always been myself.
I taught myself most of this stuff
by reading and Eric Haynes,
who I finally got to work with
after all those years
in ray tracing news.
But yeah, so
show me a cool project
that you did on your own
because you loved it.
Actually, if I could ask,
well, first of all,
thank you and your family
for coming all the way
across the country.
Thank you for hosting us.
All of us.
I love that you started your talk
with a long and deep history
of your journey
with computer graphics.
I think it's great for us to hear.
We want to know that the people
that are building the future.
And you had an interesting statement
where you said
you wiggled your way
into Waterfront.
And I got the sense
that maybe there was
an interesting story
you want to share.
Sure.
Or I just, you know,
I also get the sense
that there's a level of pride
that you had, right?
Maybe there's some soft skills
that you could also share
with recommendations.
Yeah, I can share that story
because it's interesting.
I'm not sure,
this is what I
talked to Rachel about,
whether it's useful for you.
Because my particular journey
is so weird
and not the norm
that I wouldn't recommend
most people do it
because it's probably a long shot
and wouldn't work.
But when I ended up
at Warner Brothers,
actually this part of it,
I think is relevant.
Before that,
I was interning at NASA JPL,
Jet Propulsion Lab,
as an academic part-time.
And my job was installing
web servers and web browsers
because it was 1993, 1994.
And I knew something
about the internet,
so they hired me as an intern
to go do that stuff.
And I remember watching
the web start to form.
This page showed up, Yahoo,
which consisted of like 10 links
to some interesting things.
And eventually,
it turned into like 100 links.
And eventually, they put
a little search bar up there.
It was a matter of months.
And then they went like IPO
and were worth hundreds
of millions of dollars
and billions of dollars.
It was crazy.
So in this era,
the dot-com boom and bubble and bust,
there's tons and tons
of companies being formed.
And most of them just really
look like crappy companies
that were just looking
for a way to cash out quickly
and whatever.
And I knew something
about the internet
because I'd been on it earlier.
And so 1993, the web happened.
And Jurassic Park,
there was a fork in the road for me.
Am I going to do computer graphics
or go do internet stuff?
I like the internet.
I like computing in general.
But I love computer graphics.
And I made a conscious decision.
I'm like probably
a much higher likelihood
I'll be a millionaire
in the next few years
if I go down this road
with the internet.
But if I go down
the visual effects road,
I'll make good money.
Actually, I made really good money
for an 18-year-old.
We were doing the engineering tour
here earlier with them.
And the kid that was showing us
was from the arts side.
But he looked at
what the average salary was
for engineering students
who were hired,
which was six figures,
like $100,000.
And he was shocked.
Well, I was making that
at Disney and Warner Brothers
in 1996,
which was pretty impressive.
But I knew I could make
a lot more if I did
the internet thing.
But I thought to myself,
you know, that's enough money.
I just want to do
what I love every single day.
And I watched as many people
around me became millionaires.
I kept wondering, like,
did I make the right decision
all those years?
But I always came back to
I'm doing fine.
And I wake up every morning
excited to work on
what I'm working on.
And it doesn't feel like work to me
because I've been doing this
since I was 10 years old,
10, 11 years old.
This is what I would be doing anyway
just because I love it so much.
And I'll be doing it probably
until the day I die
or until I'm too senile
to be able to do it.
So I think that's really important.
First and foremost,
just do the thing that you love.
I'm not saying, like, you know,
maybe what you love is origami.
I'm not saying go make a business
out of that.
Do something reasonable
that might actually have a career
behind it that you love,
happen to love as well.
That's always more important,
I think,
than doing the thing that just
is probably the better path for money
because, in reality,
it won't end up that way.
If you do something
you don't really like,
you're probably not going to do it well.
What do you mean?
Yes.
So when I went to Warner after that,
I had a friend who was an Amiga enthusiast
who was much older than me,
and he worked at some post house
and was doing some stuff with them,
and they had this problem.
They were working on an IMAX stereo movie
for their theme parks
called Marvin the Martian in 3D.
So this is like,
they didn't have stereo movies back then.
This is a fairly new thing that was added,
and they wanted to make a stereo movie
that looked exactly like it was hand drawn,
and they were very specific
about what Looney Tunes characters look like,
and they'd been trying to solve this problem
of making 3D graphics look like
it's hand drawn in that style
for like a year or two,
and it was unsolved.
They were basically having to hand touch up
and fix things,
which was a nightmare in stereo.
So I was 18 years old,
and my friend who was dealing with them
said, oh, I know a guy.
He can solve this for you,
and so he set up an interview,
and I'm like, what are you talking about?
I've never done anything.
He's like, no, no, you can do it.
He's like, just go do the interview.
So I interviewed, and they gave me the job,
and I solved it a few months later.
I published a technical sketch on that,
so as far as I know,
I'm the first one to have solved
the general problem of generating curvature,
lines based on curvature in Toon-like characters.
I built a whole system around it,
and we solved the problem,
and then right after that,
Disney, I ended up interviewing for them.
It was the same thing.
I was 20 years old,
and I couldn't drink legally yet,
but they interviewed me,
and I went through a series of people.
It was the head of software,
the visual effects supervisor,
the head of technology,
CTO of this group,
and the head of the whole studio,
and we all ended up in
the head of the studio's office at the end,
and they're like,
look, we can't tell you what movie this is,
but there's going to be a gorilla in the movie,
and we need to do fur for that,
and this is a real problem.
Disney is investing a lot of money.
It was like $20 million just for the effects budget
for that thing.
They're like, do you think you can do this?
I said, well, yeah,
I've kind of thought about this for a little bit.
I think you need to write a special renderer
to deal with the anti-aliasing problem,
and I said some stuff,
and so the head of production kicked everybody
out of the room,
and he's like, all right,
can you start now?
I said, hey, hold on a second.
I'm kind of making up stuff over here.
I'm not actually sure this will solve it.
He's like, it doesn't matter.
He's like, we've interviewed 13 people,
and all of them were too scared to do it,
and you're the only one that looked confident
enough.
He's like, I don't understand any of these things.
He's like, can you just start?
I said, well, let me tell you tomorrow.
Let me think about it over the night,
and so I drove home,
and it was a long drive because they had bought
this studio in Sini Valley,
which is way outside in Ventura County
from Los Angeles where I lived.
I stopped at a, I saw a Borders bookstore.
I stopped, and I bought a picture book
for children for gorillas,
and I didn't sleep all night.
I just stared at gorilla butts all night long
just to see, like, can I make that hair,
and in the morning, I called them up.
I said, you know, I think we can do it.
I wasn't sure, but I just told them that,
and we solved it and got nominated
for an Academy Award for visual effects for it
and applied the same algorithms I used
based on these froxels.
I think that was one of the first ones
to do that too with deep shadows
to general volumes and particles and whatnot,
and it was used on a whole bunch of movies there,
so I guess the moral of that one is just
sometimes you just take a risk.
You have to be confident in yourself,
and if you at least pretend you know
what you're doing, they might give you a job.
The truth is nobody really knows
the solution to unsolved problems,
so it's always going to be a risk.
There's one more.
Is NVIDIA hiring?
Well, we were hiring like crazy
up until this little downturn thing
started to happen.
My group, we hired a ton,
and I imagine most of you
would be a pretty good fit for it.
We're still hiring, but for specific roles,
go ahead and apply or at least contact me.
You know how to get to me through Shazam.
If you're really interested in working at NVIDIA
and working on Omniverse,
if it doesn't happen right now, maybe soon enough.
We'll see when the spigot opens up again,
all the hiring wrecks,
because it always cycles like this.
You interned?
Really?
You're on Brian's team?
Oh, really?
Okay.
That's why you're asking all those questions.
I didn't plant him there.
He was asking on his own.
Fantastic.
We're going to take a break now.
We're going to check out.
If any of you have any thoughts to share,
please go ahead and talk to them.
Otherwise,
if you want to come chat,
Rev's here.
Adam's done a lot of work.
There's a lot of experience in this room
Rev, thank you so much for coming out.
Loved having you,
and hopefully we'll do this again next year.
Thank you so much for listening to my ramblings.
This is a lot of fun.
It's great to see so many passionate, smart people
who love the same thing I do,
all in the same room.
Thank you.