you
Yeah.
So what is embedded graphics?
I'm going to kind of go back to basics.
I kind of want to come together for the background.
Embedded graphics is integrated screens
of all sizes and resolutions, right?
We think of the phone, but honestly, they're all around us.
We see them everywhere.
We don't think about what really powers them.
We have automobiles that have multiple screens.
We call that IVI infotainment, in-vehicle infotainment,
that also shares the same chip that
does the cluster, the speedometer, or rear seat
entertainment, or camera, or whatever.
You have watches.
You have phones.
You have tablets.
You have refrigerators.
All of these require GPU.
And so I look at this, and let me
see if I can get that little text off.
So SoC architecture considerations.
So is the device, your end device, or the SoC
you're making your end device for,
is it a single-purpose device?
Are we creating an appliance, or are we creating a platform?
What's an example of an appliance?
Appliance is like a video phone.
All it does is video phone.
Platform is like a mobile phone, or even a tablet,
something that you can load applications on.
You have to support a very complex array
of different applications.
You have to have stories, and security, and all that stuff.
Power requirements.
Is it plugged into the wall?
Is it plugged into a car battery?
Is it plugged in?
Do you have an infinite amount of power?
Or do you have a battery, something
that you carry in your pocket that you
expect to last all day long, and maybe even longer?
How many days of use?
That's one of the things that I hear at my office
more than anything else.
How many days of use can you get out of this?
And so we have to concern ourselves
with something called sustained power over peak power.
I think when you look at things like the latest
GPUs that are in discrete cards, you're
constantly worried about, what can it do?
Completely highest frequency, highest performance,
what's that?
But nobody can ever last that long.
Even the discrete cards, which I'll talk about next,
has thermal requirements, where it will completely
overheat and meltdown.
So the next thing I'd say is thermal requirements.
Passive cooling, which means it doesn't have a fan.
It's just a heat sink.
Or maybe the device itself is the heat sink.
Or is it active cooling?
You have fans.
You have liquid nitrogen. You have liquid cooling.
What are you using to cool this thing?
Because all of these devices create a lot of heat.
How hot is too hot?
I know on a mobile phone, we have requirements
that they can't exceed 40 Celsius,
which is pretty darn warm.
You don't want somebody to burn their hands.
This isn't like a pocket warmer.
You want to be able to play it.
And you want it to stay cool, which
means that you have to throttle performance when
you reach a certain thermal.
Maintainability, I talked about this a little bit before.
How long do you have to maintain this device?
Is it one and done, which means you ship it
and you never have to upgrade it again unless you have a recall?
Or do you have to provide regular updates all the time
to make sure that if somebody provides an exploit,
you update it?
Or if you find failures in the functionality,
you have to update it.
Or you have an operating system update.
So your phone gets a Android OS update once a year.
Samsung's on the hook for three or four years of support
for every phone we sell.
So that means for four years, we're
going to give you Android updates.
And then after that, you're kind of on your own.
And so with all of these things, I
like to talk about the triangle trade-offs, which
everybody's heard about.
Performance, PPA, performance, power, and area.
Performance is obvious.
How well will your device run?
But not just on a GPU isolated situation,
but also if the GPU is in contention
with other things on the die.
What happens if you're trying to play a video
and you're also trying to render or trying
to use your camera at the same time?
You're trying to do an overlay on top of a camera.
You're trying to do NPU, AI kind of recognition of faces
while you're doing the camera.
All of these things cause bandwidth contention, resource,
and power contention.
So how does it work?
What's the performance?
You have to look at the use cases.
We also have power.
Power, I think, is split between battery and thermals.
And so sometimes you're not limited
by how much power you can give something.
You're limited by how warm it's gotten.
And then also you have your days of use chart,
which is like how many hours of constant use
can you use for different dynamics.
And then last is area.
Nothing's free.
And I'll talk about that more in the next slide.
But for every chip that you fabricate,
there is yield issues.
And the yield issues might be from when
you cut the die off of the wafer,
when during the process of fabrication,
maybe a microparticle landed on one of the chips
and it's completely not usable anymore.
And it's very expensive.
In this example, you have the orange chips
represent dies that are incomplete
because you're putting a square chip on a round wafer.
Defective dies are in red based off testing.
Good dies are green.
So you're not always going to get all the chips
on a die, on a wafer.
Maybe a couple of questions.
I've only one.
Why is it so difficult?
Why isn't it perfect when it's manufactured?
So the way that wafers are grown,
or that the silicon is grown, it's grown in ingots.
And ingots are literally crystallized growths
that look like you're growing a candle.
So you have somebody make a candle,
and you dip a string into wax, and you pull it out.
And you have these cylindrical bullet looking candles.
That's exactly how they make silicon ingots.
They dip very pure, I don't know what it is,
whatever the stem is, into a very, very pure source
of silicon sand melted.
And then they slowly pull it out of that sand.
And I'm oversimplifying greatly.
And it crystallizes, and it forms
these perfect crystalline silicon structures.
And it forms the same way you would a candle
being pulled out of wax.
And so with that, the easiest way they found
is that it's going to come in a circular pattern.
And so for the longest time, most fabs
were 100 millimeter wafer size, which
means that the diameter of the wafer was 100 millimeters.
And then it got to 200.
Now we have a standard of 300 millimeters.
And some people are trying to pull even bigger.
But what that's going to cost is a lot of tooling
we've done, and it's like industries and consortiums.
Some people want it, some people don't.
So we've been stuck at 300 for a good decade or so.
And of that 300, I actually have an exercise.
We'll go into it next.
So actually, before I do that exercise,
let's talk about fabrication, how it's getting more expensive.
So back in 90 nanometers, which I think is 2005,
a wafer costs $1,650.
Then as you went to 65 nanometers,
it went to about 2,000, then 2,200, and 3,000, and 3,600.
But then right about here, it starts jumping extremely high.
And that's because if you look at the feature size
we're getting to, we're going from 16 and 12 nanometers
to 10, to 7, to 5.
We're hitting the limits of physics,
which means that more and more things can go wrong.
The more transistors you pack into a silicon wafer,
the more opportunities for something to go wrong,
honestly.
And so it's just the yields are getting like,
the yields are shrinking because there's
more opportunities for things.
The components for tooling are way more expensive.
The lithography, which is like when they pattern the dyes
using extreme ultraviolet light, and the photoresist,
and the chemicals, all of this stuff
is getting more and more difficult and harder.
And it has to have extreme precision
that there's going to be more and more room for error.
Things that were considered noise two generations back
are now considered feature sizes.
And so things are getting way more expensive.
And so the last 10 nanometers, and this
is where Intel really kind of faltered for a long time,
the wafer cost.
And this information is not Samsung.
This is actually TSMC I found off the web.
So I want to say I'm not giving retreat secrets.
So I put a link under most of these tables.
And it may be right, but I don't care about the actual numbers.
I care about the trend.
6,000, 9,000, and then with 5 nanometers
is about $16,000, $17,000 per wafer, per single thing.
And so the question becomes, what's the cost?
How are we going to make money if the wafers cost $17,000
per wafer?
And so let's do a cost exercise.
You don't have to actually come up with a number,
but I'm just going to kind of put the question to you.
You assume you have a 300 millimeter diameter wafer.
Each SOC is 100 millimeters square.
You usually do 25 layers.
Like you bake like a multi-tiered pie,
or a multi-tiered cake every time you do silicon
manufacturing.
And so you do one layer, then you
put another layer of transistors, another layer
of transistors.
You do it like 25 times.
So that recipe, according to that previous slide,
was about $17,000 for a wafer at 5 nanometers.
10% of those SOCs are non-viable because of that edge geometry
I talked about.
You're putting square silicon dies on round silicon wafers.
And then each package, which I didn't even talk about,
like you cut these little pieces of silicon out,
you have to put them in that little rubber
thing that actually has metal prongs that
talk to the rest of the motherboard.
That actually costs money.
And actually, to put that silicon die
and wire it up to the external packaging also costs money.
And so let's just assume that's a $10 cost.
So all this to say, I'm not going to make you do it,
but to give you background, what's
it really going to look like?
So you use your simple ninth grade math.
And you know that area of a circle is pi r squared.
Radius is 300 divided by 2.
So we get about 71,000 millimeters squared
of area to work with.
We cut 10% off.
We get about 64,000.
And then we just do a simple divide by 100.
And we get about 640 chips.
If that's 17,000 divided by 640, it's about $27 just
in pure manufacturing cost.
It has nothing to do with all of the IP and R&D
and everything else that had to go into that.
And then you add $10, and it's $37 per chip.
And that's perfect yield, by the way.
Let's be realistic.
Let's say 50% yield.
And most of the time, a mature process can get up to 80% to 90%.
But a very new process will be more like 50%.
Now each SOC is more like $65.
And the SOC, which is the chip on a phone, for instance,
is not the most expensive part of the phone the screen is.
And so it's just to kind of give you
an idea that at some point, there's
reasons why companies like Global Foundry decided,
I'm going to stop at 16.
It's not making money.
And so there's really only two to three major silicon
manufacturers out there.
There's TSMC, Samsung, and Intel.
And I have to be honest, TSMC is doing really well.
Samsung is close second.
Intel, not so much.
Yeah?
Going off that Global Foundry point that you said,
going off at 15, what's the benefit of going smaller?
What's the benefit of going smaller?
Actually, that's a good question.
What do you think in the audience?
What do you think the benefit of going smaller would be?
Yeah.
It's more energy.
Why is it?
That's the better question.
Why is it more energy efficient?
Well, I think the reason is, I mean,
it's more of a longer wire.
Like, you know, it's more efficient
if you can get it to work longer.
Yep.
So electrons are traveling shorter distances
to do the same amount of work.
So that means you need less power to do so.
And you can also fit more logic in a wafer.
And so less power, more function.
It's kind of a double whammy.
However, like we talked about, it's not for free.
There's a lot of technology and a lot of thought,
a lot of R&D, and a lot of process
that has to be figured out to make that work.
And so he was showing me the ENIAC,
like that's on the computing area.
And you look at that, and you think about how simple that was.
And I actually have a slide talking about it.
And we'll go through how shrinking has actually
improved compute performance over time in a slide
a little bit later on.
So I keep talking about how expensive silicon
manufacturing is, and how are we going
to keep paying this cost over and over and over again?
Is it going to keep reaping rewards to keep shrinking?
The answer is maybe.
And so we have to be, as engineers,
we have to work within those constraints
that we have to spend a certain amount of money
to make something, and we have to sell it
for a certain amount of money.
And so the way we do it in the silicon world
is we have to make tiers of SOCs.
What that means is that you make a super everything
in the kitchen sink SOC, then you
take some of those features off, make a mid-tier SOC,
and then you take even more features off,
make a low-tier SOC.
And that's going to be big, medium, and small.
And that will be for different layers.
Let's say in the phone culture, it'd
be flagship phones, high phones, which
are really good but not quite flagship,
and then mid- and then low-tier, which
are something you'd want to give your kid.
And so that's one way to do it.
And so you can also design a smaller chip,
like we said, to have similar capabilities with less cores
and cache to make it smaller so it's cheaper to make.
Or we can actually reuse some of the broken parts.
And I don't think people like to hear that.
But what happens is that if we find a chip
and it has one core that's bad, we just
lock off that core in the firmware,
and we use everything else.
And we sell it as a GPU light.
That's exactly it.
I mean, when you think about the XT versus whatever,
everybody does this.
This isn't a secret.
In fact, back when I was in college,
they had, anybody ever heard of Silicon Graphics Company?
They used to sell something called the Octane.
And they used to ship every Octane with,
I'm making this number up, but let's say 8 megabytes of RAM.
And that was a big deal.
But they wouldn't enable all 8 megabytes of RAM.
They'd enable 2.
And then if you bought the upgrade,
they would enable 4.
But the similar thing, but backwards,
is you sell something that is almost good enough,
and then people are willing to buy it.
So kind of like gently, gently bruised fruit.
And so when we look at scalability
as an investment reuse, we want to take
all of the same software and all of the same things
that we did for this massive flagship product.
And then we want to right size it
and reuse all that same things and sell similar,
but smaller part in multiple segments
so we could reuse that same effort.
And this is used also everywhere in the industry.
And so here's an example.
And this is, I don't know what they call this,
but I call it like a bus diagram of an SOC
where you have all the different things.
And I'll just go over the main ones,
which you have a camera and an ISP.
ISP stands for image signal processor.
It takes all of the bare information from the camera,
it makes it into RGB or YUV,
and then it sends it on, it saves it to disk.
Or maybe it does some processing,
like maybe it denoises, maybe it does stabilization,
maybe it does HDR.
It does all these kinds of processes
that make camera pictures look good,
and then it saves it to memory.
You have a GPU, you have an arm or a CPU cluster,
big, little, you know, big CPU cores, little CPU cores.
You have an NPU, which is a neural processing unit.
VP, which is your video codec,
like thing that decodes your movies.
DPU, which is a display controller, you know, display unit.
You have the display,
and then you have these things I call PHYs,
or physical outputs and inputs.
And these are the different kinds of things.
Like everybody's heard of like HDMI,
but, and you have HDMI in and you have HDMI out,
and that's what most people do.
Or maybe they think of it as like USB-C
or something like that, or even display port.
But we also have like things like parallel ports
and MIPI-CSI, which is a camera interface
that you've probably never heard of.
MIPI-DSI, which is like a localized display interface
you've probably never heard of.
So all these other things that they do.
And then above all beyond, you have your memory unit,
your RAM controller,
and then you have all these other things
that you may or may not have,
like a 2D engine, a GPIO UART.
UART's like a serial port.
SATA for your hard drives, PCI.
If you have to, you have your MMC SD card,
if you have a little card you put in your phone.
HDMI security controller,
your PWM pulse width modulation, I squared C,
like all of these things that you've never heard of
that are on almost every device.
Like, has anybody played with like Arduinos
or have anybody ever played with like Raspberry Pis?
Raspberry Pis has all of this stuff too.
You just never heard of it before
because you never really use it.
You might use the GPIO pins or something like that,
but it actually has a lot more stuff.
Anyway, so you make this huge device
and then this is your flagship.
And then what happens is you cut off things.
You make the GPU smaller,
you take the NPU off, you just do it in CPU.
You take some of the CPU cores out
and all of a sudden you've shrunk,
you've kept the same soul of the chip,
but you've shrunk the capabilities
in order to sell it for cheaper on a smaller die.
And then you might even do it once more.
Just have CPU, memory, a few other things,
video and display.
And this is kind of like a Kindle e-reader or something,
you know?
And so we use the same kinds of IP,
we make smaller SoCs and we reuse in order to
make it cheaper to sell it
to more mass product and volumization, right?
So SoC reuse multiple products.
IoT can be defined as a microcontroller
and an ethernet stack, right?
Everything is IoT.
So you have digital bird feeders and drones and vacuums
and cars, car-backed entertainment
or airplane-backed entertainment.
All of these are using the same kinds of SoCs.
So this is all the same chip,
maybe shrunk down or grown, whatever,
but I think we take it into account
that they all have specific use cases,
but they're all basically the same.
And so another way to reduce high development costs
is doing something called pin muxing.
Pin muxing is when you use the same pins
for two different purposes in different modes.
And so sometimes you might have pins
that you use for some kind of like,
I don't know, SD card connector.
And instead of having an SD card connector,
you use them for GPIO.
Or if it's high speed,
instead of using it for a wifi connector,
like you're gonna hook it up to a wifi antenna,
maybe you use it for an ethernet jack
and maybe they just, they're connected,
you muxed it, you set some register on the SoC
and you're saying, this is gonna be an ethernet mode.
Pretend that you have a RJ45 connected to it.
Does that make sense?
So you do this pin muxing
and then you can use the same kinds of chips
and different kinds of configuration.
That's also a way to reuse the same packaging
because then you don't even have to repackage,
you just change the mode.
And then another way that's actually pretty recent
is something called chiplets.
Has anybody heard of chiplets before?
Okay, imagine you saw that we have these like shrinking nodes
where we have like 16 nanometers to 10 nanometers
to five nanometers to whatever nanometers.
What we can do is maybe not all of the IP on an SoC
need to be in the latest and greatest node.
Like the five nanometer node is the most expensive.
Do we really need our video decoder to be in that mode?
The video decoder on average runs at three or 400 megahertz,
not very high demand.
The GPU and CPU run on the order of one to two gigahertz.
So you can use an older technology for video decode.
You don't even have to remake it.
You just kind of, you make a,
add this thing called an interposer,
which is where you have these bumps
on the bottom of your die
and you connect them in a special packaging way.
And then you can use IPs of several different nodes
on the same device.
Now, this is an extreme case, I'll be honest.
I think what we're gonna see in the future
is going to be something like one or two nodes
where you have last year's node and this year's node.
And then you're using a lot of the less important things
in last year's node and some of the more important things
in this year's node, right?
And the reason we do that is to save money
and also to save research and development costs.
And so this is also something,
this is actually kind of funny
because if you remember what I was talking about being,
when I was in college, all the chips were separate
and then we had a motherboard connecting them.
Now they're still in the same package
and we're separating them again.
And so it's kind of like the circle of life.
Oh, and the other thing to know is that like
when you have an SOC,
you have different clock and power domains.
Some IPs require really, really fast clocks.
Some of them require really, really slow clock
because they don't really do much.
And yeah, I think that's the main point.
So the question on chips, is that still the same wafer
or is that different wafers now?
It's different wafers.
And so what you might do is in a very simple example,
you might have half of your SOC on one older wafer
and then the other half of your SOC on another wafer.
You just kind of stack them like Legos
and just make sure all the bumps
and all of the vias kind of connect the right way.
And you kind of align them.
You glue them together.
That's, I'm oversimplifying,
but yeah, you align them, you glue them together.
You're done.
Embedded graphics use case analysis.
So bandwidth for GPUs is more or less based
on resolution FPS that you desire, right?
That's very simple.
And when we look at an exercise,
I used to work for an IoT-ish company
and we used to go in front of a customer
and they say, what's your use case?
And we'd have the back of the napkin kind of calculations.
And I think every engineer needs
to be able to do these things.
Is this the chip or what chip would be good enough
to do your use case for the lowest amount of money?
And so they'd say, okay, well, this is what I want to do.
And just so I can give you an example,
how much bandwidth would be required
just to render a 1080p60 video game?
And so like, what does 1080p mean?
Does anyone want to tell me?
Like how many pixels, yeah.
Right, it's about like 2 million, right?
And then how many bytes are in a pixel?
Three or four, right?
Either have RGB or RGBA, right?
Okay, and then 60 frames per second
for self-explanatory.
And so if you look at this,
this is not including scratch mem or overdraw,
which is like reading and writing.
It's just to give you like the minimum
of just pretending you're coming up with stuff
from thin air and writing it.
It's gonna be about 500 megabytes per second, okay?
Now assume that you do have to read and write
and do a bunch of other things.
Now you're causing a lot of congestion.
And 1080 isn't even the hot resolution, it's 4K.
We take the same thing and we multiply that by four.
You get like two gigs a second just on the bandwidth plus.
And so we have to do some really interesting things.
Like we have to really worry about polygon count
with embedded.
I worked at a company where we're working
with car manufacturers and they have like,
when you turn certain cars on,
they show you that little model of a car in 3D spinning
in front of the dash.
Has anybody seen that before?
And they hand it to us and say,
this is going extremely slow.
And I go, okay, well send it to us.
Let's see what we can do.
They had like a 2 million polygon,
2 million polygon like model.
And I go, what did you give me?
He goes, we gave you the actual like CAD of the car.
And that's an extreme example.
But even when I worked in video games,
we would have multiple LODs and we would make sure
that the distance and the LOD matched up
so that we weren't doing more processing than necessary.
And so this is just an illustration to say
that after a certain amount of triangles,
there's no perceptible difference.
And I think this is pretty obvious to a lot of you
that have been doing graphics for a little while.
So, but we still have to educate our own customers.
And I also want to say that I've been alluding to this,
that rendering is just one part of image composition.
Like even when you're taking,
think about like a camera situation.
You're taking a video, but it's not just the video.
Assuming that all of the ISP stuff that's happening,
like all of the color correction
and all of the camera interpolation,
all that stuff's happening for free.
You still have overlays and you have some digital smarts.
And that means that the camera image has to be read
and interpreted by either a CPU
or a neural network processing or a GPU.
And it has to have overlay drawn on top of it.
So you can have a little box around the face
or you can have like,
what's your resolution that you're capturing it at?
All that stuff happens and we take it for granted,
but that's actually real work.
And every time something like that does happen,
it's another read and write on the bus.
So here's another kind of calculation situation.
So bandwidth requirements, part two, example use case.
We have our, you know,
your normal like UI for video, right?
Just to do this much.
And so we have a decoded video streaming
in H.265 on 4K.
We overlay 2D rendered UI on top of that video content.
We read the composited frame.
So the UI on top of the video,
and then we spit it out to the display.
Lots of people actually overlook the fact
that we actually have to write this to a screen.
None of that is free.
And so when you think about how much bandwidth you need,
how fast your bus needs to run,
how much cash you might need,
you have to take all of these things into account,
especially for use cases.
And so first things happen
is you read the encoded information.
You send that to the video codec.
The video codec takes it and decodes it
and sends it to the GPU.
GPU overlays this pretty picture on top of it,
sends it to the display controller.
Display controller syncs it up with the display using Vsync
and then ships out that image.
So let's play a game called how powerful is your smartphone?
Okay.
So just as a history,
I love the fact that you had ENIAC down the hall.
In 1948, ENIAC had a magnificent 400 flops,
400 floating operations per second.
I mean, I think you can get enough people in a room
and they could probably beat ENIAC, okay?
But that was amazing.
It was really, it's actually,
I mean, for the time it was awesome.
20 years later, the Cray-1 had 100 megaflops.
We couldn't get enough people in a room to do that.
That's pretty impressive as well.
But it also took up, you know,
probably a power plant worth of power
and multiple, multiple rooms full of servers to do that.
And then you have the Cray-3, 400,
the next supercomputer in 1990,
which wasn't as long as it seems.
Anybody alive at 1990 other than me?
Any, you're still on?
Oh, man.
I don't know how much I qualify.
Yeah, okay.
So in 1990, I was alive and kicking
and playing video games at the time.
That was 1.7 gigaflops was supercomputer powerful, okay?
And now we look at consoles
because I like to look at things that you know.
So the original gangster Xbox was 20 gigaflops, okay?
Xbox 360, 240 gigaflops.
Xbox One, 1400 gigaflops.
Xbox One X, six teraflops.
That was the one released maybe two and a half years ago.
Same thing, the PS PlayStation,
I don't want to leave them out.
It's very similar.
On the last two generations,
they're basically using the same chipset.
So 1840 and 4200,
but you can see like come from very meager beginnings
and look how powerful they are now.
And I say this, but even like just released from Nvidia,
80 teraflops on a single device, 80 teraflops.
That is, I have to say, it's amazing.
Now the power on it is requiring close to a kilowatt,
you know, and it is melting its connectors.
But that's still pretty impressive
if you keep the room cool enough.
16,000 cores, frequency 2.2 to 2.5 gigahertz.
Bus is basically a terabyte per second.
GPU RAM, 24 gigabytes.
Gigabytes of RAM on a GPU only.
Okay, that's pretty impressive.
And I want to compare this to a mobile phone.
Samsung Galaxy phone from last year, one to two teraflops.
I do want to say that's damn impressive, by the way,
in your pocket.
This is more than the Xbox One in your pocket, okay?
Power, 2.5 sustained, 4.5 watts peak.
What does that mean?
That means that normal operation, you're only allowed 2.5,
but if you really want to show off,
you can get four and a half, but not for very long,
like two to five minutes, okay?
Cores, four to 12 shader cores,
800 megahertz to 1.3 gigahertz
are very frequency constrained
because of the thermals and the power.
Bus is 68 gigabytes per second.
Okay, two orders of magnitude almost.
GPU RAM, a whopping one gigabyte, which is a lot.
I feel like I'm defending myself.
I really shouldn't be.
The mobile GPU is an impressive beast.
Now, I want to ask you a question.
Which is more efficient?
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, it's a leading question, right?
Oh, sure.
I can't tell you how much the GPU itself costs.
Like I could, but I can't.
But just to give you an idea that it's multiple hundreds.
And so, yes, it's much cheaper.
Maybe that wasn't a very fair,
but you can't really buy the NVIDIA card by itself.
You can't buy the NVIDIA chip by itself.
It's hooked up to a bunch of stuff with RAM.
You can't really buy the mobile phone by itself,
like the chip, the GPU by itself.
It's hooked up to a bunch of other stuff, so whatever.
But yeah, so the cost, maybe not the right comparison,
but the efficiency is pretty darn impressive.
I don't know if I wrote anything on that,
but you can see that if you were to take one kilowatt
or even 800, and you look at the difference
between 800 and two, or 800 and four,
you're talking about 200 times, right?
But then if you look at the shader TFLOPS difference,
it's only a difference of 40 to 80 times.
So we are basically one to two X more efficient, right?
Just wanna make that clear, we win.
Just joking.
So I wanna talk about what is it like
to work on embedded GPUs?
I've done this almost my whole career.
It's a weird thing because a lot of the sexy type
of GPU work is done in different industries,
not in the mobile phones.
And just recently, like the last 10 years,
the mobile GPUs really come into its own, right?
Being able to play video games on your phone
and have them not be card games is relatively new,
five, 10 years.
And so I look at this and I kind of talked about
everything that the Samsung group kind of does in order.
And I put three years, three months,
and three weeks kind of, and some kind of,
this is maybe a little deceptive of an order,
just to give you kind of an idea of how things work.
So first we start with marketing requirements gathering.
If you're an engineer, you always have to do that.
What do we have to build?
Who's going to tell us?
Are we going to look at competitive analysis?
Are we gonna look at what our customers want?
Why are we gonna build it?
What's the killer app?
Then we do software hardware co-design.
What did we start with from last year?
Where do we need to get to?
How are we going to do that?
What features and bits and bobs we need to add to it?
We do hardware architecture, RTL design.
Architecture is actually a macro level,
like big swab changes.
And then the RTL is kind of like implementation, right?
Actually changing the gates using Verilog,
actually figuring out how we're gonna get that done.
Hardware validation and RTL design happen at the same time.
They build a model as the RTL is being built.
So you have two different ways
of getting to the same information
to make sure that you can test what you built
and that it should work.
And it's pretty amazing that you can build
trillions of transistors in the device
and get it to work on the first spin.
Physical design device integration.
This is when you,
this is like the electrical engineering part of it.
Like everything else I've been talking about
is like computer engineering,
but this is like the electrical engineering.
This is where the rubber meets the road.
You actually have electricity powering
or the simulation of powering through the device.
Where are you gonna meet your timings?
How are you gonna do the layout?
What kind of transistors are you gonna use?
There's multiple, multiple flavors of transistors.
Some of them are very leaky and fast
and some of them are not leaky and slow.
What can you get away with?
All of these are trade-offs
that a hardware designer has to make.
And I'm not even smart enough to figure that stuff out.
So we have very smart people doing,
we call it PIPD, physical design, physical integration,
device integration.
Software driver validation.
We add new features all the time.
The OS is constantly changing.
The API is constantly changing.
The games are constantly changing.
We have to make sure that they all work together.
GPU tools, ecosystem enablement.
You have to be able to debug your video games.
You have to make sure that what you think you're drawing
is what you're drawing
and you're getting good performance.
And if you're not, why?
And so we have to provide that stuff
so that people can actually debug the games.
We have to do device productization.
What does that mean?
It means long time ago,
when I worked on like MP3 players before the iPhone,
you're welcome.
We would put like, this is a real tech.
Anybody ever heard of the Diamond Rio?
Or you guys have heard of the iPod, right?
There were MP3 players before the iPod.
Okay, and those MP3 players were sad.
And I worked on some of them.
The Walkman was a flavor, but it had a tape deck.
And then you had these like weird in between MP3 players
that would have a little bit of flash, like 64 megs.
And you can put like, and people were amazed.
You can put like 100 songs on it, okay?
And that was great because you had a cassette tape.
Anyway, or a CD with 12 songs.
Now you've got to 100 and that's amazing.
So one of the tests we did, and this is an example,
is we used to put a weight on a pencil
on top of the fast forward button,
and we go to home and we come back in the morning.
And if it was still fast forwarding, you win.
Okay, that's productization.
I know that's a very simplistic example,
but things that we do do is we fuzz
or we do something called monkey testing,
which is where we have a program pretend to hit buttons
all over the Android screen and try to break it.
Okay, and we do that and we have to pass 48 hours
without it crashing in order to call it productization.
Okay, and just be glad that people are doing this
because how frustrated would you be
if it crashed all the time?
So productization is getting this polishing
and getting all of the last minute bugs out of things.
Application development.
Sometimes we have new features
and our customers don't know how to use them.
We'll go into some of those a little later.
And then field application engineering is,
it's in the field, somebody reported a bug.
How do we dive into that bug, look at the call stack,
figure out what happened and fix it on an update?
Okay, all of these things are important.
And I kind of have this line in the middle.
This is when the actual chip comes back
and you can start working on real hardware.
Everything before is emulation.
Everything after is, we call it post-Silicon.
After Silicon comes back.
Pre-Silicon, post-Silicon.
Okay, this is my team.
We have, for Android, this should not be a surprise.
We have three APIs we support.
We have OpenGL and Vulkan and OpenCL.
And we have a compiler team that supports
all the shader compilers that do all of that work.
And then we support a couple OSs, Linux and Android.
And so we have a team for doing all this
and I have a few more teams.
And everything in blue is in user mode driver space
and it's in C++ and everything in orange-ish peach,
whatever the color is, in kernel mode driver space,
privileged space, and it kind of interacts
with the OS much closer, right?
So that's basically the team.
However, it's a little different.
One thing that we did recently,
and then we just productized it in last year's,
was we got rid of our OpenGL driver.
We converted it to a Google project
that we help support called ANGLE,
which stands for Almost Native Graphics Layer Engine.
And it actually translates Vulkan into OpenGL,
or OpenGL into Vulkan.
And the reason we did that is because
it reduces our total cost of ownership.
If we only have support two APIs instead of three APIs,
we win.
This is a open source product.
And so the community's supporting it in addition to us.
So we actually distribute some of that cost
of having to maintain a whole driver.
And that's actually pretty cool.
And also, it might, the hope is actually
that we push people to using Vulkan
because it's a much harder to use language.
So if they can compile their OpenGL stuff into Vulkan,
and they can do this at runtime,
then maybe they'll just use Vulkan.
But honestly, you guys have heard the Vulkan talk.
It's a very complex, hard-to-use language.
It's not as easy as OpenGL Hello World.
Some of the classes are projected.
I give them the option of sub-GL or what.
Yeah, suckers.
You don't want to use Vulkan.
All right.
So this is kind of another pictorial version.
So a GLES application translates into ANGLE and RUNTIME.
We actually redirect the OpenGL DLL into this ANGLE layer.
It has its own compiler that recompiles GLSL into SPUR-V.
SPUR-V and the state gets converted and put
into the Vulkan, and then goes into our hardware abstraction
layer, gets the kernel, the libdrm kernel on Linux.
We'll make space and do the threading,
send it down to the kernel driver, down to the GPU.
Vulkan goes directly down, so it doesn't
have this extra thing.
We have OpenCL with its own ICD.
So this is kind of what the call stack looks like for a driver.
So if I was to update that picture, it would look like
this.
You can see apps can either call OpenGL, Vulkan, or OpenCL.
Same thing, except really, the compiler now only
has to support Vulkan and OpenCL.
I can see I'm probably leading you to where I'm going next.
So the nice thing about SPUR-V, a lot of you
guys know what SPUR-V is, right?
It's the compiler language that gets generated
that's very low level, is that it's very versatile.
And so you can basically start from any source shader language
and compile into SPUR-V pretty easily,
and actually compile from SPUR-V into any other shader language.
So it's like a perfect, what we call,
intermediate representation.
And so because of this, we're actually
doing the next project that I've kind of funded,
is we're doing the same thing for OpenCL.
We're going from OpenCL, and we're
using a project called CLVK, and we're
going to convert the OpenCL into Vulkan.
And what does this do?
It simplifies this picture a lot.
So now, my group really only has to support a Vulkan driver
once this gets done.
And I can put all of my engineers on one driver,
make it really good, and yet I can
support three different APIs.
I don't know how interesting this is,
but this is actually kind of the way a lot of things
are going.
If you're on a Windows box, you really have a DX12 driver.
Everybody has a DX12 driver, and the DX12 driver
and the DX9, DX10, DX11 are being translated into DX12.
And they actually have VK on DX, and that's
being translated into DX.
And so the model is, let people program in what they want,
and let it get converted into a singular native format
so that the hardware companies don't pull their hair out.
Yeah?
Is there any, like, if you convert OpenGL into Vulkan,
is there a performance increase, or is it
just like the actual translation
so that it runs the code?
There's two answers to that.
So one of them is we're hoping that there's not
an actual decrease.
However, there is a cost.
There's an overhead cost in the compilation.
You're compiling something twice.
So what we want to do is we want to take,
so Google has an initiative to get people to use Vulkan more.
And part of the reason is pretty obvious.
What is the Apple shading language?
Metal.
Is that a high level or a low level language?
Low level.
Yeah.
Apple used to use OpenGL, yes.
And then they decided to have their own.
And so if Android allows people to use GLSL and OpenGL,
it's really not as competitive as Metal,
because it's not as low level.
However, the programming model sucks on Vulkan,
I'll be honest.
And so the way to do it is to allow them to program OpenGL
and convert it, and eventually replace things
so that you don't have to do the double compile.
I want to talk about a little bit more
software-oriented responsibilities.
I alluded to this before.
My group's responsible for real products.
Yeah, go ahead.
I have a question.
So how long do you think OpenGL has
before it's fully phased out?
I don't think this is a secret, but I
think the idea for Android space,
I can't speak for all the other spaces,
the idea for Android space is that it
will be deprecated completely by like 2026, 7.
But that doesn't mean you can't not use it.
It just means that if you're going to use it,
you're going to literally use Angle.
So either the operating system will
have Angle compiled into it, and you'll still use OpenGL,
but you know you're going to take this overhead.
You're taking a tax, a performance tax,
if you use GL.
Or there's a possibility they stop shipping it,
and then you have to basically bring it
in as your own DLL in your application.
So like OpenGL will stop getting support, but like so.
Let's be honest, OpenGL stopped getting support
for the last seven, eight years.
So in that case, once Angle is like fully deployed,
is there any need to also update that,
because it's a converter for a static API?
There's always reasons.
People are always finding bugs.
People are always finding new things.
But OpenGL has been in maintenance mode
for at least four or five years.
And they do add extensions, but nobody really wants them to.
And so the goal here, at least from Samsung and Google's
perspective, I don't want to speak completely for Google,
but the idea is that we want everybody to move to Vulkan.
And so in the Android space, we want people to move to Vulkan.
If you want to develop on OpenGL and eventually move
to Vulkan, that's fine.
If you want to even do your shaders in GLSL or HLSL
and confirm SPUR-V, that's actually
the model that's being pushed.
So really, what they're asking for you to do
is do one of two really easy things, which is one,
use an existing engine that already has Vulkan supported,
which is all of them, or two, write your own rendering
engine in Vulkan.
And I think most people are just using an off-the-shelf engine.
And so if you get a Unity or an Unreal,
they're already going to have Vulkan support.
You just have to make sure you're using it.
And that's actually the whole reason that Vulkan exists,
is the paradigm that people are trying to say
is that we want people, or people
have been moving to game engines,
and we want those game engines to have full access
and full control of the GPU.
And the way to do that is to give them a low-level language.
Vulkan was never meant for the average Joe to program into.
It was meant for the game engines to program into.
And so all of these efforts actually make a lot of sense.
If you want to program OpenGL, great.
It'll get converted to Vulkan.
You'll lose a little bit.
Or CL, it'll get converted to Vulkan.
It's fine.
You're losing a little bit anyway,
because the state machines that were incorporated in GL
were very inefficient.
And you're just reintroducing those state machines again.
But the hope is that most of the game engines
will go to Vulkan only.
And then you'll get that low overhead of the driver.
Someone?
Yeah.
How do you find, from your perspective,
the tooling around working on Vulkan?
Not good enough.
So we work with Lunar-G, and they
have a decent amount of tools.
A lot of translation tools are good.
RenderDoc, do you guys know what RenderDoc is?
All right, RenderDoc's actually not bad.
I mean, as a frame inspector goes, it's pretty good.
The other tools, like the profiling tools,
like Google has something called Perfetto, AGI GAPID.
Those tools can be improved.
We're hoping to help Google improve those soon.
So we do have plans to make that better.
But as an ecosystem, what's happened
is, because the tools aren't good,
we have hardware vendors, and we call them IHVs,
have their own tools for each IHV.
So it looks like an ARM tool and a Vulkan tool.
And Samsung doesn't want to have a Samsung tool.
So what we're trying to do is promote better tools
within Google.
And so, yeah, I don't think they're good enough.
That's the answer.
So hopefully, we'll make them better.
And it's a fun project.
So it should be fun in the process.
So software responsibilities, I just
want to say we have to support in maintenance mode.
It's kind of obvious.
For n plus 1 is next year, n minus 1 is last year.
n is this year.
For the next three years, we have
to OS update to make sure everything
is healthy in both conformance and performance.
But for the next year, or for the current year,
we have to validate the new OS to make sure
that it passes those monkey tests I talked about.
We have to do feature tuning to make sure
all the new features are working exactly how we expect them to.
We have to make sure everything's performance
tuned to make sure that everything, all of the policies
that we have in, say, the cache policies
are updated to give you the maximum performance.
You guys know what DBFS is?
You know what DBFS is?
Is it the volume system?
I don't know.
No, no, no.
It's voltage frequency scaling.
And that's when you can reduce the frequency of an IP
or increase it and reduce the voltage based
on that frequency or increase it.
It's a power management scheme.
And that's caused a lot of tuning.
Think of it as idle mode.
If you're not using your phone, you want things to go to sleep.
And if it's going to sleep, it's
going to take a lot less power.
That's kind of what we call DBFS in the silicon world.
So dynamic voltage and frequency scaling.
OK, yeah.
Being in the slide, I'm going to get into some cases here.
Yeah.
Every time a new phone comes out,
and there is a certain brand that I've been paying,
every time a new phone comes out, all the phone teams
know, or an existing phone team knows.
So the reason for that is battery.
And I think we found this out with the company
we're not talking about, where the battery starts
to have less and less power and retains a lot less charge.
And then the firmware detects that and compensates.
And then it's like a feedback loop.
And it gets slower and slower and slower.
If you remember that same company,
this had a recall and had to replace a bunch of batteries.
The number one thing people said was, man,
my phone is going so fast.
And it's not because they gave them a new chip.
It was because they gave them a new battery.
And unfortunately, I think that's battery technology
for you.
At some point, people wanted such slim phones
that they stopped having the removable battery packs on them.
And I almost feel like we need to go back
to removable battery packs.
But I'm not in charge of that.
You could basically keep your phone alive for probably 2x
longer if you just were able to get a fresh battery
without having to take the thing apart.
But then we wouldn't be paying $400 for a new phone.
You'd be paying $400 for a new battery.
Yeah.
OK, so we have OS integration is the new one.
And then we might be developing the new technology
on old OSes, because sure, why not?
We have feature development, feature spec,
and performance analysis is always happening.
Performance is always happening all the time.
We're always trying to look at workloads
and figure out, how can we squeeze an extra instruction?
What are common workloads doing that we can do something
different and make it better?
Like, if we coupled these two instructions
and put them in a single cycle and made that one thing faster,
how much boost would that give us?
So there's constant work.
This is kind of like microarchitecture work,
saying, looking at given shaders,
looking at assembly on the GPU, what are patterns we're seeing?
What are ways we can reduce work or eliminate work or streamline
or have concurrency involved to parallelize work?
In my team, we have various validation platforms.
I'm still, the theme of this part of the talk
is, what is it like to work in embedded graphics?
We start out, we have a C functional model,
which is for somebody who literally
writes a simulator of how each part of the GPU works.
And then you can actually run it, and it's extremely slow.
And it runs in tens of thousands, of course.
And we do a lot of validation and verification using that.
We also will load the RTL on an FPGA farm
that actually simulates the actual gates using FPGAs.
And then we'll run Linux on that and run workloads on that.
And then we'll also do the same thing for Android,
which is a little bit more complicated,
because it's kind of like an OS on an OS.
Like a lot of people don't realize
that Android is actually sitting on top of a flavor of Linux
also.
And then we get a couple rounds of Silicon.
I was at Intel for a long time, and they
used to do so many spins of Silicon
because they kept getting it wrong.
I'm not bashing them.
It's a hard problem.
But at Samsung, I'm really impressed
because we do two spins a year, and we get it right,
and we ship.
And so we do this preliminary Silicon
where we do all of the big macro architectural changes.
And then we do a final Silicon where we get the process right.
Because you have to think about it's like baking cookies.
They're always changing the ratios
of the different ingredients in the fab,
and maybe the transistor counts and variations
and combinations.
They're doing all of these process tweaks
just to get it right, to get a little bit more power,
a little bit more battery savings, a little bit
more performance.
And then so they do that kind of final polish
we call Silicon final.
And then we get these different types of prototypes.
So we get these prototype boards at first,
and they look like big one foot by one foot circuit boards
with all these pullouts.
And you can hook up these debuggers to it
and measure current and power and do all this really gnarly
lab work on them just to make sure they're all
working correctly.
And then we get these engineering boards
that sit on our desk for programmers,
and they look like really blocky phones
that you just plug into USB-C. And if you've ever
done Android stuff, you do the Android debugger,
and you just kind of program them.
And then we get basically what comes
to be like the final product.
So they come in three different spins.
And so that's pretty cool.
We do this every year, and we ship a new product every year.
So we've gotten very good at it.
So I want to talk about what does it mean
to do Silicon development?
This is such a foreign concept to software people, right?
It's kind of scary.
It's like magic or something.
Somebody's got to do it.
This hardware software co-design,
that's something that actually has to happen.
And so for a specific feature, I'm just being very vague here.
You have RTL design and RTL validation
happening at the same time.
CSIM is that C simulator, C functional model
we're talking about.
They write the code that's supposed
to emulate what you're trying to do at the same time
as somebody is writing the RTL.
And you have two different formats
to kind of prove that the functionality is
going to happen the same way.
And then they model it and make sure the timing's right,
it's doing what you're expected, it's big or small,
however many gates it needs to be.
And then they do RTL debug.
And then eventually they build it for those FPGA farms
I'm talking about.
And so we can intercept in this CSIM.
We can intercept in these FPGAs.
And then we can actually log in to an SSH terminal.
And we can turn on this FPGA that's emulating.
Has anybody done FPGA with Xilinx or any of that stuff?
You load up a RTL design in Xilinx.
This is just an extremely multiple hundreds
of thousands of dollars of FPGAs on a farm, just really big.
It's called like Xibu or something like that.
And we load the entire GPU and sometimes the entire SoC
on these FPGAs.
And we run it before it's actually put into the silicon.
And then we make sure it all works.
And we debug it.
And we work, both hardware and software,
work together to make sure that the new feature that they just
added didn't break anything and it works as expected.
And then we do software development, hacks,
and prototypes in that same process.
And it's kind of a circle, right?
There's a small circle here, software development, hacks,
and experimentation.
What can we do to make the GPU better?
And there's a big one, the RTL that was written.
How do we make sure that it's OK?
Similar thing, this is a performance flow.
It's a little bit different.
We'll skip up to here.
We have these FPGA builds.
We have software development hacks.
We do this thing called trace generation,
where we take a recording of a video game, OK?
And has anybody heard of like, when you do render doc
and you capture a game, like frame or something like that,
what you're actually capturing is all of the API calls
and all the assets being sent to the GPU
and your client intercepting those, right?
And you create this like player piano type of instruction
file like this to get that same frame rendered
without actually having a game behind it, right?
So you're taking a video game recording.
So what we do is we do something similar.
We take video game recordings, and then we
put them into special kind of like hardware traces
that can be interpreted by the model.
And then we run it through experimentation,
make sure it works right.
And then we do modeling and analysis.
We look at flame charts and buckets of histograms.
And we try to figure out, where are the bottlenecks?
And where can we make it better?
And we look at a bunch of graphs,
a bunch of really patient, smart people looking at it
and saying, ooh, this is bandwidth limited.
This is GPU shader limited.
This is CPU limited, the texture limited.
And you find out where your bottlenecks are,
and you try to increase or make that better
so you can make the overall game faster.
Because just like in most workloads,
you're going to have a place where everything is bottlenecked.
Everything's going slower because some things aren't
getting fed fast enough because other things
are going too slow.
Does that make sense?
Are there any questions on that?
AUDIENCE 2 If you do single class,
I showed them how to use on the NVIDIA profile.
Yeah.
Similar thing.
So this is where I go to the what's fancy in mobile part.
What are we working on?
The first one is, I'm going to put up a disclaimer.
It's not as fancy as NVIDIA because we're on a mobile phone,
OK?
Oh, and before I get to that, actually,
I like to have this slide because some things,
the ideas always come first.
But sometimes you don't have the technology to do it right.
And I would claim that VR is kind of there still.
We're getting so close, but we're not quite there.
But watches are successful.
Watches are there.
But you can imagine somebody had that watch idea 34 years ago.
And it just wasn't going to be as good.
And obviously, this is taking the 50s and 60s.
They knew it was coming, but they
needed to wait for the tech to get it to work.
I love this slide.
But let's talk about it.
So we actually have ray tracing on last year's phone.
We paid a company called Basemark
to come up with this demo because we
were the first to put ray tracing on a mobile phone.
There was no content, OK?
So what this look shows is they took
one of their previous demos.
And what I want to show you here is
we're not doing full global illumination
because that's crazy town.
But what we are doing is reflections, shadows,
and effects.
And so you can see all of the reflections
are all ray traced with one to two bounces.
This is no reflections and then ray tracing reflections.
In the past, if you didn't have ray tracing,
you'd have to do an environmental mapping.
And they'd have to put it in a box.
And you'd have to sample from that.
It'd be extremely painful.
Here, we can just ray trace it with the BVH,
put it in, and have it reflect.
And it's much cleaner.
And it's nice.
And so this is a marketing video, so it goes on too long.
But the idea is that Samsung, we're
actually first on ray tracing in mobile.
And other groups are starting to do this.
Some of the challenges we have is, like I said,
we're working on one to two terabytes, teraflops.
We're not going to be able to do what the desktop cards can do.
Anybody have a guess on how much global illumination costs?
Just on the order of.
Like, assume the latest NVIDIA is at 80 teraflops,
and they can do it.
How much do you think between 2 and 80
you might need to be able to do global illumination?
Something like that.
Yeah, I would say 20, actually.
I'd say 20 teraflops to do global illumination.
I can honestly say that phones are probably not
going to get there maybe this decade.
Maybe we will.
I'd love to be surprised.
But maybe we'll just get there by 2030.
I don't know.
But it's not going to happen overnight.
And so a lot of ray tracing, as we see it today,
is going to happen as an effects, as an ad,
not as a complete solution.
And I think that's OK.
Hybrid ray tracing is good.
And it will get better and better
as more performance capabilities come across.
Yeah.
I guess this is a general paradigm question
about ray tracing.
Because ray tracing is one big deal.
And it looks good.
And the results are good.
But I think something interesting to me
is this year, the Resident Evil 4 remake is coming out.
And the original Resident Evil came out on the GameCube
and the Xbox 360, that generation.
And this year, the PS5 remake of Resident Evil 4.
And the thing is, people don't really see the value.
It is fancy.
There are shadows and stuff.
But at this time, a lot of people
were like, it was good enough on GameCube.
And now that we have all this real-time ray tracing stuff,
if there are more people that are going to get it.
But I think that the product you're looking at
is probably not a great example.
And the reason is because if I was the marketing guy taking
Resident Evil, whatever, and putting ray tracing on it,
I'd be going after two people, Nostalgia,
and doing a remaster.
But it's not like you're creating new content
and you're creating a new game.
You're really just trying to milk an existing
product for more money.
Yeah, I mean, it's just a remake before the cash in on that.
Totally.
And so for that, their geniuses are
going to make a lot of money.
However, what I think is, as a purist,
you want to see somebody really using,
you want Pixar-quality graphics in a real game being
used amazingly well, right?
I think it's coming.
It's just very, very expensive.
And Z-buffer render graphics and forward-rendering graphics
just has so much more maturity.
And it does it so well.
And we can be fooled so well that it's
going to be very hard to top that immediately.
The other thing is that this hybrid rendering is probably
the right way to go until we get to that point
where people have really figured out all the nooks
and crannies of ray tracing for real-time.
Because it's a different ballgame
than doing ray tracing in RenderMan,
where you have 100,000 cores and two hours per frame.
So if you're trying to do 60 FPS, 1080p,
super-scaled with denoising, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
you could probably do it on NVIDIA.
But people haven't created that content yet
because they haven't thought.
It hasn't matured yet.
So I think, give it five years.
Somebody will come up with something good.
But yeah, is it real?
I think once computing is free, it'll never be free.
But once it's free enough that this is not tasking,
like 20 teraflops is what you have on your phone,
then it will be cool.
And because when phone has 20 teraflops,
means your desktop's going to have 200, or maybe even 500.
And then you can do everything.
And then it's just going to be so much easier for people
to do stuff because you're just describing scenes
and telling it to physically render them.
Yeah.
I mean, I guess just in that case,
is the end goal, or the end game, I guess,
because ray tracing, by being physically-based,
will give a bunch of things that forward rendering
has to update, right?
So ray tracing will give us all that
to treat if we're willing to shell out to the computer.
Is that inherently just going to be,
if the compute question is not a problem anymore,
is there no reason to not do ray tracing?
The compute problem is not a problem anymore.
I think that there's multiple answers.
There's no right answer to that.
So I just want to be, I'm trying to be safe.
What do I think?
I think that there's usually the circle of technology,
and this is how it happens, where everybody goes all out,
pedal to the metal, try to get the most performance.
And then they realize that that sucks
because now you have to have a kilowatt or two kilowatts.
And they realize, no, no, no,
really efficiency is important.
And they go down the circle again,
and then they start really maximizing efficiency.
And then they realize,
hey, we got the efficiency thing down.
Now we're going to go back to performance.
And this wheel of technology is always happening.
You had your desktop computer,
and then you got your cheap phone,
and then you got a faster desktop computer,
and then you got your mobile phone,
and eventually your mobile phone serves everybody, right?
So in my opinion, when the mobile phone's able to do
everything a desktop can do, maybe today or tomorrow,
then we get to the next tier of what the killer app is.
And so I don't know what the killer app is.
Maybe it's AR, maybe it's VR,
maybe it's the meta whatever.
I don't know.
But honestly, if you look at it,
we don't have anywhere near enough connectivity,
and we don't have anywhere near enough compute
for the metaverse yet.
And so we're not there yet.
And I think that we are going to have to do
these cheating things for a ridiculously long amount of time
partially because we're trying,
because our eyes and our ears are fixed.
Like our eyes and our ears,
at least for the short amount of time
until someone does the brain implant thing,
we're going to reach some kind of like limitation
where even today, have you,
anybody here about like Europe is thinking
of banning 8K screens?
Have anybody heard that?
Why do you think Europe would think about banning
8K screens?
And?
It takes too much energy.
What does that mean?
We've reached like the matrix level
of visual capability of a screen, you know?
So that's great.
Now it's, and so we're definitely reaching,
we're reaching these levels where like MP3 sound good to us
and they're not good,
but we're able to like fill in the gaps in the MP3
and make it, we perceive that it sounds good.
And so we're not really having to do truth.
We're having to do perceptual truth.
It becomes philosophy.
I don't know what's good enough,
but I also think there's just a science love of,
we want to do it and make it better
because it's awesome to try.
And I think every engineer will want to do that.
No engineers are going to be like, nope, nope, we're good.
We don't need to make any more products, you know?
Either it can be cheaper.
Use less battery or it can be faster.
So I don't have a great answer to that.
Yeah.
It's using ray tracing queries.
So if you guys know about ray tracing on Vulkan,
there's two modes, really two modes,
pipeline and queries, okay?
Pipeline's more asynchronous
and queries is kind of the cheap version
where you throw in like BVH loads and stores
and you do everything else basically is compute.
And that's kind of what this is doing.
So we started small.
It's mostly software enabled.
Pipeline's also supported.
It's also software enabled, it's just slower.
And then as ray tracing picks up,
you can imagine that Samsung's going to increase
the hardware that supports the ray tracing
to make it faster.
But right now, as it's so new,
they're not willing to put as much hardware investment
into it until it really picks off.
We made the only mobile ray tracing app at the time.
So the demand's not there.
We're trying to create the sandbox for people
to start creating content
and then we'll increase the capability as the demand grows.
Yeah, that's the question I had was,
given the performance limitations,
and maybe when keyed in on other things,
because if you try playing a ray tracing game,
you're certainly gonna find it's gonna be a bit slow.
But doing it with effects isn't that big.
I guess, yeah.
Yeah.
Do you think you'd like to see ray tracing
be applied on mobile phones to things like AR
and camera filters and other things
before we see it full on games?
I think so.
I think that ray tracing is going to be the easier path.
Maybe this is your question answer.
It's gonna be the easier path to AR.
I think if you can bring in light sources
and detect light sources in a room
and then physically remodel them
in the scene that you're trying to overlay
on top of using AR,
that's going to be a much easier problem to solve.
So, I mean, because if you think about it,
like everybody knows that like what,
you've done like the very simple ray trace,
like path tracers, right?
Where you like, you draw a circle without shadows
and you realize it doesn't look right.
And then you add a shadow and you're like,
oh man, that's like night and day, right?
And then you throw on like specular
and all this other stuff and you're like,
wow, that looks pretty good.
And it doesn't, but you're like, that looks pretty good.
And then you throw a material on,
you're like, this is magic.
And you really didn't like do that much, right?
You put in the circle equation
and you put in a couple of intercepts
and then you throw in a KD tree
and you're like, I'm amazing, right?
And everybody does the same thing, right?
And so think about that.
That's so much easier to program.
The paradigm is so much easier.
Now say I want to detect and I want a 3D,
like what do you call it, slam the room
where you're modeling what the room's looking like.
And then you're going to try to put something
in the center of it and using ray tracing to do that.
Probably going to be the faster path
if you have all the compute you need.
So I don't know, I'm making stuff up.
Okay.
Next thing that we've done on last year's
was variable rate shading.
Has anybody heard of variable rate shading?
Yeah.
You want to describe what it is?
Yes, that's perfect.
I would call this the inverse of MSAA
MSAA, what does MSAA do?
It renders, so like for instance, MSAA4
will take four samples around the pixel,
average them to draw a single pixel, right?
This does the opposite.
It has different kernel sizes, like one by one,
or one by two, two by one, two by two,
four by two, two by four, four by four.
And if you can get away with it,
if either the application designer says
this part of the scene's not important,
then you can actually render through one pixel shader
and duplicate that information on multiple pixels.
This has become more prevalent.
Like this is almost backwards thinking in like 10 years ago
because we're trying to get more resolution,
but now we have too much resolution.
So now we need to do less work.
And so they're actually going backwards.
The two different flavors of this are attachment VRS,
which is where you have a lookup map
of the different areas you want different kernel sizes.
I call the kernel sizes like that,
four by four, two by two, or whatever.
And you can see that in yellow, those are smaller,
like one by two, two by two.
In white, it's one by one.
And then in orange, it's two by two.
Our device, this last year,
we only supported up to two by two.
We're looking to do more in the future,
but we need to get feedback and see if it's worth it.
Pipeline is different.
It means for every draw call,
the whole draw call is going to be in one by two,
two by one, two by two, or whatever.
So you can see that the whole draw is orange,
and this is an overlay,
and this is what the original scene looked like.
And so there is a lot of really interesting goodness
where if you want to see if you can save something,
you can probably do some analysis of your last scene
and then extrapolate that to your new scene.
I'll give you an example, like a typical,
like anybody know how MP3 works?
Does anybody know how it's like JPEG compression works?
The idea is that you're going to play
with the perceptions of the viewer or the listener, right?
An MP3, if you have a very dynamic sound wave,
you could probably throw away the small noise
next to that dynamic sound wave,
and you save some of that space in memory, right?
That's called compression.
Video is the same way.
If you have a very stark part of the scene
or a very gradual,
you could probably reduce the detail on the gradual
because it's not very perceptible
because our eyes are like derivative machines.
We're looking for change.
And so with this,
you can do some like DX, DY type calculations
and say, this is where we can cheat
because it's barely changing.
And this is where we can't cheat
because it's a sharp edge, right?
Very simple stuff.
Yeah.
This can be, you can actually do this as post-process.
And so you can feed,
it depends on how the application wants to do it.
So this is application dependent.
If you know what the previous scene
is going to be basically the same as the next scene,
like you didn't move,
let's say you're a character and you're standing still,
you know the last scene and the next scene
are pretty much similar.
You could probably take a sampling of the last scene
and have it infer your next scene.
And then what you're telling your pixel shader is,
hey, for these pixels, you're gonna be this kernel,
throw away, if it's like a two by two,
throw away three of the pixel shaders and reuse them.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
Coming soon, algorithmic DNN or super resolution.
This is something everybody's playing around with.
You guys have heard of like DLSS or the Intel, whatever,
or the AMD has one.
The problem with this,
and I was telling a few people about this,
is that the cost of doing neural necks
on an embedded device is extremely expensive.
NVIDIA can get away with doing super resolution
because let's say they're operating at like 40 teraflops.
If they can shave off a couple of teraflops
by like rendering at 720 and upscaling to 4K,
then they have a couple of teraflops
to do this neural net on.
We don't have that kind of like spare change.
And so the cost of doing the neural net
has to supersede the savings in not rendering those pixels.
And the ratio for embedded isn't as good.
And so instead I wrote this word algorithmic,
which is, anybody heard of FSR?
It's like what AMD does.
And so what it is,
is it's basically like a classic upscaler
with a sharpener.
You get like a Kalman filter,
which is like you're taking sampling
and you're interpolating upwards,
and then you do a sharpening pass,
and then that gets pretty good results.
And it's fairly cheap.
It's basically like good enough graphics,
and you could probably do that
if you really want to save power
or you want to save bandwidth
or you want to save processing power, increase your FPS.
And so we are looking at things like this.
And so this is kind of ongoing research.
Mesh shaders, anybody heard of mesh shaders before?
That's what AMD is, right?
It's, what is it called?
It's called the Nanite.
Nanite is using mesh shaders.
You have a form for manual framing
in 2020 of mesh shaders,
but it's a brand new thing.
I am not completely sold on mesh shaders.
We will probably support them
because we like to support everything.
There aren't a whole lot of killer apps for it yet.
That's not to say that there won't be.
I am optimistic that somebody
will come up with some amazing stuff.
The couple examples I've seen are,
this bunny shows like all the different colors
or different meshlets.
And so breaking up and procedurally generating
a larger mesh with a bunch of smaller ones,
each meshlet is going to provide
better localization and cache,
which means it's close to where all the other vertices
that it's being worked on are in memory.
And you're going to get a lot better localization
or cache utilization using that.
So that's one way of doing it.
And if you can avoid having to just look
all of these vertices up,
then you're also saving bandwidth there.
Another way is bounding box culling based on this.
And so you can do culling based on each one of these.
But if you look at what a mesh shader really is,
it's like you smooshed the vertex tests
and geometry shader into a single thing.
And some people really disliked how the vertex,
the front half of the pipeline evolved over time.
Like how many people, I almost know nobody
who's ever done tessellation ever.
Like just ever.
I actually, I wrote a tessellation translation layer
for a company to go from OpenGL to Vulkan.
So I know it intimately and it's painful.
And it's not easy and it's not very intuitive.
And then geometry shader, as soon as tessellation came out,
geometry shader kind of like the only extra thing
that geometry shader did was transform feedback.
Does anybody know what that is?
Oh, he does.
Does anybody else know what transform feedback?
It's when you can either take the output
of the geometry shader and spit it to the CPU
and CPU visible memory,
or you can take the output of the geometry shader
and do something called draw auto
and then have it introduced to a different vertex shader
without having CPU intervention.
It's like you're doing a second pass
without the CPU doing anything different.
This was very exciting in 2014.
And both of these things were kind of superseded.
So the ability to do computations
where you have to have a CPU,
that's because CPU shaders didn't exist yet.
Or compute shaders, I mean.
The compute shaders didn't exist,
so they bastardized this geometry shader to use it.
And then tessellation didn't exist,
so geometry shader was trying to pretend to be tessellation.
And so then once tessellation came out,
this really became useless.
And then tessellation never got used.
And so we have these three shader stages
that are really underutilized.
And they're like, you know what we need?
We need a new paradigm.
And I'm like, great, more shaders.
I'm not saying that people won't do exciting things about it.
I am saying that the bloat is a little disheartening.
Okay.
So I was asked to talk about careers in graphics,
and this might be a more interesting part.
So I kind of did high level of like,
talking about silicon and how it interacts with graphics.
It's a lot less exciting than really sexy
like drawing pictures part,
but it is kind of more pedal to the metal,
rubber meets road type of part.
So there are about,
I kind of like categorize six different areas
of graphics careers.
These are the first three,
and I call them the application careers, okay?
And I've interacted with a lot of these.
So you have the complete artists
where they're technical artists,
writing shaders, animators, doing mocap and translation
and updates of animation streams,
material designers, which is a real thing
where you do nothing but develop and design materials
so that they're read back and look beautiful.
And then lighting experts, which is a complete career.
Like I used to work on Mad and I shipped,
and there was like a time where like,
you have to freeze development
and then we're gonna let our lighting guy work on it.
And then the lighting guy tweaked every single material,
every single light source, every single shader
to make sure that the lighting looked good.
And he was, he sat in this black room
with like black paint on the walls and like,
foam, I don't know how foam helps light.
And then he would just,
he'd look at seven different types of screens
that all had different, you know,
profiles of colors and gamma
and figure out what lighting looked like on all of them
to make sure it looked the best for all of them.
That's a real career.
And it actually, in film, the same thing happens
where like an inordinate amount of time is spent
on just tweaking lighting because our eyes
and the way we feel about things
will make or break the uncanny valley.
Okay.
3D game engine developer, 3D tools maker.
I say 3D tools maker,
I don't think people think about that as a career.
It's a very important career.
We went to SIGGRAPH.
I feel like every talk at SIGGRAPH this last year
was talking about the lack of content creators
for the meta whatever.
And so the fact that we're gonna have this metaverse
or whatever, there's gonna be this world
and average mom and pop can't make a 3D model
to save their lives.
They all want to do something.
So we're gonna have to create these tools
to create 3D models.
And they're gonna have to be very approachable
and usable by common people.
And so it's like, that's a big deal.
And how are we gonna do that?
We have to have tools
and those tools are gonna be super important.
And I think there's gonna be a huge demand
in the tool industry for that kind of thing.
And you have to know all of the graphic stuff.
You have to know all the hardware stuff.
You have to know all the formats.
You have to know what the UI, UX,
how people wanna work with things.
You have to think about the person, the HMI.
That's actually a really insightful and hard problem.
You also have to know psychology.
The really, I work with a UX firm
and they have like multiple psychologists
working on the team because they wanna think
about how people will think.
That's a big deal.
And then I think this is kind of obvious
with visual effects and physics modeling for like film.
And I met somebody who used to work at the Foundry
and everybody heard the Foundry.
And so they do the Nuke thing.
And so like I was talking to him, I was like,
what is it?
Tell me what the Foundry does.
And he's like, well, every time a hundred million
or billion dollar movie comes out,
they make brand new tools for that movie.
And then they finish the movie
and they throw all the tools away.
And so the Foundry like buys the rights to these tools
and then maintains them, puts them into a package
and sells them to smaller theaters
and gives the original makers the licensing fee.
So that's where like Nuke came in
and all these other things.
I thought that was very interesting.
Hardware and low level software is kind of more at my area.
So you have high performance computing.
So HPC doing things in the cloud,
visualization for science, visualization for weather,
visualization for whatever, using multiple clouds.
And I think this kind of, it's not quite like movie and film.
It's kind of a different ball game.
Desktop game console, it's obvious.
Mobile industrial IOT and automotive,
we kind of talked about.
These are other areas.
Okay.
So I guess here's my career advice.
I'm gonna go pretty quick.
I'm almost done.
I like to think of this and I'm an optimist.
Every company is a university that actually pays you.
And actually if you're getting a master's
and you're not getting paid, that's also a problem
because you're basically an indentured servant.
So if you're an RA or TA, you should be getting paid
to go to grad school.
If you don't care about the product or research,
you won't stretch yourself to succeed.
So you really have to care about what you're doing.
You have to be exciting.
You have to wanna go to work in the morning.
Don't go for the money, at least at the beginning.
Go for what you actually wanna learn.
However, and this happened multiple times in my life,
canceled projects hurt.
Just be really, it's like losing a child.
And so realize that you're gonna care about something
and you have to realize, hey, the product really was me.
The product that got canceled,
that just happened to be the vehicle I used to learn.
And the one thing most projects do is get canceled.
Every team you work on becomes your family.
People should always come first,
even at the expense of work.
How did I come here?
Well, I had a great conversation at SIGGRAPH.
We're gonna be friends now.
And then the graphics community is just like that.
You operate on the same standards boards.
You talk to the same people at SIGGRAPH.
You work with them and then come,
you probably, two companies later,
probably work with them again.
Hell, they might get you the job at the third company.
Who knows?
So just be nice to everybody.
Realize that graphics is a very small, tight-knit community.
Don't be a jerk.
Okay.
Stages of a career.
I'm gonna go through this before.
I think this part's pretty obvious.
When you first get to a job,
learn as much as you can about everything.
Be humble, ask a lot of dumb questions.
I still ask dumb questions all the time
because I want to encourage other people
to ask dumb questions.
So if I'm the guy and I'm supposed to be in charge
and I'm asking dumb questions,
then it's free for all.
Take on more responsibility as you can.
Grow that, be aware.
Mentor others when you feel competent enough to.
Try to understand the big picture in your company
after you've done one, two, three.
Rotate teams and positions and then start again.
I hired this VP from a very big video company
and he's working for me now.
And I said, why are you gonna take this pay cut?
Why are you gonna come work as an IC?
You're a VP.
And he's like, that's how I do my thing.
I started a company.
I'm always an individual contributor
and I make my way up to VP.
And he's done it three times.
And I'm like, great, you can take my job sometime.
It's great.
But he's like, if you do get to a position
where you're up here,
it's always good to keep your hands dirty,
understanding what you're talking about.
Don't underestimate the people under you
and appreciate what they do and constantly learn.
That's the best part.
If you're not learning, then I think it's not worth it.
And Samsung's hiring.
I was surprised to see this.
We're actually number one on Forbes' list.
I think that might be the only list,
but we are a big company.
We're doing a lot of things.
I have many, many recs in GPU group.
If you are interested in internships or full-time,
let me know.
That's my plug.
That's it.
Okay.
I can answer any career questions,
GPU questions, bag questions, personal questions, whatever.
Yeah.
I don't know any Verilog.
I don't want to give the impression
that I'm a super-duper hardware guy.
I'm like a low-level software guy.
And the funny thing is that low-level software
is all still written in C.
It's starting to convert to Rust.
But then that's like the kernel.
Most of our drivers are C++,
and most of it's already written.
And so when you think about coming in,
I think people have this fear,
like, I won't know anything.
I'll be like, well, guess what?
The code is there.
Just be willing to learn the code, ask questions.
And as long as...
I think this is kind of how I try to hire.
I try to hire really smart people,
and then I try to find a place for them.
And so if you're willing to learn and you can code
and you can talk your way out of a box,
then there's a possibility for you
to go wherever you want to go.
And for embedded, I think it's the same.
Everybody has to get their first embedded job, right?
Coming out of school is a great excuse
to get that first embedded job.
You could be like, what did your experience have?
I don't, I'm out of school.
Hire me, you know?
And so I think it's fine.
So I don't think there are prerequisites
other than a desire to want to do hardware.
I think kind of what this class teaches
to all of its students on an abstract level
is good programming, how to use the debugger,
how to use the profiler.
Yeah.
And that's kind of fundaments
of any programming job in my opinion.
Totally.
I think don't be scared of disassembly, you know?
That's another hardware thing.
Be able to use a debugger.
Don't be afraid of like reading register specs
and things like that.
I know that's kind of weird,
but like, have you ever,
have you guys taken like a microcontroller class?
You don't talk, anybody taken a microcontroller class?
What happens is that you get this big spec
on what the pins do, what the register states are
and how to program it.
And it's just like reading standard instructions.
Just don't be as scared of that.
And then a lot of times,
most of my guys that work in the user mode level,
they have no idea how the hardware works.
They just know that this is the command
I have to send to the GPU to get that work done.
And that's okay.
And so we have different levels of abstraction
so that different spheres can work on different problems
and not have to worry about the whole full stack.
And so if you want to start out here
and work your way down, that's great.
If you want to work on your way down and move up here,
that's the other thing.
So sometimes I'll hire people
that are really good kernel people
that have never touched a GPU before, and that's fine.
We'll teach you GPU if you can do the kernel stuff.
Or if you know the GPU stuff,
we'll teach you the kernel stuff.
You can't know everything.
That kind of goes back to my point
that every job is a university that pays you.
We're willing to have to train you.
And we usually give rule of thumb, new hires,
I say six months to nine months to ramp up.
Experienced mid-level guys, I say three to six months.
And super senior guys,
I'd hope they'd be ramped up within three months.
Any other questions?
Maybe one for me.
Yeah.
On the second last slide.
This one?
Yeah, the one with the text.
The second one that you say,
care about the product, which I completely agree with.
Yeah.
As all of my students go to interview me,
how do you find out?
Like, as somebody who does interviews,
what are your recommendations for questions
as interviewees should ask?
Or learn more about what they might be working on?
Okay, so there's multiple parts to this question.
So if I was to interview with a new company,
let's put it that way,
I would be like, what project am I working on?
Similar to like, if you went to a university,
a lot of people would be like,
who's the professor I'd be working on?
I'm almost more worried about the professor
than I am the university.
At some point, it depends completely on your research.
For a job, it'd be the project and the people.
You'd wanna be able to have a beer with the people
that you wanna work with.
You wanna know that you're going to every day,
they're eventually gonna be your family.
Can you see yourself hanging out with those folks?
Honestly, that's something that's a big deal for me.
Maybe it's all project-free, that's fine.
Second part is,
is the project something you'd be proud to brag about?
You know?
I mean, you'd wanna be able to tell,
I wanna be able to tell my kids, you know, what do I do?
And I'd be like, hey, I make cell phones,
or I make video games, or I make car screens,
or I don't know, whatever.
And so you say, you wanna be proud of it.
You wanna know that by doing this thing,
you're making, you know, you're helping people,
or you're stretching technology,
or you're making yourself smarter
and giving yourself a broader level of experience.
So maybe the next move is going to be way better for you.
Because sometimes,
this job might be preparing you for the next job.
In fact, they all should be.
But maybe you even plan that this job's
going to prepare me for the next job.
Like, I know a lot of people say,
how do I get into video games?
And the answer is, be willing to work for no money.
There are a lot of people who wanna get into video games.
Yeah.
I got into video games by working for a graphics drivers
and knowing the hardware really well,
and then being able to talk like that
when I went to an interview for video games.
And then they kind of looked at me and said,
so how much, how excited?
I love this question.
How excited are you to work at video games?
And I go, not excited enough to take a pay cut.
Just be careful.
They said, okay.
So just be your own advocate on that part.
But yeah, I think video games are exciting.
Sometimes video games are redundant, and I'll say that.
Like, if you're working on an engine
and you're not writing the engine,
then really what you're doing
is you're babysitting assets and shaders.
If you're into the rendering side,
if you're not in the rendering side,
then maybe you're doing animations.
Maybe that blows your head back.
Maybe you're doing,
I mean, there's a lot of parts of video games
and not all of them have to do with rendering.
Like there's animators, there's gameplay designers,
there's physics modelers, there's gameplay logicians
that are figuring out like, is this fair?
Is this unfair?
Is this gonna make for a really exciting game?
There are technical artists and they're rendering guys.
There's performance guys and there's connective.
There's so many different places to be in video games.
So just be very accurate within your own mind
of what you mean when you say I wanna work on video games.
And then realize what that entails.
For rendering, because this is a rendering class,
if you work for a video game company
that uses somebody else's engine,
there is a lot of creativity in that.
But sometimes, like I worked on Madden, year after year,
somebody told me this was happening
and I didn't believe him.
He says, at one point, Gabe, you're gonna think,
I don't give a crap what the grass looks like.
And so, but I think other things,
you work on this dragon game and you get to design
how the dragon looks and what the textures are
and it's beautiful, that's exciting.
You get to design the physics and the rendering
of how the flame and the smoke comes out.
We were at SIGGRAPH, one guy talked about clouds
for three hours, he was so excited.
I mean, things that blow your hair back,
just know what they are for you and then go after it.
But just realize that once you've made it
into video games, maybe it's not the flavor
of the slice of video games that you actually wanna do.
So then just taking a look at it from the inside
and thinking how-
Exactly, yeah.
The other question I had was,
so you, right now you're writing all these graphics APIs
that get used by game engines of Google Graphics
and in your previous role on Madden,
you were the person using those graphics APIs.
How does it compare to what you've done before?
And maybe what you do on the big screen.
I'd like to change it.
So I like analogy I use a lot,
which is like when I started on drivers,
I felt like I was a mechanic
and that the GPU was like the engine or the car.
And I kept using and tweaking how the car was running,
but I never got to drive the car.
And eventually I was like, I wanna get out of this.
I wanna start driving the car.
So I got my monkey suit off
and I jumped in the driver's seat
and I was working on Madden and then you're using it.
And then there's other limitations, right?
They're saying you have an artistic director who's saying,
and when I worked at Madden, I worked on two things.
I worked on crowds, what the crowds look like.
And I worked on player indicators like the hit X,
kick the field goal, here's a rainbow, that kind of stuff.
And make that look fancy and all this other stuff.
And so you're not in control of what it gets to look like.
You're being given specs and saying,
this is exactly what the artists rendered using Photoshop.
We want you to make it look that way on the GPU.
So there's no like, I'm not being like,
I really think it looks better purple.
They don't care what I think.
They just say, make it run exactly like that
and make it run fast, okay?
Then I came and I was like, I get it.
And then honestly, it's a tough life.
Like the crunch times in video games is exhausting.
I had a family and I'm like, peace out.
And so I like went from video games to work on car GPUs
and SOC architecture and computer chips again.
So I like went back forth, back forth.
Then I, after that, I worked in VMware
and I worked on graphics translations for VMs,
making Windows VMs work on Linux boxes
and Linux boxes work on metal and all this other stuff.
So I did all of that translation.
That was pretty cool, working for a software company.
And then I went back, I keep going,
hardware company, software company,
hardware company, software company, hardware company.
And so now I'm back at a hardware company
that thinks it's a software company, so.
Like something, I don't know,
maybe something electronic for a hardware company.
Exactly.
Well, I mean, the main software we provide
is a tweak off of the Android OS.
So I kind of feel like I'm part of the hardware component
of a hardware company, yeah.
Software, I'm a software person in a hardware world.
I don't know what the question was.
I think I lost track.
It's just different.
Also, here's the other thing,
the progression on the next slide is real.
You go from being this and nine to five,
hands down, code, code, code, I got it,
I didn't get it, I'm frustrated, I'm not frustrated,
I got my project done, great, here's a new project.
And then you go into project, self-project,
now you're in charge of a larger module or whatever.
And now you're dealing with other people,
you're making sure that you get things going
and you're changing.
Now, honestly, the higher you get,
the more people you have to deal with.
And so it's not just about the technology,
it's about the technology and the relationships.
And then I'm in the point where I'm in a director now,
and all it is is people who talk technology
and are not good communicators.
And so that's also a different challenge.
I love talking to people,
and I love talking to people when I was down here,
but I also was very self-conscious
and I wanted to be as technically competent as possible.
And so I really strove to be as technically competent
than I wanted.
And when I was down here,
I wanted to go the principal route
and then circumstance changed me somewhere around here
and I went the management route, happens.
The difference in that,
it's just like, you're gonna have to figure out
if your personality likes it or not.
I get to be at the big boy table
when decisions get made, which is awesome.
But I'm also like not the guy,
like the people go to to say, how does this work exactly?
You just have to be comfortable with what you're good at
and what you can strive and do well in.
Yeah.
Let me go back to this slide.
It's an answer without an answer.
Sorry, too many.
It's gonna be right about...
Oh man, it's really farther up.
Sorry.
And yeah, there's a lot of slides.
Hold on.
Yes.
I think that's a better question.
I can't answer what Samsung's planning on doing
that we haven't released.
So I'll just say that because this is being recorded.
And I'll say that everything that we currently do
for a mobile phone can be applied to that space.
What are the new...
Let's talk about the use case.
What is the use case for VR and AR
that's different from a mobile phone?
I think this is a good exercise.
We can just talk about it.
If you were going to create a VR or AR chipset,
what would you need?
Yeah, I mean, so, but let's go even further.
Let's go even further.
What are your inputs and outputs?
Let's look at this picture.
You need to have lots of cameras for orientation, right?
You have at least two displays, right?
Maybe one big display that's bisected into two displays.
Right?
Yeah.
Potentially, if you're playing video,
you're gonna need one of those.
You're gonna need what they call a GNSS
or some kind of gyroscope accelerometer situation going on.
Maybe you have other sensors that are using like UART
for tracking for,
there's different ways of doing depth perception, right?
You can do stereo camera.
You can do time of flight.
You can do structured light.
You can do IR.
You can do new things that haven't.
Sure, actuator, cameras, iris tracking.
But honestly, like,
so taking it from for consideration
that what would you have to do to get it to work?
What would you have to do to get it to work?
So taking it from for consideration
that what would you have to do?
So one thing that people don't think about with AR and VR
is the refresh rate requirements for AR, VR
is incredibly high.
We'd have to do something called chasing the beam.
Does anybody know what that means?
You've heard of chasing the beam?
And this is-
Is the beam referred to the gaming?
No, it's an anachronism, okay?
It's like, you know why we double buffer?
Why do we double buffer?
Because we can't have a next frame.
Yeah, that's too late.
We can't have a next frame
because you want the camera to update
as quickly as you move.
So instead of having a double buffer,
it's a single buffer that is updating all the time.
And so you can't afford the double buffer
because you don't want to have to do this ping pong flip.
You're literally chasing the beam.
So as you update the next one,
you need to be computing the one after that, okay?
That's what chasing the beam means.
That's more like a scanline kind of thing.
Exactly.
You go to the next scanline
and start processing the previous one for the next frame.
Exactly.
And so they do things like they cheat.
And so another thing is that there's a lot of hardware
in the VR thing that like Oculus uses, for instance,
where they overdraw.
Overdraw is drawing an image way bigger than your viewport
so that if you do move quickly based on accelerometers,
you can pan the existing image
even if you haven't had time to render it.
And so that's a cheat.
Another cheat that they do is they have focal lenses
and foveation.
You know what foveation is?
What's foveation?
So render a left pixel in the corners of a VR headset.
Which actually uses, I can't do this, too many slides,
the VRS thing I talked about.
So if you VRS around the outside of your vision,
the periphery, then that's going to save space
and you can actually get better performance.
You may not even have to update the periphery.
Maybe you update the periphery at a much lower rate
than you do the center.
So you have to do perceptual hacks to make VR much more,
because otherwise if it's any lag at all, you get a headache.
So a lot of this has to do with sensors,
but also a lot of it has to do with compute.
And you probably want dedicated display controllers
for each eye.
And you probably want maybe even a dedicated GPU for each eye.
And you probably want even a dedicated CPU and NPU
and all of this other tracking for each eye
or for each camera on the bug lens on the outside.
So there's, you can, I mean, can one SoC do it?
Yeah, they have them.
And then, you know, the Qualcomm one has it.
Is it a perfect solution?
No, they're going to iterate on it every year
and figure out ways to do it better.
Could my chip do it potentially?
Yeah.
I have a question about the chip.
So, you know that the cloud consistency
is kind of a point out.
So, some larger mobile phones,
they're going to have to be integrated with the console
if you're going to do that,
or the cloud has to be integrated with the console?
So, what happened to Stadia?
I mean, it's serious.
I think, you know, I think it's a good idea.
I mean, I think it's a good idea.
I mean, it's serious.
I think Google did an amazing job on Stadia, by the way.
It worked.
Why did they cancel it?
No, what problem are they solving?
Like, what problem did they solve
that wasn't already solved in a different way?
So, like, you want a game for a reasonable amount of money?
Get a console.
If you don't have a console,
if you don't have a console,
you're probably not going to have 10 bucks a month, okay?
If you want, if you don't want a powerful phone or whatever,
I mean, it's like, they just didn't have,
honestly, like, it was like,
almost like a proof of concept
that tried to go in productization,
but they didn't do like a focus study on it.
And I think, and I just want to say the engineers,
I know the engineers, they did an amazing job,
but unfortunately, like, you read the reviews,
and I read the reviews, why did Stadia fail?
And the number one thing would be like,
they didn't solve a problem that wasn't already solved.
They didn't solve it in a way that was cheaper or better.
And so the question becomes,
and this has always been the question,
it's, can you get away with a thin client
and not have a powerful end client?
And the answer is yes, per situation.
Like, if you want information security,
the best way to do that is a thin client
to store it somewhere in a vault.
If you want, like, we do, like,
all of these engineers that make the computer chips,
they need so much processing power,
they can't carry that around.
So they SSH into a grid of hundreds of thousands of nodes,
and they launch their things,
and then they go get a cup of coffee.
You know, that's a thin client, that works for sure.
But other things you want on the end,
because connectivity is never assured,
and the central server, if it goes down,
is not decentralized enough to make you happy.
I mean, think about like, what was it?
I used to have like one of these IoT companies,
and it went down, and my house stopped working.
You need to have a fallback for everything, right?
And so, to me, I'm not like a,
I always joke about the zombie apocalypse, you know?
But if that happened, you don't wanna put all your eggs
in a cloud somewhere that you're not gonna have access to.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
Why does Qualcomm take so long to produce data?
Do you use Qualcomm?
We do use Qualcomm.
So like, half of our phones come from Qualcomm,
and half of them come from Exynos.
And I'll tell you a very easy way, it's money.
What happens when you have a single monopolistic source?
Prices go up.
Yeah, so Qualcomm can say, you know, this year,
I'm gonna give you an offer you can't refuse.
And then they're gonna say,
we're gonna charge you umpteen hundred dollars
because what else are you gonna do?
We got your entire business.
And so what you do is you have a secondary source,
and then that secondary source balances out
and gives competition to that primary source,
or I don't wanna call it primary,
but that first source and that second source.
And then also it de-risks the situation, right?
And so the other thing is, is that we don't control
where people wanna fab their stuff.
And we have our own fabs.
So another reason to do it is to fill our own fabs.
So a lot of times the cell phone will pipe clean the fabs
and use the most fastest node,
even if our yield is low, because we get double benefit.
So we get a discount on the fabrication costs
because we're also proving out the technology.
Everything's a monetary decision.
I mean, honestly, everything's a monetary decision.
Like we wouldn't make phones if they didn't make money.
Yeah.
I mean, honestly, everything's a monetary decision.
Like we wouldn't make phones if they didn't make money.
Yeah.
I mean, honestly, everything's a monetary decision.
Like we wouldn't make phones if they didn't make money.
Yeah.
I mean, honestly, like my job is a different job
from most engineers' jobs.
My job is to say, how can I do the best,
most interesting work and get rid of the stuff
that I don't wanna worry about anymore?
So a lot of these things may not sound exciting to you.
They sound amazingly exciting to me.
One is that I get to reduce something called TCO,
total cost of ownership.
If I don't have to maintain a layer and it's open sourced
and there's a thriving community and it works,
I get to take those same engineers
that would have been doing something like that
and put them on something fun.
You know?
And so by eating your vegetables, you eat dessert.
And so that's one thing.
And so is that like long-term vision?
No, that's just one part.
I do wanna make really good tools.
I think tools are extremely awesome
and I wanna make really, really great tools.
We're gonna work with people to do that.
I hired an entire team to do that
and they're really, really good.
I'm excited about it.
That's fun for me.
I'm excited about that.
We're also like on all of the standards committees
for Kronos.
So we're talking about what's coming out next.
Do I believe in mesh shaders?
I don't know, the jury's still out.
But we're gonna do it and we're gonna see what it's like.
We're gonna work with like game engine companies
and see if they can help us
to make these things work really well
and then get a lot of goodness out there
so the next super video game
can run on our phones very well.
So it's just like a positive thing.
Yeah.
So kind of like the vision is to support all new features
that are coming out.
They adopt the new features into the Samsung.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
So that's the vision?
No, no, no.
The vision is to make, I don't wanna, I mean,
the vision for my team
and the vision for Samsung as a whole.
There's different perspectives.
So the vision for Samsung as a whole
is probably to be an amazing electronics provider
that solves all of your problems, right?
Makes a lot of money doing it,
makes the world a better place.
Cutting edge technology, yada, yada, yada.
For my team, I wanna put out the best mobile phone GPUs
as I can, because that's my mandate.
I also want to start to pour into other adjacent markets.
Like I wanna prove myself out of mobile
and then start going into a bunch of other markets
like automotive and refrigerators, why not?
And drones and God knows whatever.
As many markets as I can do
and start fighting all those really interesting problems
and maybe VR, AR, maybe mocap.
I don't know, whatever products out there,
I'd love to be in it.
And because a GPU is so versatile,
it can do a lot of things.
So the other thing is to find those new markets,
talk to them, convince them they wanna use us,
convince Samsung that we wanna be able to be in this
and kind of get that going.
So there's also a business aspect
and a lot of this is driven by software
because we have the most insight.
Like hardware guys are like, just tell us what to build.
Software guys are like, I want this to be better.
I think eventually you're supposed to be talking
about your projects.
One last question, Matt, I was gonna do.
Less of a question, but I like working
in the chip packaging industry for a bit.
So I'm wondering what kind of design considerations
you make with building the chip?
How does packaging come into it?
I wish I was more of an expert.
I can tell you what little I know
is we have to fit an extremely small phone
and that it's very small.
I mean, it's very, very small.
And that not only the packaging,
I think we're almost more worried about the thermals
on the packaging than anything else
because we have to dissipate all that thermal energy
into that slim, slim case.
And then people don't think about this.
The minute you put one of these covers on your phone,
it makes our problem way worse.
You know, if everybody could just strap like three fans
on the back of their phone, that would be great.
We would be so good.
Yeah, Asus had this like huge, like ROC, like fan chassis.
I'm like, that's what you need.
If you want a game on a phone, do one of those.
But honestly, it's just a physics question.
So like, we're not doing anything bad.
We have electrons.
Electrons create heat, deal, you know?
And so, but packaging, I think one of our biggest concerns
is size and thermals.
Yeah.
The last question I have is a very dumb question.
No.
It may or may not be a dumb question.
What is your reaction when somebody at a concert tells you
we want to put a GPU on a refrigerator?
I looked at those refrigerators.
I couldn't figure it out,
but I was afraid my wife wanted one.
And she did.
I don't have one.
I pushed back on it.
But the thing is, is that marketing is emotions.
And sometimes things that don't make sense,
you can still sell things with.
I got two fun facts.
So one of them was, there was a study,
there was a psychological study done
where a person was in a room with two screens,
and they were the exact same screens,
and they had two different audio systems.
And the audio on one system was better
than the audio on the other system.
And they asked the question of the person,
which picture is better?
And you can guess, there's like 80% sigma,
like significant.
They said the picture with the better sound
was better picture.
Okay.
And that to me is marketing.
It's basically lying to you to your face
and making you say yes.
And so it's like, which one makes the food colder?
The one with video screen on the front.
So I don't know.
Maybe I'll do one last political question.
Yeah.
I guess this is like kind of half joking,
but like a potential like ethical issue in the future
is like when you install all this like hardware
into an appliance, it's like a car or refrigerator
or like your air conditioning.
Like ethically speaking, doesn't that give like Samsung
an inordinate amount of control
over your everyday appliances?
Like if you don't pay your Samsung subscription,
your car won't show you like gas gauge anymore
or like now you're-
I hear what you're saying.
I don't think Samsung is sophisticated like that.
We're not Google.
Like we honestly like, we don't do phone home very well.
I'm saying this, I'm gonna get fired.
We really are just saying like,
we barely do phone home, right?
So we are a hardware company
that supports other people's ecosystems
like an automobile company.
Like we wanna sell you the devices
and we've tried really hard to have the Galaxy store
be something and it hasn't really taken off
like the Google or Apple store has.
We don't have that kind of leverage that we think we have.
But I hear the, let's go back to the ethical concern.
If you are a company and you have all of this data,
then yes, there is some kind of quandary
that does need to be,
there do need to be laws that get made to protect people.
And I think that's kind of a place
where engineers are not good at regulating themselves.
And so that needs to happen in the public.
I don't really have a great answer for that.
It's just like the dystopian notion of like,
you didn't pay your Samsung subscription
and now your refrigerator doesn't open
or something like that.
Yeah, I mean,
I don't think people would buy that refrigerator.
BMW at the heated car seats,
Tesla did it with the auto drive.
The minute people take things back,
oh, people get pissed.
So I think that it's actually not a good model.
In fact, a lot of these as a service type things
are hitting a lot of resistance
because people just wanna own something and buy it once
and then eventually maybe get an upgrade.
They don't wanna continually pay for it
for the rest of their lives.
And so some people like,
I think as a service works great for corporations
because corporations work like,
I have a budget,
I wanna have deterministic finance oversight
for a long period of time.
And this as a service model averages all of that out.
Kind of like when you have that option
on your utility bill to like pay the same bill all year
and they'll average it and change it a little bit.
Corporations love that.
And that's their main customer for that.
People hate it.
People just wanna like buy the movie once.
People wanna buy the video game once.
And so, and people hate recurring costs.
I do anyway, I don't know.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thanks so much for that lovely talk
and answering all those questions.
Thanks again for flying in and joining us.
Yeah.
Okay.
If anybody wants to talk to Gabe
about position building at Samsung,
I'm sure he'd love to talk to that.
Yeah.
Come on down.
There's also swag.
And there's more swag than what's on the table.
So come grab it.
There's cord bags or toilet.
I don't know.
It's a bag.
You can put stuff in it.
And then here's another bag.
It's a tote for groceries or whatever.
I believe Samsung is banning or has banned plastic bags.
So it's great.
Yeah.
Take one or two and awesome.
Yeah, please do.
Yeah.
Thank you.