Just fiddling around with the Zoom settings. I'm surprised you can actually live stream
to Twitch and YouTube from Zoom. There's a button that says go live to...
I know Zoom has a lot of features that like no one asked for
and then doesn't add the features that everyone asks for.
Very weird.
Yeah, I was doing speech translation actually, which was...
Did you get to work on something cool I guess?
Yeah, yeah, it was really cool. The problem is that like there was nobody else at Roblox
that knew anything about speech. So the first two months was me just reading a bunch of papers.
That's research.
I mean it is right, but then you know it's like if you have managers and mentors that like...
So there was no one to really guide you.
Right, exactly. And then like literally five hours ago, Facebook published like four or five
papers at the same time. They just dropped it all at once. And the stuff that they did
is basically what my intern project was, but much better. So like, okay, well...
It's funny because their like metaverse bet is a bet on research.
So while Facebook like as a company's software engineer is flailing,
the research team has never been better. It's honestly been incredible.
I mean like it's not a bad bet.
I think they can translate those research into startup.
Yeah, yeah, 100%.
So we'll have to see.
So do you think it'll go back?
Through roadblocks? Possibly.
It's hard to know at this point in the year, but they have been funding my PhD actually
because they want to continue the intern project. But it's been really hard to make progress on it
when taking a bunch of classes and giving talks and submitting papers for other things. So
I haven't done that much since I left internship. So I don't even know if they'll let me back
because they're not getting a good ROI for the first month of the semester.
I actually moved to the art museum.
That's nice.
You don't have to deal with the package room closing at 5 p.m.
Yeah, or like my window was too thin.
Don't even get me started on the fire alarm.
The problem is my commute is a lot longer. It's like a 40-minute walk.
That's another bad thing, which I'm only now starting to realize given that it's getting cold.
And the bus is nice when it was freezing.
As of the last two or three weeks, he's been showing up to the weekly meetings
where I present what I've done in the last week, which is intensely stressful.
I mean, it's a good pressure because it forces me to have something substantial each week,
but it's also a lot of pressure.
I didn't, but Roblox sent a lot of people to sit down.
I wish I'd gone.
Yeah, I heard it was.
They brought like 50 people to SIGGRAPH and only like 10 of them are researchers.
The rest of them are all software engineers.
My manager was saying something like,
are we sure it's a good idea to send so many people to SIGGRAPH?
Like, there's a lot of money.
It's fun.
That's not what that means.
It definitely isn't.
I love that because over the past 10 or 15 years,
I've got people coming in and they wanna wake me up
and come back.
But I don't wanna accompany them.
I feel like it's a privilege to have Robert and Russell
coming into work you know,
and paying attention to issues that we all want them to pay attention to.
And they're so kind.
They're aware that we passed
Biden guidelines in Washington.
We're gonna help them through that.
We're gonna help them,
Babe I think they're gonna kiss tonight.
She has a
Are you, you were giving the recitation for the, for the Vulcan assignment.
It's like October 19th. How, how fast is this class going nowadays?
It's, I mean, the assignment has already been, they're gonna release it in school.
Yeah, but like, I don't, isn't that assignment like five or six?
That's fast.
That's, that's fast.
I feel like this church is like, okay, I have a question.
Like, do we not have two weeks to do the wizard?
And like, I feel like, like, I appreciate the extra time, but like,
I feel like the Vulcan, whatever, or like, you know, whatever will take longer than one week to do.
You only have one week for the Vulcan assignment?
I've done this before.
Is this someone's credit card?
Oh, we're not doing this class.
Like, and it's not like the Easter.
Thanks for bringing this in. I'll, I'll try to find somebody to hand this to.
Okay. I don't know what this class is before here.
I don't know. Maybe it's physics or something, but yeah.
That would be a very good question to ask Shazan.
It's a very reasonable opinion though.
Okay.
Cool.
All right.
So.
No, no, I'm gonna, I'm gonna decide to start at some point.
I'm just giving people like a minute or two to get settled.
Okay, cool.
So hello everyone.
Did you miss me?
I don't know.
So yesterday's lecture, I realized looking back on it was really, really fast.
And I did not give people enough time for breaks, especially for people
that like haven't seen machine learning before.
I can imagine that that was approximately like a month and a half of course content
in like two hours.
So I'm making a pledge to myself to go a lot slower in this lecture
and then give people a lot more breaks.
And so hopefully that will help out alleviate some of the mental burden.
But yeah, this lecture is super exciting because it's a topic that really doesn't
get talked about a whole lot in machine learning classes in other areas,
both in the actual theory machine learning classes at Penn
and also the applied machine learning classes.
So like computer vision, computational linguistics and whatnot.
And that's how do you make machine learning fast?
And if you are attempting to go get an industry job writing GPU code,
I would argue that a lot of industry jobs are writing GPU code to do machine learning
as well as do graphics.
So I'm super excited.
I had a lot of help from friends at NVIDIA and other places in compiling
the stuff for this lecture.
So I'm excited to show it to you.
Okay.
So the topics we're going to cover today.
First, I'm going to start by quickly reviewing what I talked about on Monday,
which is just kind of like the groundworks that we can talk about this stuff,
which is the good stuff.
Then we're going to go into implementing a neural network in CUDA.
We're going to walk through the CUDA code for a very simple neural network example.
And I'll also provide the GitHub link so that you all can download it, run it,
verify to yourselves that it works and also look at the code in more detail.
Then we're going to talk about ways to speed up neural network inference.
So the optimizations you can make directly in your CUDA code to make neural networks faster.
And then also talk about kublas and cuDNN,
which are two really important libraries for making machine learning code much faster.
And then we'll go on to talk about things like PyTorch and TensorFlow,
which some of you may be familiar with.
They're the primary way to train and deploy neural networks.
And then I'll talk about TensorRT for a little bit.
Cool.
So let's review what we were talking about last time super quick.
Okay.
So like we said before, neural networks are just high dimensional functions.
They'll take an input vector, which would be a representation of some input.
Let's say in this case, it was handwritten digits,
but you can also do this for sentences, for videos, for whatever you want.
And then they pass it through a giant function,
which is parameterized by weights and biases that can have various different architectures.
And then it outputs a vector.
Sometimes this is classification.
So each of the points in the vector correspond to classes.
Sometimes this is a vector that is the same size as the input,
but denoised, so on and so forth.
You can have this be anything you want.
It's just a vector to a vector.
The cost or loss function is the function that tells us
how bad our network is doing for a given input.
And you can use a lot of different functions for this,
but a very common one is to do mean squared error.
We also talked about cross entropy loss for classification as well.
And what we want to do when we are training a neural network
is to try to minimize this cost function.
So to learn our parameters, we iteratively step in the direction
of the negative gradient of the cost function.
So the gradient is the direction of steepest ascent for a given function,
and we take the derivative with respect to all of the different parameters to get the gradient.
And then in order to minimize the cost function,
we just step in the direction of the gradient over and over again,
and then we find some minimum cost.
Cool.
Any questions so far?
This is all review.
Cool.
We calculate the gradient using backpropagation,
which is just derivative chain rule.
And so you apply the derivative with respect to each portion of the neural network
over and over again, and then just multiply backwards
to get the derivative for any one spot in the neural network.
And the small caveat is that for fully connected layers,
you have to sum over all of the activations of the previous layers.
And also, worth noting that all of these formulas change completely
when you change your architecture.
So these are the formulas for a fully connected linear layer.
But if you were trying to do a convolutional neural network,
these formulas would change.
The fundamental principle of applying the chain rule over and over again still holds.
Okay.
So things that we do to improve performance.
Add more depth.
More layers always works.
Almost always, but always.
And this is very expensive.
And the theory behind this is very unclear.
But it seems to be that the more layers you add,
the better the network learns to generalize
and map complicated functions and distributions.
When comparing probability distributions, we use cross-entropy loss.
You can use mean-squared error when doing other things like image denoising.
But yes.
AUDIENCE MEMBER 2
Does it change the type of inputs also?
Like, do you do what makes the input really...
Yeah, exactly.
So when you say number of inputs,
do you mean the size of the vector representation of each input?
Yeah, exactly.
And that would...
A larger input vector size means that you have more weights to learn.
However, it depends on the representation.
So if by making the input a larger size,
you make the function easier to learn,
like you make it a more simple function,
then yeah, absolutely, it would make that a lot easier to learn.
Right, because if you're doing some...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right.
Cool.
And just as a reminder, cross-entropy loss is p,
which in our cases would be like the correct answer,
times log of q, which is our predicted answer.
AUDIENCE MEMBER 3
We use ReLU instead of sigmoid.
We talked about this.
Why is this important?
People that remember from one day?
Yeah, exactly.
The vanishing gradient problem.
With sigmoid, if you have very high activations going into sigmoid,
the gradient becomes very, very small.
And this is a really big problem if you have random initializations
because you might randomly initialize to some point
and then the gradient is very small.
So it's hard to come back.
Mm-hmm.
Cool.
Instead of using vanilla gradient descent,
you can use momentum or the more common option,
which is adaptive moment.
And don't forget to pick a good learning rate.
Just because you use adaptive moment
doesn't mean you don't have a learning rate to tune.
Like these beta parameters are hyperparameters.
So they're just like the learning rate.
And because they're included in gradient descent,
you can't learn them and you have to just choose them.
So sweep over values, find a good learning rate,
and then you can do it.
Cool.
When dealing with images,
we want to use convolutional layers and max pooling layers.
The reason why we do this
is because we want to reduce the number of trainable parameters
so that we can reduce the amount of time it takes to train the network
and also the amount of data it takes to train the network.
The way that convolutional layers work
is that we run a filter over the image
and we only learn the weights of the filter
rather than learning a full linear layer.
And both of these are taking advantage of translational invariance,
aka an object anywhere in the image is the same object.
So learning a filter allows you to apply the same filter
no matter where the object is in the image.
Cool.
And then this is just the diagram from before of AlexNet,
which is what many people would consider to be
the beginning of like the deep learning revolution
where Alex implemented this network on the GPU in CUDA
and showed that you can make networks with 9 or 10 layers
train in a reasonable amount of time
and then get incredible performance improvements.
And we're going to talk about AlexNet more in this lecture in more detail.
Cool.
And also just to be very clear,
convolutional neural networks do not have to be only convolutions.
It's very typical to have some convolutional layers.
And then once you get towards the end,
you have these dense layers.
These are linear layers.
There's a lot of names for this.
But you have these dense layers at the end
where after you take all of the convolutions,
then you can start to use the fully connected linear layers at the end.
Okay.
It's the same exact thing.
Yeah, they're just different names for it.
Linear layers are dense because they have,
like we said earlier, n times k weights per layer.
So some people call them dense layers
because they're densely connected
to distinguish it from convolution layers,
which aren't as densely connected.
Same thing as linear.
Well, what about if you drop out?
Would they still be called dense?
They would still be called dense,
partially because dropout only...
The percentage of times that you drop out a weight
is going to be less than 10% usually.
Sometimes people would put it more towards 20.
But even then, a 20% decrease in n times k is still...
There's still a lot of weights, way more than convolution.
But yeah, I don't love the name,
which is why I haven't been calling it dense layers.
But yeah, they're the same as linear layers.
Cool.
All right.
Convolutional filters at the beginning of the network
will learn very low level filters.
They're just sort of horizontal lines or vertical lines.
But as you get further and further into the network,
the later convolutional filters
will be learning really high level things.
So down at the bottom here,
you see something that looks vaguely
like a pelican or something.
This would clearly be very good at detecting
whether or not there was a pelican in an image.
Because if that filter output something really, really high,
you can have very high confidence that there's a pelican.
Cool.
Oh, and one more thing to mention, by the way, about this.
This completely depends on the data
that you're training the neural network for.
So these filters, the reason why you would learn something
like this filter for the pelican looking bird
is because you're training the network to classify birds.
If you were training the network to do something else,
like denoising, you would learn a completely different set
of filters.
And even if you're doing the same neural network
more than once on the same set of data,
your initialization will change what these filters end up being.
It's just because there's not one local minima.
So these filters are not always going
to look something like this.
But generally, the trend is that they get higher and higher
level as the network goes.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's a great question.
So these images are generated.
I should have mentioned this earlier.
Apologies if I did not.
These images are generated by finding
the input that would maximally activate a given filter.
So if I looked at the filter weights,
I say, what image could I generate
that would maximally activate this filter?
And there are also other visualization techniques
that they use to make it so that it looks vaguely
like, for example, the gray outlines.
Like if the weight is under a certain amount,
just gray it out.
And so that makes the picture look prettier.
But generally speaking, it's whatever maximally
activates a given filter.
OK.
There are lots of different architectures.
I won't go into detail of these.
But please send me an email or come up to me after class
if you're curious of any of these.
OK.
Final thing is very important for final projects
is that you can learn a CNN for many useful image tasks.
So denoising can be learned with a CNN.
Resolution upscaling can be learned with a CNN.
And frame interpolation can be learned with a CNN.
And the paper links are here.
And I'll post the slides later so that you can check it out.
All right.
So now let's get on to the good stuff.
So how do we actually implement a neural network?
It's great to talk about this in general terms.
But if I had a blank terminal or a blank VS Code file,
what would I actually write?
How would I implement this?
And how do I make it fast?
How do I make it take maximum advantage of GPU parallelism?
OK.
So first off, let's define some tasks
that we're going to try to solve.
I'm going to keep it super duper simple, even more simple
than handwritten digits.
We're going to try to write a neural network that
will learn the task of determining which coordinate
a point is on a 2D plane.
So it's not just which coordinate,
but which diagonal set of quadrants.
So whether or not a point is in the first and third quadrant
or in the second and fourth quadrant.
So first things first, what is our input representation
for a point in the 2D plane?
Yeah, exactly.
So it would be a tuple.
You have the x-coordinate and y-coordinate.
You can think of this as a 1 by 2 column vector
if you really want to.
But yeah, it's just x and y-coordinate.
And then what's our output look like?
Yeah, just one value.
And since we're doing binary classification,
that would be 0 or 1.
And we can arbitrarily choose that 1
means first and third quadrant.
I should say.
So we can pretty easily write a function ourselves to do this.
It's just a couple of if statements.
If the point is both positive or both negative, give 1.
Otherwise, if one of them is positive
and the other is negative, give 0.
But let's think of a function that would solve this task.
So what I mean by a function is like function notation.
So f of x1, x2 equals some implementation.
And then that function would output either 0 or 1
for these points.
OK, so importantly, could I write that function?
I'm going to slightly write on the board here.
Can I write this function in the form?
I'm running out of space because there's always something.
So for those of you who can't see my tiny handwriting,
could you write this function in terms of a linear combination
of the input points?
So weight 1 times x1 plus weight 2 times x2 plus a bias term,
a.k.a. what I'm asking is, is this actually a linear function?
Is this?
Can you give me the weights for it?
OK, it's not easy.
This is not a straightforward question.
This is actually a difficult one, right?
Because it's hard to be confident in a no answer
because there could be a set of weights that does this.
And maybe you just haven't thought of it yet.
I will spoil the answer in a bit.
One way to know whether or not a task is a linear function
is whether or not you can actually
draw a line that can separate two points.
Because if you can draw a line, then you
can say all points on one side of this line get 1,
and all points on the other side of this line get 0.
And then you can make that line a linear function.
Be positive for points that are over it and negative otherwise.
And that's pretty easily writable as an equation.
This is actually a very famous example of a function that
is very simple but non-linear.
And so back in the 50s and 60s, when people started learning
neural networks, all of the neural networks had one layer.
And they did not have any activation functions.
But then the skeptics of machine learning,
which at the time this was just called the perceptron,
gave this example and say, you can't learn this function,
as simple of a function as this, because it's non-linear,
and you have only linear layers.
This is actually the XOR function.
So whether or not both inputs are positive or both negative
gives 1, and then the opposite gives 0.
If this is 0, you need 2 times 2 divided by 2.
Exactly.
So this is a non-linear function.
And so the smallest neural network that could feasibly
learn this would be two layers.
Because if we had only one layer, we can only learn linear functions.
OK, everyone clear?
So that's what we're going to do.
So we're going to implement the smallest neural network
that could learn this function.
And we're going to walk through an implementation of this
in CUDA to do this task.
So our loss function here will be binary cross-entropy loss,
where we have y log y plus 1 minus y log 1 minus y,
y being the confidence in the probability of the class.
So if I have 90% probability of it being output 1,
then we have 0.9 log 0.9 plus 1 minus 0.9,
which is the probability of the opposite class.
And then our network architecture is going to look like this.
We have linear, ReLU as our non-linearity,
and then linear, and then sigmoid,
which functions identically to softmax in the binary case.
Yeah, so this sigmoid here, it's not acting as our non-linearity.
It's acting as basically softmax.
So instead of doing softmax, we're doing sigmoid.
I would almost forget that sigmoid is here.
We're going to actually go into the implementation.
But the non-linearity we are using is ReLU
for the reasons that I talked about yesterday.
Cool, all right.
So how will this network actually work?
First off, I think it's really important to start out,
before we get into the code, to talk about the fact
that we're going to be passing all of our inputs in in batches.
So before I was talking about, we did mini-batch stochastic gradient descent,
where we passed a batch of examples through the neural network in parallel,
and then computed the gradient for all of those examples,
and then averaged over all of them to get the actual gradient that we would apply.
In this code, everything is going to be in terms of batches.
And so if our batch is size m, what is the dimensionality
of the input we're going to get to our neural network?
So one point, a reminder, is just some tuple.
And if we had m examples in a batch, the dimensions of the input would be,
yeah, it is 2m, but it's like 2 by m.
Yeah, exactly.
And so this is a matrix.
So when you see things like the input value being represented as a matrix,
don't get confused.
It is still a vector, but it's a matrix of many vectors,
because we're doing it all batched.
What we're going to do is we're going to pass the input through our network
to get m different predictions.
We're going to compute the loss for all of those m examples,
and then we're going to compute the gradient and average them.
And then we'll update the weights and biases accordingly.
OK, so what classes would we want to implement in order to do this?
The first thing is we have a matrix class.
And this is very useful, because you can save the weights of the matrix,
and you can also save the gradients.
And then you can have a function to apply the gradients.
You can also have functions to copy them from host to device and device to host.
Also good for memory management, all that good stuff.
We also have to implement the three layers, so sigmoid, ReLU, and linear.
Our cost function, and then we have some parent class for the whole neural network
that will implement a dot train function or something.
Cool.
Why are we making classes, though, for all of these?
Especially something like, I don't know, a sigmoid activation function.
Couldn't you just apply the sigmoid function without having to make a whole class for it?
This is a difficult question, though.
It's not just that we're happy and we want to make everything a class, because it's pretty.
Any thoughts?
Yeah, so the reason why we want to make classes for these is because when we pass things through
the network in the forward pass, we want to remember what the activations were for all
of the different neurons on the forward pass, so that when we go to compute the gradient,
we know what we're actually taking the derivative of.
So we can evaluate the actual value.
And so all of this allows us to be stateful about our sigmoid function,
so we can remember what the input was and what the output was,
as well as for linear layers, of course.
Of course, we have to save the weights and biases for the linear layer, but also remember
what the input and the output was to the linear layer, so that when we go to take the derivative,
we can remember.
Cool, all right.
So we're now going to step through the CUDA code.
It's not important to understand every single line of this code.
I'm going to be flashing a lot of code on screen, but I'll point out the stuff that's important.
And what I want to get out of this is I want to give you all a solid foundation, right?
So if you were looking at this code yourself, would you be able to reasonably understand
what's going on, and also to highlight some of the nice optimizations that they make,
even in this simple code base?
Again, the link is here.
These slides will be posted.
Highly encourage you to download this code and run it yourself.
And also, you might want to try it around and implement a few of the improvements,
maybe use mean squared error and see if that does worse, something like that.
Cool, all right.
So let's start.
So first off, I'm going to talk about the matrix class.
One of the important things about the matrix class that I thought was cool is that they
have Booleans to denote where the matrix is allocated.
So one of them is whether or not it's allocated on device, and the other one is whether or
not it's allocated on the host.
And note that they have functions for allocating the memory.
What this means is that when you first instantiate a matrix, it doesn't automatically allocate
memory for the contents of the matrix.
You have to explicitly call this allocate memory function, which is good because that's
more just in time.
When you go to initialize your neural network, you're not going to initialize the entirety
of every matrix in the whole network.
Another thing is that the data is a shared pointer.
So I'm sure you all already know what shared pointers do.
But just in case, can anyone tell me what a shared pointer does?
Yeah, exactly.
And my understanding of why shared pointers are used here is probably just because they
want to make sure that things are freed when the matrix is deconstructed.
That's fine.
But yeah, so we have a pointer, both host and device pointers here.
And we also, of course, we overload the array index operator for easy access.
Cool.
Side note, this shape class is just like a struct of shape.x, shape.y.
OK, cool.
The layer class, this is the parent class that all of the different layers will inherit
from.
The only thing you need to inherit when you're a layer is you need to have a forward and
you need to have a backward.
So forward and back propagate.
Name is also convenient.
OK, so let's get into our first layer.
So we're going to start off with sigmoid.
For the class variables of sigmoid, we have a, z, and dz.
Reminder that a usually stands for activation.
So it's usually the output of a full layer.
And the layer is usually considered the linear part plus the nonlinearity.
So a would be the output of sigmoid.
And the z is the input of sigmoid.
And then, of course, we have dz for when we do back propagation, which is the derivative
of the cost with respect to the input of sigmoid.
Cool.
And of course, it has forward and back prop.
So forward takes in the z and outputs the a.
And back prop takes in da and outputs dz.
Cool.
OK, so this is the only time I'm going to show you the host function for forward and
backward, the host function that calls the CUDA kernel.
So here, we have the z, which is the input.
And we save it to the sigmoid class.
We allocate memory, if not already allocated, for the output a.
We define the block size, number of blocks.
And then we call the CUDA kernel sigmoid activation forward.
Likewise, for back prop, I'm only going to show this for sigmoid.
For all of the future layers, I'm just going to talk about the CUDA kernel.
So again, the back prop function takes in da and outputs dz.
So allocate memory, if not already allocated, for dz.
Get the size.
Call the CUDA kernel.
OK, so let's look at the CUDA kernel.
Pretty straightforward, right?
So as a reminder, sigmoid is 1 over 1 plus e to the minus x.
So we have our device function, which is just sigmoid.
And then we have our forward pass, which you find the index in the matrix.
And then you just compute sigmoid.
So sigmoid of z is a.
Simple.
Any questions?
All right.
Back prop kernel, similarly simple.
One thing worth noting is that the derivative of sigmoid is sigmoid times 1 minus sigmoid.
It's a very, very clean way of writing it.
And so same thing.
So dz is da times sigmoid of z times 1 minus sigmoid of z.
So where is this da coming from?
And why is it being multiplied?
Our derivative should be sigmoid times 1 minus sigmoid.
Activation from forward pass.
Well, so z is the activation from the forward pass, though.
Where's da coming from?
The derivative from the previous layer?
Exactly, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So when we're doing the chain rule, we have to multiply the derivative from the previous layer
times the derivative of the current layer.
So da is the derivative of cost with respect to the activation.
So cost to the output of sigmoid.
And then this is the derivative of a with respect to z.
So when you multiply them together, you get the output, which is the derivative of cost
with respect to z.
Exactly.
And so we'll be doing this for every back prop layer.
We have this da, which is passed in, and that's the derivative from the previous layer.
And we multiply that by the derivative of what the actual layer itself was.
Cool.
All right, so the ReLU class header is identical to sigmoid.
This is still the sigmoid class header, but you get the idea.
ReLU looks exactly like this.
We have az, dz, forward, and back prop.
All right, forward kernel for ReLU, it's just a reminder that ReLU is max x and 0.
So we have a float max of z and 0, and that gives us our activations.
The back prop kernel is interesting because the derivative of ReLU is interesting.
If x is greater than 0, the derivative is 1.
Otherwise, it is 0.
And so we have this if statement here, where if x is greater than 0,
then the derivative is just da.
So da times 1 is da.
Otherwise, it's 0.
And so generally speaking, you're not supposed to make if statements in CUDA kernels.
Is this a bad if statement?
Why not?
That's fair, yeah.
Not only do we not have any way around it, but these two operations take
approximately the same amount of time.
I mean, not really, because you're accessing memory here.
But your weakest link is not significantly worse than the other branches of the if statement.
You had a question?
Because it's the, I mean, I was just wondering if all the,
if all the values inside of this block would value the same thing.
But maybe, probably not actually.
Probably not.
But that is a good, that is a possible optimization.
It would be pretty tricky to sort of do on the fly.
But it could be the case that if you knew everything was 0 already,
we don't even call a CUDA kernel.
We just know it's 0 instead of 0.
And that could possibly happen if you dropped out certain chunks of the neural network.
We can know not to call CUDA kernels.
Cool, all right.
So now let's get to the slightly more difficult class, the linear layer.
So the linear layer has these five variables.
So you have the weight, bias, and then z, a, and da.
Reminder that a here would be the activation from the layer before this linear layer as our input.
So we have the activations from the previous layer,
and they get passed into the linear layer.
And then the equation for a linear layer is w times x, in this case a, plus b.
And then the output is z.
And right, so updating weights and biases, you get dz passed in,
which is the derivative from the previous layer.
Okay, and then it again implements forward, backward,
and then you have some getter functions.
Okay, forward kernel.
Again, equation wx plus b, you see w times x, or a, equals z.
Now, one important thing to note is that when they're doing this sum,
this is a dot product, right, they are actually doing a for loop.
And they're updating the z value variable over and over and over again.
Instead of updating the value in the z matrix over and over and over again,
over and over and over again, and incrementing it,
they have a separate variable, which they increment.
And then at the end, do the update to memory, right.
Because you don't want to update memory, you know, what is this, wxdm times.
You want to update memory once.
And so you have some accumulator, and then you update memory.
Another important thing to note here is that a here is not just a vector, it's a matrix.
And so when we're looping here, we're looping from the columns of a
to the rows of w, because we're doing a dot product with one
vector of activations by one row of weights.
So, cool.
All right, so the backpropagation is slightly more difficult,
because we have to compute three different derivatives.
Can someone tell me why we have to compute three different derivatives,
and it's not just one derivative like the previous layers?
Okay.
You might get some hits from da, dw, and db.
Yeah, exactly.
So we compute the derivative with respect to the weights and biases,
so that we can do a gradient descent update.
We compute the derivative with respect to the activations,
so that we can propagate it to the layers behind us,
so that they can update their weights and biases.
So for the very first layer, aka the last layer that you get to in backpropagation,
you don't have to compute this da, because there's nothing behind you.
You just have to finally compute your dw and db.
I'm sure the code does not have a special case for when you are the very first layer,
but theoretically you do not have to compute it.
These are the equations.
Last time I gave this lecture, I actually went and derived these,
but it was very boring and not necessary.
It's straightforward to derive these.
You have w times x.
The derivative with respect to the x, aka a, is w,
and the derivative with respect to w is x, aka a.
We have w times a, so the derivative of a is w times the previous thing,
and the derivative with respect to w is a times the previous thing,
and then db is just the previous thing.
And the reason why we're doing this sum is very subtle,
but reminder that our batches are of size m.
So because we want to do a gradient step which averages over all of the examples in the batch,
it's not that db is just dz, it's actually the average of all of the dz's.
And likewise for the weights, we are also taking the average of all of the weights,
except the sum is not explicitly written here, it should be.
So this is a slight typo, but yeah.
And then this dj dz is weird notation.
Oftentimes the cost function is called c, but the loss function is called j.
Both of them refer to the exact same thing,
and I don't know why they do j for loss, it makes zero sense.
But if you see j, just know that that's derivative of loss slash cost with respect.
Cool.
All right, first, activations.
Note w transpose times dz, we have w times dz, and then da is the value.
Again, we do the thing where we accumulate in da, and then only access memory once.
Cool.
Next, for the weights, we sum, we have dz times a first,
and then weights equals weights minus learning rate times dw divided by ax dim.
Ax dim here is m, because this is the x dimension of our activation matrix,
which is columns, one for each.
And when we do the update, we're literally doing, this is literally gradient descent,
so it's learning rate times this.
There's no atom, no nothing here.
But if you wanted to implement atom, this is the line that you could change.
Finally, doing the biases, this is quite interesting, I think.
In the previous update, we actually explicitly did a for loop inside of our thread.
So we had a thread compute an entire dot product, and then we updated.
In the bias calculation, they decided to, instead of doing a for loop within one thread,
they decided to have each term in the dot product computed by a different thread.
They decided to have each term in the dot product computed by a different thread,
and then atomic add them to the value.
And note that atomic add is a thread safe add.
So all of the threads are trying to atomic add to the same value,
they will serialize themselves.
Or I should say that atomic add can't be interrupted.
So it's thread safe.
But yes, this computes one of them.
Okay.
Finally, we have our loss function.
Binary cross entropy loss, I'm just writing the equation out.
Again, which is y log y plus 1 minus y log 1 minus y.
If we had more than two classes, we would have more than these two terms.
We would have one y log y term for each of the classes.
And then, of course, the derivative is, we know the derivative of log is 1 over,
by the way, this is natural log.
And so we have y over y minus 1 minus y over 1 minus y.
And so here, we have y times log y, 1 minus times log 1 minus,
and then we atomic add.
So it does the same thing as the biases,
where you do one thread per computation of a single index.
And then instead of having all of the threads sum over all of the batches,
you can take the value divided by m and just atomic add them from m different threads.
And then we have the backward kernel, which is 1 times whatever,
y hat minus 1 minus y, 1 minus y hat.
Cool.
Finally, we get to the satisfying part.
So now that we've gotten all the machinery down,
we have the parent class, which is the neural network class.
And what does the neural network class contain?
So we have a vector of layers.
This is a pointer to the parent class neural network layer.
And then we have a function called add layer,
which allows us to add as many layers as we want.
So again, once you've implemented all of these layers properly,
you can actually just make the network as deep as you want
without really writing any more code,
because you just call add layer like 10 more times.
We also have y and dy as part of the parent class.
This is our predictions and then the derivative with respect to the predictions.
We also have forward and backprop,
which are the parent classes forward and backprop.
So that forward would call all of the forward functions of all of the layers.
OK.
This is satisfying.
I think this is very satisfying.
This is the forward pass of the parent neural network class.
Any questions?
You just take the input, four layers, call forward pass, and then return.
I don't think you necessarily need to rename this x to be z and this z to be y.
They could have just returned z.
That's fine.
But it is still very satisfying.
That's like two more lines than I would have liked.
I would have three line function here.
Backprop is slightly less pretty, partially because the for loop is annoying.
Oh, oops.
The for loop is annoying because you have to backwards loop over the layers.
But it's still similar because we take backprop of all of the layers in the reverse direction.
We compute the cost explicitly here.
So we get the predictions as the input, compute the cost with respect to target,
aka the correct answer.
And then we have dy, which is not returned from the function, but populated by the function.
And then we pass that over and over again.
And then note this CUDA device synchronize here.
This is actually super important, and it's kind of subtle why it's here.
So when we do this backpropagate, we don't actually do the gradient update.
And the reason why is because there was a small implementation detail, which is
they save the gradient updates, but they don't necessarily apply it until you say apply.
Because sometimes you might want to pass through points, but not update the gradients.
Like, for example, when you want to actually do prediction after your network is trained.
And so we want to do CUDA device synchronized so that when we go to, say,
apply all the gradients, we know that all of them have been finished.
Like, the computation for all of them are finished.
So all this does is calculate the error of just a pass in these current weights.
Where is that information sent?
This error is just defined within the method.
Yeah, exactly.
So this error is the error of our predictions.
We pass this through backprop function for each one of these layers.
And if you remember from our implementation of, let's just say the linear layer.
Right here.
Now, I guess I didn't show the actual backprop kernel because there's three different ones.
But when we pass the error through the linear layer, it gets saved into
the variables of the linear layer class here.
So we have DA, for example.
And this is the derivative of that error with respect to the weights.
And then we can decide to say update weights and update bias.
And this is actually doing the gradient update.
So that's where all of the error information is saved.
It's saved statefully within the classes for all of the different layers.
And I think that that design choice makes the parent functions very, very clean.
OK.
Any other questions with this?
It seems pretty straightforward, right?
You have each layer.
Every one of them implements forward and backward.
And then to train the network, call the forwards and then call the backwards.
And you're done.
OK.
Initializing the neural network is as simple as just calling dot add layer,
new, linear, ReLU, linear, sigmoid.
This is the architecture that we laid out.
Why do we have 30 here?
Like, what is this 30 representing?
Not batch size.
Yeah, it's the number of nodes in your linear layer.
So this number can be whatever you want it to be.
And the larger the layer, the more different functions it can learn.
So if you have, like, say we characterize, we say one linear function is one weight and bias.
If we make the layer wider, we can learn more different linear functions.
For a task as easy as this one, 30 is plenty.
If anything, 30 is a bit much.
You probably only need to do maybe four, right?
No guarantees that that would train very well.
But you probably only need to do four.
However, you can make this, like, 10,000 if you want.
And there's a lot of experimental evidence to show that the wider your layers are,
the more powerful.
But depth is usually more effective than width.
But width can help, too.
Right?
So we take in an input of size 2.
And then we project it to 30 different neurons.
And then back down from those 30 to 1.
Cool.
Just as a side note, this problem is very easy to generate data for.
So there's a coordinates dataset class in this code that just generates coordinates
on a 2D plane and gives them labels.
And then batches contain 100 data points.
This is also a design decision.
You can pick whatever doesn't make your GPU CUDA out of memory.
But this neural network, aside from the fact that it only currently takes in inputs of size,
you know, like, 2 by n, it can generalize to any problem with an input of 2.
That's true.
Yeah, 100%.
Yeah, I think that's also really important to stress, is that just because we decided
to make a neural network for this task does not mean that it's limited to this task.
Like, you could directly apply all of this code to whatever problem you want and then
just change this dimension from 2 to whatever the size of your input is.
Like, the only engineering work that you have to do is getting your input into a vector
of that size.
And then all of this code works perfectly well for any function.
Thus the magic of machine learning.
You write one function, and it does every task.
OK.
Training, straightforward, right?
We have epochs, and epochs are generally, one epoch is generally one pass over the entirety
of your training dataset.
And so here we've defined 1,000 epochs.
So we're going to be training by looping over the entirety of our dataset 1,000 times.
And then for each one of the batches, and we have some implementation of, you know,
getting a batch from our dataset, we call forward, we call backward, and then we increment
the total cost for the entire batch.
And then if we have an even multiple of 100, we will print out the epoch and then the cost.
So importantly, this is an important question.
If you look at the for loop, we loop until we have number of batches minus 1.
So we only loop through n minus 1 batches instead of the full n.
Why do we do that instead of looping over the full n?
And then shouldn't we use all of our training data?
Use the last bit of it.
Yeah, exactly.
So this code does not have a train dev test split.
It only has a train test split.
They use the last batch as their test data.
That's not good practice, but this is a toy example.
Anyway, it would be fairly straightforward to have a different held out batch from even
that one that you don't test on until the very end.
But yes, exactly.
You need to evaluate on some held out data that was not trained.
Any questions about that?
Computing accuracy, also very straightforward.
We just pass the batch forward, and then we have a compute accuracy function, which I
didn't explain up here, but it's fairly straightforward.
You just do it all.
And if we put it all together, training actually works.
We have cost, and it goes down every single set of 100 epochs.
So we start out at 0.66, which is, again, cross entropy loss of our predictions, and
then we get down to 0.34.
And then the accuracy is printed out at the end, and we get 93% accuracy on our points.
Now, this is a low accuracy for something that's this simple.
Why, if people have either machine learning intuition or are basing off of stuff I said
on Monday, why do you think this accuracy is not 100%?
Neural networks are powerful.
Why can't they learn this simple task?
That's a very, very strong possibility.
If your learning rate was too low or too high, you might either take way too long to converge
to the minimum, or you bounce around the minimum and never get higher than a certain level
of accuracy.
My gut says that the learning rate is very likely too high for this example.
There's also another thing here that is suspicious.
So do you have a bad randomization because the first 400 all hover before they start
going down?
Yeah, that's a very, very strong possibility too.
So if we just randomly initialize this badly, then this training run is going to be bad.
And if we ran this same exact training run 10 more times, we might get lucky and have
accuracy much higher.
Another thing is that our data set we generated, we passed over 1,000 times, the same data
points 1,000 different times.
There's a high chance that we're actually overfitting to this training data set.
And what overfitting is, I mentioned it very briefly on Monday, is if you give a neural
network the same data over and over again and train it for too long, it will learn to
just memorize the data rather than generalizing to the function that you wanted to learn.
So another gut feeling of mine is that it might be actually overfitting.
If we had stopped this at epoch maybe 50, I wonder if the accuracy would have been higher.
Now, clearly the cost didn't go down until later.
So probably a combination of learning rate plus too many epochs.
But also generating a larger data set would be helpful because we can generate as much
data as we want.
So many things that you could do to improve accuracy.
Again, highly recommend downloading this code and running it and then tweaking it and see
if you can get higher accuracy.
Cool.
All right.
So recap.
Neural networks are actually pretty simple to implement in CUDA.
I just ran through all of the code in, you know, what, 50 minutes?
Straightforward to understand.
And for each type of layer, when you're implementing a neural network in CUDA, you want a forward
pass and a backwards pass.
The backwards pass should update the gradients or at least save the gradient updates so you
can later select update gradients.
And it also is very important that you batch your training.
So you want to be able to do all of the examples in a batch in parallel.
For the full neural networks forward backward pass, you just call all of the different layers
forward pass and then call their backwards pass.
And then when training, you loop over all of your batches and then call the parent classes
forward and backward for each.
Cool.
All right.
So we can take a short break before we get into the more high-level part of this lecture.
That was like the most dense part.
So it's a 5-10 minute break and then we'll start again.
Hi, how are you?
Yeah, for sure.
Yeah, 100%.
No, no, no.
That's exactly how I would have attempted it.
The difficult part is that you kind of want to know the depth mapping of your surroundings
so that you can actually properly like...
I know there's something called a Kalman filter, which will take, let's say, some camera
that has depth information and create some sort of 3D scene.
And then you can be fairly sure where you're going.
If you don't have depth information, it's definitely a machine learning task for sure.
Is that only for two cameras or does that also work for one camera?
No, just your mobile camera.
OK, so yeah.
But mobile cameras tend to have two.
I have one.
That's probably also using machine learning.
Yes, I know that.
OK, then yeah.
So I would say even without the depth information, I would just do what you were saying.
Yeah, no, 100%.
Like even something as simple as taking the difference between this frame and that frame.
That's what I was thinking.
Yeah, 100% possible.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Absolutely.
In terms of whether or not it could be a final project, that's obviously Shehzad's discretion.
It can definitely be a project and totally be worth working on.
I would imagine that a CNN would work really well for that because...
Because you were talking about...
Right, well, so...
Yeah.
Yeah, so as like a quick disclaimer, I'm not a computer vision person.
But I know people in computer vision and I can quick ask what makes the most sense to implement
for a task like that.
I think taking the difference between frames or at the very least just having two frames
as your input, both frames like concatenated together as your input embedding.
And then you can say something like predict the vector like r and theta, let's say,
of where the person is actually turning.
You can also do left or right as zero, one, and then speed maybe of turn.
Right.
But yeah, like...
Try to let them know that they're doing the project.
Exactly, yeah, yeah, yeah.
A lot of the complexities in machine learning projects are input representation questions
and then architecture questions.
And I think the architecture is 99% chance going to be CNN, possibly Transformer,
but I think CNN is better.
And then it just now becomes a question of how do you represent the input?
Like, do you do edge detection or do you just concatenate the frames
or you take the difference between the frames?
And then what's your output representation look like?
Like, do you predict zero or one for left or right?
Or do you predict speed as well?
Do you predict like vector of momentum or whatever?
Okay, yeah.
What is it that we are trying to find out from...
Right, right.
And then the final thing that is super, super important...
How would we...
Is the data.
If you don't have data, you can't do anything.
You could theoretically record accelerometer data
if you could access it from some VR headset or...
Sorry, some VR headset.
Or just like, I don't know, tape a phone to someone's head
and then read out the gyroscope data and accelerometer data
and then have them just turn and then generate a bunch of data for you.
But you'd have to do that for a lot of hours.
And you also want to get a bunch of different scenes
so that your network can generalize to any...
So we better first have to start with generating a dataset.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
But for all I know, there might be a dataset out there.
Like, one of my roommates from undergrad
does pose estimation from head-mounted cameras.
And I imagine that he didn't go and collect all the data or something.
So I get the feeling that it's out there.
But yeah, if you...
Do you have my email?
Okay, I'll give it to...
I should have it on the slides.
It's just bad that I don't have it on the slides.
But I'll follow up with either Wayne or Rachel
and ask them to sort of get my email out.
And then if you want to,
you can just give the overview of the project
so I can have the details and I can ask people.
Yeah, no problem.
Okay.
So I'm going to continue on with the lecture now
because I want to make sure I give Wayne enough time at the end.
Yeah, basically halfway.
So, all right.
So if we want to speed up our neural network,
how are we going to do it?
What are the optimizations that we can make
both to the code that we just talked about
and then also to general applications of neural networks
that could speed things up?
Okay, so the implementation that we just talked about is pretty good.
But it's definitely not the best we can do.
Definitely not.
One easy way to improve performance
is to improve the performance of matrix multiply.
Like this is an obvious one.
Matrix multiply is used in every single layer constantly.
So if we can make our matrix multiply faster,
we're going to get a huge speed up.
So remember back to,
I'm assuming you guys have already done the performance lab
where Shazon talked about improving matrix multiply.
This is a fantastic example of why that would be very useful.
One thing here,
and I'm going to pick on this example code for a bit,
is memory coalescing.
So when we're reading from GPU memory,
we want to read sequential indices in memory
so that we can batch the reads.
Here, when we're looping over the activations,
what's our access pattern looking like?
All right, we have our for loop I,
and then how do we index?
So we're looping over a column in the matrix.
But if this matrix is column major, that's fine.
But if it's row major, it's not fine.
And we have the same matrix class for both W and A.
W we access by row, and A we access by column.
And one of the two is definitely not coalesced.
Very straightforward implementation would be
transpose this first, then access it.
Something like that, right?
Or at the very least, don't do one read per for loop
at random points in the matrix.
So super easy speed up.
Next speed up, shared memory, everyone's favorite.
So if you copy large portions of a matrix into shared memory,
you don't have to worry about a bunch of different accesses
not being coalesced because everything is also in shared memory.
So I know Shazon talked about this in the performance lab as well.
But copy in shared memory, do matrix multiply within shared memory,
and then write it back out all at once.
So I promised I was going to talk about AlexNet, and here I go.
The AlexNet source code actually does a ton of these optimizations.
This is the main workhorse function of the code,
and this is to implement a convolution.
Note that they preload all of the filters
and all of the images into shared memory.
Then they do the matrix multiply within shared memory.
This is the main part of the convolution,
and they have, note the pragma unroll here.
So we know these by compile time,
and we can unroll all of the things in the loop.
And then these writes are actually coalesced here.
Yeah, so I took time to read this code
and figure out these are coalesced, but that was last year.
So I can't point to exactly where in this it is coalesced.
But trust me, if you take an hour out of your day
to go figure out what all these variables are,
they are, in fact, coalesced.
It does make the code significantly harder to read, though,
because they're indexing in really, really weird ways,
and indexing is already kind of difficult when it gets complicated.
But yes, all right.
And then note that they also have sync threads here.
So they take all of the different threads
and make sure that they all are waiting on each other at the end
so that they can do one big kernel to compute many things
rather than calling multiple kernels over and over again.
This is something that's called layer fusion,
where you have one CUDA kernel that computes many layers at once.
Just to quiz you really quickly,
what's a very simple layer fusion technique
that we could use on our previous code base
to speed up substantially?
Having one kernel compute multiple functions in a row.
So that's a quick reminder.
We called CUDA kernels for linear layer,
and then for sigmoid, and then for ReLU.
Especially for some of those smaller CUDA kernels,
especially the ones that just basically call sigmoid and then end,
makes a lot of sense to have that as part of the linear layer.
So instead of just having a kernel that computes the linear layer,
and then another kernel that computes sigmoid,
just compute sigmoid within the linear layer.
Especially because sigmoid doesn't have any state to update.
It seems like you could definitely get away
with just putting it directly in the linear layer.
Doesn't that only give us one layer though, the sigmoid and the end?
That's true.
But I'll talk about...
So there's obviously a limit to how much you can do layer fusion.
Like you can't implement the entirety of the neural network
in one gigantic CUDA kernel,
because you'd have to load so many weights and biases into memory to do that,
that it would then hurt performance.
However, you can do this for specifically the nonlinearities
on layers is very common to have in the same kernel call.
It's like a ReLU with linear?
Exactly.
Each of those becomes compound one.
But what about like, I guess there'd be two, right?
It'd be like linear ReLU and then linear sigmoid.
Exactly.
So we can reduce our number of kernel calls to two instead of four.
And as I'm sure you guys know,
actually calling a CUDA kernel takes a lot of overhead
because you have to copy code to the GPU
and then it has to like initialize all of its whatever operating system state.
So this actually gets a very large speed up.
So another easy thing to pick on about the previous code base
is that it definitely sacrifices speed for ease of readability.
That would be another good exercise is to fuse those two kernels
and then see how much speed up you get.
Cool. Okay.
So can we do better than AlexNet's implementation of convolutions?
Any ideas on how to improve over this?
Don't think too hard about that question because it's a trick question.
No, we actually can't.
And the reason why we can't is because in the 10 years
since this paper has been published,
this is like the go-to implementation of convolutions, right?
It actually turns out that Alex was a pretty talented GPU programmer
and also that machine learning researchers
don't want to think about this GPU optimization stuff,
which is more jobs for us, I guess.
However, one way to speed this up even further
is by calling other people's code that have more access
to sort of more low-level implementation capabilities.
So I'm going to introduce this concept of a basic linear algebra subroutine or BLAS.
This is a standard set of functions for fast matrix operations.
And it's kind of like there's like a spec
for what you need to implement to be BLAS compliant.
And almost every machine implements their version of these BLAS functions.
They're often optimized by hardware manufacturers
for speed on a particular machine.
So you'll have Intel implements their own BLAS.
You have AMD implements their own BLAS, all of this stuff.
And then they'll use things like the vector registers
and special SIMD instructions,
which would be single instruction, multiple data.
And they try to make the best possible matrix multiply on their hardware.
And if you just call these functions that the hardware manufacturers provide,
you're going to get way faster matrix multiply
than doing these matrix multiply operations yourself.
So there should be no reason to actually write matrix multiply yourself in CUDA.
You should almost always call a basic linear algebra subroutine.
In fact, libraries like MATLAB, NumPy, R,
and then of course you guys have been using GLM.
They all call these under the hood.
The reason why MATLAB is fast at computing matrix multiply
is because it's calling BLAS under the hood.
So all of the scientific computing libraries,
they're all doing this and that's why they're fast.
And this is, you can have CPU-based BLAS implementations,
and then you can also have GPU-based BLAS implementations.
So in the BLAS spec, there are three levels.
Level one is vector operations.
So AXPY is short for AX plus Y.
You can see X and Y would be both vectors,
and then A is just some constant.
So this is very useful for computing linear functions with one constant.
Level two is vector times matrix operations.
So we have GEMV, which is generalized matrix vector product,
and that's Y equals some constant times matrix A vector X plus some constant Y.
All right.
These two levels are very niche.
It's very unusual to be using these two
because you're trying to take advantage of massively parallel computer architecture.
If you're going to go parallel,
you might as well go to matrix matrix and compute many things in parallel.
This level three, aka the GEMM, some people call it GEM.
I don't know how I feel about that.
But yeah, so GEMM is generalized matrix multiply.
And oftentimes when you think about BLAS,
you're going to hear people talk about GEM.
And this is matrix A times matrix B plus some matrix C.
And this is what is like the backbone of every scientific computing environment.
Cool.
Any questions about BLAS?
Do you work with NavMesh in NumPy at all?
I've never worked with NavMesh.
Is that like a library on top of NumPy?
Because in the CV class, they also ask us to parallelize their code.
But it's not like this.
So MeshGrid basically generates a 2D, because it's for images,
but it generates a 2D array.
And it goes like 0, 0, 0, 1, 2, 3, 0, 1, 2, 3, 0, 1, 2, 3 for like x.
Like 0, 0, 0, 1, 1, 1, 1, 2, 2, 2 for like y.
And then to do image-wide applications, you pass in the x NavMesh as the x-coordinate,
and the y NavMesh as the y-coordinate.
I'm guessing there's a bunch of GPU optimization under the hood.
Yeah.
Yeah, for sure.
So oftentimes, when you'll hear people say that you should vectorize your code with NumPy,
for example, or pretty much exactly what you're talking about,
where they'll create matrices with these index indices.
It's almost always because that's going to be used as input to some library,
which under the hood, calls gem.
Any vectorized code, any fast matrix multiply on either CPU or GPU
always calls some gem implementation.
And that is hardware-specific.
So when some library calls gem, that accesses Intel's implementation of gem,
which is written in machine code.
Cool.
All right.
So as I'm sure you could guess, there is a CUDA implementation of BLOS.
So BLOS on the GPU, which is even faster than CPU BLOS.
CUBLOS is closed source, unfortunately.
We don't actually know how it's implemented.
And I'm sure that the way it's implemented is a trade secret.
Because this is the backbone of why NVIDIA can claim that they get x speed up on x architecture,
because you make an improvement to matrix multiply, and everything is fast.
But there's a lot of effort put into CUBLOS optimization,
and every major ML framework that runs on NVIDIA GPUs uses this under the hood.
I have seen niche blog posts about people being able to beat a CUBLOS implementation
with something very clever, but do not try.
That's a PhD thesis, for sure.
Cool.
There are a bunch of different gem functions for different data types,
because, of course, you can get bits of performance
if you know that you're dealing with shorts rather than longs.
When in doubt, just do SGEM, because people don't tend to use the full precision of longs.
But technically, you have real values and complex values that you can use,
and you have short and long precision.
And over here is the spec, naturally, for a very fast and optimized function.
There's a bunch of different inputs, and it's a pain to use,
to sacrifice for performance.
Yeah, on the same note, directly using CUBLOS is actually pretty cumbersome.
There's a lot of state to set up beforehand.
As you can see, this is where I call the SGEM from CUBLOS,
but you have to create the handles, you have to initialize this,
and then you have to, of course, check errors if you're being safe.
If you want a sample program,
when you have your CUDA install and program data,
they have a bunch of samples.
So if you go check the samples, I think CUDA version is now 11.7 or something,
maybe even higher than that.
But if you just go to the samples directory,
you should be able to find examples of SGEM.
Also, a GitHub link to a 2015 version of the sample is available.
I wouldn't go there for the most updated sample that runs CUBLOS.
This is the 2015 version.
But if you check this directory on your computer,
and you have CUDA installed, you'll have it.
So what about for other layers that aren't matrix multiply?
Like, great that we have matrix multiply,
but what about speeding up stuff like convolutions?
What about speeding up MaxPool?
So there's another library that's also very important called CUDDNN,
which stands for CUDA Deep Neural Network.
And it's another closed source library built on top of CUBLOS.
And it provides functions, both forward and backward passes,
for convolution, MaxPool, Softmax, Sigmoid, Relu, Tanh,
even though no one uses hyperbolic tangent anymore.
It does not provide a linear layer, importantly,
because that's literally just calling sgem once.
So they force you to use CUBLOS at least once.
But for everything else,
they have specifically optimized versions of convolutions.
And so packages like PyTorch and TensorFlow
call this for their CUDA implementation.
And this is obviously, again, very optimized.
So CUDDNN is also here.
Sorry, go ahead, yeah.
General question, who owns TensorFlow or Keras?
Is this a company?
Yeah, Google owns TensorFlow.
And Facebook owns PyTorch.
I think Google also owns Jax, which is another employee.
That's a good question.
I don't, I feel like it's one of either Google or Facebook,
or maybe, I don't know.
But I haven't seen Keras in a long time.
So whoever did own Keras got a bad return on investment.
Who owns Scikit?
Scikit?
That's a good question.
I have no idea who owns Scikit Learn.
But they're less of a deep learning framework
and more of if you want to implement linear regression
or something that's easy to do on the CPU.
And I also imagine that they probably call
the CPU loss routines under the hood as well.
But yeah, that's a good question.
I think it's some non-profit collective or something.
ONNX, I think, is also an open source.
It's like, I'll talk about ONNX later in the lecture.
But I think it's just a standard.
And so they have some spec that they write up.
And it's some inter-company designed specific spec.
And then that's just operated by everyone.
So similar to Linux, where it's just kind of open source.
Cool.
Right, so talking about CUDNN as well,
it's pretty cumbersome to use.
Again, that's the price you pay for performance.
But there are a lot of resources on CUDNN.
And it's also a really nice niche skill to learn.
Like, very few people get experience
writing CUDNN directly that aren't
in machine learning performance.
And that type of thing is great to have on a resume.
C++ code with Kuboas and CUDNN is the industry standard
for machine learning performance.
I have on very good confidence that things like DLSS
and things like most of the performance-critical machine
learning applications are all written directly in C++
by calling CUDNN code.
So if you want to have the fastest possible code,
this is what you want to do.
Cool, all right.
So here's a sample of an improvement
that CUDNN likely, again, we don't know the source code.
But likely makes.
So normally, to do a convolution,
you need to take the filter and apply it
to each position in the image.
You sort of sweep the filter across the image.
And that's some big for loop.
And we for loop over the indices.
And then we sweep the filter.
But can we improve this by framing it as a matrix multiply
rather than sweeping the filter?
So if you unroll the pixels that would
be multiplied by the filter.
So the pixels of the image that are under this patch,
for example, into columns.
So instead of a, let's say, 3 by 3 by 5 block,
you have just one vector of 3 times 3 times 5 pixels.
And then you take the filter.
And you unroll that into one column vector
of 3 by 3 by 5 pixels.
You can then frame a convolution as a gigantic matrix multiply
where each of the patches get their own row vector.
And the filter is just the same column vector
copied a bunch of times.
And then you could just matrix multiply.
So this is way, way, way faster, especially
when you don't have that many patches to go through
when you're doing convolution.
What are the drawbacks of doing this?
Can anyone tell me?
Is this just faster in every possible scenario?
I guess that if it's a simple case,
it's like the overhead is basically not worth it.
Possibly.
But there's another subtle detail to this.
I think directly when you read about
use these sorts of unrolls, it has to be done at compile time.
That's also true.
But we do know the bounds of our input.
We know our input size is a fixed size at compile time.
So we would know the bounds.
But yes, that's another important point.
So maybe I could turn your attention to this kernel matrix.
And if you have one filter and you have that as per column,
in order to apply the same filter to every patch,
what you're doing is you're actually OK.
Instead of this, what happens when your patches overlap?
Yeah.
So in your input matrix, if you're unrolling every patch
and some patches overlap, this input matrix
is going to be very large.
Because you will include the same data multiple times
for every overlapping portion of the patches.
So if memory is your bottleneck, like say
you're running on a small device,
you might not be able to do this for convolutions
because you actually don't have enough space.
And it's also very common that filters are large.
Let's say 7 by 7.
And then their stride is 1.
So 6 of the 7 indices are actual overlaps.
So you might blow up your memory usage to 6 or 7 times
just to get the small speed up.
And also, that involves copying all of that information.
So you can see why for large filters that have short strides,
this would be suboptimal.
But especially in a case like this,
where the filters do not have any overlap, perfectly fine.
And if anything, this is a very, very, very good
optimization of this.
Cool.
And of course, when you're calling convolutions in cuDNN,
they would check what your filter size is
and what your image size is.
And they would know whether or not
to implement an optimization like this
based on what you've passed it.
And fairly confident that this is,
at least some version of this is going on in cuDNN,
but we can never be sure.
Cool.
So again, my text-filled recap slide.
So BLOS is a standard set of linear algebra subroutines
that are typically implemented by manufacturers
on different machines.
cuBLOS is a parallel BLOS implementation
that NVIDIA takes a lot of pains to optimize.
And then cuDNN is a library that uses cuBLOS
to do convolutions and compute forward and backward passes.
And all of the modern GPU-based deep learning
is built on cuBLOS and cuDNN.
And so both PyTorch and TensorFlow both call it.
Can these things be patented or...
Probably.
So you can patent an implementation
for an optimization?
Yeah.
In machine learning, it's very, very taboo
to patent basic techniques
because that kind of slows down the progress of the field.
Like I talked about on Monday
where Google attempted to patent Dropout
and got huge blowback.
I would assume that the reason
why techniques like this aren't patented
is partially that,
because they don't want to get the blowback,
and also partially because
when researchers come up with a good technique,
they want to publish a paper about it.
And patenting is like a sort of alternative
to publishing a paper
where you give the information out,
but it's in a patented form.
Whereas paper is just,
you give the information out, free to use.
And luckily for us,
machine learning research culture
is one that prioritizes giving information out.
Even the big company research teams
tend to publish all of their research,
which is great
because that's the reason
why machine learning is progressing so quickly.
But yeah, to your point,
you totally could patent something like this.
Why is that the case?
Because I took an IT class
that I don't remember that much from,
but in, say, modalities with the Swiffer,
or that stuff is all very competitively patented.
I think also Google tried to patent PageRank.
I think that was overturned
because new legislation came out
about how abstract that can be.
Right.
Yeah, I imagine that the reason
why it's not typical for machine learning
patents to happen
is because machine learning is moving so quickly
that things that you patent,
you can't release.
And by the time your patent goes through,
it might be obsolete.
Like dropout is one of those rare techniques
that we know is going to be relevant basically forever.
Right.
But it's very hard to confidently say like,
ah, yes, my convolutional neural net optimization
is going to be relevant forever
when convolutional neural nets
might go obsolete by some new architecture suddenly
within five years, right?
Like it's already somewhat starting to happen
with transformers, right?
Convolutional neural nets have a lot of competition now.
So yeah, it's probably from that,
but also at the same time,
it's just such a fast field.
And I think the culture is mainly the reason.
Anyway, right.
So going beyond KUBLAS and QDNN,
is there any easier way to implement neural networks?
Of course, the answer is yes.
I've been alluding to PyTorch and TensorFlow,
but we're going to finally talk about it.
So C++ code that directly calls KUBLAS,
QDNN is the best performance you can get,
but it's super cumbersome to write.
So what if we don't care too much
about speed of prediction, right?
Like what if we just want to rapidly prototype
a new network and then check its accuracy
and then sort of iterate really quickly?
Is there a less cumbersome option?
So the two biggest frameworks are PyTorch and TensorFlow.
PyTorch is the bigger of the two frameworks,
but TensorFlow is very substantial.
And most all of the Google teams use TensorFlow.
Both have C++ and Python bindings.
It's much more common for people to use the Python bindings
because it's less code to write, easier to iterate on.
But if you want to have faster performance,
of course, you're going to use the C++ bindings.
And they both call QDNN under the surface
when running on NVIDIA GPUs,
but they will call other things under the hood
when running on, let's say, TPUs
or running without access to a CUDA GPU.
They'll sort of abstract away that.
So is this the standard or do they just prototype it?
They're research standard, for sure.
And so I guess that answers your question, right?
They're mainly used for prototyping
and in companies that don't know better.
So if someone's trying to deploy
some machine learning application
and has PyTorch code to run it
and they don't know that you can get
like 100x speed up or whatever,
then yeah, they would use it.
And again, like PyTorch is not actually that slow.
And I'll get into some of the reasons why.
There's small optimizations you can make
if you really need the extra, let's say, 30, 40%.
You want to do C++, QDNN, Kubas,
but like, it's really not that bad.
So some companies are like,
fine, it's not mission critical for this to run
in 0.001 seconds.
So, yeah.
Does that mean that like NVIDIA GPUs
have their own like QDNN, like?
Yeah.
So I don't know off the top of my head
what it's called,
but I imagine that they do have it.
It's just not common to run machine learning
on AMD GPUs.
So do like, is research like never run on an AMD GPU?
Almost never.
And is it just because it's-
Correct.
Exactly.
Yeah.
And NVIDIA has been writing that all the way
for the last at least 10 years.
Cool. All right.
Both PyTorch and TensorFlow are amazingly easy to use.
I love them.
Everyone does.
And they're built-in classes for every single type of layer
that you could ever need.
So if you want a linear layer, they have it.
If they want convolution, they have it.
Very simple API.
There's not a lot of overhead, no state setup.
Tons of resources in blog posts.
There's very comparatively little on Kubas, QDNN,
and there's an unbelievable amount of resources
for PyTorch, TensorFlow.
And there's also lots of built-in models.
Like for example, this is one of the built-in models
that comes with PyTorch.
Does anyone recognize this architecture?
We have Conv, ReLU, MaxPool, Conv, ReLU, MaxPool,
Conv, ReLU, MaxPool over and over again.
And then we have a couple of linear layers at the end.
Yeah, this is AlexNet.
Yeah.
So this is the implementation.
Look at how nice this is, right?
They have the size.
All you have to do is make sure the dimensions match, right?
So you have 64, 64, 192, 192, so on and so forth.
Each of these layers have the kernel size.
So that's the size of the filter.
So that's three.
And then the stride, which is how many pixels the filter moves
when it goes to sweep across the image.
And as long as you match the dimensions up,
you can prototype neural nets really, really fast.
So again, the only thing you need to implement
for a new model is the forward pass.
Self.features here is the concatenation
of all of these different layers.
And then self.classifier is the concatenation
of the linear layers.
So this is the forward pass for AlexNet,
which calls the features pool and then the classifier,
which is calling the convolutions and then the linear layers.
And that's the forward pass.
Even more interesting is that you don't even
have to implement the backward pass
because the backward pass is completely
determined by the forward pass.
So PyTorch, to use as an example,
TensorFlow also does this.
But PyTorch will completely abstract away
writing the backwards function because it
can figure out what the backwards function is
by what you wrote in the forward function.
So all you have to do here is, so if you have the forward pass,
you just call it on inputs.
You get your outputs.
You calculate the loss.
And then you call loss.backward for the backward pass.
And then you're done.
It's fantastic.
And then optimizer also is what gradient descent you're using.
So when you call optimizer.step, that
is update the weights and biases from what
we calculated with the gradient.
And it gets even worse.
So in this next part, shield your eyes.
So if you want to send data to the GPU, what you do
is you first initialize the data on the CPU.
So this is a vector of all ones.
And let's say you initialize your neural net.
And then you call .CUDA.
And then it moves to the GPU.
And that's all you have to do.
It's just .CUDA.
No memory management, no dimension calculations,
no shared memory, no nothing.
It's just .CUDA, and it'll take care of it.
So this is painfully easy if you've
had to deal with all of these indices and stuff
that we do in this class.
So no wonder people don't use CUDA directly.
But yeah, nothing about the code changes at all.
If you want to train on the GPU, all you have to do
is as long as your network has been like you have network
equals network.CUDA.
So this updates the state of the network class
just to say that it's on the GPU.
Call all of the code normally.
And it will run on the GPU.
And then all you have to do is run .CPU
after you're done to get things back on the CPU.
And that's done.
So there's got to be a catch here.
This is way too quick.
For training and prototyping, there's actually not a catch.
This is really, really fast.
They use kubos and cuDNN.
So once you start the training loop,
and once everything is settled, it's still fast.
Unless you're trying to build the world's biggest
neural network, like you're trying
to push the boundaries of what is possible
on modern hardware, this should be totally fine.
But what if we want to do fast prediction?
What if we want mission-critical prediction?
So to better understand where PyTorch and TensorFlow are weak,
I'm going to introduce this idea called
the computational graph model.
Really, all this is, it's just a graphical representation
of what's going on in a neural network.
So the forward arrows, these black arrows,
are inputs into different layers.
These boxes are the different layers.
And they're not just the different layers.
They're actually just operations.
So x would be the input.
x times weight, this is multiplication, plus bias.
Then we do the non-linearity.
And this is times weight plus bias, non-linearity output.
So this is just an example of a two-layer neural network
in graphical format.
And these red arrows are the gradients.
Computational graphs are a nice way
of representing a neural network flow of information.
It helps us understand what derivatives
get backpropagated where.
Important question, does the computational graph
fully describe a network architecture?
Or is there things that it leaves out?
So if you have, well, as long as you
have nodes for the activation functions themselves, then yeah.
And it's very typical to have it.
So not quite.
So it turns out that the computational graph does
actually fully describe a neural network architecture
with small additions.
So as long as you have the input dimensions
and everything is fine, yeah, this completely describes it.
And you mentioned ONNX.
ONNX is a format for representing
the computational graph of a neural network.
So it's just some sort of serialized format
that you can print out what the computational graph looks like.
And then you can load that in to other frameworks.
And if they support ONNX, that will fully
describe what the neural network is.
So they can initialize whatever state they want.
So yeah.
So PyTorch and TensorFlow both allow dynamic just-in-time
updates to the computational graph mid-training.
So what this means is that you can stop halfway
through a training run and add a new layer.
Or you can add conditional layers.
And the main reason why they do that
is because of this conditional thing.
It's very nice to be able to add debug prints.
Let's say if weight is over a certain amount,
do this instead.
Or if weight is over a certain amount, stop.
TensorFlow v1 used to not allow this just-in-time updates.
But now TensorFlow v2 does because they
need to optimize for the main use case, which is researchers.
And they don't care as much about performance.
Why would this be really bad for optimization?
Like, if we can change the computational graph whenever
we want, what can't we do?
Like, what sort of optimizations can we
make if we know the computational graph will never, ever change?
So one optimization we talked about earlier
was trying to combine things in the same CUDA kernel.
Right?
So that's generally called layer fusion.
If the computational graph can change,
it might change in ways that do not
allow us to fuse two layers.
Like, let's say we fuse two layers,
and then the user decided that the computational graph can
and then the user decided that they actually
wanted a different layer in between those two layers.
Right?
Then we are screwed.
Because we fuse those two layers, we can no longer separate them.
Or at least it's very difficult to separate them again.
It's easy to fuse things.
It's kind of hard to, like, un-fuse things.
So this is actually a pretty big area for optimization
for PyTorch and TensorFlow.
And again, it's not like they don't know this.
This is a design decision that they
made so that it's easier to use.
But if you're looking for the extra boost in performance,
this is what you can do.
When you make everything into one big kernel,
you can get a big speedup.
And there's a lot of other optimizations
that can be done on the computational graphs.
Layer fusion is the big one.
But you can also prune different branches
if you know that you're not going to go down.
So like what you were saying earlier,
if you had a whole chunk of an image,
let's say, that got relu'd out to zero,
you can decide not to call the kernel.
That is not easy to computational graph,
because you don't know if someone's ever
going to put a new layer in there.
Another thing is quantizing the weights.
So these optimizations are actually
impossible on PyTorch and TensorFlow.
But what if we want fast inference
on a PyTorch model anyway?
Is there any way that we can make these optimizations?
And so now I get to talk about TensorRT.
So one of my friends from undergrad
is on the TensorRT team.
And I was talking to him in preparing for this lecture.
And TensorRT is a really great resource.
So I'm kind of both plugging it
and also educating people about it,
because not enough people use it.
But it's an SDK for fast model inference.
So what you can do is you basically output
your model in ONNX, as I was saying earlier.
And it can basically run a bunch
of different optimizations on it.
Once you print a model to ONNX,
that's fixed computational graph.
There's no just-in-time updates to that.
That is what the graph is.
So once we know what the graph is
and we know it doesn't change,
then you can make updates.
So TensorRT will go through and do
these plus extra optimizations.
So quantization is a big one.
You don't have to always have 32-bit
floating points for every weight.
You can do int8, even, in the worst case.
You can do layer fusion.
You can auto-tune the different kernels.
So they have different, say, convolution kernels.
You have the matrix multiply version versus others.
And then they can sort of test
to see which one works best.
Also, the memory thing is another big one,
like dynamically resizing memory
to get the best sort of tiling of memory
so that you can get the fastest reads.
It's really cool.
And so why bother with kubelos and cuDNN
if TensorRT is so great, right?
And I asked this question to my friend,
and I summarized his bullet points here.
So TensorRT doesn't actually guarantee
anything about the accuracy of your model.
So for example, if we did quantize the weights
from floating point 32 to int8,
there's no guarantee that we're going
to get the same prediction.
And that might actually cost us a lot,
especially if we're doing something
that's actually really critical, performance critical.
We would want to implement this ourselves
because we don't want the sort of loss in performance.
Also, TensorRT, as a design decision,
is a giant black box, right?
So it decides what optimizations it's going to make.
And you have very little control
over what TensorRT decides to do to your model.
So if you want to specify,
I don't want you to fuse these layers
or I don't want you to quantize, you really can't.
But despite these drawbacks,
it's actually pretty useful as a baseline.
So if you were going to try to improve inference speed
on a model that exists,
which has been a very popular topic for final projects,
this is a good baseline to run.
So you just take the model, print it out to ONNX,
run it through TensorRT,
and then that's your baseline.
So you could try to write CUDNN to beat that.
Okay, final recap slide.
So C++ code that directly calls Kugloss CUDNN
is the industry standard for ML performance.
However, unless you're trying to push the limits
of scale slash inference speed,
training time is generally cheaper than inference time.
Right, and what I mean by that is,
the more time you spend in production
trying to get your model to actually run,
the less time it is actually out there running.
And so if you are willing to spend extra time,
like if it's not important to have the inference speed,
you should have faster iteration on the models.
For training small models also,
PyTorch and TensorFlow are fantastic.
There are lots of resources,
easy to prototype, flexible.
But for inference, aka prediction,
PyTorch and TensorFlow are not great
because of this just-in-time computational graph
design decision.
And TensorRT is a pretty good middle ground
where you can train a model with PyTorch and TensorFlow,
and then you export the graph to ONNX
and then run with TensorRT.
And it does a lot of the optimizations
that are missing from PyTorch and TensorFlow.
Cool, all right.
So that's the end.
Many thanks to these three people
for helping me out with researching this talk.
It was really fun to get to dive
into the actual machine learning performance field.
And yeah, so I don't have my email on this slide,
which I've lamented earlier.
But if you want it,
I'm sure that I can send it to Shazan, Wayne, and Rachel.
And then also I'll be around for final projects
and will mentor any team
that wants to do machine learning stuff.
So feel free to let me know if you have project ideas
and we can talk.
And yeah, cool.
Thanks a bunch.
So I think that we can take a break,
maybe 10, 15 minutes, and then-
Yeah, we'll start at seven.
Okay.
We're supposed to help you get off in one,
and then Rachel's gonna come in to do web sharing.
Yeah, she did on Monday.
She did the WebGL API,
so this time it's actually in Python as well.
Okay.
There was only one decision you had to worry about today,
just the one that she's on the same page.
Only one what?
The Zoom one.
Yeah, exactly.
It's the one that she's on the same page now.
And there's like no one on the Zoom,
it's just her recording.
Yeah, you're right.
There's no one on the Zoom.