All right.
So an atomic add internally would be implemented
something like this.
Now you'll never have to write a function like this device
because it's already given to you by CUDA
but this is more of an exercise, okay?
So what we start with is an incoming address
which is the value you want to update
and a value here that you're going to add to that address.
And each thread is going to try to do this
because this is essentially a register.
Each thread can try to add a different value
to your address, okay?
So one, so each thread tries to execute this.
They come in here, okay?
They, and remember the return function here
has to be the old value, okay?
The new value stored here, it returns the old value, okay?
That is a key thing in atomic operations.
So we come in here, we create a register for old
so that we can return that writing code.
And then we try to do some kind of a lock.
I'm making up a function here, okay?
I want to try to block this address.
If I'm successful in locking it,
then I'll come in, store the old value in old
and then add the new value in address.
And then I'll return old.
Does this make sense to everybody?
How this locking mechanism is working?
Any questions here?
So what would this essentially do in CUDA
when we have blocks of threads?
What does this do now?
Yeah, exactly.
In a way, this is what it's meant to do.
This is what is known as a locking mechanism.
So in programming styles of coordination,
there are three mechanisms.
And these are derived from GTC sites that I created.
You can have locking, which is what I showed you.
You can have lock-free.
Lock-free doesn't necessarily mean not parallel.
It's just lock-free.
And I'll get to that in a little bit.
And then there's wait-free.
Wait-free is essentially what we do in CUDA
for all the things like reductions and stuff
that we've done is wait-free.
So let's take a look at each of those.
So first, locking essentially means
that all threads try to get the lock.
One thread that is successful in getting the lock,
it doesn't work and releases the thread.
So as long as every thread doesn't get a lock and release,
we have to wait there.
Okay?
So it's not...
So if we go back here,
essentially, until all threads did this to be true,
they can't come down here.
All the threads can't come down here.
So that's locking.
Let's take a look at lock-free.
So this is a little different, okay?
What happens here is, unlike before,
where all the threads try to get the lock,
all the threads will try to get the lock.
If they fail, they'll go back and try again.
And then the one thread that gets the lock
will execute the instructions.
Okay?
The main difference here
is how the loop is essentially structured
in how the lock is picked up
and how the threads that are not successful,
the work that they're doing.
So over here,
if a thread is not successful in getting a lock,
they'll try to keep getting the lock
over and over and over again
without moving to the next line.
It'll wait at that line.
Here, you're gonna change what happened.
You're gonna change so that it goes back to a certain point,
does the instructions again, and then comes back.
So as a reminder, CUDA has free compute, right?
So this proves to be better
because now you have threads working in lockstep
and doing compute,
rather than just checking for memory
over and over and over again.
So this is essentially,
this kind of lock-free style
is essentially what is called Atomic CAS.
And we'll take a look at that a little later.
Atomic CAS stands for Atomic Compare and Swap.
And we'll see examples of that later.
And also Atomic Exchange and Atomic Add
in CUDA use this kind of lock-free mechanism.
The last time, which we can't do for Atomics
is all the threads make progress.
Each thread makes memory updates automatically
and no threads are blocked by other threads,
which is essentially what is Paddle programming.
So I'm gonna switch to a different deck here
and I've linked it from here
because I wanna walk through
some of the stuff from the NVIDIA slide.
So let's take a look at it.
Yes, both could serialize everything,
but it depends on what address they're trying to,
and that's what I'm getting at here.
So you can have different atomic access patterns, right?
You can have all the threads
trying to access the same address.
You can have all the atomics
trying to access the same cache line
because remember all the cache line stuff
is being read together, right?
So that could happen as well,
or it could be more scattered.
So those are different atomic access patterns
and why I'm showing you this
will become clear in a second.
So locking guarantees essentially access control
about which threads have the ability
to read, modify and delete data.
You can't have different threads
trying to do different things.
You can just get memory corruption.
So we have to make sure that it works correctly.
We'll skip a few slides.
Yeah, sure.
So when we think about what divergence and atomics,
we have to remember that CUDA works in walks, right?
32 threads execute in lockstep,
which means all the threads have to do the same thing.
As a reminder, if we have this kind of function here
where we have an if condition as, and all that,
you get this kind of a pattern
where some threads are doing work and some threads are not,
but essentially some threads are idle at that point.
So if we try to do this with locking, right?
And let's say one thread gets the lock
and this is a locked side programming,
what happens is all of these threads that are not locked
just idle at that place until they get people,
until this thread unlocks it.
So these threads don't do anything at all.
In a different way, if the wrong thread idles,
and remember, we can do atomics for different reasons
for different threads, okay?
It's not always an atomic add
that is adding the same thing to the same address.
You can have atomics for different reasons
that have a thread condition for writing to global memory.
What is an example of this?
What could be an example of this?
So if you remember, we did reduction, right?
Imagine doing one block of reduction
using atomic add.
You can do it serially where you do thread one
plus thread two plus thread three and so on,
or you can do it in the tree structure
that we did for our scan algorithms and stuff.
But you can do that within a block for atomic add, right?
Now, in that case, you will be trying to use,
trying to check which address you're adding to,
and then different threads are gonna try
to lock different things.
So in that scenario, you would get into the situation
where the wrong thread could try to access
the wrong location, and then it's kind of like
you're failing at what you're trying to do.
So what we want to do is,
we don't want to use locks in threads
because it causes divergence and hangs.
What we want to do is elect one thread to take the lock
until other threads can get the lock.
So this is called a lock-free mechanism.
So lock-free mechanisms are essentially
what we'll do with compare and swap,
which is to read, modify, and then write the operation.
So the reason this works,
and I'll show you how exactly it is,
is that it's much higher throughput
because it's not trying to read memory
all at the same time,
and exactly one thread is guaranteed
to succeed at all times.
So let's take a look.
So in lock-free updates,
this, oh, sorry.
When it tries to take the lock,
so the first step is every thread is gonna try to lock.
If it succeeds, it's gonna read and modify the value
and unlock.
Otherwise, it's gonna try taking the lock again.
This code, and we have it in the slides,
the class slides as well,
is essentially, what this is doing is
while this lock-free mechanism,
and atomic exchanges is kind of a lock here,
while this lock doesn't succeed,
keep trying to do that, right?
If it succeeds, you come in,
you change the value, and then you return, okay?
So this line becomes the locking mechanism here.
What we want to do and change this to
is something like this.
We generate the new value
based on the current data that we have.
So we essentially do the add, okay?
Take the register that was passed in,
do the add anyway,
but you change the value only if you succeed on locking,
okay?
So let's see how that works.
I'll come back to the slides here.
So I'll keep this here so that I can switch back to it,
but let's take a look at how this is gonna work.
Okay.
One second.
All right.
So what we are gonna do is
we had this mechanism, right?
This lock mechanism that was essentially
holding up all the threads here
without allowing them to work in lockstep.
How would we implement this without locking?
So I've put the code down here,
the old code down here for reference, okay?
And we are gonna use atomic comparisons for this
as suggested in the NVIDIA slides.
And atomic comparisons has this mechanism here
that what it does is it's going to take an address
of compare value and a final value, okay?
Now here's the trick.
If it gets a lock on the address, okay?
The atomic pass, not atomic add.
So the atomic pass, if it gets the address here,
what it does is it stores the old value in address, okay?
If old is the same as compare, okay?
What that means is if the current value in address
and whether it is able to get a lock
is the same as the compare value, the condition value, okay?
Then only, then do we actually switch it
to the final value.
Otherwise, and then we return the old value.
And this will make sense when we come to add in a little bit,
okay?
Just understand how compare and swap work.
In compare and swap, we have an input value
that we are comparing to a compare value
if true value becomes address, okay?
So once again, if address equals compare,
if the value in address equals compare,
then we write value into address, okay?
That is compare and swap.
So we lock, do the swap, and then return.
So now let's take an example.
If address equals one, okay?
What is the result of atomic pass, the first line?
Okay.
But remember, we have address.
The compare is one here, and value is two.
What's the starting point then?
So the,
all is,
all is at the end.
So,
address, the address,
at the address currently, the old value is one,
so one equals compare and swap one.
So then we will return one, but now address stores,
stores two.
Right, so like both of you suggested,
what's happening here is, if we look at this again,
if this is true, let's assume it's true,
old, we store old of address,
and then old and compare are the same.
Remember, we are not comparing address to compare,
we are comparing old to compare,
and that's the intention.
So the one gets stored in old,
and old one equals one, true,
so we put two in address, okay?
But this returns one, and stores two.
What happens in the next line after this?
What's the value in address here?
Two.
Now what is the result of compare?
False, so we don't, we don't, we don't fall.
So address still remains two.
What about the next line?
The compare is true, so now address becomes three
and returns two.
So you see how compare and swap kind of builds
towards atomic add, essentially?
So if given atomic pass, how do we implement atomic add?
And the answer to that is something like this,
where you take the old address and put it in old,
and create a new assumed value.
Now look, there's no locking mechanism here.
So now, we're going to do,
and we put the old and assumed value intentionally.
And this assumed is important
because we want to keep doing work without having locked.
So in that case, old will essentially become,
compare and swap the address,
so we have to still give the address,
we can't replace that, we still need that pointer.
The assumed value, and then the value plus a zero.
Value plus assumed is the final value of an atomic add.
Until we know that assumed is not old,
why is this condition important?
What is that condition essentially telling us?
Old only equals old if the add fails, I guess.
Exactly.
Assumed will not equal old if the atomic pass succeeds.
Because what will happen is,
this will update and store a different value node,
because atomic pass will return a different value node
because the address is getting faked.
So that's why, if this condition fails,
that's when we know the atomic operation has succeeded.
So while this happens,
all the threads will keep doing this
without actually updating address,
and only the thread that receives the permission,
the locking to update address will actually update it.
So this will guarantee that the thread we intend to update
will update it.
So just to highlight that again,
if the value address didn't change, then we update it.
If some other thread has the locking and changes the value,
then we still, we don't increment it at all.
So that's the method behind the madness here.
Any questions on this?
So this is essentially to show you
how atomics are built into CUDA.
You will never have to write any of this code.
You can just use atomic add function from CUDA anyway.
This is to show you how people
who are building the CUDA SDK and the libraries
think about all of this while doing performance.
And if you are using any of these atomic operations,
that you think about it as well,
about how you are gonna be using this.
So it's not just atomic add,
but you get a bunch of atomic functions as well.
In addition to add, you get add, subtract, exchange,
which swaps values, min, max, increment, decrement,
and then compare and swap, which we saw.
You also get bitwise.
You can do bitwise and, or, or, x, or,
and then build various things on top of this.
So now two questions.
I've always maintained in the class
that two threads from different blocks can't work together.
Can they, now you think about atomics?
Okay.
From different blocks, threads can't work together.
There's no sync block function.
There's only sync thread in a block.
How can atomics help or not help
in different blocks working together?
Okay.
Threads in different blocks
may be trying to access the same thing.
Which one?
Not shared.
Shared is limited to a block.
Yep.
So very, very bad.
Don't ever do it.
But you can have different threads from different blocks
trying to access the same memory using atomics.
And based on that, you can make that a conditional.
For example, when you ordered reduction,
you had your block sums, right?
That you wrote into memory, read it on the CPU side,
and then computed it there.
What happens if you selected let this block zero
and be like, okay, block zero after all,
or not all block zero, but memory space zero.
Thread zeros of all the blocks
should atomically write to that memory space
so that now you're just computing the reduction,
the block sum reduction
within one memory space in global memory.
It's possible.
You can do it.
You can absolutely do it,
but I wouldn't recommend it
because what you're doing then
is essentially serializing all of your code.
Why should we use atomic spelling?
I kind of just gave you the answer for that
before asking the question.
Serializes.
Yeah, it serializes.
What's the worst case?
All the threads are serial.
Yeah, all the threads could become serial in that case.
If all the threads are trying to access the same memory
and do the same operation,
you could make a thread serial.
It's worse, even more worse,
if you try to do it in global memory.
Doing it within shared memory is not too bad.
Don't ever, ever, ever do atomics in global memory
unless you absolutely need to.
And there's no other alternative
because remember for each of those blocks,
the thread has to go to global memory,
get the value updated.
There's like 200 cycles of time.
By that time, one of the block
could have already updated and you don't know.
So it's kind of like communicating with Mars.
The round trip to Mars is what?
12 minutes, 24 minutes, something like that.
By the time you send a message and you receive those,
the situation has already changed.
So don't try to do atomics in global memory.
So as a conclusion,
atomics essentially allow creation
of much more sophisticated algorithms
where you can actually tweak the algorithm
to take advantage of atomics in a good way.
You could absolutely do atomics in a bad way.
So make sure you're doing it in a good way.
And the GPU has parallel hardware to execute atomics.
It's on a memory level.
It's covered in the slides that I was showing you before.
You can take a look at that,
but I don't want to dive that deep.
But atomics also force serialization.
So this line here essentially says,
don't forcefully do serialization because you find it easy.
Don't use atomics because you find it easier
to check your algorithm.
Try to optimize your algorithm to do it without atomics,
but if you absolutely need it,
only then do you actually use it.
So that's all for atomics.
Any questions before I switch over to our advanced topics
and cool that part of it?
You, I don't think Project 4 uses atomics,
but if you think of the kernels and stuff,
if you were trying to add all the values,
so at some point you could use atomics
in different algorithms that are similar.
All right, I'm going to switch over.
Make sure, this slide is just really good.
I haven't, I'm trying to find the video for it
so that I can link it.
I'll do that when I am successful in getting that.
All right.
All right, so in advanced topics,
we're going to cover a bunch of topics
like we did in performance lab.
And we're going to walk through all of these one by one.
So first we have what is called CUDA Unified Memory.
And this really is for people
who haven't understood CUDA like you have in this class,
who don't understand the memory management side of things
and allocation, reallocation and stuff like that.
So CUDA Unified Memory is essentially a memory manager.
That's essentially what it does.
All it's doing is that it has two pointers,
one for device and host,
but allows you to use a single pointer for it.
The API to allocate CUDA Unified Memory
is CUDA mallet managed.
Again, memory manager, mallet managed, you get the point.
And that is synchronized using CUDA device synchronized.
So here's a visual overview of what that looks like.
On our CPU, we have system memory.
On the GPU, we have GPU memory.
And this is how all of you have written for so far.
What CUDA Unified Memory does is it makes a virtual memory
that essentially makes it appear to your program
as if you're working with the same memory
on both GPU and CPU.
Okay.
Why is this good or not good?
Yeah.
I can think of a reason it's not good
because you have to use extra resources
to maintain this unified, this virtual memory
that needs more overhead.
Yes, but in certain cases it can be good, that problem,
where you're frequently synchronizing
between CPU and GPU, you can simplify this.
But you can do that with other APIs.
What makes CUDA Unified Memory different from that?
And it can be good and bad in some way.
I'm not saying it's only bad.
Could be good, it could be bad.
Yeah.
So, what this essentially does is,
it's for people who may not be so used to CUDA,
which is not new, it's okay.
This is for, you're in a lab,
you give your co-worker an idea.
Hey, let's try to use CUDA for this.
You're doing all the core memory stuff
and they're writing the program.
This makes it easier for them.
But what it also makes you do is a lot of synchronization.
Okay.
You can't do CUDA memcpy on this.
Or you shouldn't do CUDA memcpy on it.
Okay, because you just get one point
of what's your host point or nothing.
You just get one pointer for it.
So, it's much more explicit to use CUDA memcpy
than it is to use Unified Memory.
So, here's an example of what that looks like.
We have two float pointers, X and Y.
We, just like CUDA malloc, we do CUDA malloc manage.
But now see, we are not doing new float
or something on the host side.
We are only doing malloc manage.
This code is gonna do both the host side
and the device side allocation, all this.
From there, you can do host side stuff using X and Y.
You can also do device side stuff using X and Y.
There's no difference.
And then you do CUDA device synchronize.
The device synchronize will essentially copy host
to device or device to host.
Now, here's the rub, okay?
What happens if you change both the host and the device?
Right?
What happens if you...
Remember, this is asynchronous.
You could be doing stuff here on X and Y.
How do you resolve that?
CUDA doesn't know how to resolve that.
So, that's where the disadvantage starts coming in,
that it's not as explicit as you want it to.
If you are writing a sequential program
that doesn't do any X and Y policy,
sure, you could use it,
but make sure that you're being safe about it.
So, for unified memory,
there's no significant advantage.
There's no hardware advantage on Kepler and Maxwell GPU.
So, this is your six, seven, eight, nine GTX series,
essentially.
From Pascal onwards,
which is the GTX 1080 kind of series onwards,
that's when you get some modern concepts
around managed memory as well,
such as prefetching, page fault handling,
and even simultaneous GPU and access.
So, this is where I was telling,
oh, if GPU and CPU are trying to write it simultaneously,
what happens?
So, on the newer hardware, it can work.
The last place it has a pretty big advantage
is if you're doing out-of-port.
And out-of-port means,
if the memory you need doesn't fit into the GPU's memory.
So, for example, if you have maybe a 4GB GPU,
you have 16GB RAM on the CPU,
maybe 4GB is not enough for whatever algorithm you're doing,
and you need some more space.
You could assign a lot more on the CPU side,
and then have it copy to the GPU on demand.
So, it allows subscribing only on the newer GPUs.
If you try to do it on Kepler and Maxon, this will fail.
Okay.
So, takeaways for CUDA Unified Memory.
It's good for beginners,
wouldn't recommend it for newbies.
You guys know a lot better about that.
It's synchronous.
What that means is anytime you change
which device is writing,
it's gonna synchronize both the CPU and the GPU.
It's gonna make everything hold,
and then only then it'll do the operation
so that it knows it's still atomic.
Good for the new hardware,
but the direct APIs are still the way to go
if you know how to use them.
And then you can write your own memory manager
when, if needed.
You can create your own APIs around it if you want.
So, any questions around Unified Memory?
Yep.
So, I assume it's not the copying memory back and forth.
No, that is exactly what it is.
So, that's a good story.
CUDA Unified Memory was introduced in CUDA 6.5.
Back then, CUDA would make two releases a year,
a 0.0 release and a 0.5 release.
Nowadays, they make a lot fewer
because the SDK has essentially evolved
to a pretty stable point.
So, at that point, I remember I was working on a project,
a medical imaging project
that was working with large images
and small versions of those images.
So, for example, it had a 32 by 32 image
and a corresponding 1024 by 1024 image.
Again, it was doing some bacterial culture analysis
or something on it.
Now, 1024 by 1024 large image is great for GPUs.
You can throw like a thousand of it on GPU
and it'll work really well.
Those tiny 8 by 8, 32 by 32 image,
we asked ourselves, why should we copy this on the GPU?
The CPU is gonna be faster for it.
You know that overhead and copying it to the GPU
and copying it back is not worth it.
So, what we did was we created an asynchronous operation
and I'll talk a little bit more about how you do that
where the CPU was working on the small images
and the GPU was working on the bigger images.
And we needed to know that everything
was synchronized and stuff.
So, as part of that project, we wrote a memory manager
and this was right before CUDA 6.5 came out.
So, CUDA 6.5 comes out and really announces unified memory
and we're like, yeah, we already wrote that.
So, we don't need to use unified memory.
We had our own memory manager for it.
So, yes, under the hood, it's doing pretty much exactly that
with the exceptions of these few things here,
which are, again, you need to know how you're using
your data before you decide, okay, this applies to me.
You don't really get too much advantage
in using unified memory.
The direct API calls will give you more advantages
than this one.
It is easier, but...
Because there's a reason you don't use Java
and you use C++ for performance.
You don't use JavaScript for performance, you use C++.
Just because programming one way is easier
doesn't mean it's the best way to program.
So, that's what you have to remember.
Any other questions on unified?
Leo?
So, since you declared the memory on the host,
I assume the address is like an actual address of the host.
So, you can do that for your...
Yeah, yeah.
It essentially, I don't know for sure,
but what I think this does is on the host,
or at least on the host or device, one of the places,
it creates a pointer to a pointer or some kind of a mapping.
So, the driver essentially knows that,
hey, if I am doing anything with this address,
from this address, go to that address and do it.
Because it's almost impossible to have
the exact same address in both the GPU
and CPU become available.
It's nearly impossible.
So, yes, some kind of a mapping has to happen
under the hood.
Any other questions on this?
Okay.
All right.
So, let's talk about faster memory transfer.
I've said, unified memory is not great.
Okay, how do we do this faster?
And some of this you may have actually picked up
in performance lab.
So, GPUs are useful because of all the compute they have,
all the memory bandwidth they have,
but they're limited in one way, the PCIe memory bandwidth.
Now, of course, this is improving PCIe,
five is out, six is coming, seven is coming and so on.
But a lot of this is still very limited
by what is essentially tens of gigabytes of bandwidth
between the CPU and GPU versus the hundreds of gigabytes
of bandwidth you have on the GPU.
So, for example, on a 1080 Ti, which was a PCIe 3 card,
you had 16 lanes maximum.
And based on that, you would get 16 GB theoretical
copy speed or approximately 13 gigabytes
of realistic copy speed.
Compare that to the 330 global memory bandwidth
that you have, okay?
But if you run your programs and you run your profilers,
what you're actually gonna see is most of your mem copies
between CPU and GPU probably get around
four to six gigabytes a second, okay?
And the performance lab has all of this code.
So if you open performance lab,
you can check how much mem copy speed you're getting, okay?
So ultimately, this bandwidth is 55 times lower
than global memory bandwidth on the GPU,
which is not good, right?
We don't want this to become the bottleneck
and the downside of using GPUs.
So how do we make this at least hit this limit here,
that the theoretical limit that we have, okay?
So one solution is don't use hosted device drivers.
Not really a practical solution, right?
Like there has to be some transfer.
We can't always have random number generation
that is generating all the data on the GPU for free
because compute is free.
So the other solution is optimized,
but how do we optimize that?
We optimize that by reducing the overhead of the copy, okay?
So when you do, let's say any line,
like on the CPU int A equals new or malloc
or whatever your favorite memory allocator is,
what you're telling your operating system to do
is assign pageable memory to your pointer.
Pageable memory essentially means that the memory
can be moved by the operating system
into different locations,
whether that's in hardware or into virtual memory,
page memory, et cetera.
And that's why it's called pageable memory
because there's a hashing mechanism behind it.
The key thing is that you can't do mem copies
from pageable memory.
You can't do mem copies from pageable memory
because there's a certain latency in copying that memory
from CPU to GPU.
And if the operating system changes that in any way,
then you have corrupted memory.
So what we need to do is change the pageable memory
into what is called pin memory.
Pin memory means the operating system can't change it.
The operating system won't change it.
And that's when you can copy it to the GPU.
So essentially what it's doing is
it's taking all the pageable memory you have
copying that, literally copying that in hardware
to a new pin memory location.
And then you copy from the pin memory.
What if you could remove this entire overhead?
What if you could allocate pin memory directly?
So that is done by this form, CUDA malloc host.
CUDA malloc host allocates pin memory on the host side.
And please always check for errors on this.
It can result in failures.
You're free using CUDA free host,
but all the other uses remain the same.
So this is an example of page memory when you use malloc.
If you want to allocate pin memory for that same thing,
you use CUDA malloc host and assign it by.
So kind of like CUDA malloc,
but you're assigning it on the host.
What could be the problem with this?
Why can this result in errors,
especially CUDA malloc host?
Yeah, not enough space could be available
on the host side to do this.
So to compare performance, again,
this is a screenshot of a performance lab
you can go home and run it.
So in this GTX 770 example,
I believe this was on my Intel Signing Bridge,
probably like 4770, so VE1.
So see how pageable transfers have a bandwidth of 4.6.
And then the same transfer using pin memory is 12.
So three times, almost three times faster.
Behind the text is,
is there's another name for pin memory
that let me move this here
so that we can all read it.
I forget the name of that.
All right, it's called page log memory
for obvious reasons that the page of it,
the page of the memory can't be changed essentially.
So concluding on pin memory,
it allows faster memory transfers,
but it's a blocking host allocation,
which means that blocking on the host,
similar to blocking on device,
can mean that all your threads
in the program will get blocked.
Like no new memory or operations can be allocated
or done until there's a lock,
the pin memory is allocated,
and only then can you continue.
Until all the threads pause and the memory is allocated,
other threads won't be able to continue.
So that's a blocking host allocation,
and it will also take longer to do so.
The key thing is that we use it wisely.
One way to put a malicose can fail
if there's not enough memory,
but why am I saying use it wisely
is because the operating system can't move your memory.
How can you get in trouble because of that?
How can you get in trouble if you use pin memory, right?
There's no, like in case you get no new memory,
there's no other way to do it.
That's it.
All right, so you can get in trouble in two ways.
One, you can assign so much pin memory
that the operating system can't do anything about it.
Again, pin memory literally means
I know what I'm doing,
operating system don't move this around and stuff.
Now, let's say I have 16 GB RAM,
I assign 16 GB memory,
the operating system can't assign anything more
and could lead to crashes or hang or anything.
The other side is also true where you assign the memory
and maybe you assign it in the for loop
but you don't free it.
Now it becomes even more important
that you're doing good memory management
and you're freeing it as necessary.
Otherwise you'll just overflow
all of the memory that you have, okay?
So that's pin memory.
We will discuss a couple more advantages
when we discuss dreams later on.
Okay, one more memory thing
and we call that zero copy, okay?
So zero copy is a mechanism in CUDA
that maps your host memory to the device.
And I mean that literally.
You could access the host side RAM
from the GPU over PCIe.
Now, obviously it's gonna be very, very slow, okay?
Compared to the 330 gigabytes
of global memory bandwidth that we have,
if we are accessing that over PCIe
up to 16 gigabytes per second,
that's like 15 times slower.
So obviously it's gonna be slower.
But what it allows you to do,
especially in like machine learning or other things
is where you have those giant kernels or images
that you can't copy onto the GPU,
it still allows you to use your host as a memory bank, okay?
So there isn't, unless,
except for out-of-port situations,
if you're not using very large images
or matrices or other things,
there's no real advantage for most desktop applications.
But I said desktop applications.
What about system on a chip?
What do you notice in this?
This is a conceptual architecture diagram
of a Tegra processor.
What do you notice in this?
Okay, just read out what you're seeing, okay?
And then tell me what I'm looking for.
So there's obviously a big CPU here,
an ARM CPU and a big GPU, right?
Or big is relative to the system on a chip size.
What else do you see?
A bunch of specialized processors, absolutely.
What do you see in this image?
This is a Tegra K1.
Okay.
What do you see in this image
that you are not seeing elsewhere?
Or what are you not seeing in this image
that you may have seen elsewhere?
I'm not sure if this is working.
GPU side of the thing, right?
So what are we looking for here?
Is it the GPU and the CPU are sharing memory?
You're sharing memory?
Thank you.
Yeah.
If I'm looking at this diagram,
do you think they're both using the same DDR7?
This?
Okay, now tell me this.
Can you tell me what the same thing in this image?
The DDR4 here is the memory.
So you're exactly right.
On system on the chip,
there's only one memory.
Okay.
Everything that we've discussed so far
for the past many weeks,
has been the full-side memory and a device-side memory,
and you have to do memcpy between the two, right?
But what happens on the system on a chip
where you literally have the same physical memory?
CUDA programs will still work.
If you take your performance lab
or your ray tracer or something
and put it on a Tegra GPU, it will still work.
It will do your CUDA mallocs and stuff
and it will still work.
But here's where you can take advantage, okay?
So because they have physically unified memory,
that means using our standard pipeline
where we malloc host, malloc device,
CUDA memcpy host to device,
we are actually creating two copies of the physical memory.
Okay?
This is our standard pipeline to the right, right?
Where we initialize and host the device,
copy memory to device and stuff.
That's creating two copies on the same memory.
Okay?
That's where zero copy comes into its element,
where because it has literally the same physical memory,
you can use the same physical memory
for both host and device.
Now you only have one copy.
And there's no PCIe there either.
It's all system on a chip.
You have your memory, your GPU
and your CPU on the same hardware.
So you can use pin memory for this
and there's no unified memory.
There's no, you know, waving your magic wand
creating unified memory.
There's no memcpy and literally there's no gimmicks.
You are literally operating on the same memory
at the same time.
So here's an example of how it works.
The first thing you have to do is set the device flag
that allows you to map host and device.
So that's done by CUDA set device flags,
CUDA device map host.
Okay?
That's just a state flag that you'll set.
On the host side,
you're going to create two pointers in our example.
And then you're going to do CUDA host add.
Okay?
And you're going to do this same thing
that we've done before,
where you give the pointer the size
and then you have to pass this flag,
CUDA host add map.
Okay?
That tells that the memory should be mapped
on the GPU and the CPU.
Okay?
Everybody follow through, any questions?
Okay.
So from there,
what we are going to do is create two device pointers.
I have a question.
It's a dumb question to play.
Would system on a chip be more like a game system
where everything is connected?
Or?
It could be.
But even like, for example,
an Xbox or a PS5 have different system,
different host memory and device memory.
This would be more like your phone,
a Nintendo Switch has a Tegra chip in it.
Your autonomous cars may have.
M1 Macs, yeah, great example.
M1 Macs have unified memory,
although they don't support CUDA,
but they have unified memory.
Yes.
So, okay.
So we do the host,
we do CUDA host add map to initialize all the maps.
Now we need to get the device point.
So from the device point that we do,
we create the variables to store those pointers.
And then we don't do CUDA malloc or anything.
We do CUDA host get device pointer.
See the function.
Host, get device pointer.
And what we're doing there is
we want to write to the device pointer.
Our host pointer is in,
and then the zero is just a flag or an offset.
If you want to do it from the start,
you can do it from the start,
otherwise you can get like an offset pointer as well.
What this does is there's no allocation
or anything happening on the GPU
or access on the same system on the chip.
This is essentially saying,
this is my host pointer,
get a CUDA readable device pointer for the device.
Okay.
Here's the reason you have to think a little bit about this.
All of you may be wondering,
hey, if it's a system on the chip,
why can't I use my host pointer on the device?
Most of the time,
this function will actually put the same host pointer
in the device pointer, most of them,
but it's not guaranteed.
That's why you need to run this function.
There may be times where this could be mapped
into a different pointer address.
And so you just have to make sure
that you are always running this function.
And then you can use the device pointer in the terminal,
but there's no need to copy the out back, right?
There's no CUDA mem copy now.
If you just use H out,
you're getting the memory from the kernel anyway.
So unlike CUDA unified memory,
you would have to have to do a CUDA device synchronizer.
Don't have to do that.
You're getting updated memory by default
because it's all in the same physical address.
And then to free it,
you don't have to free device arrays
because we haven't actually allocated any device arrays.
We just need to free the host.
So that's the only thing you have to do.
So this makes a real difference.
So your kernels will remain the same
because you're still using device pointers.
It changes how you are mapping host and device memory
like you've seen.
No changes how any of the pointers are used
and no overhead of mem copy.
You're not duplicating, you're not synchronizing,
you're not doing any mem copies.
And an example to the right is for transpose,
like we've done in the performance lab.
The standard pipeline,
which is having two copies of memories
and doing CUDA mem copy,
gives transpose bandwidth of three.
And this is comparing to 6.6 on a Teger-K1, okay?
So you get half the bandwidth
and that's pretty obvious, right?
You're doing the mem copies.
But in a zero-copy pipeline, you get 5.8,
which is pretty close to the 6.6.
So that's where you see the performance benefits.
If you're doing any system-on-a-chip kind of things,
if you're using the Tegra chips,
especially in your final project, use zero-copy.
It's gonna give you a huge performance advantage
over standard things.
But also make sure that
if you're writing a portable program
that could be doing a system-on-a-chip
or could be doing desktop,
that you're checking for it
and using the correct pipeline.
You don't wanna be using zero-copy inadvertently
on a desktop application.
You're just gonna kill your performance, okay?
Any questions so far?
I mean, it's probably depending on the application, right?
If you have a mobile phone,
you can't put your desktop chip on it.
So you probably have a smaller chip
that's consuming less power, less resources,
but it's all system-on-a-chip, so it's much more efficient.
So it's what kind of application you're building.
An example of it could be a drone.
Your drone is flying, it's doing image processing,
it's doing collision avoidance.
All of those things are actually happening on the GPU.
All your GPU builders, DJI, Skydio, others,
they all take advantage of Tegra-like chips
that are doing a lot of machine learning on the fly.
And if you have this kind of zero-copy,
all of the images that are coming from the camera
are sitting on the same chip, on the same memory.
And now you can have different applications
on the CPU side and the GPU side,
use the same physical memory
without the overhead of copies.
So you get a really good performance improvement
because of that,
which can hide some of the limited performance
it has because it runs off a battery.
It's not running off an electrical grid.
So that's where you have to differentiate
between mobile devices versus desktop applications.
What other questions do you have?
So let's see streams.
Streams and concurrency, okay?
This is probably the most important performance benefit
you'll get from advanced CUDA topics.
Okay.
So once again, a reminder for our standard CUDA pipeline.
The standard pipeline is your input data comes from the CPU
and goes to the GPU, okay?
You launch a kernel,
you copy the results back from the GPU to the CPU
so that you can do things on the CPU.
And then you repeat this as many times as you need to, okay?
So concurrency for CUDA
is essentially designed for parallelism, right?
It's not just designed for parallelism on the GPU
and within the CUDA threads.
It's designed so that you can have parallelism
in more than one way.
So why should we limit ourselves
to one workflow pipeline,
which is do CPU, do GPU, copy to CPU,
do CPU, then copy to GPU again and stuff like that.
We can do, we want to do more, right?
We want to do more kernel launches.
We want to do multiple mem copies.
We want to do multiple mem copies
from host to device of 64 KB or less.
You want to be able to call different functions
at different times.
So now the need for concurrency becomes important
where you can do concurrent operations from time to time.
And most modern GPUs, except for some of the initial ones,
do support concurrency.
And we'll talk a lot about that today.
So in CUDA, every operation that you do,
whether that's management, mem copy, mem set,
your kernels, all are executed in an order.
And streams are a way for you
to define different orders, essentially,
different sequences.
So in this example that I've shown here,
you have stream A that has command A1, A2, A3,
and you have stream B, command B1, B2, B3, okay?
What do you think is the right order here?
We have two streams that execute A1, A2, A3,
and the second one executes B1, B2, B3.
What do you think are the correct order of execution
in this?
Let's start with the first one on the left.
Is this one the right order of execution?
Yes, no, could be, could not be.
Maybe not, why maybe not?
It looks very serious,
but could it be a valid order of execution?
That's what I'm asking.
Maybe, okay, what about the second one?
Okay, the third one.
What about the third one?
Maybe, okay.
I'm just asking, is it valid?
So I'm not asking what the probability is.
Is it a valid order of execution or not?
What about the last one?
It is?
Maybe.
Yeah, exactly.
So these three are all valid,
but within this,
you're seeing a reorder of A3 before A2
and B3 before B2.
That is not allowed.
You can't reorder within a stream,
but you can reorder different streams, okay?
So that order of execution will have to be maintained.
What about now?
Let's say you have two streams on your GPU,
which one of these is valid?
Both of them are valid,
because as long as you're maintaining
the sequence of our execution within your stream,
you're good.
You can jump them around, no problem, okay?
So all CUDA operations actually have a stream.
Even though you may not have used the API so far,
all CUDA operations are streamed.
Both there's async host to device
and device to device memcpy,
as well as kernel launches, they're all streamed.
The condition on the memcpy is that
the async memcpy will always have to be pinned,
because you can't do async
and then have pageable memory being copied
into pin memory and such.
So async operations will always require pin memory.
So the stream that all of you have been using so far
is called the default stream.
Also stream zero for most of the time, okay?
So if you don't specify any stream,
all your operations go into the default stream.
And the default stream is special
because it's always synchronous to the GPU, okay?
All the operations are happening sequentially
and synchronous in the GPU.
You may not, you haven't seen it,
that's why you won't notice it,
because synchronous is like the safe way of operating.
So essentially, if an operation is launched on the GPU,
operation can be a memcpy, a kernel or anything,
then all previous GPU operations
that you may have launched before,
other kernels, other memcpys will have to finish,
only then can you start the new operation.
And you can sync all of those operations
using CUDA device synchronize, okay?
In CUDA 7, just as a note,
you can have different default streams for different threads.
This wasn't possible before that, okay?
All right, so let's take a look
at how we create, destroy, use streams, actually.
So the first thing to note is this CUDA StreamT object.
Like other CUDA objects,
this is a struct that you can create
using CUDA StreamCreate, pass the address,
and you'll get the result back.
Result is an error,
but the stream ID is actually stored in stream one here, okay?
To destroy the stream, you do the same thing,
except you call CUDAStreamDestroy, all right?
Now let's take a look at the memcpy example.
So the function here is called a CUDA memcpy async.
Anytime you do an asynchronous operation,
you'll see the suffix here, that is async, okay?
And it needs pin memory as a reminder.
So what you're gonna do now
is do everything that you were doing same before,
so your destination, your source, your bind signs,
and which direction you're copying it in,
host to device, device to host,
but now you add one more operator,
one more parameter, which is your stream ID, okay?
Because you haven't been using it so far,
it's always the default stream, stream zero,
that goes in there.
But if you are trying to create streams,
you're gonna put a stream ID in there, okay?
If, oh, one caveat here,
if by mistake you use pageable memory in this,
it will just become CUDA memcpy synchronous,
which is the default memcpy.
It'll just call it in the backend as a regular memcpy.
For kernels, again, all the kernels you've written so far
get launched on the default stream zero.
Kernels are always asynchronous,
so there's no async suffix
that you need to add to your kernel.
But what you need to do is now add a fourth parameter,
we need a triple tag.
So we started off 565 with just block and thread,
then we added shared memory for block
when we were looking at shared memory and performance lab.
Now we are adding a fourth parameter, which is stream.
So if you don't pass stream, it's on stream zero.
If you pass the stream,
then it will run asynchronously to other kernel.
If you don't have shared memory, just put zero in there, okay?
Any questions on this?
We'll see in a little bit
about how these actually become parallel,
but just wanna make sure that all of you understand
how streams get used in your operations.
Okay.
All right.
So let's take a look at an example.
So let's say we have two streams,
which I'm gonna create like this.
So I'm gonna create an array of streams
and then put the stream IDs within those, okay?
Then down here, I'm just gonna do my whole style
malicose, which is as a reminder, allocating pin memory.
I'm not doing new here.
I'm not doing host pointer new equals something.
I'm doing put a malicose, okay?
And then the other thing here is allocating
two times pin memory in a single call,
because you don't actually need to separate it out.
You can just create two pointers for hosts
for two different streams.
That's entirely possible.
You don't need to do two put a malicose calls
is essentially what I'm getting at.
Okay.
So here's one way to do a stream operation.
And this is a very simple example.
You can do this in very different ways.
You're gonna call your put a malicose async
pass the device and host pointers here,
copy host to device and the stream parameter.
Then you call your kernel,
whatever the block sizes might be.
We don't use shared memory.
So we put zero and then you call the stream.
While this kernel have non launching an async kernel,
okay?
This you can write CPU code here that executes
while that kernel is executing.
And then,
then this put a memcpy async operation happens.
That's copying the device to host back, okay?
So what's actually happening is that,
so what's actually happening here
is that for these three calls,
put a memcpy, kernel and put a memcpy again here.
Those three operations within the stream,
remember how we had A1, A2, A3?
So this is A1, this is A2, this is A3.
For the next iteration,
because the stream of I will change,
these become B1, B2, B3, okay?
Now, A1 versus or in the A operations
and the B operations can happen in any order.
But within A, A1 has to happen before A2, before A3.
So you can call your kernel,
do a bunch of CPU code and come here on the host.
The host can be like, okay,
I need to execute a put a memcpy async.
But the CUDA driver will essentially tell you,
hey, no wait, my kernel is not done.
You need to wait for the kernel.
And then the host will wait here.
So that's what happens.
Okay, and then finally,
after you're done with all of your stream,
you should destroy the stream as well, okay?
So the other thing to note is
like we have CUDA device interface,
CUDA device synchronize will synchronize all the streams.
It will wait for all the stream,
all the operations and all the streams to execute, okay?
Which is like synchronize the whole GPU.
However, there may be times
when we only need to synchronize the stream.
We may need to be like, okay,
all the stream operations foster here.
So for that, we use CUDA stream synchronize.
We don't use CUDA device synchronize,
we use CUDA stream synchronize for that.
And there are a few different ways you can synchronize.
There's four different ways.
CUDA device synchronize synchronizes all the commands
from all streams, okay?
All of them need to be completed
until you can move to the next step.
That's first.
CUDA thread synchronize is all the commands
from all the streams issued in that thread
need to be synchronized, okay?
So you're gonna have multiple CPU threads
making calls to CUDA,
but the thread synchronize means only those calls
from that thread need to be completed.
Other threads can keep doing whatever they want.
Stream synchronize means you block
until all the commands in the stream are finished.
Other streams, other threads
could be doing whatever they want.
But within that stream,
even if it's assigned from different threads,
we'll need to finish.
The final one is CUDA event synchronize,
which we haven't seen so far,
but we have seen events.
We've seen events in our performance lab
where I use them for marking our ranges in the profile.
You can do an event synchronize,
which means you can have a start event and a stop event.
And if you do an event synchronize,
then all the commands that were issued
between those two events will need to finish.
So there are four ways to synchronize in CUDA.
So now with events, those can be used to,
those can be added to streams to monitor device progress.
You can check on whether an event has finished
or not finished and stuff,
because you can assign events to stream too.
So here's an example of that.
And very similar to performance lab,
you can create your two events using these two lines,
event create using the CUDA event.
You can do an event record.
So now you're saying, hey, event get activated, okay?
And you're giving it a start and a stream.
And then you can stop the event
and then do a synchronize to ensure that all the stuff
between those two is done.
And then CUDA event synchronize
will essentially stop all of those.
Or wait until all of those are completed.
Once this is done, you can actually use start and stop
to find how much time was used asynchronously
for all of those events to happen.
Any questions on this?
Any questions on how events are used?
So once again, you create those two events,
record events before and after each stream is assigned.
And then you delay any additional commands
until all of the work between those two streams is completed.
And then you can check the performance,
how much time it took here.
So any questions on this?
No, everybody clear with events?
Okay, so what's wrong with this?
Okay.
What might be wrong with this?
So here's the mistake.
While this may appear innocuous to all of you
and you may have done this in various classes.
The first memory property is synchronous on the GPU.
You see how we haven't used CUDA memory property async?
The CUDA memory property is always synchronous on the CPU.
And the CPU waits for it to finish.
So this is perfectly safe.
The kernel launch is asynchronous on the CPU.
And while it executes on GPU,
there's actually no way for the CPU to wait for it.
Okay, so the CPU, as soon as it says,
hey, GPU, go work on this kernel,
it can go to the next step.
It doesn't care, right?
There's nothing more for it to do at that line.
There's no return statement to wait for, okay?
So we can go to the next line here on the CPU.
So once the CPU is done here,
the CPU goes and is like, okay, put a mem copy,
execute a copy for me to get my memory back.
And this kind of operation can lead to race conditions.
So when you have the CPU not executing the mem copy,
it's just waiting for this kernel to finish.
So the CPU is just waiting, idling, and not doing anything.
Because all of this is on the default stream, okay?
Now, what about this?
What might happen here?
Right, so here, what happens is CPU does the mem copy,
CPU comes to the kernel,
CPU launches the kernel on the GPU,
and now the CPU can be like,
hey, but while you're running,
let me do some of my own work
before I have to do the mem copy back.
So you actually use the CPU actively
while the GPU is also executing.
So remember when I was mentioning
that we had those big images and those small images?
That's exactly what we did.
We said, hey, GPU, go work on the big images.
The CPU was working on the small images
while those kernels were working on the big GPUs.
So now you have essentially the GPU doing work
and the CPU doing work at the same time.
So you're taking advantage
of all your resources concurrently.
So this is known as either compute-compute overlap
or compute-copy overlap, okay?
So this is essentially CPU and GPU overlap,
where both devices are doing compute.
Why should we stop there?
Why not even overlap our memory copies
and our compute, right?
So CUDA allows your kernels and your mem copy to overlap.
We saw CUDA mem copy async,
which does asynchronous mem copies.
We know that we can assign streams to kernels
and we can do mem copy back using kernels, right?
So if our mem copies and kernels are on different streams,
which we know can be executed in different orders,
we can do different mem copies
and different kernels at the same time.
So depending on your GPU architecture,
you can actually be running 16 concurrent kernels
at the same time, not just one.
You can run 16 concurrent kernels at the same time.
And again, depending on your engine,
you can run one mem copy in each direction.
So you can be running one copy to device
and one copy from device at the same time.
And one easy way to check this is,
let me bring up Visual Studio.
I think Visual Studio removed it.
So let me check the prompt.
So here, what I've done is on my command prompt,
I've run a command called NVIDIA SMI,
but dash Q means query, dash A means all, okay?
So if you just run NVIDIA SMI,
you'll get something like this,
which shows you all the GPU processes that are running.
I have my Epic Games launcher here
because I do stuff with Unreal.
So that's what's showing here.
If I was running a CUDA program,
that would show you that as well.
Okay, now to the part where I want to show.
Of course, I have a 3050 Ti in my laptop.
It's an Ampere architecture GPU.
It's, oops, it has a PCIe 4 bus,
so you can see that here.
But what I'm really looking for
is how many async engines I have.
Let's see, I'm not entirely sure if this will show,
but I'm going to check.
Clocks, application, clocks.
No, I don't think it's showing here.
Let's see, let's open Visual Studio.
Before you could, before Visual Studio allowed you to do
Nsight's GPU info without having to launch a program,
but I think they changed it now.
There's no like Windows system tools now,
so I may need to open something.
So let me open, let me go to the start page.
Start window, we're going to open performance lab.
Let's do transport, well, let me, we can do a deduction.
So now if I do Nsight start CUDA debugging,
hopefully I put a breakpoint.
So let me put a breakpoint.
There, Nsight start CUDA debugging.
Nsight now in Windows is available,
and you can go into resources, which gives you CUDA device.
So now the first thing you see, conveniently for us,
is async engine count.
Async engine count tells you how many asynchronous things
your GPU can execute at once.
So that's the first thing.
And then there should be one more, which is,
if you take a look here,
we can search for async.
So you might also need to check for things like this,
can map host memory, which is, as we discussed before,
for mapping host and device memory.
Can you stream memory operations?
So this is false, so you can't necessarily stream
from one to the other.
This is not the streams that we are talking about,
by the way, so just manage memory is true.
So it supports our manage memory thing
that we spoke about earlier, using unified memory.
But no, it's not showing how many mem copies
it can do at the same time.
So maybe I'll check that and post it in our discussion
about which flag it is.
Let me exit this.
I took the next slide.
So, okay.
So we saw this before, right?
This kind of code, we saw it in our previous example
where I was showing how asynchronous operations
can be done.
Now, here's my question, okay?
This seems pretty good, right?
Like we have n streams, we're creating some offsets.
So for example, an easy way to think about it is transpose.
Let's assume you have a very, very, very big matrix, okay?
That you may or may not want to run in one turn.
You may want to break it up, so you can transpose.
You can transpose different parts of the matrix
at different times.
So let's say we have n streams.
We do put a mem copy async compose to device
asynchronously.
Launch the kernel view to do that.
And then the copy the result back, okay?
Is this efficient?
Now you have to think of compute copy overlap.
Both things, yes.
Why is this either efficient or not efficient?
That's the only thing I think, right?
So it should be efficient.
Different streams doing different things.
Async compose starts inside of the button.
Okay, and each time it's going to give a different stream ID.
No, because these are all async commands,
the CPU can be like, okay, I've launched uasync,
I've launched uasync.
Let me go iterate on the next loop.
CPU doesn't have to wait.
From a GPU perspective, is this efficient?
The CPU is fine.
So here's the profile of new focus.
See how this part that I'm marking,
I'm just using NVVP, NVIDIA Visual Profile Log.
You should have it installed.
It's a very old application that I've been around
from like CUDA 3 or 4 or something.
So definitely check it out.
So here's what's happening.
This sliver is essentially all of this space.
There's a huge CUDA memcpy runtime API.
So this row is runtime API,
but this is essentially what is happening here.
You're doing CUDA host to device kernel
and then host to device back.
So you have different streams of host to device,
device to host, and compute,
and it's doing it on different channels.
This is exactly what I'm trying to highlight,
that while this kernel only takes this much time,
this memcpy is essentially waiting from here to here,
because it's still in the stream.
So you don't necessarily get that concurrency.
Now in basic concurrency,
which is what that call loop was,
where we had some ASAP.
Now you get some concurrency.
So let's see how this is looking.
This is a full global view.
This is for streams, those streams.
So in each stream,
we know that we have to do host to device,
we have to do a kernel,
and then we have to do a device to host.
See how we are breaking it up.
Here we had these large memcpys,
here we have broken up the problem into smaller.
So we do a smaller memcpy,
we run the kernel on it,
and then we run the memcpy back.
And we are getting this waterfall model,
which has some possibility of, say, async,
but not really.
And this could be a factor of my GPU as well.
So I'll be clear about that.
This waterfall model,
because I may not have an async engine,
is being a waterfall model, okay?
I may not have the ability to do two memcpys
at the same time.
That's why this is waiting, okay?
The other thing I want to point out is,
instead of having CUDA memcpy, a kernel launch,
and a CUDA memcpy again,
see how there's a few lines here,
and then everything is CUDA device-in-place.
Why?
Because all of these are asynchronous here.
So from a CPU perspective,
the CPU has done all its work,
and it's now waiting at CUDA device-in-place.
That's where the CPU is gone.
This is the CPU view, okay?
This is the GPU view,
where you have all of these async operations happening,
and only when these operations are all done
does the CPU get its control back, okay?
So now this is a GTX 950, no asynchronous engines.
This is a GTX 1080 Ti.
Now look at what we are seeing, okay?
We see on the CPU sides,
we still see the same CUDA device-in-place,
no difference whatsoever.
But look at what's happening here.
We have, on the global view,
or let's do the stream view first.
For stream 14, which is the first stream that we launched,
we do a memcpy, the blue is the kernel,
but as soon as the kernel launches,
so I put my finger there so you can see,
as soon as the kernel launches,
there's a host device happening on the next stream.
Now we are getting memcpy on the computer overlap.
While this kernel is running,
we've already started the second computer.
While this copy is happening,
and the kernel finishes,
we start device-to-host memcpy.
So now we have two memcpys running,
and you could potentially,
if you had a third stream as well, not in this program,
but if you had a third stream that was executing a kernel,
that would have been executing as well.
So now this chart and this chart
are running the same program, there's no difference.
The difference is in the GPU and what it's capable of
and how much concurrency it's capable of.
So now you get this different kind of waterfall model,
and what does this remind us of?
Where did we see something like this before?
Exactly, so take warp scheduling
and put it on the whole GPU
where you're essentially hiding all the latency
for all the compute behind memcpys.
So your computer essentially is completely free of this.
So you are not paying more,
if you look at all the way from here to here,
all the expense is in memcpys.
The kernels are all hidden.
So this is what is called compute-copy overlap, okay?
Now I'll ask the question again,
is this efficient on the GPU?
Yes, no, maybe?
It looks efficient.
Is it better than before?
Is it better than, is it better than this synchronous query?
Yeah, no concurrency, definitely better.
Can we improve this?
By now, all of you should know
when I ask that question, the answer is yes.
Okay, so that is what we'll call basic memcpy.
What we've essentially done is taken the problem
and divided it into different parts.
The problem we have now
is that we're still dependent on copy-compute-copy.
So this is still copy-compute-copy, right?
So how can we improve that a little bit more?
Even though all our operations are async
with respect to the CPU, right?
The CPU was like launched everything and synchronized.
Everything is asynchronous to the GPU.
The compute-copy overlap isn't as good as it can be, okay?
There's an enormous weight there.
So how do we fix this?
What if we do this, okay?
So let me come back here and show this.
What I'm talking about is that all the compute
on all the streams depend on the memcpy to happen first.
On that stream.
Without the memcpy happening
before the kernel-to-kernel panel.
And the memcpy here is launched
after all memcpy two-device kernel and two-host
from the previous stream.
Although it's not dependent,
that's how the CPU is launching it, okay?
So we want to change that.
So here's version two of our code, okay?
And it does the exact same thing.
Instead of doing it in one for loop each time,
what if we change it to do all the device
to host memcpy first, all the kernel launches second,
and then all the kernel launches to copy back third.
Now, from the CPU side, still everything is async.
From the GPU side, the order doesn't change.
Because remember, as long as we have that A1, A2, A3, A4,
it doesn't matter that we launch one memcpy async
on stream one, one memcpy on stream two,
stream three, and so on.
And then we come to kernel and launch kernel on stream one,
kernel on stream two, kernel on stream three.
Doesn't matter at all.
It's just within the stream, it has to be continuous.
So here's a better view of it.
So this is, again, on a 950M,
no change in hardware where we had,
let me go back to show you,
that we had this kind of view,
where we had memcpy, kernel memcpy, right?
And then you had memcpy, kernel memcpy.
Let's take a look at what a new structure looks like.
So now look at this.
You have memcpy, kernel memcpy,
kernel memcpy, kernel memcpy,
even though this device has only one async engine.
So now you get this kind of kernel.
Now we come back here.
Why does it not happen here?
Same hardware, right?
Why do we not get that kernel memcpy?
Because, right, when this kernel finishes,
this memcpy starts.
And this memcpy was launched afterwards.
So you're not getting that CPU async
that is translating to the GPU.
So if you change how your for loops are structured
and how your streams are launched,
you will get better memcpy.
So you get the kernel, memcpy, kernel.
Now you get other memcpy, kernel.
But now, because all the time,
the host to device memcpy is gonna happen first,
this stream's device to host memcpy
has to wait until all of this is done, which is fine.
We still get the compute copy overlap,
but we just have to wait for it to come back,
for the control to come back.
Okay?
Now, what happens on a 1080 Ti
where you have two memcpy?
So now this is a similar view, not too different,
but take a look at how this is structured again.
So you have host to device, device to host, and kernel.
And this is running a lot better as well.
Visually, you won't see too much difference in this
because this already had two async engines.
Okay.
So now by breaking that problem down into different streams,
but also how we launch those streams,
we have proper concurrency.
We have our GPU concurrency
where everything is running in parallel.
You're getting all the memory bandwidth
and stuff like that.
But you now also have host to device memcpy
where you could be, for example, in your path tracer,
it's entirely possible for you to launch the next frame
of your path tracer
while you're copying the old frame back, technically.
Okay?
So just stuff like that.
You could have two buffers.
For example, where did you do ping-ponging?
You did ping-ponging in Boids, right?
You could do ping-ponging like this
where you have different streams running different frames.
So those are the kinds of ideas here.
Of course, you get much better performance
from a standard pipeline,
but also remember that not one size fits all.
You can't just be like,
hey, I'm gonna take my reduction and apply streams to it.
No, no, no.
Think carefully about what you want to do.
And the streams are there for your benefits,
but you have to tune your algorithm
so that it works for streams as well.
Okay?
Any questions on this?
We are at the end of streams.
I want to make sure I take any questions and answer stuff.
If you're doing a final project using CUDA,
I expect you to use streams.
All right.
Any questions?
Yeah, Tom?
You went to the slide a few days ago.
This?
Yeah, yeah.
So why wouldn't some copy pose a device
that overlaps?
I've seen it.
It has two ways in it.
So, okay.
So let me show you what I was talking about.
Maybe it's not that obvious as I would expect.
So look at this.
You have the host memcpy,
device to host memcpy is happening here.
You have the kernel happening at the same time,
and you have host to device happening.
So this is happening both in the basic version
of this code,
this code here.
So this allows you to do this as well.
So with one mem is for one async engine,
you don't get that.
But with two async engines,
you do have device to host memcpy kernel
and host to device memcpy running at the same time.
When you come to our new method, this method,
even with one async engine, you get the benefit.
But with two async engines,
you are already getting the benefit from the code.
So this is not going to change too much.
There might be some optimizations GPU does,
but from a profiler view, it may not change that.
It really depends on how many async engines you have
that are going to determine what kind of optimization
you may need to make on your CPU side.
Any other questions?
All right.
So in that case, let's take a break.
It is almost seven.
So let's come back at seven, five,
and then we'll do some last parts
of advanced CUDA stuff before we end.
Okay.
I think it's like two minutes ago.
All right.
Okay.
All right, let's get restarted
and hopefully we'll be able to finish this part of it
by in maybe 20, 30 minutes and you'll be on your way.
Okay.
So the next part we are going to cover
is called what functions.
Okay.
So as a reminder,
if we are sharing information within a block,
what are the ways to do that right now?
What are the ways that we've covered so far?
To share information within a block between sites.
Shared memory.
What is the other one?
Global memory.
You can, not that I recommend it,
but you could use that if you wanted to.
Okay.
But actually there's one more.
It's called what functions.
And it was introduced after Kepler
and it's essentially a what level interchange
of instructions where you can share registers
with other threads.
Okay.
And remember, this is something I've never said before.
Share registers and information with other threads.
Okay.
So let's see how that works.
There are a few different types of what functions.
So let's go through all of them.
The first one is called what vote.
Okay.
And elections are coming up.
Probably some of you are going to vote.
So this is essentially what is known as a broadcast
and reduce function,
where all the threads give their condition or predicate,
essentially as it's called.
And then there are three types of things you can do.
You can do all, which means are all the threads true?
You can do any, is any thread true?
And then you can do a ballot.
And I'll come to ballot in a little bit.
Okay.
So let's start with all, probably the most important.
And remember, this is happening inside a kernel per thread.
Okay.
But here's what's happening.
So this line, in result, all at a predicate,
is local to the thread.
Okay.
So here are two examples.
In result, all,
and IDX.X equals one.
What do you think the result of that is called?
False?
False always?
Like this one is 233 by 233 by 245.
Warp size could be anything.
Warp size is always done.
Yeah.
This, again, remember, this is in the warp.
It's not per block.
It's per warp.
So is this always false?
So, okay.
Let's break it down.
Let's take 1D blocks.
Okay.
Then I, let's take 1D blocks from zero to 1024,
or zero to 512.
It doesn't really matter.
Is this true for any warp?
No.
Okay.
Let's take 2D blocks.
Let's take 16 by 16, or 32 by 32.
Whatever your preference is.
Is this true for any warp in a 2D block?
That all of the threads should be per IDX.X equals one.
No, right?
What about this?
Let me take, what's the IDX?
Yeah.
Okay.
What about this?
Oh, sorry.
I'm sure none of you have ever given blocks this way.
So I have one, 512 comma one.
Will it be true for any of them?
Yeah.
But that IDX.X equals one?
What happens if this is zero?
Oh.
If this is zero, that becomes true.
Okay.
If our block configuration is that,
and this is that IDX.X equals zero, then this is true.
That's the only condition I know is this is true.
Otherwise, it's false.
Okay.
R.
R is one index.
I hate those lines.
I hate them.
So, I hate one index.
Yeah.
Zero.
Everything starts with zero.
Okay.
The second one.
In result, all thread IDX.X greater than 60.
What about this line?
Let's start with one deep block again.
Let's say we are going from zero to 512.
For the first one, all,
what happens?
True or false?
The IDX.X greater than 60?
False.
Second one.
33, 32 to 63.
False.
What about the third one?
64 to 95.
True, because they're all index.
Okay.
So, all of you get this.
What about this?
Now we have, instead of doing all, we are doing any.
Let's take one deep, one deep blocks.
Any of this true?
Which one?
Or all of them?
One deep, one deep block.
Only the first one.
No other words will have this.
What about two deep?
Maybe 16 by 16.
16 by 16, how many words will have this true?
All of them.
All the words will have it.
Yeah.
Because all the words will have at least two rows, right?
So one row of Y, another row of Y.
You have 32 threads.
So one row of Y has 16, so you get 32.
So each of them will at least have one pair.
What about this?
One deep, in this case.
Yeah, first one is gonna be false,
and then the rest will be true.
What about two deep?
Let's say 32 by 32.
Is this true or is this false?
In a 32 by 32 case.
All these ones, thread IDs will never go to 16.
Now, here's a different one.
64 by eight.
If you have a 64 by eight block, what happens to this?
Other than the first one per row, right?
So you have 64 by eight.
The first one is gonna be zero to 31, zero.
The second one is gonna be 32 to 63, zero, right?
So that is gonna have this true.
Same zero to 31, comma, one, which is false.
Then the second one will be 32 to 63, comma, one.
And that'll be true.
So again, you don't have to just put threadIDx.x.
Yeah, I just put it there for exercise.
You can literally put any condition here if you want.
Where can this and this...
Any ideas?
You can kind of check if all the threads are active
or not, for example.
For example, all I can tell you are all my threads active.
Maybe do something then.
And you can tell you,
oh, there's only one thread in my warp active.
You know?
I can remember, I told you,
if you have 32 threads in a warp,
all 32 will stay active or not active, right?
If in our performance lab,
we saw how we can exit warps early,
all the threads are not active,
exit warps early, all the threads are done.
If only one thread is doing stuff,
annoyingly staying around,
we might just be like,
no, exit, I don't really care about the other thread.
In certain algorithms, you can do that.
Yes, absolutely.
So let's take a look at our last warp warp,
which is Barrett, okay?
So in Barrett, remember,
there's a neat thing about this.
You have 32 threads for warp.
How many bits does an int have,
int on an unsigned int?
32, right?
Oh, what you can do is,
instead of just getting the result from all of these,
you can share information between all the threads
by doing a Barrett where each thread warps
and the result is stored either yes or no,
true or false, within an unsigned int.
So what we're essentially doing is,
if your Barrett here is,
let's say Barrett of threadIdx.x equals one,
only the threadIdx.x equals one bit is going to be true.
All the rest are going to be false, right?
So you're essentially voting.
And then if you have something like this
where threadIdx.x warp two,
where you're checking even or odd thread IDs,
then you'll get alternate numbers.
Now, what you can then do with this
is a few different things, okay?
Here are a few crazy ideas that you can do with this.
You can count how many bits are true or false
by checking the number or doing XOR and XOR not,
you can check how many bits are true.
Like I was mentioning before,
if you wanted to see how many threads are active,
you can do this and check how many threads
are active within your warp.
You can also, for example, in your path tracer,
check what type of materials things are in your warp, right?
You can, if you wanted to, you can see is material A,
and then you can do a balance within the warp
to see how much divergence you're going to have.
You can also do in-warp reduction with this.
If you wanted to do,
remember how we had the warp shuffle, I think,
back in performance lab,
you can do that with this to count.
So this becomes really useful in understanding
how your warp is operating, okay?
So warp-warp then essentially allows
removing branch divergence like was suggested,
and it reduces dependency on shared memory
because everything is happening in registers.
You're not necessarily sharing registers,
but you're sharing information about registers,
and that is going to all the other threads.
Inactive return threads always return zero,
so they don't participate in it.
And so with CUDA 9, there were a few changes here,
so they added a mask and stuff in that.
So that you can read in the programming guide for CUDA.
Okay.
The last thing we are going to cover today
is called shuffle.
Again, this works on a warp as well.
So shuffle allows you, as we were doing in warp-warp,
we were sharing information about the register.
We were sharing whether it's true or false.
Shuffle actually allows you to share values
between threads, okay?
Other threads can essentially read registers
without using shared memory,
and it's all a single instruction.
There are four types of shuffle.
You can shuffle indexed,
where you're shuffling based on some index value,
like in an array.
You can do shift-right, also called up.
You can shift-left, also called down.
And then you can shift-butterfly,
where you're exchanging.
Okay.
So let's take a look at this.
So for index-shuffle,
what we have is this function here,
which is shuffle.
You've given your variable.
You've given your source name.
Again, remember where we heard lane from.
It's in the debugger, right?
When we say lane, we mean on the hardware level.
So this is lane of the warp.
So you go from zero to 31 only.
There's no 32nd name.
And then you give your warp size,
which is always 32 in our case, okay?
So here's what happens.
If source name is less than width,
then source name is always 32.
It doesn't work to wrap around.
If width is not equal to warp size,
then shuffle behaves as a subset.
So you can actually shuffle
only between like 16 threads, for example.
You don't have to go all the way to 32.
If a source name is inactive,
means it may have returned already,
then the value is undefined.
Don't do that, okay?
Check your stuff.
And if all of these conditions are done,
then the return value is a copy.
Remember, copy, not the exact variable
of the value and source name.
So you're giving, let's say,
let's say you have int t equals thread ID x.x.
You want to get another thread ID.
You would put t here.
You would put the source name of whichever thread you want.
And that lane's value comes back here as a copy, okay?
So let's look at an example.
If we have warp source name,
and I'm doing an example of 16 threads
just because it's convenient in PowerPoint.
This is my source name value.
It's some jumbled value here
based on my randomness that I wanted to have.
It's really odd numbers in that area, okay?
What's happening is if we do t var of source name,
okay, that's what that is.
Then what we are essentially doing for thread zero,
the value in t should be the value of var in lane 15.
Okay, you understand that?
t equals var of source name.
So 15 is here, var is p, so we bring p here.
And similarly, and n is from index 13 and so on and so on.
You can have whatever function or distribution
you want for source name, depending on your algorithm,
but you can mix and read values from different threads
using shuffle, okay?
Any questions on this?
Okay, so, and then there's shuffler
where you have not index,
but you're essentially moving all the values
by some index.
So in this case, you would have the lane ID,
and then you would give your delta.
Delta is by how many you move.
In this case, you're moving by five.
For anything below five, no change happens, okay?
T doesn't change.
But after five, then we start reading the value problem.
So it's shuffling the values up.
There's no circular shuffle here, okay?
Similarly, you can shuffle down, which is the reverse.
And the last values in this case don't shuffle.
They don't circle, again, not circular.
I should have edited that, but it's not circular.
Maybe I should fix the slides.
Okay, any questions on shuffle up and shuffle down?
All right.
The last one is the more powerful one.
It's called shuffle XOR, okay?
I don't know about shuffle up and shuffle down.
I haven't thought about it.
I haven't used it.
Shuffle XOR, definitely.
Yeah, so I don't have any more things.
I'm pretty sure somebody's used it.
I just haven't, so I don't remember.
Okay, so now shuffle XOR is pretty interesting
because what you're doing is now you're copying
from a link on a bitwise operation of your own link, okay?
So it's essentially like an exchange,
but it doesn't have to be two-way.
It can be a one-way exchange as well.
And one of the ways to do this is based on bits
that are flipped, okay?
So the API here is you give your variable
that you want to shuffle.
You give the lane mask and the bit that's flipped.
For which we'll just assume it's 32 for now,
or 16 in my next example.
But here's what it means.
The target lane is the XOR version of lane ID
and lane mask, okay?
There's not and or or, it's XOR, okay?
Remember that.
So there's always going to be a target lane
that is not zero or one.
The result then is VAR of target lane, okay?
Let's take a look at an example, okay?
So we said P equals VAR of mark and lane ID is XOR, right?
Zero and one, what is the XOR?
One.
So the XOR is one, T of one is B, right?
Let's come here.
One and one XOR is zero.
So T becomes A, it's zero.
All right, let's come here.
Now remember, these are two and three, not zero and mark.
So let's come here.
Two XORed with one is T.
So I'll do bitwise operations here.
So two is one, zero, and one is zero, one.
XOR is one, one, which is three, right?
So you get these two swap.
So the three and XOR one, so if I switch that here,
this becomes one, this becomes zero.
So now you get C2.
And so this is essentially, you compute the mask
and then you get the result back.
So this is a very, very quick way
to get neighboring values, as an example.
Yes, so the mask can be a full integer.
I'll just use one for convenience.
You can have a full integer.
So, but I'm doing the same for...
No, no, not at all.
Again, those are just, so no, it doesn't have to be.
I just made it simple as an example.
So I have more examples here.
So again, this is now mask one, one, one, one,
two, two, two, two, four, four, four, four, okay?
So this is how you would do other things.
The reason I selected the specific order,
what does it look like?
Why do you think I picked the specific order?
They're not switching between labels, right?
This is switching between labels, for sure.
Or what does that remind you of?
Can, yeah, you're on the right path.
So you can decide for this on your own.
But what I want to say is,
don't think of it as individual bits.
Think of it as XOR of integers.
That's the most important thing, okay?
So where is this useful?
Remember this?
Okay, remember this crazy code that we wrote?
So now, this whole thing in all of these instructions
can actually be done with Shuffle.
So what you essentially can do is
share memory of thread ID X.
You can do this, I'd call the same thread on it.
But the same thing with Shuffle.
We can say X equals Shuffle,
X name ID, what does it do?
And then you're gonna get that information back in X,
and then you can add it in that register.
If you want to do it without the same thread,
then without memory, then you can use something like that.
So trust me, this works.
If I take the example,
if I try to explain that, it'll take me 20 minutes,
but trust me that it works.
And this results in a pretty significant
performance improvement.
Our shared memory and shared memory unsafe.
So this implementation that we have here
is shared memory unsafe,
where we're using all the threads, okay?
So shared memory is this part.
Shared memory unsafe is much faster.
But using Shuffle, it's a lot faster.
Because you're sharing that information
through registers and adding it a lot faster.
You don't even have to go to shared memory
or using registers.
That's why it's faster.
And also shared memory doesn't use
any shared memory per block.
So you lose that resource requirement.
So because of that,
this Shuffle way of doing our last warp reduction
will always be faster than shared memory.
It's also safer because we don't have to use
volatile anymore.
And we also don't have to using threads.
And not having that shared memory makes it better.
So let's see how we can implement that.
Now I said I want to explain it in that slide,
but I haven't.
So we can do warp reduce using Shuffle XOR
by doing this, okay?
So sum plus equals Shuffle XOR of 16.
And then the second iteration,
we will do sum plus Shuffle XOR of eight.
And the reason this works is something like this.
Now, our warp size is 32.
I can't put everything in the PowerPoint,
so I'll put it to 16.
Shuffle XOR value of eight,
does all of these registers come here?
If you're at home, you do Shuffle XOR of zero and eight.
XOR of zero and eight is eight.
And you get here.
XOR of eight and one is nine.
So you get the next value.
XOR of eight and two is actually 10.
So you kind of get this additive mechanism
that you get here.
Then you get four.
Shuffle XOR of four.
And you bring those elements here.
So now you're not even using shared memory.
You're still registered.
So the time you were taking in shared memory
that was two or four cycles is registered as one cycle.
So it's a lot faster.
And same as before,
we don't really care about this memory anymore.
So that still applies.
We don't care about that.
We can overwrite it, no problem.
So by doing this, Shuffle XOR any of these,
what's actually happening is these four values come here,
but also these four values go here.
That's happening.
I haven't drawn it here, but that's actually happening,
but we don't really care about that.
So this becomes a lot faster.
So in code, this is what it looks like.
So instead of having all of these lines of code here,
all of these six lines of code here,
we go to these two lines.
Then we have a for loop that goes from warp size to mass.
And all we have to do is do the Shuffle XOR
and the value store the sum.
This can also be done with ShuffleDown,
but it's much easier with XOR.
We can also do this for all the warps.
So let's say we have 1024 threads.
We have 32 warps.
All 32 warps can compute their own sum.
And then the 32 warps can do 32 additions for each warp.
So now it becomes a lot faster to do as well.
And then you can write the final result
to the global memory.
Here's the full code for ShuffleToBlockReduce,
where we start with,
we only use shared memory of 32
so that we are storing the warp results.
For warp, we are storing the results
of using shared memory for the entire thing.
We have a lane and warp ID.
And then we are doing warpReduceSum here,
which I'll come to in the next slide.
And then we are, if we come here, down here,
we are only adding the shared memory for warp
where the source lane is here.
And this is what the kernel looks like
on the global model,
where we are calling this blockSumReduce and getting,
so this is blockSumReduce here,
and warpReduce is here, this one.
So yeah, that's a whole different way
of writing a reduction algorithm
where you significantly reduce how much shared memory you use.
So conclusions for Shuffle.
It is one of the needless tricks in the book.
A lot of people don't use it.
It requires a creative way of thinking about your algorithm
like we saw with reduction.
You can use it for a lot of things.
You can use it for sorts, reduction, transpose, et cetera.
And it always has excellent performance numbers
because it's working on registers,
not even with shared memory.
So you don't have to use unsafe.
You don't have to use sync threads.
Can be used in different ways for different algorithms.
And it also has no bank conflicts, which shared memory has.
So if you find a way to use this in your algorithms,
so certainly think about it and try to use it.
So that brings us to the end of our advanced product topic.
So with this, you're very well set on how you use CUDA.
We'll be on next week,
Liam will be covering machine learning with CUDA.
So that'll be, those are two amazing lectures as well,
especially if you have that machine learning interest
as well as computer vision or NLP
or image processing and stuff.
And then Rachel and Wayne will cover intro to WebGL.
We'll do an intro to welcome recording
and then on next Wednesday
will be project five recitations for Vulkan and WebGL.
So that's it for today.