All right. So today is one of my favorite lectures of the year. It's the CUDA performance
lab. This is, this lecture is essentially how I got started in 565 after I graduated
from the class. Once I graduated, I started working for a company called Rayfire where
I was doing CUDA and OpenCM day in, day out. So I was using the debugger, the profiler
every day. So when I was taking this class 10 years ago, there was no class, there's
no recording about how to use the inside tools back then. So because I was doing it daily,
I told Patrick back then, Hey, let me come do a guest lecture about the profiler, about
the debugger. So this lecture is essentially an evolution of that, where we take it up
as an exercise about how do we go from something that is very basic to something that is very
extraordinary and utilizing the complete GPU performance. So that's, that's exactly what
we're going to see today. What we'd also see is, we'd also see a bunch of inside tools,
the especially the inside compute. But we'd also revisit a bunch of topics from last week.
So remember how I said, we'll revisit bank complex, memory coalescing and stuff. We'll
do those today. And we'll do it as part of two very small exercises. That should be very
easy on an algorithmic level, but we'll take it forward in a performance level. So those are
transpose. And the other one is reductions. Okay. So if you haven't already done it, again,
it was optional. I know you guys are focused on project three, but I've set up this repo here.
And before the class, I committed matrix transpose naive and matrix transpose shared,
because I want us to get started with a little bit of a heads up in class so that we have enough
time. So if you haven't completed those, just pull, just pull from GitHub and you'll be fine.
And that's about it. Okay. Any questions on this?
Okay. So let's get started with memory coalescing. Okay.
Actually, let me hold that. Let me show you the project itself.
So I'm going to pull up my visual studio and I have a transpose here. So as you can see,
I have my kernels completed. So this is the code I have published. If you need the text to be bigger,
just let me know. I'll zoom in. Okay. It's especially the last row. Let me know if the
text is big enough for you. What we have here, and I'll go to the host side of it,
is a bunch of kernels and compute that build on top of each other. So what we get started with
is a few benchmarks. So this mem benchmark here essentially runs CUDA mem copies to give you
a baseline for what mem copy speeds you should be expecting on your laptop. And I'll talk a little
bit more about this later. Then what we do is we set up some host arrays. We make sure we have
gold arrays. So these gold arrays are essentially, we know that these are correct because we are
doing them on the CPU. And we are always going to check our output against these.
We set up our device arrays, do CUDA mallet, and this is where we are doing our gold standard.
We do a CPU transpose so that we have a CPU benchmark. Again, this is a naive version of it.
If you wanted, you could do a highly parallel versions. It's up to you, but I'll just stick
to the naive one. We have a device-to-device copy. I'll get to this in a little bit,
why I have this. We have a naive transpose kernel. We have shared memory. And then what we are going
to look at today is bank conflicts, unrolling the loop, and doing a little bit more with that. And
then we'll go to the reduction side. But if we take a look at any of these kernels, so let me
pick shared memory transpose here. What we have is setting up our sizes here for the number of
blocks and threads. This give up function is something that's very common in CUDA land,
essentially. What it says is it does a seal. So instead of doing a seal function, it actually
does, if you look at the code up top, it's essentially size x plus block.x minus 1 divided
by block.x. That's essentially what it does. So it's very simple, just rounds up.
And VTX region. So this is essentially what you call a markup in our profiler. I'll show this,
when I launch the profiler, I'll show this to you. It essentially marks a section that you
want to look at. So it's like a bookmark. So that's what you want to see. CUDA event record
is a way, again, for performance profiling. You can see events in your profiler. So that's why I
have this here. And then, notice this, for performance compute, I'm not doing one iteration,
I'm doing 10. Anybody know why I'm doing 10? All right. For example, 100. Why am I not doing just
one? Yeah, exactly. There's a warmup where the GPU needs to initialize the kernel and maybe
run it a few times so that you want an average. And this applies to CPU as well. If you're doing
any CPU benchmarking as well, you want to do it n number of times an average amount.
For matrix transfer shared, these numbers will essentially give you the templates for
assigning shared memory. CUDA event record is stopping this record here. Event synchronize
means it's going to synchronize everything that happened between start and stop.
And then, this is marking the end of this benchmark. Then you essentially
calculate the elapsed time, you do a mem copy, and then you check the results to make sure that
they're correct. So that's essentially how we are going through each one of these kernels
in the code. They're mostly copy-paste. So what I'm going to do is make sure first
that you're in release with debug info. Because if you don't do debug info, you will always run
into an issue where the function names and the code are not visible to the profiler and the debugger.
So we want to check performance, but we also want the debug symbols. So make sure you're
in release with debug. Now, I'm not going to run the profiler first. What I'm going to do is hit,
what should I hit for performance profiling? What keys or what shortcut should I hit for
performance profiling? F5? How many of you say F5?
Somebody, I mean, how do you guys run? Everybody, you all run your code, right?
So F5 is essentially the shortcut for this launch with debugger. So if you see here,
well, in Visual Studio, I guess they changed it to F7. Sorry, F7 is built, but let's run.
Did they change these menus? They always do. Here, start debugging is F5. So if you are hitting F5,
what that means is the code that you're running is still attached to the Visual Studio debugger.
You may be launching a command window and maybe not debugging it, but you're still
launching it as debug. For performance, you should always be launching with control F5.
Like without a doubt, if you're generating a chart, launch with control F5.
So that's what I'm going to do. I'm going to hit control F5. Probably going to take a little bit
to compile and run. But what we are going to see as an output is a few things. So let me pull
this up here. So the first thing you're going to see is my GPU name. I'm printing this using
the CUDA device info, and I'm transferring 16 MB of memory for checking my bandwidth.
So the first two are called host-to-host device. So I'm essentially benchmarking my post copy. So
from RAM to RAM, how fast is it? And I have a new XPS. I believe it's a DDR4 memory, and I'm getting
about 40 gigabytes per second of copy. Next, I'm doing what are known as pageable transfers. So
these are 11 and 8. Anybody know why these numbers are significant or what these numbers tell me?
What is this related to?
And what is it limited by? What hardware is it limited by?
What is that connection called? The PCIe bus. The PCIe, when you are going in the
market and buying GPUs, you're always going to see PCIe 3, PCIe 4, 16 lanes, etc. On some of the
AMD Threadripper, you're going to see 64 threads. So it's both ways. You need 16
lanes on your GPU, and you need 16 lanes on your CPU for the swapping to happen well. So right now,
those are the speeds I'm getting. We'll get to the pin memory in a little bit, but look at this
number, device-to-device bandwidth. That's a CUDA global memory-to-global memory copy bandwidth.
And look, it's four times faster than CPU. On my laptop GPU, I'm not even talking about a big,
fast, beefy GPU. Even on my laptop GPU, it's four times faster than the CPU memory.
So that's where you know that the global memory is fast, but yet not fast enough for a GPU computer.
Now, let's come to the CPU side. So on the CPU transport, transport is expected very slow.
We only get 0.8852 gigabytes a second. Compare that to 43 gigabytes a second.
It's a lot, right? It's a huge difference. It's like 50 times slower. So not great.
Our device-to-device copy. So now think about the device-to-device copy.
What is that actually doing? A device-to-device copy kernel, what is it doing?
It's doing the same thing as a CUDA memcpy, right? The exact same thing. There's no difference,
except that we are doing it inside a kernel. And that is 146 versus 162. You could say some
level of error, but it's close enough. That's like 90-something percent there. So we'll give it a pass.
Naive transpose is 35, and shared memory transpose is 7.
Tell me what operation transpose is most like. And there's a hint here.
What operation is transpose most like? It's like copy. It is taking one element
from one place and putting it in the other place. Forget about indexing. But if you think about
the comparison between copy and transpose, the only difference is where the output is written.
Otherwise, the operation is exactly the same. So why should our transpose bandwidth
be anything less than our copy bandwidth, right? There's not much compute happening
in transpose, right? So in last class, we discussed compute, copy, overlap, and stuff.
That's out of the door. There's not enough compute. We'll forget about that. But we should
at least be getting the same amount or close enough to the same speed as we are with the copy,
right? But if we look at a naive method, we're only getting 35. We're getting less than a quarter of
the speed as compared to the device. Are we satisfied with that? No, right? We're here to
do performance. We are absolutely not satisfied with it. So that's why what we're going to do
in this class is essentially work through this and see how we optimize it, OK? So let me close
that for now. And I'm going to go back to Visual Studio. And now I'm going to launch
Insight Compute. And I'm going to say interactive profile.
Sorry, it's launching here. So let me bring these.
So I'm going to say Windows. It's already attached to this. Make sure it's the right
configuration. So I've released for you. Make sure NVTX support is yes, because we want those
markers, right? And then all looks good to me. And then I'm going to hit launch.
So it's going to run in the background. And it will generate some stats. And we'll see when
it's ready. This paused. At the first instance of CUDA commands, it will pause because I hit
the interactive profiler. But I'm just going to hit this Play button. And that will run all of it,
OK? So let me, I think I need to enable this auto profile before I do that. All right.
So it'll run a bunch of times. It'll collect a bunch of metrics. And I'll show you a first version
of how to read that. We'll come back to the profiler again multiple times through this lecture.
But at least initially, I'll show you how to use the profiler in a very generic way.
So as you can see, it's all filling up here. And each CUDA call is getting filled up. And
these are not kernel calls. These are like driver level calls. So if you're doing a memory copy,
you're going to see it. If you do events, you're going to see it and all that. So you can see some
events synchronized and stuff as this goes by. It should be. Any questions so far while this is
running? I usually call it .nbprof, usually. But there's no rule around it. Essentially,
you can save the profiler's output and bring it back up if you wanted to.
OK. So my profiler's done. What I'm going to do is I'm going to go to session first, OK?
So in session, what you get is, OK, how is this run? The first thing you're going to get. So
what command line arguments did you use and all that? So you first get some system information.
But if you scroll down, now you start seeing some GPU information, right? You start seeing
attributes. You start seeing some numbers that matter. I'm going to highlight a few here.
And there's another way to see this. So let me do, I have a breakpoint already.
Yeah. So I have a breakpoint, right? So another way to see this is if you hit
CUDA start debugging and it's going to hit this breakpoint here.
So once it hits that breakpoint, if you go to inside window, resources,
and you go to CUDA devices. Let me try to see if I can zoom in. It's not allowing me to zoom in.
Yeah. So let's look at it here.
So a few numbers I want you to pay attention to, OK?
Let's start here. These three. These are max block dim size x, y, and z. So these are the
maximum size of any dimension of your block. So the number of threads in a block. While we've said
the total number of threads in a block can't be greater than 1024, what this is also saying is
you can't have more than 1024 threads in x or y, but you can only have 64 threads in z.
OK? So you can't have 1, 1, 1024 in the z configuration as an example.
The other thing I want to show you is this. Grid dim x, y, z. Those are the number of blocks you
can have in each dimension. And for all intents and purposes, that's basically infinite. You have
2 billion around x. You have another 65,000 around y and another 65,000 around z. So if you
multiply all of those, that's a lot of blocks. So basically unlimited. So the other thing here
is this line. Max blocks for multiprocessor. For me, it's 16. So what that's saying is,
assuming other resources are fine, the number of blocks that can live in one SM at any given time
is 16. This might be different for your GPUs. It's 16 for my GPU. OK? But when you're going
into the industry and writing programs, you're going to have to choose what the baseline GPU
or the most optimized GPU is going to be, or what the most optimized hardware is going to be.
And this is how you're going to choose it. OK? And speaking of choosing here, so max registers
per block, max registers for multiprocessor. For me, both of those are 65,000. And that's 65,000
bytes. So that allows you to choose how many registers per block you should have and stuff.
Same with shared memory. I have shared memory per block, which is 48 kilobytes for me. And we have
shared memory for multiprocessor, which is one megabyte. So I can have a lot more shared memory
across different contexts, across different blocks, within an SM. The other thing here,
so going back to our previous conversation, max threads per block. Again, we have max threads
for dimension blocks, block domain, block divide, block density. But total across the block is also
1024 for me. And then max threads for multiprocessor, these are active threads, is 1536.
OK? So you can have 16 blocks per SM, but a total of 1536 threads. Let's see what else.
So warp size. Remember how I said warp size will always be 32? I've never seen this change. OK.
It's there as a piece of information, but it has never changed. And then the other thing I want to
show you before we quit is L1 cache, L2 cache size, persisting L2 cache size. And there should
be one for total global memory. That's what I'm looking for. So let's see.
Stock rate, total constant memory. I'm surprised it's not showing here. OK.
So that's devices. If you want to know your device information, that's where you go. OK?
Let's look at...
OK. Let's quit this for now, and let's go back to our profiler.
So in the profiler, we are going to see the same information as well. OK? You're going to see
pretty much exactly the same information that we saw before, but maybe in a little bit more detail.
But most of it will be the same. The only one here, total memory is added here. I have four
gigabytes of global memory, so that's being shown here. OK. So that session, in summary,
so if you go into your profile and change page to summary, what you're going to see is a bunch of
API calls. So you're going to see kernel calls here, what dimensions they were called with,
both block and grid, how much time they took, what was the memory throughput, what was the
compute throughput. You're going to see an overview of all the kernels that were called
in this page. If you go to details... Actually, let's come back to details.
If you want the source code, like if you have a thrill for reading assembly-level source code,
you're going to see it here. So if we go to, let's say... Let's go to a copy kernel,
because that'll be simple, right? This is what your copy kernel looks like to a GPU.
Let's try to identify some instructions very, very quickly. So we are doing some move, OK?
I don't know what that is, but we are doing... What is S2R?
What do you think S2R is? I think it's shared to register, but... IMAN?
Integer, multiply, and add. IMAN is integer, multiply, and add. So when you see
threadIdx.x plus blockDim.size, that is an integer, multiply, and add operations. The
GPU can do it in one instruction. It doesn't have to do the multiply and addition separately. It can
do it in one instruction using three inputs. So you see three inputs here, and then one output.
And then move is a copy. IMAN wide is if you need the long integer, you use a wide.
And then exit is when the kernel is done. Again, not important for you to know, but if you want
to look at, like we discussed in the last class about how threads can be reordered or commands
can be reordered, this is where. And you kind of see this here in this column here. So if you look
at this column, dependencies, you can see which registers or which instructions are dependent on
which other instructions. So that way you can tell where the GPU might be remapping it.
The other thing you can see here is the number of live registers.
Even though your kernel might be written in one way, the GPU can optimize registers out once
they're no longer in use. So what we see here is the maximum amount of registers our kernel uses
is five at any given point. But at different points, it can be using five.
But then it reduces the number of registers when it doesn't need them.
Let's see what else.
All right. So let's look at details now. And I'm not going to go fully into this. I'll step
through it as we do different kernels. But the first thing to look at is the GPU speed of light
throughput, as they call it. And immediately, what you notice here, let's read this line.
This is the first thing. Even before I expand it, you can see it. High memory throughput.
Memory is more heavily utilized than compute. Yeah, go ahead.
I know, I know. That's why I'm reading it out.
If you're running it on your screen, that would be the best thing. I want you to try it out.
It's not something I know. You're not able to run profiler?
OK. With the latest clone?
Yeah, if I were, you'd just have to allow it.
OK. All right. So let me drop this Zoom link here then. But hopefully, it works.
And make sure you're on mute. And you can have your cameras off.
I'll do that one second. You don't have to.
OK. I've never done that. You have to allow the firewalls, but you don't have to run it as admin.
So let's see.
OK. So I've posted the link to add this question. So if you, it's on the performance lab, which is
pinned. So if you look at the second link in the pinned and scroll down, the link is there.
So I'll give everybody two minutes to join that. And during that time, I'll show how to run this
again. So if you're in, and then let's,
OK. Make sure you're mute, please. OK. So to recap, to run, make sure your build is done.
Then you pick release with debug info in your configuration.
And then insight, compute, and run profile. OK.
Once you run profile, I won't run it. But essentially, what you want to do is
you want to make sure you can do profile or interactive profile. First time I did interactive
profile, now I can do profile. It doesn't really matter. Just make sure that in the filter or
wherever it's NVTX support is enabled. That's the most important thing, because we have NVTX
in this file. If you select interactive profile, you're going to be able to see this here.
Once you hit launch, you will see a pause on the first PUDA command. OK. In that case,
what you need to do is, I'm going to close this because I don't want to run it again.
You want to hit this button. It's called auto profile. Click that button. And then you click
this button, which is the pause play button. And then it'll profile everything for you. OK.
Anybody seeing any errors?
All right. So for the sake of time, I'm going to continue because otherwise,
this will become a very, very long lecture. Just make sure to follow along. OK. And then
maybe after class, if you guys still have an issue running it, then I can help debug that.
OK. So I was talking about speed of light here. And let's read that first line there. OK. It says
high memory throughput. Memory is more heavily utilized than compute. OK. Even before we proceed
with that, what do we know about this kernel? What kernel is it? It's a copy kernel, right?
It's a copy kernel, right? It doesn't have much compute. It maximizes on memory bandwidth.
So this statement, while a warning, is almost like factual. It's just confirming what we already
know. OK. But look at what it's also saying. Look at the memory workload analysis section
to identify DRAM bottlenecks. DRAM is your global memory, dynamic RAM. Check memory replay
coalescing, which we are going to talk about again today, to make sure you are efficiently
utilizing the bytes transferred. Also consider whether it's possible to do more work per memory.
What does that sound like from last class? Do more work per memory access.
That's kind of like the Rube unrolling part, right? And whether there are values you can
recompute. Essentially, what that last part is saying is, are there values that you're storing
in global memory that you can pretty quickly do as compute? So that you don't have to read it
from global memory. It'll be faster to compute itself. So that's what it's saying. OK. So it
told us to look at memory workload analysis here. So I'm going to click that. All right. This is a
beautiful chart, one of my favorite ever. OK. Let's look at what this is showing.
On the left, we have kernel. OK. And on the right, we have different types of memory.
And as we move left, we get closer and closer to the threads, or closer and closer to registers.
So we have L1 cache, L2 cache, and different types of memory. So in the copy kernel,
what type of memory are we using? Or types of memory are we using in the copy kernel?
We are using global. What else? Maybe. But in the code that you see, we are directly copying
from one global memory to another global. So let's take a look. We are not using any
global memory. So that's 0. Don't need. We are not using any texture memory. We are not
using surface memory. We are not doing any load store on global. And we are not using
any shared memory either. So all of this is 0. But we are using global memory.
And what this is saying is we have 1 million instructions doing global memory to kernel,
and about 525,000 requesting global memory from cache. And to fill it into cache,
we are getting a lot of it from L2 cache. And from L2 cache, we are getting it from device memory.
Why is this 67.11 MB? Why is this significant? Why is it exactly 67.11 MB?
So think about how much memory we have. I'm copying 4096 by 4096
elements. So that 16 million was the data type. It's a float, right? 16 million elements
times 4 bytes each is 64 million, right? 64 million, if you convert that, if you write it
out, because when I say 1,000, it's not really 1,000. It's 1024. 64 million is essentially that
much memory space, maybe with a little bit of overflow. So that's why you'll get exactly that.
So we'll see a lot more of this in a little bit. But this is in a very simple copy kernel.
And what I want to show you is this part here. It has 1 million wavefronts, and the peak is 6.11,
not very high. And then you see how many local loads you have, how many global loads.
And then you have global stores. So you're reading and writing, and the number of bytes
is here. That's how many bytes you're reading and writing. So it's a very great chart to compare,
if you have a known algorithm, to see exactly how it's performing.
Let's come back to this. Let's take a look very quickly at transpose naive before we go ahead.
Because here, take a look at this.
This is 67.11, right? We are reading 67.11. Well, how much are we writing?
536 megabytes? Where do we have 536 megabytes of data?
Where is this number coming from?
Why do you think we have 536 megabytes of data? Writing. We don't have that much data to write,
but we are writing it. So if you scroll down, let's take another different look at it.
Take a look at this. The number of wavefronts, and the number of sectors,
and the number of bytes. Why are all these three different?
Any guesses? We'll take a look at it in the slides, but any early guesses why this might be
different? Wavefronts, let's ignore. Sectors is kind of like blocks of money.
But you're on the right front, I gave you a hint there.
But why are these different, these numbers,
compared to our copy kernel or even compared to the read?
Yes, exactly. What is that called?
Not memory coalescing. Yes, exactly. So look at this. Again, if you didn't know that,
if I wasn't here to tell you that, you're going to read this. Kernel exhibits low compute throughput
and memory bandwidth utilization. Remember what we did in copy kernel, it was just compute.
Memory bandwidth itself was fine. Here it's in low compute and memory bandwidth. And if you read
ahead, achieve compute throughput and a memory bandwidth below 60%. What that is saying is,
hey, you launched a GPU kernel. Yeah, you made your stuff go faster, but you're below even the
60% mark of utilizing your GPU. That's kind of what it's saying. So if you read that,
know that there's some optimization you can make in your kernel.
And then if you read below on the compute workload analysis, you're going to see more info there.
So with that, let's pause. Let's pause on the profile and let's take a look at our slides.
All right, so let's look at memory coalescing. As Tom mentioned, it's a problem in a naive kernel.
Right? So memory coalescing is concurrent access of threads in a wall leading continuous memory
or writing continuous memory to global memory. Let's take a look at a few examples.
So let's say we have theoretically L1 and L2 cache. And L1 cache is 128 bytes continuous,
which means you can store your four bytes. You can store an int. You can store a float in there.
But if you read or write, you have to do it for the entire block. You have to do it for 128 bytes.
You can't do four bytes at a time. Similarly, L2 is multiples of 32 bytes. Everybody clear
how this is structured? So let's take a look at a few examples. So this is only for information,
but let's take a look at an example. So let's say we have 32 threads in a wall. Right?
And they're reading 32 floats, which are four byte words, if you want to call them in memory.
32 times four is 128. If they are aligned and all within the same cache block,
then this is read in one read cycle, in which case you get 100% bus utilization.
OK? This is like the optimal scenario. You have each word reading continuous memory.
It is perfectly aligned, and you get perfect bus utilization. Everybody clear on this?
OK. What about this scenario, where you have different threads reading different parts of
the same block, but all the threads fall within the same block? Is that fine? That's fine as well.
The memory bus doesn't care which thread is reading what. All the memory thread gets,
in a conceptual way, is I need memory from 128 to 256. OK? And then the memory bus reads
OK? And then it lets the threads do whatever it wants with that. The memory controller is only
getting how much memory it needs. And in that case, it's still perfect. No problem whatsoever. OK?
Exactly. That is a great analogy. That is exactly how you think about this. OK?
What about this? Let's say you have alternating elements. You're not reading continuous,
but maybe you're reading alternating. Or maybe some fall in the previous one. It doesn't have
to always fall within the exact 128 bytes, right? Maybe it's shifted a little bit. In that case,
while you may only be reading this much of this block, you have to read the whole thing.
The bus has to still read the whole block. In this case, you're still reading 128 bytes,
but you're using 128 bytes, but you have to read 256 bytes,
in which case your bus utilization becomes 50%. OK? Everybody on board with this?
So when you're doing alternating or jumping around, where do we do jump around?
Well, in which algorithm did we jump around? Or have some kind of a step?
These are just introductions, right? Where we had steps, where we were reading from one place,
writing to another. That would give you a different bus utilization.
And you can do this. Yeah, yeah, yeah. You can do that.
Any other questions on this?
OK. So let's look at an L2 example. Now, let's say we have the same example,
OK? But it's falling in L2. Now, let's take a look at it. Now, because L2 blocks are smaller
than 32 kilobytes, or 32 bytes each, now we need five of these blocks, and we get an 80% utilization.
Utilization shouldn't be the only number you focus on, but it is an important number.
OK? But what you're seeing here is the total number of memory, total amount of memory that
you read is 160 bytes compared to 256 bytes. But this may be faster if you are excluding enough
blocks. It may be faster. Not always, OK? What about this?
All the threads are reading one place from memory.
Right. You're still reading the same amount of memory as you did in our first example,
but all the threads only need one value. So as a ratio of reading one value compared to 32 values
that you're actually reading in the bus, it's not great utilization. But if you have to read it,
you have to read it. If you can avoid this, fantastic. Avoid it. OK? So make sure that
if you're reading something like this, you are doing it purposefully and intentionally.
Don't do it by mistake. Yeah? So if we look at L2, the same example in L2, now we get 12.5%
utilization. Still not great, but maybe better than what we had before. OK? So that's why don't
only pay attention to the bus utilization. Make sure that your algorithm is well thought out.
This may still be bad. If you're doing it unnecessarily, it's still bad.
But in some algorithms, you have to do it. For example, in the last step of reduction, where you
have to write something to global memory, you can't avoid it. Right? You can't just throw away
the result. But make sure you're only doing it when absolutely necessary. So as a function,
just like you have registers that are closer to the poles and global memory is further away or
slower from the poles, you have L1 and L2 cache, which take global memory and store it in L1, L2,
and then they give it to your register. So if you're having...
So there are blocks. When you get into designing hardware, you make certain tradeoffs
about what can be random and what can be sequential. So the more faster you want,
the more sequential it has to be, the more predictable it has to be.
The slower it is, for example, hard disk drives have complete randomness. Whereas if you look
at even solid-state drives, you're going to get some level of sequential. So that's kind of what
you get. That's kind of how hardware is designed. So you get global memory, it gets stored in cache,
and then the cache becomes faster way to access it from the threads. Any other questions on this?
Okay. So if we generalize this, if you have threads reading from all over the place,
in L1 cache, you're going to get n times 128 total reads, and your bus utilization will be 128
divided by n times 128, if each n is reading from a different block.
And similarly, in L2, you'll get an n divided by 28. That's kind of how you get it.
Okay. So these are conceptual examples to show you how bus utilization works.
We'll come back to it in a little bit. Okay.
The other thing I want to talk to you about, this is just two slides, is a reminder for
shared memory. And I'll show you how to launch shared memory in a new way at this point. So
you all remember underscore underscore shared, you've used it plenty of times,
please continue to use it, it's always good. To define this, you should do shared underscore
underscore float myvar. This happens with the kernel. Or there's a second way to specify it.
You can say extern shared float myvar. This goes in the kernel. This line goes in the kernel.
In your kernel launch, you have blocks, you have threads, now you have a new number,
shared bytes. Okay. What's the difference between these two? What's the main difference between
these two? What's the requirement here? The cycle is picked at compile time. So you can determine
it based on what code you're running, how big your data is and stuff like that. You can't
determine that here. Here you can, this is dynamic. This allows you to compute the shared
memory at runtime and then tell the kernel how much shared memory you need. Okay.
So as a reminder, shared memory is communication only within the block, you cache it,
improve global memory access, and then it's divided into 32-bit banks, which we covered last
time. Okay. So we'll come back to that. Everybody clear on shared memory? Any questions? Anything
you want me to revisit from last time? Except banks, which I will revisit in a little bit.
Any questions on this? Okay. All right. So let's take a look at matrix transpose.
Okay. We did the theory. Let's take a look at a practical example.
So matrix transpose is what we call inherently parallel or embarrassingly parallel. Okay.
The parallelism is so obvious that if you don't do it, it's kind of like an embarrassment.
So it's very simple to do. Like we discussed before, it's literally the same as a copy
operation, except we are copying it into a different location. We are copying each element
into a different location. So on a CPU, I'm not even going to bother reading the code because
all of you know this. There's nothing complicated there. It's very easy to do. It's slow because
it's often squared. You have two for loops there and it's often squared. Okay. But we are not in
a CPU class. We are in GPU class. Okay. So on the GPU, the idea is to do transpose that you launch
one element per thread, you compute the index, you compute the copy index, and you copy the data.
Okay. Pretty simple. Like the algorithmically, it's not complex whatsoever. Our performance
is now O of one. We went from O of N squared to O of one because the parallelism is built in.
It's implicit in the CPU. So now, essentially what you're doing is on the GPU, you're doing a
memcpy. Even though it might be in different indices, you're still doing one global memory
to global memory memcpy. Okay. So if memcpy bandwidth is 100% of practical GPU bandwidth,
different for all of our GPUs, how much should we get for transpose? So I want you all to do
something. I was going to get posters. I want you all to do something. Take whatever pen you have,
paper. If you want to come on the board and write on the board, I'm more than happy for you to.
That was another thing I was going to ask you to do. Come write your predictions on the board.
Actually, let's do that. Let's do that. Why don't all of you come up, write your name and
write a number for how much faster. So two things. I want you to write as a percentage of
device to device copy bandwidth. So if you think it'll be 50%, write 50%, okay,
of device to device bandwidth that we'll see. And then I want you to write how many times
faster it'll be than the CPU. Okay. Let's do those. Let's do that very quickly. Okay. Let's
not spend too much time. That's fine. Somebody wanted you to erase that side.
Again, this is all fun and games. I'm probably going to base the entire
class's data on this thing. Okay. So make sure you get your predictions correct.
Come on, come on. Don't, don't be shy. Don't be shy. So, so this is how I'm going to write. Okay.
So I'm going to write a percentage. Okay. And I'm going to write times and then put some numbers
and then they're not talking to the entire chat box. So just write your numbers.
Anyway, it doesn't matter. Come quick, come quick. Don't want to spend too much time.
Remember, the times was faster than the CPU, not faster than the
copy kernel. That's impossible.
Don't look at other answers. Just come up with yours.
There's more talk here if you want to take a break. And then anybody talk?
There's more talk here.
Yes.
Percentage compared to GPU bandwidth, device-to-device bandwidth.
So if I use half of them, do I have to read half of them to write this?
No, just write it as a percentage.
It should be like a copy, but if you're getting 100 on copy, how much should you get on transpose?
All right. Anybody left?
I think a lot of people are here, but okay.
Make your guess. We'll find out.
All right. Last call. One minute to write.
Okay. All right. 30 seconds.
So conservative on the times faster. Remember, it was faster than CPU, but okay, we'll see.
Okay. So let's take a look at the naive transpose algorithm.
And this is purely just to walk through it just like we did on the CPU.
We compute the global row index in the matrix. We compute the global column index in the matrix.
We have an index in and an index out, which is flipped.
Sorry about the capitalization. I'm sure PowerPoint did that.
But look at how we have flipped i and j and also x and y.
And then index out equals index in. That's it.
Nothing more than that whatsoever. Any questions about this?
Okay. What are the problems? Yeah.
Not really, but we'll kind of get to the nuance of that. So what are the problems with this?
We already saw one problem. What was it?
From a profiler. Yeah. So we are not reading convenience memory, right? Okay. So let's take
a look at this. So we saw memory coalescing in different patterns, right? Which ones of
these are used for matrix transpose? Okay. Six. Where are six used?
I think, okay. What else? What other memory patterns are used?
What other memory patterns are we using when we are writing the transpose kernel?
So Ed says he thinks six is used for writing. For example, what are we using for reading?
Which ones are we using for reading?
Is it one? Okay. Our reading is generally continuous, so one. Are we using anything
else? So we are using one for reading, six for writing? Possibly, yes. What else are we using?
Or are we not using anything else?
So we are using one and we are using one for reading.
So we are using one and we are using six, but we're also using two. Two is getting used when
we are writing diagonal blocks. Remember, when you're doing the diagonals, you're reading and
writing within the same space. Okay. So that's why we use diagonal blocks. One is good. We know
one is good. One gets maximum bus utilization. Four is bad. This is what we're using for
writing. This becomes bad. This is where, remember how we saw the 500 number?
Remember this? Remember this number? That is coming because you are writing
that is coming because you are writing one memory for each block in a way. Okay. So now,
even though you're only writing one element within that block of memory, you're still
processing that much memory. You're still reading or writing that much memory,
because that's how the memory controller works. So that's why you're 67 when reading is perfect.
It's 100% utilization is what you need, but now you're writing 530 megabytes,
which has all of that extra memory that you need.
So that's kind of, again, reading this, you can infer it back. I'm here to teach you as an
example, but every time you see this and it doesn't add up, it doesn't make sense,
that's kind of what is happening. Okay. All right. Another example, another way of looking at this
is you're reading two elements, so you're reading 10 blocks, but then you're writing in random way.
So for example, you may be reading in thread one, you may be reading three and writing in here,
but you can actually be writing that much. That's kind of the problem that's happening.
Okay. So our problem is coalesced memory, and to improve that, we want coalesced memory.
How do we do that? What's a solution to flip to having coalesced memory reads a byte?
Shared memory, kind of a given, given that I gave that in the code. Okay. So let's take a look at
shared memory. What it allows us to do is instead of having randomized writes within a block,
you use shared memory to flip within a block. Okay. And then you can write it
streamlined to the GPU. Okay. So we'll change the algorithm a little bit. We'll compute the
input index, same as the naive transpose. We'll then copy data into the shared memory.
We'll then compute the output index. Output index doesn't change, but except that it has
coalesced memory access now. And transpose only happens in shared memory. Okay. So this is kind
of what it looks like. You have a global memory of a matrix. You read that into shared memory
everywhere. You do a synthreads, because every time you write into shared memory, you should
do a synthreads. Do the transpose in shared memory. See how the transpose is happening here.
And then you write all of these out. Okay. Another way to see this, another visualization. I just
give you different visualizations so that you understand it. What's happening here is for this
block, you're reading it into shared memory just normally. Do a synthreads. Within the block,
you're flipping. Okay. So see how this is 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 CD. You're flipping this
into columns. So instead of 0, 1, 2, 3 as a row, you get 1, 2, 3 as a column.
This is perfectly fine. Shared memory gets you random access. You don't have a problem of random
access in shared memory. Okay. This is perfectly fine. But now, what you get is this very well
written out here. Okay. So now, look at this. So you have 2 as a row. 2, 3, 4, 5. 2, 3, 4, 5.
6, 5, 2, 1. 6, 5, 2, 1. 18, 2, 7, 9. 0, 4, 3, 7. Transpose, right? So you took that and put it
here, except what you did is you flipped it in shared memory. So what's actually happening in
the background is this thread is writing to this thread. That's easy and clear.
Well, where was this thread writing in 9? Don't think about the element.
The thread which read this element, where did that write in 9?
It wrote it here. You're right. It wrote it here. 4 wrote it here. 5 wrote it here.
If we take this 7, this 7 wrote it here. What's actually happening is threads that were continuous
here now have to scan all of this memory, scan all of this memory to go to the next thread.
So they're not continuous anymore. They're not writing continuous. We're changing this.
This is getting transposed here. That's easy to understand. Now what's happening is
instead of the 3 writing 3 here, 3 writes to 6. 3 takes this element here and puts it here.
This thread here takes this element and puts it here. So now you have threads writing continuously
as well. Make sense? All right, let's take a look at the code.
So the first thing we do is compute the blocks. Why do we do the blocks?
Because if we take a look at this matrix, forget the elements inside.
If you think of the thick lines, this transpose is essentially here. If you think of them as
submatrixes, you're first transposing the submatrix and then transposing the elements inside.
So that's why we store this Bx and By because we have first transposed the Bx and By.
Input, transposed output. So see how input is Bx times threadIdx.x. Output Ti,
transposed Ti is By. See how we are switching these blocks. Remember how I said we'll transpose
the blocks first? So that's what is happening. Bx is becoming for j. By is becoming for i.
But notice threadIdx.x and threadIdx.y don't change. x is associated with i, y is associated
with j. This is so that our threads write sequentially. And then we go to reading
our input into matrix, into our shared memory matrix, same threads. And then see how we're
flipping x and y. We have y and x, we're getting x and y. So we are flipping it in shared memory,
we are transposing it in shared memory. And this output, see how Tj times size y plus Ti,
j times size x plus i. So j is always the major component, i is always the minor component.
And that's why this will be a sequential write.
Yes, so we solve memory coordinating. Any questions?
Everybody get this? So let me take a pause here. And I'm going to come here.
And I'm going to run this again.
Yes, so we had device for device at 135. Naive at 35. Shared memory at 75.
I thought we solved memory coalescing. Why aren't we getting 130 something?
Why are we only getting 75? I mean, it's an improvement. It's quite fast, which is amazing.
But not satisfactory to our goals, right? Our goal was here. This is our goal.
So why are we only getting 75?
What's the problem?
Is anybody happy with this performance? Will you be like, OK, my work is done, I'm going home?
No, right? We are in a performance class. We are in a GPU class. So let's minimize that.
And I'm going to go to our profile. And I'm going to go to our shared kernel.
So let's take a look at first our speed of light. This kernel exhibits low computer
memory bandwidth. It's saying less than 60%. OK, so in our naive kernel, it said it only exhibits
low compute, but didn't save memory. Now it's saying memory too. OK, so let's look at why.
I love this chart again. Let's take a look at it. Now we're using shared memory. So not only do we
get this 67, 67. So first of all, we fixed this. This is now fixed. There's no 536 megabytes being
read. That's our first confirmation that we are on the right track. Now let's take a look.
This is equal. This is equal. This is equal. Fantastic. Amazing improvement.
Shared memory. We are using shared memory now. That's equal as well, right? Shared memory doesn't
have that block situation that it's reading from M day. So where's the problem?
Let's scroll down. Let's see what the profile. Remember, the profile is there to help you. OK,
let's scroll down. What do we see? Hey, there's something here.
We have a new table here for shared memory. OK, what are we seeing?
Conflict? So what's our problem now?
Dynamics. OK, so let's see how to solve these now. OK, so see, remember how I said,
I'm here to teach, but really you should all be running this profile on your own code.
You would be finding things like that. OK, so let's take a look. Let's come back to PowerPoint.
So problems. We're not close. We are about halfway from a bad conflict. We've doubled
our live performance, but we haven't, we're not even close to 50% of our GPU bandwidth.
So our solution is to remove band conflicts. Before we get there, I'm going to explain
band conflicts once again, because it never goes, almost nobody understands it the first time.
And that's no insult to anybody in this class. It is a complex topic. OK, different charts. I'm
not reusing the same slides from last time. So shared memory is organized into 32 packs. OK,
and this is the way you think about it. So you have a warp. You define, let's say,
shared float of file 64. This is how your memory is going to be laid out.
OK, there's index 0, index 1, index 2, and so on.
So if you want to access indices in a parallel advance, that's perfectly fine.
Each index goes to a different bank, grabs that memory. Everybody clear?
What happens if you do something like that, like this? Let's say this index here, which I've given
a few examples of. So thread ID wants index 0, that's in bank 0. Thread IDX1 also wants index 0,
that's also in bank 0. Thread IDX10 wants index 10, that's in bank 10. 16 wants 16, that's in 16.
16 wants 16, that's in 16. 30 and 31 both want 30, which is in bank 30.
What happens in this case?
Exactly. It should be fine because they're requesting the same address. See how both
are requesting 0, 2, 30, and so on? They're requesting the same address. They're requesting
the same bytes of memory. So this is fine. In this case, where we have now different,
same bank, but different memory. So you're trying to access 0 and 32, 2 and 34,
6 and 30 and 62. What happens now? This is a bank conflict now. This is a two-way bank conflict
because what's happening is these two threads are trying to access different memory, but B0
can only give one value at a time. In between the same bank, if you think of this vertically,
only one memory can cross this. If you want to think of this as a barrier or a dam or whatever,
or a tollbooth, as I mentioned last time, only one of these, any one of this, it doesn't have
to be a specific one. Any one of this can only cross one at a time. You can't have two crossing
at a time. So essentially, what happens here is 0 goes first and then 32 goes first.
So you get that in sequence. Between different banks, so for example, 0, 2, 30, they can all go
at once. There's parallelism in that. But there's no parallelism between 0 and 32.
What about something like this? This is a worst-case scenario. This is entirely sequential.
You've turned your wall from a parallel wall into a sequential wall. What does this remind you of?
What does this remind you of?
Right? What part of transform?
So if now you think of this table as your sum matrix,
you've put memory in there from the lead operation.
When you put memory in there, you put them 0, 1, 2, 3, 2, 31 at one time. Then you put 32 to 63
another time, and so on. Different wards are putting different rows. But now,
each ward is leading vertically. Each ward is leading a column.
Each ward is leading a column.
Right? So if you remember that diagram that I had with the sum matrices,
it had reading as rows and writing as columns.
So now that's essentially what you're doing. You're running into 32-way bank conflicts.
So if you take a look at the code, in our input, y represents row and x represents column and bank
number. So if you look at this, this is x, this is y. y is the row, x is the column number. But
in the output, x is the bank, x is the bank, and y is the column number. And within the ward,
this is going to change. Or this is going to stay the same, and this is going to change.
Remember, this is the bank number. So this is going to change, and you get a 32-way bank problem.
So if you take a look at this again, what you're seeing is you're reading one way,
and then you're writing another way. So that's your bank conflict. In global memory, it's perfectly
fine. But when you're reading or writing to shared memory, that's when the problem happens.
But when you're reading or writing to shared memory, that's when the problem happens.
So what we want is, when we read from input, there's no bank conflict, right? No problem.
But when we are writing, we are getting this kind of a 32-way bank problem. Worst kind possible.
You can't have a greater than 32-way bank conflict, even if you wanted to, because warp size
is 32. So how do we resolve this? So the answer is, we have to remap or change the way we are
either storing the memory, or how we are using threads.
What other ideas do you have?
In this case, the different algorithms will require different things to solve bank conflicts.
There's no one universal way to solve bank conflicts. But for transpose, there's a very
simple way to do it. We change the number of shared memory per row size. It's very simple,
but it takes a little bit of math to understand. So see how we are declaring
block size y and block size x? That's probably intuitive. That's what we would all do. Why do we
want to give extra memory? But if we change this to block size x plus 1, we are only changing the
size of the memory per row. We're not changing the number of elements or anything like that.
We're only changing the size of the shared memory. We're not even changing the size of
blocks, threads, global memory, not changing any of that. Take a look at this.
Our problem is, to step back, our problem within a block. This problem only exists within a block
because it's shared memory bank conflicts. Within a warp, our y is always going to be the same.
Assuming 32 by 32, our y is always going to remain the same. Our x is going to go from 0 to 31.
So our old index was 0 times size x, 1 times size x, all plus y. These all multiply to 32
and then you have a y as a constant. Size x is always 32 in our case.
So anything times 32 plus y will go to the y's back. That's what you have to remember.
But now if you change this to have 0 times size x plus 1, 1 times size x plus 1, because that's
what we're changing here. Now you go to different backs. Look at how you become y plus 1, y plus 10,
y plus 16. You're not changing how much shared memory we are copying. You're not changing how
many blocks we have on. You're not changing how many threads we have. You're not changing a warp
size. All we're changing is we are telling, hey shared memory, give me one extra useless element
in your memory. Why does this work? I've given you the answer. Now I'm asking you why it works.
So now if I show it to you visually, this is what has happened.
What we have said was, so now we are allocating 32 plus 1 times of memory per row. Remember that.
That's the key. But we are not changing the number of elements. We are still going to read 32 by 32
elements. All we said was, change this to x plus 1. So when you do 1 here, Smem 1, 0 is going to
come here. It's not going to change. In our old system, Smem of 1, 0 would have come here. First
row zeroth element. But now it comes here. Because there is this extra dummy element from this plus
1 guy. And that creates an offset. So we are not using that element for anything except to
avoid background. No memory gets written to it. No memory is there for me. So just to clarify,
the number of banks is always 32? Yes. The number of banks is always 32. The number of
sizes is always 32. So this is the only thing you are changing.
Now what happens is, the first row, your first row is written from 0 to 31 times.
Where is the second row written? Here. Our second row is written from D1. And then where?
Where does it go? It goes this way. But does it finish at 63 here? Or maybe I made a mistake here.
Maybe 62 here. And then it finishes here. Row 1 goes from here to here. Row 2 starts here and
goes till here. Still storing the same number of elements. What this grey element allows us to do
is offset where our 0th element of each row is within the shared memory.
The 0th element of 0 row is 0. The 0th element of row 1 is in bank 1. The 0th element of row 2
is in bank 2. And so on. So when you are trying to read all the 0th elements
to write as a column in a transpose, you are reading all different banks.
Very simple, elegant solution. Just adding two characters, plus and a 1. And it solves bank
conflicts. So all you need to do in your code is change this line to this line, plus 1.
Or it should have been flipped the other way, I think. But yeah.
OK. All right. So let's take a look at that in code.
All right. So let's make sure my CPU side is set up correctly.
Knife transpose, shared memory transpose. So let me copy this.
And then I have to set this up so that I have 32.
What happens here?
33, right? No, there's 32. It's block size. I think I add plus 1 there.
All right. So let's
I'm going to copy that exact kernel and paste it here. And all I'm going to change,
like I said before, is plus and 1. All right. Let's run this.
So we've got 75 before. We went from 37 to 75. How much are we going to go to now?
I have a compiler.
Oh. No, I don't want that. 159. Oops. Visual Studio doesn't like people. I keep forgetting
to recap that. I use Vim, by the way. If any of you use Vim, you have my support.
How did we get?
35. In Knive, we got 35. In shared memory, we got 74. In shared memory with bank conflicts,
we got 120. That's how much faster we've made our code with a few changes.
OK? And if you run this in the profiler, for the sake of time, I won't today,
you will see that the number of bank conflicts will go down to zero, literally zero. It won't
even be one. And that's how much better you'll have made your code. OK. All right.
All right. So again, a note slide, but I'll skip that for now. OK. So we are close to
production ready. We are 120 versus 140 something for device-to-device copy.
Still some way to go, right? We're not satisfied. We want that last 1% of it.
How can we improve? There's two ways. We do more work per thread, and we do loop and roll.
Why is that? Remember, I initially said, transpose doesn't have that much work to do, right?
So maybe we increase how much work a thread does, so that we reduce the number of blocks
that are waiting. And that will improve our performance. So we do that by essentially
loop and rolling, where we have one thread copy multiple elements. Or to think of it in an easier
way, one block to multiple blocks of transpose. OK? So this is kind of how it works.
You reduce the number of threads. You go from, let's say, a thread of size 4x4 to a thread of
size 4x1 in this example. And that 4x1 loops and does three more rolls. So you're doing the work
of 4x4 threads in 4x1 threads. OK? So this is done using a time and a size factor. OK?
So the walkthrough of this code is, on the host, you set the same number of blocks.
But there's a new number of threads per block, which is, let's say, reduced by a factor of time.
I won't say 4. I use 4 for this example. But of a factor of time, as we follow.
On the device, on your kernel, you want the same amount of shared memory. You don't want
to change the amount of shared memory. You still need to copy that same amount.
Compute the indices same as before. Then you need to use a loop to make sure you're doing
the multiple elements. And then you're copying the data from source to device.
So let's take a look at the code. So we still have just a look at tile and tile plus one.
Remember, we still have bank conflicts. You still want to protect from bank conflicts.
You have an input. OK? See how we use tile here? And then we have a pragma unroll. I showed this
in the last class. It tells the compiler to unroll the loop. And then you have thread id and thread
x plus k. This k is a factor for each row. And then you do y plus k here. And you get the
indices for that. Do a sync thread. You're writing to shared memory, so do a sync thread.
Change it so that now you're working on output indices. OK? Again, the pragma unroll. And now
you're going to write it out the same way. OK? So let's see how this works.
I'm going to go into Visual Studio. Let's keep having it. That's not good.
OK. It really seems on this time.
OK. Something's happening.
Yeah, it's coming back. I thought I had to restart.
This is what happens when you do live demos in class, by the way.
OK. Yeah. OK. We're back. So I'm going to shamelessly copy it because I already
have the solution. But you guys should definitely try to implement this. OK?
Copy and paste. OK? Let's make sure our CPU side is fine.
32.8. OK. Thailand side. OK. This should all be good.
Yep. All right. So we had 120 last time. How much do we go to now?
By reducing the number of threads we use by four.
I'm sure I made the same mistake of controllers.
Our side is not defined.
Let's try this one more time. I made a bad copy paste. Sorry about that.
All right. So let's see. There's a final part in transform. Let's see if we have some guesses.
We have a 90% 10x, 90% 25, 90% 30, 100% nx. That's a cheapy guess. 90% 1,000 times faster,
80% 30 times faster, 54 times faster, slower than memcpy, slower than memcpy by 30%,
so 70%, I guess, approximately. 75% n3, 50% n3, 50% n5. We can clearly see these people
copying each other. 80% n5 times, 80% n5 times. Somebody copied that. 30 to 100% faster.
All right. So let's see how much faster are we.
Device-to-device bandwidth 164. How much do we have here? 162.
I mean, within margin of error, 100%. Right? So even though we are doing a little bit more
compute for shared memory and this and that, all that latency is hidden away.
All that latency, literally all that compute we have is hidden away and we are almost equal to
device-to-device bandwidth. Okay. How many times faster are we? 1592 milliseconds,
approximately 1600 milliseconds on the CPU, 8 milliseconds on the GPU. How many times faster
is that? 200 times faster. We are 200 times faster than the CPU.
That's how we improve GPU performance. Okay. So let's take a look at a few more slides before
we take a break. So this is on my old laptop. I didn't generate new laptop numbers, but here we
had about 86 times faster than CPU. Then, oops, on a 1080 Ti, I had this on my desktop. Again,
the beefier the GPU, the faster it's going to be. 550 times faster than the CPU. I got 200 on my
laptop. A 1080 Ti, a few years older GPU, got 550 times. Okay. Of course, if you make CPU
multi-threaded, blah, blah, blah, or asterisks and whatever, but it's still going to be a lot
faster than your CPU. Okay. All right. So yeah, some of you made good predictions. Some of you
were underestimating the GPU, but we'll do this again for sure. So let's take a break.
Let's come back at 7pm. I'm giving you a slightly longer break, but I'll start sharp at 7,
so make sure you're back. And then we'll do the reduction side of the performance level. Okay.
Let's resume recording so that it's there. Okay. So the other exercise we're going to see today
is reduction. And reduction, like transpose, is a simple algorithm. We've seen it. We've
implemented it. But now we're going to see how do we go from a simple reduction
into a complex reduction. And I'm not talking about, like, if you get into scan, there's like
work-efficient scan and stuff like that, right? We're not changing the algorithm.
We're just optimizing the algorithm that we already have in a more computer-efficient way. Okay.
So let's take a look. So to recap, a reduction, at least in the case of today's
exercise, it's going to be a sum, is an operation where you take an array of elements,
then you run a binary operation on them, on each two elements, and then you get a
single element as an output. Okay. So we have two examples here. Another way to look at it,
or on the CPU side, is kind of like this, where you have this tree you're building, and
you have some identity you start with, and you keep performing the operation n number of times.
Okay. Everybody clear on this? Okay. So it's also binary in nature, right? So you can do
this not only with addition, but multiplication and, or whatever you want. And then you do that,
you kind of build this tree, and you get the result. Okay. So on the GPU side, you want to
do parallel reduction. You want the whole array being computed at the same time.
And what that gets you is to maximize the occupancy, as we call it, which is how much
time are those streaming multiprocessors busy? How much work are they doing? So you want to
hide the latency, essentially. You want to hide the memory latency. And you want to process where
the latency is. Okay. This operation is not very arithmetic intensive. Like we have seen
in work efficient and before that, there aren't many compute operations. It's just one,
one floating point operation, in this case, an add. And it's completely memory bound.
What does it mean if it's completely memory bound?
When I say memory bound, what does it mean? What? Sorry?
Bottleneck is? Memory. So what does that mean? What is the maximum performance we can get?
The memory bandwidth is the maximum performance we can get, even for this.
Even though transpose and reduction are completely different operations,
they're still limited by the same thing. So on GPU, you're going to see either
compute limited or memory limited or bandwidth related. Memory limited or bandwidth related kind
of means the same thing. But in this case, they're going to have the same theoretical max
performance. Okay. But we still want to hit that. We don't just want to settle. We still want to hit
it. So what we need, what's different from transpose is that we need a way to communicate
the partial results between blocks. If you have very, very big arrays,
not all, even the blocks, the result of the blocks also need to be computed patently.
So you need some way to do this. And a global thing is not patently. So what we do is,
essentially, we do a recursive reduction, where you do a reduce, you get all the results of the
blocks, and then you do a reduction again. But let's get to that a little later. Let's get to
the recursive part a little later. So comparing serial and parallel reduce. Serial reduce, you
get O of n, because you're doing n operations. Whereas parallel reduce, you get O of log n,
so you're reducing it significantly. And then you get runtime complexity of O of log n as well.
So if we look at the code walkthrough, this is going to be pretty much the same as
on transpose. In our first part of optimizing reduction,
we are going to do the secondary reduce on the CPU. So we are going to do
that for now. Later on, we'll see how to optimize that as well. So let's take a look at the code.
So I have number of elements set to 32 million, and the number of threads per block to 256.
I'm going to jump down to main to show you that that looks very similar to how we had it in
transpose. So for reduction state 0, we are defining the number of sets per block. This
is 1D, so you don't have the 2D thing. And then you are copying memory, allocating output, setting
the output memory to 0. 0 is identity in case of addition, so remember that. Then we are calling the
kernel. And then we are making sure we do a CPU side addition for the secondary recursive addition.
Once that happens and we verify that our goal result matches our true result, that's when we'll
start doing a performance benchmark. And see how the performance benchmark does include a memcpy
here, because it's part of the algorithm. In a lot of cases, we've told you don't do memcpy inside
the timer. In this case, it's needed, because without memcpy, you don't have the proper result.
So memcpy becomes part of the algorithm. So we do that n times, and then we get a result for it.
All right, let's take a look back at this.
So we are going to divide the code into four parts. The first part, and the fourth part,
we are actually not going to touch at all in this class. The first part is
dynamic shared memory and computed nets. That's going to be the same for all the
terms. We are not going to change that. The last part is copying the result of each block. That
is the final reduced element from each block into global value. Not going to change that,
because there's nothing to optimize that. These are the only two parts of the code we are going
to change. If these don't make sense, it will in a little bit. So let me show you what that
code looks like. Actually, let's just take zero first from there.
So state zero. Now, like we had in transport, we had naive shared, shared without back conflicts
and unrolled. In our reduction example, I'm just going to call it state zero, state one,
state two, and so on. So in state zero, the obvious way we started with, even in our lectures,
this is when I asked you how would you do reduce, this is what normal average people
would think. Okay, let's just keep adding two numbers. So to do this algorithm, this is the
code. And this is the exact code from the x-axis, so I'm not changing anything. So part one is you
do the, you declare the shared memory, and then you compute your 1 in d index. This is not going
to change whatsoever across this entire exercise. Okay, there's nothing to optimize between these
two statements. And at the last, part four is if threadIdx.x equals zero, write it to global
memory. There's nothing to optimize here. You can't get rid of this if, you can't have it passed
away from shared memory to global memory. So nothing to optimize here. All you can optimize
is between these two. So let's take a look at those. In the first part two, what we're doing
is checking the condition, and then reading the data from global memory to shared memory.
Simple operation, no problem. And then because we are reading into shared memory, call the
sync threads. And notice that I didn't put the sync threads inside this. Don't do that.
Okay, the second part is straight out of our slides from parallel adverts.
What do we have? We have c equals one, c less than blockdel.x, c times two.
For every alternate thread on the left, so you can remember this, for every alternate thread
on the left, add its right counterpart. Okay, and then we copy. Okay, so let's run this.
Okay, one, two. Let me escape that. I want to do something.
Let's see.
Okay, so what I wanted to do was I wanted to pre-run all the kernels in the background,
so I'm going to go back in a second. So while that runs, tell me over here in the slides,
what is the problem with that kernel? What are some of the problems you already see with that
kernel where we need to optimize it? We've already discussed this, so some of the ideas should be
written off. The modular? Yes, you want to get rid of the modular. What else?
What are the problems?
There is one more very easy.
This condition, right? Why are you doing c times equal to every time? So that's another.
And then what are some of the bigger changes?
So let's start with those. Let me make sure this profiling is done so that I can show it to you
in class. Okay, it wants to do a little bit more.
That'll be added.
Okay.
So many times.
Sorry, I wanted to run this so that I have the entire profile ready to show you,
so maybe it's just taking a little bit of time. Any questions in the meantime of what we're doing
here? Questions on this stuff? I'm sure all of you have written something similar in your
project too, right? Okay. Any questions about how the shared memory gets written?
Let me show you that maybe very quickly.
Yeah, so let me show you that. That's a good way to spend some time. So you see how
in... So here, unlike transport, we aren't saying anything about the amount of sharing.
There's no template. There's no number inside the bracket. So we have a new way of declaring this.
Okay. And that is seen here. Pay attention to this.
We have how many blocks. This is how we have a new number.
Size of float, size bin.in, in which case is that block size. So we're doing block size,
number of floats. That's how many bytes in here. So that goes into the amount of shared memory that
we want to add. Okay. So this is more dynamic way of allocating shared memory. It's generally...
In terms of whether one is faster than the other, no, not really. This allows you to do it at runtime,
whereas the way we were doing it with transpose was more static because everything had to be
known at compile time. Okay. The other thing you can do with this is also you can have different
shared memory. So with the old way, you could very easily do different shared memory. This
also allows you to do different shared memory if you want. Okay.
Let's check on our profiler. Yeah, it's done. Okay. So I can close that. Let me...
Okay. So I'm only going to copy state zero now.
Okay. Let's copy production state zero. Again, if you compare this code,
it's exactly what I showed in the slides, except for the comments.
Okay. Any guesses on how much faster this naive version of reduction is going to be faster than
the CPU before I run this? Yeah, Tom, five times? Only five?
Mine is only going to be five times faster than CPU for 32 million elements?
I'm going to say 25 at least. I'm pretty sure I'm off with that. All right.
CPU reduce, 102 milliseconds, 7.37 gigabytes per second on the CPU.
47 milliseconds, 28.63 times. Tom, good guess? Almost five times faster.
I think we are about four times faster. Okay. But look at this number, 28.63. How much bandwidth
did my laptop have? 140, right? We're nowhere close. We need to improve this a lot more. Okay.
So let's go back to PowerPoint and see what we have going on. So Tom suggested
modular is a problem, right? So these are numbers from GPUs I tested on,
won't go over each one of them. But the problem was, as Tom suggested, two things.
Interleaved addressing, where we are jumping around, and divergent warps. Remember that?
Divergent warps that we don't want to be doing different things in different threads?
What are the solutions? First one is easy. Remove the modular operator. Second one is remove the
divergent branches. So let's take the first one first. But before that, let's do warp divergence
for a little bit. I'm sure I'm going to be reiterating a lot of this, but essentially you
have 10, 24 threads, up to 10, 24 threads per block. You have 32 threads each. Okay. And you
want all of those threads, all of those 32 threads to execute in lockstep. You want them to execute
the same commands at the same time. So as an example, if you have, let's say my warp is eight
threads here. If they all execute the if condition at the same time, half of them go to
the first one, half of them go to the second one. That's a problem. Now threads are not doing any
work and waiting for it. Okay. Now you have a different condition where the entire warp
does one thing or the other. That's fine. Okay. All the threads in a warp should ideally be doing
the same thing at the same time. So the suggestion here is to have the threads in a block,
first of all, make the multiples of 32. And then incomplete warps are essentially unusable. So
what you want to do is you want to take all the used and done threads and put them in warps by
themselves so that they exit early. Okay. But back to reduction. So we want to do two things
first. Okay. We want to, we want to remove the module. Okay. As step one in removing divergent
clutches. And if you look at this, okay, every time for each operation, we are checking,
each time the loop goes, we are doing C less than locked into X. We are doing C times the
move. And we are doing this, which is a very, very bad operation. Okay. So how do we change this?
We do something like this. Remember, I'm only showing you part of the code. I'm not going to
show you, if I'm only showing you, for example, part three here, that means part two and part
four and part one remains the same. Okay. Okay. Let's take a look at this for loop now.
We changed this a little bit. We did C equals one, C less than block bit.x, C
multiplied equals two. This is the same as our old for loop. We are not changing this.
This is our old code here. Okay. We're not changing the for loop. What we are changing
is we are storing this index. We're using a register to do multiplication and then do a
comparison compared to using a modulo. It's checking the same condition. Okay. It's the
exact same condition, except you're removing the modulo. So if you're ever using a modulo
in a knit condition, think about how you want to change that. That's the first thing you do.
You don't even try to restructure the for loop or anything like that. The first thing you do is
how do you remove that? Okay. So this is essentially what I want you to notice here.
Okay. Let's take a look at our performance now. I'm going to go back to my reduction copy because
I don't want to code live and I'm going to copy this and paste it in my reduction.
All the CPU side for reduction is set up already. So I'm not changing any of that.
And this is purely for saving time. Okay. So we were at 25 before. How much are we going to get
to now? Just by removing the modulo. We were at 25 gigabytes per second or 28 now, and we are at 41.
One operation, we removed a modulo operation. There's nothing else we did. And we went from 28
to 41. No change in memory, how we are reading, how we are writing, no bank conflicts or anything
like that. We removed modulo. That's the only thing we did. Now you know how bad modulo is.
Okay. All right. So let's go back to our slides and some more performance numbers.
So of our two part thing, we removed modulo. We went to from 28 to 41, but there's still
a hundred more gigabytes that we need to accomplish. Okay. So our second problem
was interleaved addressing. So this is what stage one and stage two are doing.
What do we want to change this to? We saw this in class last time,
in parallel algorithms. What do we want to change this to?
We want to shift it onto the left, right? You want all the left elements to be writing
and reading from the right. Okay. You want this. Okay. So this is sequential addressing
and non-divergent warps. Okay. So to do this, what is the start? What is the start of our
We are not changing the for loop, right? We are not changing how the indexing is done.
What is the start of this for loop?
No, you're starting, this is now your step. It's not your offset, it's your step.
So what is the step in the first case?
Sorry? What if I do? No, you're starting with the largest difference and halving it every time.
So what are we starting with? Block to length? No, that's power. You get the power.
If you think there's a block size of 16, what are we starting with? What is our offset
in the block size? Yeah, block size divided by 2. So our start is block them by 2. What is our step?
In our for loop, so in for loop you have start, condition, or start, step, and end, right?
End is your condition. What is your step? What is changing in each iteration?
Yeah, so what is happening to the offset? It's going down by half every time,
right? So C equals C by 2. Is there a faster way to do this?
What is that operator called? Bit shift. Bit shift. You do that. That is way faster.
What's the end? What is the exit condition for the for loop?
So that. So C equals 1 or C greater than 0. C greater than 0 is a better condition.
And that's all we're going to change. This is the only thing we are going to change in stage 2 now.
So this is our old form, OK? Now we're changing this for C equals block them by 2, C greater than
0, C greater than greater than 1. Look at this beautiful if condition here. There are 8.x,
so it's indigent, digital compilers, and ringing power. If you compare these two,
even stage 1, it's an improvement because now you're reducing how many compute operations
you're doing. That's way better than stage 0, which had a modular limit, OK?
Any questions about this? Any questions about this operation and why we did it?
OK. Let's see how much performance improvement we're getting.
Reduction, stage 2.
All right. We were at 41. Any guesses how much we go to now?
Now we are changing how we are reading and writing memory, by the way,
or at least in shared memory. How much do we go to? So we went from 28 to 38 this time to 50.
So with that margin of error, another 25% improvement. How many times faster are we
than the CPU? So CPU is 183 milliseconds. We are already at 27, right? So we are making big steps,
all right, but we are not satisfied. We need to go fast.
All right. So now what's the problem? We did fix our addressing. We fixed modular operation.
What are some of our problems? Is bank conflict the problem?
How many of you think bank conflict is a problem? Or don't think bank conflict is a problem?
OK. How many of you think memory coalescing is a problem?
OK. How many of you think that the problem is thread tap usage?
For instance, what's the problem with thread usage?
Talking about these threads, right? So this thread, nothing happens. These threads, nothing
happens. That's what for instance, let's try to highlight. That is a problem. Let's try to solve
it. So in stage two, in the first iteration, already half the threads are not used.
OK. So remember in transpose how we, using tile, we made one row do the work of four rows,
right? And that improved performance, that it got us to 100% bandwidth.
Here, the reverse is happening. Half the threads are not doing anything.
At least in transpose, all the threads were actually doing something.
Here, in the first iteration itself, half the threads are not doing anything.
Second iteration, three quarters are not doing anything. So as the number of iterations increase,
the number of threads as a percentage, most of them are not doing anything.
That's too much wasted work. The warp, some of the warps will exit, but not all of them. OK.
So let's, how do we improve this? So the first thing we do is let's have a warp type.
How do we have a warp type? What do we need to do?
We use some shared memory to store some data. OK. This is called a shared memory.
This is called add-on load. What we essentially are going to do is,
now that we've halved our threads, so let me actually go back to this image.
OK. So what was happening here is we launched with 16 threads, OK, and each thread read one
element here. OK. We know that's useless because already 16 threads are doing just a read and
nothing else. What if we don't launch these threads at all and just make these elements
or these threads also read this? Why not? Right? Each thread can do one more read. It's not the
worst thing in the world. So that's what we want to do. So what it does is it's not increasing our
global memory usage. Remember that. We were reading that same amount of data anyway. We're
just making threads reread different parts of the global memory. OK. But now that we are going to
make the same thread read global memory, why don't we just add it when we're reading it? Right?
So let's take a look at that. This is kind of what I'm talking about.
The first few elements I'm going to read anyway. Maybe you store them in shared memory or a
register. It doesn't really matter. When you read these elements, instead of giving them more memory,
just add it in. Right? Why do we want to put these in separate registers or separate shared memory?
Kind of pointless, right? Because all you're going to do is add them back in. So why not add
them in when you load? This is called add on load. OK. So in terms of code, all we're going to
change is, instead of having this if IDX less than n read global memory into shared memory,
now what we're going to have is open the same condition, read the first element into shared
memory, same as before. See this line and see this line. But now, if IDX was
blocked and not active less than n, so you're moving that to the second half,
read the global memory, not a different shared memory index. You just plus equal it.
So you're getting rid of one iteration now. Because you're having the number of elements you have.
OK. So any questions about this?
Any questions about why this works and how this is making an impact?
Yes. Yes. That still happens. So what we're solving here, if I can go back a few
slides, is, look, as a total number, this is the majority of our message. That's literally
half our message. So we are solving this first one by doing add on load. We are solving this
first part. But by solving this first part, we are getting rid of half of our problem ID.
And that's going to be the maximum chunk of it. So any other thoughts on this?
What do we do after this?
So we are doing add on load for two things, right? What do we do next?
We are doing add on load for two elements, or one element, and then you're adding it.
In terms of optimization, what do we do?
Instead, in terms of getting rid of that, we only get rid of the first half.
What would we do if we wanted to do more?
Why don't we do one more add on load?
So we are doing add on load for two elements, and then you're adding it to the first half.
Get rid of more threads.
So instead of doing a single add on load, so this is a single add on load, right?
Why don't we do multiple add on loads? We are not using more global memory.
We are not using more shared memory. We are just doing more add on loads and reducing
the number of threads we need for reading global memory.
That's the biggest change we are making.
Yes, exactly. We are unrolling how we are doing in our stages.
Okay, so let's take a look at it.
So what I'm going to do now is, instead of a single add by itself, we are going to do a single
add within the loop, and then have a counter called tile that does it in the loop.
So this is what our code is actually going to look like.
We're going to start with shared memory of thread ID x.x0, that's identity.
This loop, very simple, but we have a stage three tile.
That tile is going to tell us how many adds on load we want to do,
preferably a power of two.
So you want it to be two, four, et cetera.
And now we have this condition, same as before in a single add on load,
except we do seed and plot them, and then we are doing just a bunch of add on loads.
Okay, everybody clear on why this works?
So if I go back a bunch of slides...
One more.
So what we're essentially doing is, in a single add on load,
these elements will load and add these elements, okay?
That's a single add on load.
What we want to do with tile is, why stop here?
Why not have these elements load and add these elements?
These four elements load and add these four elements, and so on.
So you're removing a bunch of iterations there, okay?
So the secondary for loop you have in part three,
essentially gets rid of the for loops,
and reduces the number of threads per block you need.
So let's jump forward again.
I think we were here.
Okay.
So I'm only going to edit part two now, I'm not editing part three.
So let's take a look at Visual Studio,
production, stage three, and I'm going to copy it from tile, by the way.
Okay.
So let's do tile equals two first.
So tile equals two means add on load one time, okay?
So we are only getting rid of the first interleave.
How much do we go?
We went from 40 to 75, or 73, 70, within margin of error, right?
Almost doubling our speed, because we removed that first element.
What does that mean?
We essentially reduced half of our research time by doing that, okay?
But why stop there?
We did it in the for loop, right?
And we want to test our performance.
I'm going to change this to four.
So now we are doing four add on loads.
Now we reduce two levels, essentially.
So let's see how this does.
What is this number?
127.
And I didn't even change anything.
I just changed the number of adds on loads.
I didn't change anything about the algorithm.
I just changed how we are utilizing our threads in a useful manner.
You don't want a thread just reading and going away.
That's kind of pointless.
You want the threads to actually be going somewhere.
And now we go from 40 to 127 by doing adds on loads.
Yeah, pretty much.
So that's kind of what I was going to get at.
Yes, you could take this number all the way to 2 power 10.
And that'll be 1024.
You could do that.
But at some point, you're going to have diminishing returns.
So look, we hit 156 now.
So that's like 96%, 98% of memcpy performance.
So yes, your adds on loads will get you closer.
Depending on the algorithm, yes.
So you don't want to be doing too much work,
have too much branching, and stuff like that.
You also want to have enough warps to replace your memory reads.
Remember that?
So you want to have at least a level of compute.
You don't want to have memory things holding up your compute side.
So yes, it does make a difference.
OK, all right.
All right, so that performance that we're getting
is similar to what I've seen on other GPUs as well.
So now, I did this as well.
I went from 1, 2, 4, 8.
But one thing that you should see is, even with all of these adds on load,
the last warp is still divergent.
Right?
No matter how many adds on load you do,
no matter how we've changed the algorithm,
the last warp is still exactly that diagram that I showed you before.
Within the block, as you have, let's say, 256 adds, you have 8 warps.
Some of those warps will exit because all the adds are done.
But within the last warp, as you're doing 32 to 16, 16 to 8, 8 to 4 elements,
that warp is going to diverge.
OK?
So what's a possible solution to that?
Because if we are able to improve that last warp performance,
we are still going to improve the GPU algorithm.
So that's kind of the motivation there.
How do we extract that last, to quote National Treasure Nicholas Cage,
how do you extract that last full measure of devotion from your algorithm?
And this is kind of what I'm trying to do.
And this is kind of a complicated thing, but it kind of extends what we've been doing until now.
Here's what have we done in stage 3.
Unroll that operation, right?
Can we unroll it on the warp level?
We want to unroll it now at the warp level.
Let's just see how we do that.
So now I'm going to split Part 3 into two parts to explain what's under this.
OK?
The first part is everything under C greater than 32.
That is, everything until we have multiple warps in a block remains the same.
No difference whatsoever.
When we hit one warp, that's when we want to do something different.
Is this clear?
Just the split up of this.
I want to make sure everybody's clear with that.
As long as we have multiple warps, we do what we've been doing before.
No change.
Once this condition exists, that means the number of threads are less than 32.
Or 32 or less, which means one more.
OK?
So this is where we are going to do something different.
We're going to do something different.
We're going to introduce a new function called warpReduce.
So when we have one warp, we're going to call this new function called warpReduce,
and we're going to give it the shared memory and the thread IDX.
OK?
In this function, we're going to do something like this.
This is like almost magical.
The beauty of how it works is that we're going to have a new function called warpReduce.
Almost magical.
The beauty of how it works is amazing.
What we're going to do is, firstly, we're going to have this keyword called volatile
assigned to the shared memory.
What volatile does is, it tells the compiler and the GPU,
I'm doing something in very normal speech.
It's saying, I'm doing something crazy with my memory.
I know what I'm doing.
Don't try to be super smart about it.
OK?
So that it doesn't reorder things.
It doesn't mess things about.
This is very detrimental code.
Don't touch my code.
Don't optimize it.
That's what this volatile is.
OK?
Now, what we're going to do is, look at this unroll.
Remember, this is only happening for one warp.
And the first warp.
Only the first warp.
Not the last warp.
Not the middle warp.
Only the first warp.
0 to 31 threads.
OK?
What we're doing is complete unroll.
This is still in parallel.
Each thread that is between 0 and 31, go add 0.
In this case, it will become 32 to 63.
OK?
Once that is done, all threads, 0 to 31, go add, in this case, what is it?
16 to 48 or 47.
Something seems wrong, right?
OK, let's do one more.
All threads, 0 to 31, add 8 to 40 or 39.
Something seems weird, right?
So let me write that down so that it's easy for you.
So we'll run this.
OK?
And this is the same for all.
This indexing doesn't change.
We're not exiting any thread.
There's no return.
There's no if conditions.
Nothing.
So this remains the same.
OK?
Now, on the first line, we have PID plus 32.
So this goes from 32 all the way to 63.
OK?
Same thing here.
This goes.
Now we have 16, right?
So 16 goes to 47.
8 goes to 39.
4, 35.
2, 33.
And then 1, right?
32.
Have you ever seen indexing like this?
What's the problem with this?
Or what is odd about indexing like this?
OK, let's come back to this.
I'm writing to shed memory.
What am I not doing?
Why am I not doing sing threads?
Why do we need sing threads?
Let's start here.
Tom?
Yeah, exactly.
We use sing threads because within a block,
we can have different warps executing at different times.
So sing threads tells all the warps,
hey, get to this point, and then we'll continue on again.
How many warps do we have now?
One, we've guaranteed that.
By this previous condition, we've
guaranteed we only have one warp left.
Anything else will be like, oh, I
don't need to do that work.
I'm going to exit.
In this point, there's only one warp left.
So no need of sing threads.
First, we've gotten rid of that condition.
Why does this condition work?
Why do these indexes work?
First, tell me, if we did that in a normal algorithm,
not here, if we did that in production as a whole,
what would be the problem of that kind of indexing?
What would be the problem of reading and using that kind of indexing?
Because remember, your read indexes are 0 to 31.
Let's take this example.
Your read indexes are 0 to 31.
Your write indexes are 4 to 35.
What happens?
Not time complex, but close.
Race conditions.
You could have race conditions, right?
Or read over write, write over read, whatever it might be.
Why does this work?
I'm not saying race conflicts and write over reads are gone there.
But this still works.
Why does it work?
Imagine that diagram earlier, the arrow diagram and the sense.
Why does this work?
This works because the useful part of shared memory,
where we are writing things at each step, are still consistent.
But the part where these things overlap is all useless to us at that point.
Do I have a diagram?
No, I don't have a diagram.
So I'm going to step back a little bit.
Actually, I do have a diagram.
So let's say we are at S-MEM, TID plus 2.16.
What we are essentially going to do is, for all the times
we are going to be adding an offset and saving it, right?
So let's take this step for example.
We do the first one.
And even in this, even in this step, even in this stage,
there are these threads, even though I haven't shown it,
are going to want to write to this.
We don't have any if conditions here.
So we are going to be adding an offset and saving it, right?
And they'll copy from somewhere here, and they'll try to write.
But what do we know about this memory now?
It's never used in the future.
So we don't care about overwriting this.
So once you have this, you can actually write to this.
So once you have, in this stage, it will be like plus 8, right?
So we are doing TID, TID plus 8.
So for 33, you're adding offset of 8.
16, you'll put that here, OK?
So you're doing that.
So you're doing TID plus 8.
Then you're doing TID plus 4.
0 adds 5.
1 adds 6.
Sorry, 1 adds 5.
2 adds 6.
3 adds 7.
This part of the memory is still consistent, OK?
So we're all good.
57 is going to try to add 16 and write it to this 57, even though I haven't updated it.
57 will try to add 16.
121 will try to add 66.
113 will try to add 69.
We are not preventing those.
We're not stopping them.
We're not putting an if condition.
The fact is, we don't care about that memory.
Once we've read that, at that stage, we don't care about it anymore.
That's what this algorithm does.
Then that's why we are able to unroll it at the walk level.
And because we are able to do it like this, no more walk divergence.
We may be doing useless work.
We may be, this 57 may try to add 16, which is fine.
Because we are doing it in a walk level.
That compute is going to happen anyway, OK?
It's just that we don't care about the result.
And we are not spending more time doing it.
That's the key thing.
And that will help improve performance.
So let's see how this works, OK?
So I'm going to go back to Visual Studio.
I'm going to go to Reduction.
So that WordProduce is already copied.
I'm going to
copy stage four.
And so that we are comparing apples to apples, I'm going to make stage four or stage three
also tile equals two.
So now we have stage three tile two and stage four tile two.
So that we are comparing apples to apples.
Let's see how that performs.
Now, this is kind of the last 2%, 3% of performance.
So you may or may not see a huge improvement.
But let's see what it is.
Oh, pretty good.
So stage three was 74.
Stage five, just by WordProduce.
Remember, we did an unroll and then we did a WordProduce.
And we are at 125.
The tile IDs are the same.
Now let's change the tile IDs and see how much we get.
So I'm going to make stage four tile also four.
Stage four tile four.
And then stage three tile also four.
Let's see how this works.
I don't remember these results yet.
And this year, I don't have a new GPU.
So I don't know what to expect.
OK, so stage three now became 137, which we kind of expected from last time.
But stage four also improved for 131.
So it's not kind of in vain.
We are making significant and noticeable improvements by extracting that last mile
of performance as well.
OK.
But I'm greedy, right?
I like performance.
Why should I stop there?
OK, so those are some numbers from all the GPUs.
But what does stage four require you to do?
Remember, in stage three, there's still a for loop.
OK, let me bring up stage four core conditions.
So this stage four, we have a for loop here and we have a for loop here.
And we have these conditions all over the place.
So what does what produce inspire you to do?
You want to get rid of these conditions?
Is that what you want to do?
Let's try to do that.
So what if we get rid of the entire for loop itself?
OK, so we know for a fact that GPU block sizes are 512 for older GPUs than 24 for modern.
So there's only a limited number of conditions we have to write.
And if we make block sizes power of 2, or more preferably multiple of 32,
then we can take advantage of this.
But one tricky thing here is that block sizes are not known at compile time.
So if we can make block sizes known at compile time,
and this kind of stretches the boundary of what we can do,
then what we can do is we can use templates for the block size.
And that means that the compiler will know what our block size is.
So let's see how that works.
OK, so let's see how that makes a difference.
So if I know my block size at compile time, not at run time, this is what I do.
I've completely unrolled this, OK?
If block size greater than or equal to 32, never true by today.
Do that.
Again, inspired from our loop operator, there's the same line,
except with a different offset.
If block size greater than 512, same thing.
Just do the same thing over and over.
Now there's a question there.
Have I committed a cardinal sin?
What have I done?
It's a very, very, very readable, beautiful code.
But what sin have I committed?
Sixth sense.
There's a sixth sense inside the condition.
Why is it not a cardinal sin, and why am I OK with it?
All the threads are not going in here.
So for example, if we have 1024 threads, OK, not all the threads might go in here.
But there's one other catch that will make that true.
No.
Remember this?
This template does not have compile time.
So the kernels can generate different versions for different block sizes.
If you get different block sizes here, if you get 1024 or 512 here, OK,
the kernel will generate, the compiler will generate different versions of this kernel
in runtime code that have different sections of the sorting.
So for example, if you pass threads equals 256, for example, OK,
it knows in the kernel, it knows block size greater than 1024,
never true, because the template you plot, this block size here is my template.
This threads that are passing here is block size here.
So if I already tell my kernel, block size is 256,
this will never be true, the compiler will just get rid of this code.
Block size is 256 greater than or equal to 512, false, it will get rid of this code.
Now this line, block size 256 greater than or equal to 256, yes, true.
But what it will do is, this is always true now.
So it'll just get rid of this if block and just leave this here.
So that's the compiler level optimization we are taking into account here.
So this will, this inference is not a sin by itself,
because of what we are doing on the templates level.
I would not recommend using if conditions inside of FragModel.
But it's possible.
It has to be that the if condition has to be resolved at compiler.
That's the key thing.
So then we don't probably get rid of the if condition?
Yes, because...
Without FragModel or they have access?
No, there's no FragModel.
This is harder to import.
Okay, so yeah, essentially this is the explanation for that.
Because all of these conditions in red are evaluated at compile time,
the compiler kind of gets rid of them.
And if any of them are false, it'll get rid of the code inside of them as well.
Okay, so let's take a look at how this code actually looks in Visual Studio.
So I'm going to go into reduction and copy this.
Okay, so let's take a look at this.
The copy part is the same.
The add on load, I'm not changing.
The add on load remains the same.
But now you have these if conditions here that are getting resolved.
So block size, if I scroll up a little bit, is my template.
Okay, so all of these conditions are known at compile time.
So the compiler can get rid of them if needed.
And then for the last part, which is the single warp stage,
that's when we do the warp reduce.
All the other code exits.
So let's take a look at how that works.
We have tile equals four.
So I'm going to make this four as well.
And let's run.
So let's see how this performs.
We got 151 and 154.4.
Close enough, I would say.
I'll put that in within margin of error.
So now you know, at this point, you know, okay,
we are getting to diminishing returns.
If you're trying to convince your manager,
hey, let me work on reductions, you're going to get a no,
this is good enough, start doing something else.
So let's reduce our add on loads and try one last time.
Okay.
All right.
So we have, when we get tile equals two,
then we got 140 and 140.
So the difference is slightly larger.
As you increase the number of adds on loads,
the closer you're getting into full unrolling anyway.
So that's what this is doing.
Okay.
So I think that satisfied my hunger for performance.
So here are some numbers from older GPUs.
These are the charts.
So again, look at it.
I'm doing better now.
Look at my chart.
Very clearly, elements versus time, the world is better.
Time in milliseconds.
Not MS, not just MS, time in milliseconds.
And there's a clear progression.
Numbers in there, 0.25, 0.5, 1 million, 2 million, 4 million.
I'm not putting six zeros there and making my audience
talk about how many zeros there is.
This is numbers in English.
Just put some numbers.
Makes it very, very easy to read.
Okay.
All right.
So there was one thing, there was one thing that we skipped.
There was one assumption we made at the start of reduction
that we were like, oh, we'll take a look at this later.
What was that?
What about reduction did we skip?
Oh, not the algorithm.
But I did say that we are not going to look at something
for now at that time.
And what was that?
I said we are only going to do a single pass reduction, right?
The secondary pass would be on the CPU.
Remember that?
So the way to optimize this further
is we call reduction again.
So for example, if we launch 32 million elements
with blocks of 256 each, how many blocks do we have?
So let's do calculator because even I need one for this.
I have 32 times 1024 times 1024, that's 32 times 1024.
Times 1024.
So that I clearly can't type, can I?
32 times 1024 times 1024.
That's 32 million elements.
I have 256 threads per block.
I have 131,000 block results that now I need to reduce again.
So that's what recursive reduction comes in.
If we have 131,000 elements sitting on the GPU
that we until now have been copying over to the CPU
and then doing single threaded CPU reduction,
would it instead be better to do 131,000 reduction
on the GPU?
We are not copying any additional memory now.
It's already on the GPU.
We just have to run the process.
And then we copy 131,000 divided by 256,
probably like 512 elements back.
It's going to be faster.
And then you can do 512 threads on the CPU.
So essentially what we do is,
and I'll go through this quickly,
is let me...
So I have this here.
So what I'm going to show you is more on this.
Yeah.
So what we're going to do is we're going to create these wrappers.
So for state zero, I'm just going to call it a state zero wrapper.
And what I'm going to do is if elements,
the number of resulting elements,
the number of elements that are going to be
resulting elements,
the number of block results is less than one block.
Until that happens,
I'm just going to copy memory to...
I'm going to do a recursive reduction.
Okay.
So let's go back to our example.
So we have 32 times 24 times 1024.
We have that many elements.
That's greater than one block, obviously.
So we are going to say,
okay, launch my kernel,
which reduces to divided by 256.
We get that many elements after the first pass of reduction.
Is that greater than one block?
Yes.
I'm going to divide it again by 256.
So now I'm doing a reduction on the GPU a second time.
512 threads.
Is that less than one block?
Yes, possibly.
If your block size is 1024.
So that's what it means.
So we won't do reduction once,
we'll do reduction twice
so that the amount of data we copy from the GPU
and the amount of CPU reduction we have to do is reduced.
Okay.
So for the sake of simplicity,
what I'm going to do is take this entire file
and I'm going to post it in my reduction
so that I can show you how much better it is.
Okay.
So I'm still running 1024.
Let's see what our tile is.
So it's stage two,
stage three tile is two,
stage four tile is two
and stage five tile is two.
Okay. Let's run that.
So remember now our algorithms are the same.
We're just running reduction multiple times if needed.
Okay.
All right.
So it's kind of the same,
not too much faster.
Okay.
But what happens when,
for example,
we increase this to 128 million elements.
Okay.
So now we have,
now this recursive reduction starts making a difference
when we have many elements
because our CPU time will increase.
So now our stage four and five are basically the same
and stage three has also increased.
So now if you're starting a total time for GPU
and CPU reduction,
this time will start looking a lot better
for elements that are much larger.
Okay.
So now if we take a look at also,
I don't have all the numbers for my latest slide,
but single GPU pass plus CPU reduction
versus recursive GPU passes plus CPU reduction.
There's a clear increase there.
It may not be much,
it's still about 10%,
but it's still valid improvements.
And then on a 1080Ti it's a lot better.
It's up to 60% better in this case,
30% better in other cases.
And here's the chart for how that looks.
And now if we compare side by side,
single pass versus recursive reduction,
here's how you see it.
So the left two columns are single pass
for 32 million elements.
The right two green columns
are 128 million single and recursive.
Lower is better.
So you can clearly see how much difference it's making.
It's a lot different for stage zero
because there's a lot more improvement that we had.
And as you get to stage five,
as a percentage similar,
but diminishing in terms of numbers.
Okay.
Quiz question before we end the class.
Who knows the difference between these?
So this is easy, right?
So this one is easy.
Data can't change and the pointer to the data can't change.
Okay.
This one, float star constex is a constant pointer.
The pointer can't change,
but the value can change.
Okay.
The top one is the opposite.
Const float star is the pointer can change,
the data and the pointer can't change.
Okay.
So make sure you remember that.
There's a neat trick.
Also because it affects the compiler.
If you have your compiler,
const float star constex,
it will make a lot of assumptions
that will improve your performance.
Because it will cache everything.
It knows the data can't change.
So as soon as you copy it to the GPU,
it already pushes it to L2.
So that because it knows whenever you launch a kernel
and you're using this kind of addressing,
it knows that the data is going to remain constant
and it can apply those optimizations.
So make sure you're using some form of this
depending on what addressing you're doing.
Last thing is this restrict flag.
It's really cool because
what it allows you to tell your compiler
is my memory doesn't overlap.
So if you think about matrix multiplier reduction,
matrix transpose,
you're giving your kernels multiple pointers, right?
You're giving it addresses.
But there's no way for the kernel or the compiler
to know that those addresses don't overlap
in your compute, right?
You can access the entire memory
if you want it with that pointer.
You can do minus, you can do plus, you can do strides.
You can do whatever you want in the kernel
and you can make two pointers overlap with each other, okay?
Restrict tells your compiler that,
hey, I've taken all the precautions
to make sure that A and B don't overlap.
And that again will allow your compiler
to improve performance and reduce a bunch of checks
that it's going to be doing.
Remember, these compilers and these systems
have a lot of error correction built into them, okay?
By passing flags like restrict,
tells the compiler that,
hey, I'm a good programmer.
I've taken care of my memory.
You can skip a bunch of checks
and that improves performance.
Realistically, it improves performance, okay?
So essentially the conclusion to today's performance lab
is that while you may start thinking
about parallel programming naively,
you very quickly should run the profiler,
understand what your kernel is doing,
understand what the bottlenecks are
and just keep running it.
Understand where the complex situations are.
Try to think about your for loops,
your if conditions, loop unrolling,
how much work your thread is doing,
all of those kinds of things
to unlock the maximum performance from your GPU.
And templates are always there to help.
So that's graceful.
So a few more guides.
So of course the CUDA programming guide,
all of you should be referring to it.
There's a best practices.
And this was a talk in 2019 given by NVIDIA at GTC
that essentially walked through all the profiler steps
and information about the profile and stuff.
So it's very good.
Definitely take a look at it.
I always refer to it before this class.
So make sure you take a look
and then run your path traces to it as well.
The path trace, of course,
is a much more complex algorithm.
So you may not get that much useful information,
but definitely go back and try to run project two through it.
And you'll see a lot of benefit in that.
So that's it for today's class.
I hope you enjoyed improving that performance.
And you'll be inspired to do a lot more in your own projects.