All right, let's, let's get started with our first question.
This is our first proper lecture.
So what I'll be doing over the next probably an hour will be giving an introduction to
CUDA, which is what we use for at least the first three projects.
So to give you, to give you a history of, you know, different graphics APIs, 2001, 2002,
there wasn't even thing called GPU programming.
It was called general purpose GPU.
This was well before, you know, modern graphics cards were a thing, they were more like VGA
cards and stuff.
And they were used for how, how essentially you could use that hardware to do different
kind of computing.
2007 is when NVIDIA released CUDA.
And that's where, you know, the, the real shift in GPU programming started.
And then 2008, Chronos released OpenCL, which was an open standard for compute devices across
all manufacturers.
2011, WebGL came out that introduced that onto the web.
2013, OpenGL released compute shaders.
Now you can do compute shaders within OpenGL, I believe it was 4.3 back then.
2015, Vulkan and Spirry came out, which allowed compute shaders on, on, on Vulkan and combining
OpenCL and all that started happening.
2018 was RTX GPUs.
That's when ray tracing became much more popular, at least real-time ray tracing.
2019, Apple released Metal.
And then 2021, 22, which is now, is people are working on web, web GPU.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
As I said in the beginning, you know, there are no stupid questions, go ahead and ask.
Yeah, so there's, there's different levels, right?
So let me, let me give you an example.
What's your favorite programming?
C++, I mean, that's my favorite.
When you're writing C++, what's, what does the computer know?
You know C++, what does the computer know?
Exactly, you know, you know, zeros and ones.
Zeros and ones talk to probably assembly.
The assembly language talks to the operating system.
Operating system probably talks to the compiler.
And then that talks to your code.
So there's different levels of abstraction that's going on.
When it comes to graphics APIs, whether that's, you know, general purpose, more like CUDA
or like Vulkan, they're essentially ways to talk to the hardware
to get pixels rendering on the screen.
And you could, if you wanted, write assembly language for GPUs,
but nobody's going to try and do that, that's failed.
So we built APIs on one or the other.
There's more advanced APIs like Vulkan, which make you do very explicit
decision-making on how your memory and your compute flows, essentially.
And there are more implicit APIs, like WebGL is wrapped up in a lot of useful things.
And then even on top of that, you may have other libraries,
like Three.js is a WebGL-based rendering engine.
Or you may have Unreal Engine or Unity,
which are game engines built on these APIs that abstract them even further.
So what we are going to be looking at in this class is a few different ways
of GPU programming about how do you take code
and make it do really complex and amazing things in a very parallel way.
A simple way to describe it, and I'm sure I have examples,
is if I were to, say, add a million elements,
you're probably going to write for i equals zero, i less than a million,
add them up. We don't do that on GPUs.
What we do on GPUs is what I'm going to show you today.
Any other questions on this?
Most likely no, because they use a lot less power.
So they have GPUs.
They have the same architecture as your big GPUs,
but they probably have a lot less power.
They have a lot less performance.
So it's all about scale at that point.
Even between a laptop and a desktop GPU,
what we'll probably see in probably next lecture or maybe after that
is about how the scale between different GPUs changes.
Yeah.
Now, these days, it's called system on a chip.
I think what I was trying to say before was
what the older generation of GPUs,
they're more called fixed functions where they have one job to do.
You give them pixels and they're end of pixels.
I'm simplifying quite a bit, but that's essentially what it is.
Modern GPUs have a lot more that they can do,
a lot more programming you can do with it to do amazing things,
not just rendering pixels on screen,
but running machine learning algorithms,
running scientific simulations and all of that.
The output doesn't have to be visual.
It can be a lot more than that.
Yes.
You get more programmability on your phones.
I'm sure Gabe Duggani, when he comes,
is going to enlighten us, including myself on that.
I'm probably not an expert on mobile GPUs.
I know it from a high level, but I'm looking forward to that guest lecture
to learn myself.
What other questions do you have?
Okay.
Let's get some terminology out of the way.
When we talk about GPU programming,
we are going to use these terms all the time.
First is the host, and that is typically your CPU.
Common languages, you write this in C++,
maybe Python, Java, whatever else you want,
but most of the projects in this class, at least, are going to be C, C++.
The second term is device, which is used for the GPU.
When you're writing programs, when you're writing your code,
you're not going to be calling it CPU and GPU.
You're going to be calling it most likely host and device,
which we'll see as later on.
Host and device have separate not only processors,
but also memory.
You actually have to explicitly copy it from one place to the other.
A CUDA program likely contains CPU processing
as well as GPU processing in it.
The other term to know is a kernel.
Now, if you've taken an operating systems class or something like that,
you know kernel has a different meaning there.
In GPU programming, a kernel is a data parallel function
where you're writing your code once,
but it's executing for a lot more data
and then a lot of it in parallel.
If you've done shader programming, this is very close
to what a shader is in OpenGL, WebGL, Vulkan,
those kind of things.
A CUDA kernel is executed by n times.
When I was giving the earlier example of how do you add
a million elements, on a CPU you do
for i equals zero, i less than a million.
On GPU, you do it a little different.
On the CPU, what you do is you do a kernel launch,
and that's the bottom half of our mini program.
On top is the kernel itself.
The first thing to know about kernel
is that it has that underscore underscore global
specifier, which tells the compiler
and the runtime that this function runs
on the GPU and it runs in parallel.
That's first.
Everything other than that is standard C code,
where you have pointers and other things.
The first line you see in there is
int i equals thread IDX.
Thread IDX.x is a way to denote
which thread you're running on.
You're going to be literally running millions of threads at a time.
These thread IDX, and we'll get into it
in a little bit in deeper detail,
is a way to identify which thread you're running on.
That will help you identify what data you need
to work on.
When we get to that third line there, which is the actual addition,
what you're seeing throughout this program is that there's no
for loop anywhere.
Essentially becomes implicit because you're launching this kernel
that works on many, many threads.
Now you go from O of N to O of 1
essentially when you do GPU programming.
The normal
flow of a GPU program looks like this,
where you have some serial code where you're setting things up.
You launch a kernel. It does a lot of things in parallel.
You maybe have some more CPU code that's doing something
with the result of that, and then maybe you launch more kernels
and repeat that kind of thing. At a very, very high level,
this is what happens in a CUDA program.
We spoke about threads. Now, how are threads organized?
If you have millions, if not billions of threads,
you need some way to organize them.
Threads are grouped
in what are known as blocks.
Blocks are an array of threads, and that can be arranged
1D, 2D, or 3D.
All the blocks that you launch with a single kernel
will have the same number of threads.
Then groups of blocks are then
called a grid. Grid is more of a
system-level concept. We don't necessarily program
grids by themselves. We program more on block
level. Within each block,
threads can synchronize. They can share some shared memory
and talk to each other, which is not
necessarily possible at a grid level.
Visually, this is what it looks like.
You have posts on the left side
where you're running your code and launching your kernels.
Then each time you launch a kernel, it's going to be
launching your blocks on the GPU
arranged as threads. Each block has
its own indices, and then within each block, the threads
have their own indices.
Another way to think about them in each block
is the threads can be arranged as a vector, as a
matrix, or as a volume. Most of the times
you're going to be dealing with vectors or matrices.
Rarely will you ever get into volumes.
Any questions on this so far?
Okay.
Like I said before,
when you're trying to launch these many threads, it's
important to know what data you're supposed to be working on.
If you get the
index, you're going to be working on the wrong data.
Multiple threads might be working on the wrong data.
One of the most critical things you're going to be
learning is how do you arrange your threads and make
each thread do the right thing.
A core part of that is the
thread IDX identifier, which
essentially is a three-component identifier.
You have .X, .Y, and .Z
that tell you the index of the thread within a block.
Your block, if you have, let's say,
512 threads,
will go from 0 to 511.
Or if you have, let's say, 16 by 16,
then it will go between 0 and 15 and 0 and 15 in each
axis.
Looking at a quick example, this is what we would
structure it as.
We would call the kernel with how many
blocks you want and how many threads you want.
Let's say in this example you have one block and you
have two-dimensional block of threads.
Maybe think like 10 by 10 or whatever your favorite
number is.
If you're using that to add a vector, you're going to
convert that into a 1D index using that formula
before.
Block dim is another identifier that essentially
tells you how big each block is.
Again, because we're doing a lot of this programmatically
at runtime, we're able to pick what our block size is.
We'll be looking at how to pick the right block size
later on.
The important thing to note here is these APIs and
runtimes allow us to control and get information about
how big our block size is and stuff like that.
Any questions on threads?
Yes.
Sorry.
Here we're specifying
all of the grids that we have available.
One block.
Then threads per block, we're specifying that it is a
2D block or are all blocks like...
The first part of what you said was
right.
What I'm trying to show you here is that in this
vector add, I am specifically launching one block
that is of size n by n.
For example, if I pick n equals 16,
I'm launching one block with 256 threads.
That's it.
No more, no less.
I can choose whatever n I want.
For this slide, what I want you to know is
if I launch one block with 256 threads for this
terminal, I have 256 threads
that I can do work with.
If I wanted to change that to 512,
I have to call, let's say, 32 by 16.
In this example,
it's purely to show how you arrange a block and a
thread in an API call rather than
understanding how many you should launch,
which we'll get to in a little bit.
Go ahead.
The more on the hardware level,
I think it's too early
to explain that. I don't want to confuse you, but
we'll see how they become a concept.
That's a typo.
That should be matrix addition.
My bad.
Yeah?
Good question.
Where do you think it is?
We will get to universal memory,
but most of the time
I would not say actually use that.
It's a concept for people who don't know GPU programming,
if I'm being clear.
The memory that we have here
is a pointer
in memory on the GPU.
If you try to use A, B, and C on the CPU side,
you'll get garbage because you can have the same
pointer IDs on CPU and GPU,
but they point to completely separate memories.
For example, you can have Walnut Street
in every single city in the US,
but Philadelphia is different from Walnut Street in New York.
That's an important concept.
Any other questions?
I did change the typo, by the way.
Right.
I haven't gotten to memory yet,
but I will get to that.
Any other questions?
All right.
A thread block
is essentially a group of threads,
and it does have limits.
You will see me refer to G80 and GT200 quite a bit,
but be pretty assured that none of you
will ever encounter that hardware ever again.
G80 and GT200 were the first two or three generations
of GPUs that NVIDIA released,
and those have lower specs just because they had lower
number of transistors.
They could do lesser things.
They had 512 threads, but most modern GPUs
have a block limit of 1024.
All threads in a block
reside on the same processor core.
When you think of GPUs,
they're not necessarily one execution unit,
but they have what are called streaming multiprocessors
that allow you to execute those.
The key thing to remember from this slide is that
threads in a block are kind of neighbors of each other.
They all execute together.
Then they share the memory of that core.
Within each block,
like I said, you can have it 1D or 2D,
and just like we have ThreadIdx.x
and ThreadIdx.y,
similarly you have BlockIdx.
Just like you identify which thread you're working with,
you can identify which block you're working with.
The dimension size of each block in the kernel
can be identified using block diffs.
Let's go back to our matrix addition example.
Let me go here.
I'll jump around my slides.
I told you that the maximum size of a block
is 1024, right?
If I give this limit of block equals 1,
what is the maximum number of matrix additions I can do?
What's the maximum size of my matrix?
If you're
arranging your block
as n by n,
that means you can matrix add
a maximum of 32 by 32.
You can't go bigger than that.
But we all know that we can launch
millions of threads.
32 by 32 becomes the limit of one block.
Now let's see how do we scale that up.
We do that kind of like this.
Let's say you have
a matrix of size whatever.
Pick a big number.
Whether it's a million or a billion, it's up to you.
We define first the number of threads per block.
This is going to be the same for every single block.
It can be 16 by 16 like I've shown you.
It could be 8 by 8.
We'll get to how to choose that much later on.
But let's define it as 16 by 16.
The number of blocks we need
is n divided by the number of threads per block.
Now you have many, many, many blocks.
The number of blocks
are essentially infinite for all intents and purposes
in GPU.
It's basically infinite.
That is where the scaling comes from.
Your block is limited,
but the number of blocks you can have is basically infinite.
That's what allows you to do
this one.
There you're going to identify
the global X and the global Y.
If you just use thread IDX.X and thread IDX.Y,
within each block,
they're going to go from 0 to 15,
0 to 15 in each axis.
You'll be overwriting the same data.
You'll only be working on the top left of the matrix.
But what you want to work on is the entire matrix.
That's how you subdivide your matrix into blocks.
Let's look at a math example here
where n equals 32.
Here n is the size of the matrix.
If our matrix is 32 by 32,
1024 elements,
purely used because it's simple to understand.
We have a block
that is 16 by 16.
Then our thread IDs go from 0 to 15 in the X axis
and 0 to 15 in the Y axis.
How many blocks do we need
if each block is 16 by 16?
We need four blocks.
Same if we have two by two blocks.
Each block is going to do four elements.
We need 256 blocks for that.
Here's how the math works out.
I said how we want to convert
local thread IDs into global indices.
Our minimum
for the X axis
is
the block IDs
from 0 to 15.
Multiply by 16
which is the block size.
Then you add the thread IDs
which go from 0 to 15.
Minimum is 0, 16, and 0.
The maximum is 31.
Now you see how we go from
row 0 to row 31 using our block.
Same with the Y.
You go from 0 to 31 as well.
That's how you use blocks
to help your scaling.
You can change that to a million
and the math will remain the same.
The equations don't change whatsoever.
Any questions on this?
This is the fundamental thing you need to understand
to do GPU programming about how these threads and blocks
are structured.
We'll get into scheduling and stuff later, but yes.
Technically, all memory is sequential.
On the hardware level,
there's no concept of 2D memory.
Everything is 1D.
2D is for humans to understand how the memory is arranged
and visualize it and imagine it.
When you're doing programming at that hardware level,
it's important to understand how the memory is arranged
so you're optimizing for that as well.
In future lectures, we'll be talking about how memory should be
arranged and how you can take advantage of certain patterns
in memory to help with performance.
Any other questions?
Again, this is fundamental, so please ask the questions you have.
Go ahead.
You mean type as ints and floats or something?
They're all
unsigned integers
or long integers.
Yeah.
They have notations in hardware as well,
but they are all runtime concepts.
You set them up.
There's no default.
You have to explicitly specify what your block size is.
Yeah, that's a very good question.
If I can rephrase your question,
what you're asking is,
OK, we have very neat numbers here.
We say our matrix is 32 by 32, which is 1024.
In this class, by the way, powers of 2 are your best friend.
If you can memorize them, that would be the best.
What happens if our matrix is 25 by 25?
Right?
It can't go well as a square, right?
Or it can't fit into a block nicely as a power of 2.
Or maybe it's 23 by 27.
Whatever.
Pick a number that doesn't fit into some of these nice numbers.
And the question is,
what do we do with the extra threads that we have?
What happens is, when you launch
any number of blocks with the thread configuration,
every block always launches
with the same number of threads.
When you write CUDA kernels, it is your responsibility
to check the indexes and return them
if they're not going to be doing anything useful.
So let's say you launch 1024 threads
to do vector addition, but you only have a thousand elements.
What do you do with those extra 24 threads?
You return them.
So i is less than size, and if not, you return them.
So that is an important concept as well.
Any other questions?
They will try to access whatever memory you tell them.
No.
So we'll get to exactly what returning means later on,
but no, they won't be used elsewhere, as you've suggested.
So that they don't access invalid memory
and overwrite results that they shouldn't be.
What other questions?
Okay.
I have an example of proper matrix multiply example
at the end of this deck, so we'll see a lot more of it,
but for now, I want you to understand the principles
that are involved.
So I said that all the threads in a block
execute together.
Blocks by themselves, different blocks,
can execute completely independently.
They don't talk to each other in any way, shape, or form.
They can execute in serial, they can execute in parallel.
We'll get to that in future lectures, but the scheduling is in any order
based on the number of cores available to us.
So a visual example of this is something like this.
Let's say you want to launch eight blocks.
I have a laptop GPU with two cores.
It's going to launch something like on the left,
where it does two blocks at a time and then serializes them.
You have a beefy desktop GPU that has more cores.
You're going to be doing more of them in serial
or more of them in parallel and then serial later on.
So that's kind of the visual representation of how
GPUs scale the blocks.
Those are my final slides on threads
and blocks, so please ask questions.
Yeah, exactly.
Mm-hmm.
There are APIs to check for that.
Yes.
That's where scheduling comes in.
I want to keep that for later.
Any other questions?
Yes, there are some considerations.
It's called resource allocation.
So far, we've seen choosing threads and blocks
based on our total number of elements,
the total number of work we want to do.
But as we go further in the class, what we learn is that
those are not the only two considerations.
Memory is a consideration.
Performance is a consideration.
How big your kernels are and what they do.
What kind of read patterns do they have?
How do we pick an optimal block size for that?
Sorry, I think there was a question there.
Yeah, so
I specifically said shared memory is shared within a block.
Shared memory is a special type of memory.
I'm going to start on memory with the next slide.
But when you say, let's say you bought a GPU
and it has 8 GB of memory,
that's the global memory, essentially.
Every thread can access that.
Shared memory is a special type of memory that sits much closer
to the threads themselves.
From the next slide, I'll get to what it actually means.
Any other questions?
All right, so let's look at memory.
There are different types of
memories we have on a GPU.
First, let me start with the host part.
On the host, you have one memory.
If you pick your favorite memory allocator,
you're allocating memory in your RAM on your CPU.
Most of the time, that's the only memory you have.
On the GPU, you have various different types of memories.
You have shared memory, like we were just talking about.
You have registers, where if you do essentially
int i, that's where it's getting stored.
And then you have global memory and constant memory.
So let's start looking at each one of those.
So the host,
that is your CPU. Again, I will use more hosts
than CPU, but I'm using it in this class so that we're all getting used to it.
So the global memory
and constant memory
are the only memories the host can read and write from.
It can't access shared memory directly.
It can only read and write global memory.
So there's APIs for those,
and they're called CUDA mallet
and CUDA free. If these names sound familiar to you,
because they are. They are essentially CUDA versions of mallet
and free like you use on the CPU.
CUDA mallet allocates memory. CUDA free frees memory.
Please be good programming citizens and use both.
You don't want to mallet allocate and then not free it.
So this is how memory transfers work.
First, you do a CUDA mallet.
Notice how we use
a pointer
of a pointer.
So when you do the void star star, you're doing pointer to a pointer
so that the
CUDA mallet call is going to allocate memory
and then write the address of the pointer
into device memory.
And then the size is how much memory you want to allocate
in bytes. So for example, if you want to allocate
one int, that's four bytes.
But of course, you're going to allocate much more than that.
Any questions on this? Any questions on how you
allocate memory?
Okay, so what you want
when you do, let's say, mallet from the CPU,
what you're essentially getting
is a memory pointer.
So the runtime is giving you the address
to a memory space on the CPU.
On the GPU, it's similar
where the GPU is giving you
a memory space, the address to a memory space on the GPU.
So in CUDA,
most of the API is like this
where it's writing two variables
instead of doing, let's say, device memory equals CUDA mallet.
It's going to be CUDA mallet equals
and you give the pointer to the memory,
to the variable you want to put that address in.
So the value inside device memory
is a pointer.
So that's why it's called pointer to a pointer.
And then you do the size is how much memory you want to allocate
on the GPU itself.
So
the word casting is mostly just to remove warnings
because we are allocating in bytes.
We're not allocating floats or doubles or unsigned ints.
We are allocating in bytes.
So the CUDA mallet call doesn't care what the data type is.
You could be allocating vectories, for example.
The mallet call doesn't care what type it is.
So we use the void star star to remove any warnings
or things compilers might complain about.
Yeah.
Right.
So here's how it kind of works.
So in your CPU memory,
you have various things, right?
And device memory
is actually one of these.
Okay.
And then on the GPU
you again have more memory
and let's say
this is the memory you are allocating.
The value in this
is the address here, right?
And the reason we don't use,
we could use potentially any type that we wanted.
But again, for readability sake, we want to know what type
of pointer it is so that the compiler can understand
and make sure that it's doing the right things
and the right optimization with it.
Could you do void star? Absolutely. No problem whatsoever.
The compiler won't complain about it or anything,
but it's more for human readability that we do that.
It's a pointer to a memory address.
Yes.
This is a GPU memory point.
So that means, for example,
sometimes lines are like a manual CPU memory.
So it never allocates the same address
as it would allow.
It could.
For example, both GPU memory
and CPU memory have the address zero.
I'm not saying it will allocate, but it could allocate a zero
or it could allocate a XYZ
or whatever it might be.
You can't.
That's why you have to manage that.
You have to declare your variables in a way that you're tracking it.
So usually the most common way is to do
H underscore A or B underscore A.
And we'll see that in the example later.
But you use variable names to essentially track those things.
Yes.
Many lectures down the line, we'll see a different way
to take care of it as well.
What other questions do you have on this very basic
CUDA mallet for you?
Okay.
So now we've allocated memory, right?
Now we want to copy that memory.
Again, when we do this, we're only allocating memory.
We've not actually created any useful data in it.
So we need to copy memory in different directions.
So we have four directions that we can copy in.
Host-to-host, which we'll almost never use
using CUDA memcpy.
You can do that using various CPU calls,
whether that's STD copy or anything else.
You can copy host-to-device,
which is essentially one of the first things you will do.
You will copy useful data from your host to your device.
And the way to do that with this CUDA memcpy API.
Here, you're putting the destination first.
Remember, in CUDA APIs, the destination will always come first.
Even if you look at CUDA mallets, the destination is coming first.
So you take your destination pointer
and your host pointer.
To your question, this is how we're tracking it.
We're calling it device pointer and host pointer.
We have to name these in a useful way so that we understand.
We're copying the sign in bytes.
Again, that's why CUDA doesn't care about what data type you have
because we specify everything in bytes.
And last is the copy direction.
This is an enum.
There are different enums and we go through them in the API.
But this one is saying CUDA memcpy host-to-device.
Very obvious what its function is.
So any questions on this?
Okay.
The next one is device-to-host.
You've allocated memory. You've copied it to the GPU.
You've run a kernel on it.
Now you need to copy the result back to do something more with it.
Again, you use the CUDA memcpy for this.
Destination first. So we're copying to host.
So destination comes first.
Device pointer, the source, comes second.
And lastly, the enum, which is CUDA memcpy device-to-host.
Should be fairly obvious at this point.
The last thing you can do
is device-to-device.
You want to copy memory from one place in the GPU
to another place in the GPU.
And you use device-to-device for that.
Same thing.
See how we're not using device and host here
.
Again, choose the names.
And finally,
the enum is device-to-device.
Any questions so far?
All of you ready to get into an example
of a proper program?
Yeah.
So let's say
you wanted to
do matrix transpose.
Very simple example.
You could do matrix transpose in place
where you read all the memory and write to the same space
or you can create a copy of that matrix
so you have the matrix itself and a matrix transpose.
That's a very simple way of explaining it.
What are the questions
before we dive into an example?
This is all global memory, yes.
No.
I haven't shown it here, but
there are ways to set which device is active
or which device is the device you're calling stuff for
and that's how you would control that.
What are the questions?
Okay.
Let's take a look at combining all of this,
combining how we do threads and blocks,
how we allocate memory and how we call kernels
into a very simple program.
So let's use matrix multiply
because it's better than vector addition
and vector addition becomes very, very simple.
So matrix multiply has a few things going for it.
It has each row of a matrix
is essentially a vector
and each matrix multiplication for each element
is essentially a dot product.
And then you need to have clear conceptual understanding
of row major and column major,
what changes first and how things are stored in memory.
And then each dot product is
a result to the output matrix.
So visually, this is what is going on.
For each output matrix,
this one, the result
of this element here is the dot product
of this vector and this vector.
So you're essentially doing
whatever row this is, you're taking the first element
here, multiplying it with that first element,
second element here, multiplying it with the second element
and adding all of those up to give you
a dot product. And that's what matrix multiply
essentially is.
So we have a thousand by thousand matrix.
How many operations are we doing?
And I'm talking about multiply and add operations.
Just to do a matrix
multiply. Anybody want to take a guess?
We can get to the answer later, but anybody taking a guess now?
Okay.
We'll come back to it.
Have your guesses ready then.
All right. Let's take a look at CPU example.
Everybody's done a few matrix multiply at least once, I hope.
Okay.
This is all CPU code.
You have the first two lines
for i and j, which are essentially doing
your rows and columns.
Generally, i and j in matrix multiply
the first two are always representative of the
output matrix.
So this element is i column.
So this row is i,
this column is j.
So for each element,
now you have to do a dot product.
So you're going to do sum equals dot,
where it's going to store the dot product.
And now you have to walk each vector.
So you're going to use a for that.
You're getting the a element from matrix n,
you're getting the b element from matrix n,
you're getting the cumulative sum of a time.
And then finally, once you're done with all of that,
you're writing that into p,
into the element.
Everybody on board with this?
Any questions?
Because we're going to be taking this and putting it on the GP.
Okay.
So anybody have a guess on how many operations this is?
Yeah.
Close.
I think that is it.
So essentially for a thousand by thousand matrix,
you have a thousand times a thousand dot products,
so a million dot products.
And each of those, each of those dot products,
there's a thousand multiplies and a thousand adds.
So you have a billion multiplies and a billion additions
on the CPU.
Now, this is where you can start to see,
well, billion is a big number.
CPUs are fast, but we can still see how it might take time.
If you were to put this on a GPU with thousands of cores,
now we start seeing how we can get performance really well.
So let's,
let's get to how we program this actually on the GPU.
So let's make a CUDA skeleton.
Okay.
So we start with three steps.
First, we want to allocate and initialize our matrices.
We want to copy them to the device.
So that's part one.
Part two is actually running matrix multiplication on our device.
Part three is copying it back onto the CPU.
Okay.
And of course, freeing the memory,
freeing the memory,
freeing the memory.
All right.
So let's start with our first part.
Hopefully none of this is new to you by now.
So I have a function, I'm not calling it main,
but it's a function on the CPU.
You don't see underscore underscore global,
but it's just for understanding.
And again, for good naming purposes,
see how I've called them float devN, devN and devP,
which means they are on the device.
Okay.
So now first step is to allocate memory.
Using CUDA malloc,
we pass the pointers and we pass the sizes that we want.
Okay.
The second step is to copy memory.
Now I'm not showing you how the CPU memory was initialized
and all of that, all of you know how to do that.
I'm just showing you how we are going to copy memory
from host to device.
So you get your host pointers for M and N,
your destination is devM and devN respectively,
and you're doing a host to device copy.
So now once you do this, all of your CPU memory for M and N
gets copied onto the GPU.
Okay. We'll get to the kernel later.
Part three is getting that memory back.
So once the kernel executes and P is multiplied properly,
we can copy from devP
from the memory on the device after our kernel.
Our host is where we want the return back.
And we go CUDA and copy device to host
so that we have the memory back.
And finally, we'll free all of it.
So that's just sort of straight up CUDA free and give the device pointers for.
Any questions on the skeleton?
Because we are essentially done with part one and part three of our skeleton.
All right. So step two
is writing the kernel in CUDA.
Okay.
So let's start with the matrix kernel.
And first we start with global,
which is the kernel specifier.
Why is the return type always void?
Maybe.
But what if there could be?
Right?
Let's see.
See, you could.
Let's say there was an automatic way to get GPU.
Go ahead.
Yeah. Okay.
But get one step higher. Go ahead.
Sorry?
No, I think you're going too low. I want us to come higher up.
So you're close.
A kernel runs in parallel. That's for sure.
Why isn't there a return type?
What happens if every thread tries to run again?
We're talking about millions of threads here, right?
Can every thread return?
What does every thread return mean?
Every thread could return different things.
Right?
Yeah.
Essentially the problem is a combination of all of that.
Of all of what you said.
There's no specific, there's no direct way to transform one value from GPU to CPU.
Because the performance will be very bad.
There's the programming stacks of CPU and GPU are definitely different.
Everything runs in parallel.
So how do you return something?
Different things could be running at different times.
So like I said before, different blocks can be executing at different times.
How do you know when to return?
And then, you know, based on having different threads,
what does it even mean to return from many, many threads?
So to avoid all of those, there is no return from a global.
Okay?
And then for our host,
our parameters,
what we're going to do is specify cons for where we are only reading data.
And not cons.
For the memory buffers, we're going to be writing data.
So just be good citizens about it and help the compiler understand the
different memory access patterns that could be taking place.
Any questions on the declaration?
Because that's not necessarily the compiler's job.
It may give you a warning, but it won't necessarily complain.
No,
CUDA is all C.
I mean, there are versions of CUDA that are mostly C++-ish,
but what you're seeing here is all C.
There's no C++ in it.
So M is a memory buffer.
All of these are just memory buffers.
We are representing them as matrices.
What other questions?
Okay.
So let's take a look at how a matrix multiplies.
The first thing we do,
again, I'm putting some constraints here that are probably obvious to
some of you.
We'll get to those constraints later.
We want which element we are going to be operating on.
So if we had an INJ in our CPU that pointed to the P matrix,
we are getting those INJ here as well,
using TX and TY.
We allocate an accumulator.
Where is this going to get allocated?
Which memory is it going to use?
No, it's not going to be used.
Remember, every thread is doing this.
Every single thread.
So this will be in registers, actually.
If you're doing a float P,
it's going to be in registers.
I've not shown you how to use shared memory yet.
I'll show you in the next class or next Wednesday.
But this, if you do float P,
if you do TX and TY, these are all registers.
These are the fastest way to access memory.
And they are individual to a thread.
Let's say these are all threads.
This thread's TX and TY is going to be different from this thread's TX and TY.
And they can't talk to each other.
So these are all registers.
So K is kind of similar to how we did K on the CPU.
But what happened to the two outer loops?
What happened to the I loop and the J loop?
Yeah.
Exactly. They're taken care of by the implicit parallelism
that a kernel provides to us anyway.
So instead of writing for I equals
zero I less than N, that is taken care of
by a block and thread configuration anyway.
So that's the number of threads we are launching.
So each thread has to do just one element at a time.
So when we get to this 4K loop,
that's very similar to what we did on the CPU.
So you're taking memory from devM and devN.
Remember the 1D access?
You have to convert TX and TY into a 1D memory buffer.
And then you're going to do the
multiply and add here.
And then finally you're going to write that
into the global memory.
Exactly.
So that's where the parallelism comes in.
Because you're doing the same,
you're literally doing the exact same operation for every thread, right?
So you're calling many different threads
and they're all going to be doing the same thing.
And that's where GPUs are.
They want to be doing the same thing many, many times
and that's where the parallelism and the performance comes in.
Okay.
So memory.
Yes.
So like access.
Okay.
So let's take a very small example.
So let's see.
Okay.
This is a matrix.
Hardware memory is never 2D.
It's always 1D.
So I'm just going to erase this.
How many?
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
Okay.
So this is a matrix.
So this is probably going to be stored as A, B, C,
D, E, F,
G, H, I.
Now let's say our point of view is DP.
Okay.
DP of 0.
DP of 0, 1
in value.
Like you can do this on CPUs.
There's no such thing on GPUs like this.
Okay.
So what we essentially have to do is use some human I
and J to convert each index from here to here.
So let's take F, for example.
Let's say this is I
and this is J.
This would be 1, 2.
The 0 index. Remember, it's always 0 index.
So when you take 1, 2,
you're going to do 2 times
1 times
then
whatever the dimension is, plus 2.
Dimension here is 3.
So 1 times 3 plus 2 equals 5.
What is D of 5?
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
Float?
Yeah.
I got that part.
It's for the data type.
But you're reading it as an array.
Float pointer
and nothing is the same thing.
So when you
let's say it's on CPU,
let's say you're doing
in
equals
if you pass a float pointer
0, it's just like that.
You can't say
1.
So let's say you have A of 10.
What this is doing is
actually, this is the same as
writing int
star A equals
new
I'm sure I'm making a mistake here, but ignore it.
So this
A and this A are basically the same.
The pointer here is just
the pointer to this thing.
You could absolutely do
A plus 1, right?
And it would essentially add the A pointer
plus 1 byte.
So that's how it works.
So when we do
DP of let's say 1,
what this means is DP
plus 1 times
size of
whatever the type is.
That's essentially what we're doing.
So we are essentially adding
4 bytes to the address.
It's handled by run time.
It's allocated at run time.
We'll get to that
in the next lecture.
But yes, you've raised a very good question.
What other questions do you have?
Everybody understands how the matrix kernel works?
Because this is really important.
We are going to use this to build
on our GPU understanding.
So understanding this basic thing is super important.
Okay.
So let's move on to the next
question.
So what is the
kernel?
So we've done three parts.
We've done the CUDA memory transfers,
probably the simplest part.
We've done the implementation of the kernels,
but now we have to do invoking the kernel,
which we haven't done so far.
We haven't actually called the kernel.
So that is done using this.
Let's call it width-by-width.
And we launch one block.
And then we launch the matrix itself.
So we launch matrix-multiply-kernel.
We'll define the blocks and threads
and then see how we've given
dev-n, dev-n, dev-p.
Why do we have width there?
Or why is width not a pointer?
So width is an integer.
You can see it up there in the matrix-multiply-cpu function.
It's a constant width.
But we are not passing it as a pointer.
Why?
Right.
These are passed as pointers
because they're literally on the GPU memory.
You don't want to be copying it when you're calling the kernel.
But when you call width, like an int
or a float or something very simple, a very implicit type,
that gets copied by,
passed by copy, essentially.
So every thread is literally getting a copy of width.
Okay.
So now a few questions for you.
What is the major performance problem of our implementation?
I can go back to a kernel
to show you what it looks like.
What is the performance problem here?
Now, I haven't given you all the information
to identify all the performance problems, but I'm looking for guesses.
Go ahead.
So the for loop is important.
We can't necessarily get rid of that, but you're close.
I want you to think more.
That's the answer to my next question.
Where?
Tell me which lines.
Which lines are we copying that memory?
You're getting this point here.
So where are we copying memory?
So we're not copying memory here.
We're reading memory here and we're writing memory here.
So where is the problem?
Is it here or what?
The problem.
So what exactly is the problem?
I think that we are reading memory in a for loop.
So we are reading it many, many times.
So it will discard and reuse the same value.
So that's not missing.
Okay.
Yeah.
Anybody have anything else to add to that?
That is one part of the right answer.
What else do we want to add to it?
Yeah.
So not necessarily.
Not exactly that.
But where is this memory stored?
It's in global memory.
What did I say was the fastest memory?
Where is shared memory?
It's on that chip, so it's pretty close.
The worst memory, albeit it is very fast,
the worst memory on a GPU is global.
It is in a way the biggest,
but it is also the slowest.
It is still very, very fast.
It's 10 times faster than your CPU,
but it is still the slowest.
So when you're doing this,
on every thread,
now you have a performance problem.
This kernel is still going to be faster than your CPU.
If you're trying to compare matrix multiplier on CPU
versus matrix multiplier on GPU,
this will still be faster,
but it doesn't mean it's the fastest version of the kernel.
When I said performance is going to be a key theme,
this is what I'm talking about.
We won't settle for, okay, we are faster than CPU.
No, we want to embarrass the CPU.
Any other thoughts to add to performance?
That's a very good idea that we'll touch on next time.
I want you to hold that thought
and bring it to the next class.
What other ideas do you have?
It's a register,
so it's perfectly fine.
Good answers and good thoughts.
I'm glad you guys are already ahead of the curve.
What is the major limitation?
I'll come back to you on that.
What does one block mean?
What are we limiting then?
What does that mean?
Because if we use one block,
the maximum square matrix,
because right now we're dealing with a square matrix,
is 32 by 32.
A thousand elements.
Not very big.
We want to be millions, if not billions of elements.
This kernel does not have that.
In first class here,
we will build up on this.
It only works for a thousand elements at most.
That is a major limitation.
What are the assumptions we made in our matrix?
I just mentioned one of those.
It's square.
Most of the time, it may not be square.
We didn't check for any bounds.
That's a major limitation as well.
What we're going to do in the next class,
on next Wednesday,
is dive into a bunch more concepts about
programming, get into a little bit of scheduling,
a little bit of more memory,
talk a little bit more about the performance of each kind of memory.
Then we will look at how do we make this kernel perfect.
That's all for my lecture today.
Definitely take a look at the slides if you want.
Finish project 0 and take a look at project 1.
Enjoy your Labor Day break.
I will see you guys on Wednesday.
Take care.