Okay, so I want to get started today by talking a little bit about read-me's.
How many of you in project one, how many of you did a proper read-me for the first time
when you're writing GitHub projects?
And I'm talking about a public open source read-me, I'm not talking about a read-me that
you submit with build instructions and stuff, a read-me that has screenshots and that has
performance analysis.
Anybody else raising their hands?
Okay, so I see a few more.
So remember, the reason read-me's are important is because when people like myself, we are
going out there and looking for really, really smart students to hire, it's very unlikely
that I'm actually looking at your code and your algorithm.
Like I'm sure they're amazing, all of you sitting in this room are probably the smartest
people that are graduating this year, but I'm not always looking at your code, I'm looking
at your results.
I'm looking at the impact you've created, and that is seen through your reading.
So as much as you put into your project, let's say for project zero, you spend five days,
for project one, you're going to spend a week, for path tracing, you're going to spend more
than two weeks on it.
The result of the two weeks is summarized into your read-me, so imagine how much impact
that should have.
So let's talk a little bit more about that.
Let's talk about what makes for a good read-me, what do people look for, and you always want
to remember the audience.
So let me touch on the audience a little bit.
How many of you have spoken to recruiters, company, technical recruiters, people from
HR reaching out to you?
Probably everybody, right?
If you've looked for an internship, you've looked for a job, you've spoken to them.
How many of them are actually technical?
How many of them have written maybe 15 lines of code in their life?
Very, very few.
Right?
Most of them probably zero.
So they don't always understand if you give them super technical information, and that's
going to be your first audience.
Most of the time as a student, if you're getting into an interview process, you're likely doing
a phone screen with an HR person.
And your job at that level is just to get to the next step.
It's not to convince the HR person that you're the most amazing, if you're able to do that,
fantastic.
But what the HR person is going to look for is, hey, if I recommend this to my technical
lead, is he going to continue the process?
Or is he going to think that I'm basically like, that's kind of the decisions HR people
are trying to make.
So you want to be speaking to them.
And then you also want to be speaking to people like me, who are very technical, who understand
the work you're doing, and want to see that, hey, this student is really smart, and I want
to hire him because he's doing amazing work.
So you want to be able to balance both of those things.
So let's look at those tips about what makes for a good readme and how you should structure
it.
The first thing is that you want to provide your context and your contact info.
Talk a little bit about the project, not in full detail.
You should start with what is this project?
It's performance analysis, it's CUDA points, it's a path tracer, you know, very, very simple,
very succinctly.
And because you're in the position of, hey, here's my information, if you like my project,
reach out to me, share your contact info.
You may not do that later in your career, like if I'm writing an open source project,
it's unlikely that I'm putting my contact information up front.
But in your position, you want to be doing that.
You want to share your contact information, your LinkedIn, your GitHub, so that anybody
who's looking at the project is able to reach out to you, okay?
And you want to put your best image up right up front, you know, very clearly that showcases
exactly the work you've done.
And then once you've passed that, you want to show a little bit of walkthrough, you know,
use screenshots, use debug images about what you've done.
So this is a great example from a few years ago about how, I believe this was computer
vision, right?
So how you take an input, run it through different algorithms, what are the intermediate stages,
and how you come to the end result.
And what this shows is you have a clear understanding of the work you've done, and a clear understanding
of how to explain the work you've done.
You can be the smartest engineer, inventing the craziest algorithms.
But if you're not going to explain the value of that algorithm, and how it benefits the
team you're working on, people are not going to understand it.
So it's really important to communicate clearly and succinctly what the flow is, and how to
understand it.
And then you also want to annotate, again, going back to, you know, let's say, the audience
of HR people, they may or may not understand what a CUDA path tracer is.
Maybe somebody at NVIDIA does, but maybe somebody at, you know, pick your favorite new company
probably doesn't understand what a path tracer is, and what's involved in a path tracer.
So you want to annotate, you want to showcase the different features.
We, most of us in this room are coming from a graphics background, so we understand what
the different features in this kind of an image are.
There's reflections, refractions, caustics, and other things.
But the average run-of-the-mill HR person, or even the software developer who doesn't
have a graphics background, isn't going to understand this feature.
Not all of this comes for free, so you want to be able to highlight those.
And then you want to include debug screenshots.
This, I cannot state this enough.
If you include debug screenshots, I am going to give you brownie points, because what it
tells me is, you know how to use a debugger, you know what the steps in the process are,
you understand the different phases of your algorithm, and you're able to use that information
to then make your algorithm better.
It checks so many boxes that I'm pretty sure those four points that I said aren't even
covering it.
Debug images are some of the, if other than the best screenshot you put up there, debug
images are probably the best thing you can add in your read, okay?
So they really communicate the value that you understand your algorithms and your implementation.
So the other thing is, you also want to include side-by-side comparisons.
It's one thing to include one image.
If you just include this image, something like this or this, it's fine.
You know, we get it, we've all seen smooth spheres, nothing new.
But what you want to explain is, this is non-default.
You actually had to put in work to get it to be smoother.
This is default, this hard edge thing, and it doesn't look like a sphere, not to the
average person at least.
So having these side-by-side comparisons of the before and after of your work really help
the average reader understand what you're trying to implement and how you're trying
to improve on your work.
Bloopers.
So I spoke a little bit about this in last class, but again, just like debug images,
bloopers are amazing in showcasing that you as a developer are able to overcome problems.
Bloopers are a perfect example of that because they show that you stumbled, you ran into
a problem, but you were able to overcome that.
How you overcame it is something for your interview, you know, when you get to your
interview and the interviewer asks, tell me about a time you ran into a problem.
And boom, you're like, hey, can you open that, read me and see that screenshot?
Because now you're going to talk about something like this and be like, I ran into this, I
didn't know what was happening, I was only getting red and green and my path tracer didn't
work.
And then you start talking about how you solved it, right?
They're a perfect way of showcasing the problem you ran into visually, rather than just telling,
oh, I ran into this bug in a for loop, you know, and people won't get it.
You show this, people understand what this problem is.
Even if they don't know all the algorithms behind it, they understand, yes, that is a
problem that doesn't look right.
But when you show them your main screenshot that actually looks right, it clearly shows
that you were able to overcome it.
And then you tell the story of how you overcame it.
A few other bloopers I'll show again, from previous years, that was a void run.
How many of you did something like this in your voids?
Yeah, see, you're not alone.
People are, you're walking in the footsteps of many people who've come before you.
And I've run into the exact same problems you have.
So don't worry, don't feel that, oh, I'm, if I'm posting a blooper on that discussion
or anywhere that it's been embarrassing.
No, not at all.
We are all running into this.
I've been in your shoes once upon a time.
I've done way worse, trust me on that.
So really, really important to share bloopers.
Here are a couple more.
An inverted ducky, what's happening there, anybody guess what's happening there?
Especially our graphics folks.
The camera's perspective is wrong.
Yeah, I think that's it.
Yeah, the projection matrix is backwards, exactly.
The thing is rotating completely inverted.
This is from the path tracer.
I'm foreshadowing this, but this is from the path tracer.
If any of you run into this, please post it on that discussion, okay?
Anybody guess what's happening there?
Sorry?
Yeah, and they're probably also not doing any bounces and things like that.
And they're also not computing the normals correctly, I think.
Okay.
So as you can identify who did this.
Sometimes they look amazing.
Again, I'm not showing this because I want to brag or anything, although I think it's
pretty cool.
Anybody guess what's happening here?
This wasn't in the old 5.6.3 that we had, it was a fluid simulation.
Anybody guess what's happening?
Let me back it up again.
And then slow it down as well.
It's not the simulation.
What's going on here?
What looks weird in this?
The color.
What about the color?
So let me pick a nice place and stop it.
What's weird about this?
Great.
Yeah.
How did that happen?
So that happened because I had a bug in my code, and I'm talking about 2012 spring, okay?
So literally more than 10 years ago.
That happened because I had a bug in my OpenGL code where I was not clamping my color values
between zero and one.
So they went all sorts of ways, and they kind of like looped around, and they gave me really
cool ring out of it.
So complete bug, but it looks amazing.
So I can pass it.
Okay?
All right.
So any questions on images and debug views and bloopers so far on readings?
All of these in here are probably project two doesn't have any visuals, but hopefully
some of them are definitely in project three, right?
And don't worry about going and revisiting and updating these things, okay?
We will grade them.
You're free to work in a branch that you want, and once you receive your grade, go update
that project.
Please do that.
I encourage you to do that.
Just because the project is done and you've graded, it doesn't mean that repo is dead.
Okay?
All right.
So let's see.
So to recap, you want to do your images and stuff.
You want to add your bloopers, and for video and animated GIFs, the cellular tools, Lyscap
used to be a good one.
Screen to GIF is really nice.
If you're capturing videos, OBS, Open Broadcaster Studio, I think it's really good for videos.
So be sure that you're optimizing the settings.
Capture it in full HD.
Don't skimp on the resolution and stuff, so be sure to do all of that.
Demos are really good.
If you want to put a live demo link or something, it's good.
If you're putting in build instructions, that's good as well, so be sure to do that.
Include performance analysis.
You've done that as part of project one.
You'll certainly do that as part of project two, and be sure to continue doing that.
Again, it shows that you understand the value.
Even today, like this morning, I was talking to one of my engineers at Cesium who's working
on improving how textures are loaded, and I'm like, okay, you're going to work on this,
but tell him how much improvement I should expect.
Should it be 5%?
Should it be 15%?
So just being able to get even preliminary numbers that showcase what the potential of
a feature improvement is becomes really, really valuable.
And then lastly, this line is A here.
There's 30 of you in this class.
There's probably hundreds of you across DMD, CGD, robotics, CIS, et cetera, right?
You want to focus on what you...
Even within the 30 projects in this class, you're going to have differences.
You're going to work on different things.
You're going to work on extra credits, right?
You want to highlight those.
I can...
Any recruiter I can connect with, I can be like, hey, go look at my CIS 5, 6, 7, 8 rules
and tell me which one would be good.
And what they're going to look for is how to differentiate.
They're going to see five projects that all look the same, and they're going to think,
oh, this is average.
Right?
They're going to...
Even if you've done the best one, you're going to have the five best projects, but they're
going to look, hey, these guys all did the same thing, so maybe there's nothing special
about it.
So it's as if you focus on what you need by showcasing side-by-side comparison, by annotating
your images.
That's how you differentiate yourself.
Even though you may have done the same implementation, focus on what's unique about you and then
highlight that.
That's the key thing.
You want to be able to communicate that value so that it's creating an impact that is helping
you get those interviews, helping you get those jobs, right?
So that's the ultimate goal of these read-me's.
Any questions on this?
So I've linked a bunch of really good read-me examples.
I'm not going to open most of them.
There's also a link on more of read-me guides and stuff, so all the links for you to check
out.
Now let's talk a little bit about graphs.
This is a graph from Anand's site.
I'm sure most of you have read similar charts like this.
What are some properties of a good chart?
This chart is an example of a good chart.
Tell me what are the key things in there that make it good.
Yeah, just shut up, you don't have to read it.
Well-annotated, and then some of these, whatever.
Tell me which part of it is well-annotated.
Well-annotated, well-annotated, well-annotated, well-annotated, well-annotated.
It sounds like it's already labeled but it says better so you know which one's better.
Yes, so yeah, I've highlighted on something very, very important that a lot of students,
and not just students, even professionals, miss on.
This very line here, higher is better.
How many of you did a chart, and put a point where you used time?
Probably at least half of you, if I remember correctly, maybe more,
where you're like, how much time did a simulation take,
or how many frames per second did something take, right?
Time is usually lower is better.
But if you're drawing a line like that, I'm going to think higher is better,
if you don't specify it, right?
So even in this chart, you always want to mention higher is better, lower is better.
Good point here.
What else is good about this?
I think...
Exactly.
So in these, both of these issues are different, except these two,
which are more flat, you have a founder's edition and a regular edition.
And then the 2080 and the 2080 founder's edition are similar products.
And then you have 1080 Ti and 1080 here, which are similar products.
So if you are doing, you're preparing different algorithms
with different settings within the same chart,
give them similar colors, okay?
You may give one light blue and dark blue,
you may give one yellow and orange kind of thing,
but make sure the colors mean something, okay?
What else?
What are some other good charts?
He specifies the configuration, the resolution, the quality.
Absolutely.
It says what was actually tested.
What else?
Yeah, good.
Yeah.
Yeah, especially when the lines are this close,
like especially for example, 161.8, 161.7, 161.6,
if these numbers one that you didn't have, right?
So you want to make sure that when it's this close,
you're always putting the number in.
What else is good about this chart?
Who's the audience for this?
Sorry?
Gamers, yeah?
Technical people, people who are interested in GPUs.
Does this speak to them?
Do they understand everything that's on this chart?
Yes, right?
They understand frames per second.
They understand GPUs.
They understand resolution.
They understand which game is it.
Ultra quality is generally a setting
that most gamers would understand.
So make sure that you understand your audience.
Now, if you show this to a non-technical person,
would they understand it?
Would they know what frames per second means?
Probably not.
They probably don't care.
So you always want to give information
that is right for your audience as well.
So all good points there.
Now, let's see some example of maybe not so good charts
and how we should improve them.
And these are all from previous years in Py65.
Not picking on names or anything,
but let's see why they're not good.
We saw why this is good,
but we also need to understand why they're not good
because if I go back and look at project one
and I'll be sure to share feedback
with you during the training,
is what changes we should make
so that your charts are actually good and useful.
So let's take a look at a few of those examples.
So tell me what's bad in both of these.
We discussed what's good, right?
What is missing from these?
Yeah, doesn't specify.
This time, right?
This time in milliseconds,
I'm going to assume green is better
because it's higher.
Higher to the right is always better by default,
but in this, it's not.
Red is better than this.
So yes.
What else?
Red is a bit wordy, yeah?
Because you're essentially saying
CPU line, work efficient,
trust implementations off-scan,
but you're repeating those here.
Average runtime off-scan.
That's it.
Four labels and three lines.
The CPU one, I believe is right.
Maybe.
It looks like that.
So, yeah.
What else?
There is no label for specific data.
The line is continuous,
but we don't really know
what are the actual number values.
You mean something like put a number here?
I would say that depends
on what you're trying to share.
Sometimes it can clutter the chart too much
if you put too many.
Like in this chart,
if you're putting four numbers on the lines,
I think that's fine.
If you're trying to put 15,
it's going to look too cluttered
and you won't know what to do.
So that depends on the situation.
What else?
Is this zero to 10?
Is it zero to one million?
Is it 10 to one million?
I have no idea.
Right?
What should I read in that?
What else?
Definitely.
Why are we zero?
Why are we wasting space?
And again,
we said time in milliseconds, right?
How many of us think 0.025 milliseconds?
None of us, right?
So again,
think about what scale you're using
for your time axis as well.
What else?
Maybe last column B, sorry.
Any other thoughts?
Doesn't say what GPU this was or not.
At all.
Anyway, right?
Right?
You can't predict anything.
What else that I can identify?
This one?
Yeah.
Specify it again.
Because this chart,
you're probably going to put it
in your presentation.
Right?
So specify it again.
Say that it takes you five more seconds
to write what GPU it's on.
Don't be stingy on things like that.
Okay?
All right.
Let's take another example.
What about this?
So here,
here what I'll show you
is that the number of units.
Again,
make your chart from your side.
And I'm specifically going
to pick this chart.
How many of you can tell me
the powers of 2 by heart?
I'm sure if you think about it,
you can come up with it.
But if I ask 2 power 13,
who knows the answer?
Right?
So if I ask you 2, 4, 8, 16,
you'll probably get it.
But 2 power 13, 2 power 18,
you know,
we might have to think
about it for a second.
And if we have to think about it
for a second,
where we are talking about
two powers in everyday class,
how does an HR person look like?
Right?
So why are we using
these two powers here?
Use many.
Use hundreds of powers.
Right?
Why use two powers?
Again,
speak to your audience about it.
The other thing I want
to share in this chart,
and maybe I have another slide
for it,
but I'll share it here.
What's wrong with this chart?
Yeah,
the data is just here.
This is the only thing
that matters.
So why are we using
all of this space?
Just get it all.
Just start here.
Right?
And GPUs,
as I've already said,
are for big data.
We are not going to,
we are not going
to be testing in this class
for a rate size
of 2 power 4 versus 16.
You're never going
to test 16 elements
in Wi-Fi.
You're probably going
to test 16,000,
but you're never
testing 16.
So just get it all.
Start from the beginning.
Okay?
On this slide,
again,
a rate size,
we have something
here,
time in milliseconds.
Okay.
But again,
it doesn't say
high respect.
It doesn't say
low respect.
Right?
I'm going to think
all green line is amazing.
Green line is going up.
Blue line is,
blue line is low.
Blue line is 5.6.
Or,
yeah.
So,
so make sure
you're thinking about it.
Put your time into it.
You're going to,
you're going to be doing
weeks worth of work
for every project.
But if you make
bad charts like this,
all that
six and a half days
of work
is kind of thrown
under the water
because you're not
communicating it correctly.
All right.
So direction we spoke
about it.
And this is a very
good example of this.
Again,
if we go back to,
you know,
things that are
bad about charts,
running time,
you know,
things that are bad
about charts.
Running time
doesn't say higher
is better,
lower is better.
Array size,
2 power x.
And also look at,
look at this.
We don't really care
about 2 power 2,
but we don't care
about 4 elements.
And almost
neither do we
about
4,096 elements,
right?
We care about
4 million elements.
So this chart
is completely skewed
from the data it has.
Also doesn't,
doesn't show
higher is better,
lower is better.
So everything
gets messed up.
Now,
we know that this
is running time,
so lower is better.
So what we're actually
saying is,
yeah,
I did all of this
work for the GPU,
but my TTL is still better.
Charts are not
very communicative.
If you are,
if you are doing
GPU performance
for,
this is at,
at even 4 to
4,000,
right?
Of course the GPU
is going to be faster.
The overhead
of the GPU
is going to make it slower.
If this was
4,000
to 4 million,
you're easily
going to make
the GPU look
a lot better.
So,
this is not
false.
It's not what
GPUs are meant for.
Talk about why
the algorithm that
you implemented is good.
If you put
a chart like this,
you're like,
hey,
I did all of this
work and my GPU
is still faster than
the GPUs.
Why are we taking
this class?
Right?
Okay.
And,
and like we said
before,
I mentioned that
I probably had
another slide.
Use the number
of elements that
are actually
good for GPUs.
Communicate that well.
If you,
if you are
in doubt
about what the size
should be,
start with 2 power 18,
start with 256,000
That's like
the minimum.
Yeah,
you can go to
64,000, 128,000
but if you're not
sure,
start with this.
You're doing scan,
start with this number
and go to like
4, 8 million
elements.
Okay?
And that's where
the GPU performance
is going to shine.
It's going to
absolutely smoke
the CPU
in performance
and it's going to
make the GPU
algorithm look better.
Okay?
Um,
so,
we already discussed
this,
color lines,
make sure they are
similar.
You can use
light color,
dark color
and stuff like that.
So,
especially if you're
like,
let's say,
let's say in our scan
you're going to have
this naive,
efficient and trust.
Make sure to use,
let's say
for naive
and efficient
you may use
similar lines
and then trust
can be a different color.
Okay.
So,
any questions
on this?
All of you
are going to make
really beautiful charts
of project 2?
Okay.
I'm expecting it.
I do,
I spend 30,
45 minutes every year
on this and
you know,
hopefully it's going
to make a difference.
Okay.
Last thing I want
to talk about
before we get
into the lecture
is actually
promoting your project.
Okay?
So,
here's a question for you.
How many
of your potential
employees,
who might be
have
some sort of
a social media
on any platform
that is relevant
to that company?
I should probably
add Snapchat,
Instagram,
TikTok to this
but let's leave
that out for now.
But,
probably every single
one of them,
right?
At least on LinkedIn.
If nothing else,
they at least have
a LinkedIn presence.
Can we all say that?
On that LinkedIn presence,
how many of them
promote their work?
How many of them say,
hey we have
a new product launch,
we have a new feature,
we have interns
joining today,
our interns graduated
today.
How many of them
are saying that?
All of them.
None of them.
All of them are
promoting their company,
their business,
their work.
Okay?
So, why should you not?
What makes you
hesitant to share
your work
on social media?
Choose the platform
of your liking.
I'm not saying
go post your
images on Instagram
where your
friends and family are.
I'm asking
why aren't you
posting them on LinkedIn
where recruiters
are looking for you?
Right?
So, let's take
a look at
some success stories
from this class
about how they've
made a difference.
So, this is from 2018.
This was
Ziyad,
Liam Hall,
Latif T as well
and Henry,
their final project.
This was the first
DXR project
done in this class
and probably,
I'm pretty sure
I can claim this,
the first
student-led
DXR project
in the world.
I'm pretty sure
I can state that.
Okay?
And these guys,
Ziyad,
Henry and Liam,
they spoke about it
extensively
on social media.
They tagged
all the right people
who were doing
DXR
and it got
really popular
and not just
on Twitter
but they also
created blogs
about it.
They actually wrote
down what was
their process,
how did they
build this up.
Again,
in the infancy
of DXR,
there was no
documentation.
I can tell you that.
So, their guides
have helped
countless more people
understand how
DXR works.
So, even if
you don't do
a blog,
make sure
a GitHub readme
is really there.
Lastly,
you know,
be sure to share
on Twitter as well.
A lot of people
are going to be following
you.
If not,
they'll follow me
and when I retweet it,
we're going to be seeing
a lot of people
approaching you
about, hey, good work
and things like that.
Trust me,
it happens
and I'm not making it up.
Okay.
Let's see a few more.
So, this was
Ziyad,
I forget his name.
Anyway,
they were doing
a shadow
water
simulation.
Okay.
And they were using
this person's
paper for it.
They put
their image
on Twitter
and thanked
the person,
thanked the author
of the paper
for writing it.
Really cool gesture.
Trust me,
that is the
most amazing thing
you can do
for an author
of a paper.
And when they
put that,
the author
of the paper
replied.
You know,
what happened
after that?
They ran into
a bug
in their final project.
They ran into
an issue
where they couldn't
do it right.
They emailed
the author
and they were like,
hey,
we are running
into this issue.
The author
of the paper
was like,
hey,
make sure
you're doing
X, Y, Z.
And they did that
and they fixed
that issue.
And I,
there is
a paper
not just
in this class,
anywhere.
If you are
going to be
implementing
somebody's work,
I highly recommend
you just
reach out to them
and be like,
hey,
thank you for
writing the paper.
I'm going to be
implementing it.
I'll let you
know how it goes.
That's it.
You will make
somebody's day
by doing that.
And once you
finish that
implementation
and you share
your work
with the author,
okay?
More examples.
So,
you know,
again,
most students
posting their work,
whether it's
on LinkedIn
or Twitter,
it just helps
us amplify
it even more.
It's one thing
me writing
to say,
hey,
we did
an amazing
path tracer,
you know,
go check out
her project.
It's another
thing for you
to write it
and promote
it.
And I'm
just becoming
a microphone
for you
in getting
connected with
the companies
and recruiters
that you'll
be interested
in.
Okay?
So,
that
project
here,
this was
from 2018,
Emily sent
a message
to Bucket
around that
time where
that tweet,
her tweeting
that and that
getting reshared
led her to
have
an opportunity
at Xbox
or to talk
to Xbox engineers
and stuff,
you know?
And
that's what you are
looking for.
All of you
in this class,
not because
you think,
yes,
you learn a lot
from 565,
but ultimately
you're at Penn
so that you find
really good jobs
that pay you well
and you can do
really good stuff.
And being able
to promote yourself
is a gateway to that.
You can do
a lot of services
and stuff
and they'll all be great.
But
promoting yourself,
you won't get to 100,
you'll get to 100,000
companies who might
want to
see your work
and
maybe
you'll reach,
you'll get connected
with companies
you didn't know
existed
and they'll be
doing really cool work
and you might
want to go work
for them.
Last couple
of examples.
So,
this was done
by
Yusuf Victor
in 2017
and
he did
a library
using
Metal.
So,
Metal was brand new
back then
and he did
a random number
generator
as part of
doing a path tracer
using Metal.
So,
this became
his library.
A few
weeks later
when he checked
out his library
he sees
two people
kind of following
that project
and both of those
people are from
Apple.
Right?
So,
it's possible
that
a student
written
random number
generator
for Metal
was being
used in
Apple software.
I don't make
claims about it
but it's possible.
So,
last one.
This is a
personal one,
right?
So,
when I was
in this class
10 years ago
and did
the path tracer
or
again,
I wasn't very
very forward
so
we used
to write blogs.
Patrick,
instead of reading
we used to
write blogs
and Patrick
tweeted my
path tracer
back then
and using
this hashtag
CUDA here
so,
a company
called
Accelerize
back then
followed
the CUDA
hashtag
because they
were doing
GPU work
and like I said
I had
two or three
followers
and I'm applying
everywhere
and I'm not
having very
good luck.
So,
Accelerize
follows me back
and I'm like
who is this
company that's
trying to
follow me?
Like,
what makes
me special
kind of thing?
So,
I check out
their website
they're doing
CUDA and
OpenCL
work and I'm
like okay
apply,
you know?
And that's
what led
me to
Accelerize.
So,
that's the
story.
Like,
I'm standing
here because
of it.
So,
I can't
emphasize enough
that while
you may be
innovative
or,
you know,
being like
oh,
I'm just
a student
in a class
who's going
to care
about my
work,
a lot
of people
are going
to care
about my
work.
So,
even if
they're not
good,
even if
you think
they're not
good,
right?
Trust me,
you're going
to be having
very high
standards for
your own
work.
The world
will think
they're
me.
So,
I encourage
you to
always talk
about your
work.
You know,
just simple
messages like
that go a
really,
really long
way for
promoting
how you
work and
how your
code looks
and how
you're
thinking about
software.
Because
today,
you might
be promoting
yourself.
Today,
you might
be promoting
yourself
through your
projects.
But what it
tells me
is that
you have to
go to
conferences and
talk about
it,
right?
And that's
a key factor.
A lot
of engineers
just want
to be in
a dark
room and
code all
day.
But yes,
they're great,
no doubt
about it.
But I also
want the
engineers who
are going
to be going
to conferences
talking about
it,
right?
Because
that's
the key
factor.
So that's
all for
the slides
that I have.
I hope
I've inspired
you to do
a lot more
around ReadMe.
But if you
have any
questions,
I'm more
than happy
to take
those.
So
yeah.
Maybe.
I'm not
saying you
should
publicize
every single
project.
In this
class,
maybe.
But
outside of
this class,
I can't say.
But
what I'm
trying to
say is
you,
let's say
you get
to the
path stage
or you
don't need
project 2
for the
next
project,
you may
be producing
amazing
charts or
images.
And you
may think,
oh,
I slogged
for this,
I ran
into so
many bugs,
I don't
know what
my data
is going
to be.
That's
all fine.
But take
that chart
and be
like,
hey,
I
implemented
one
percent of
all
CIS
programs
across the
world.
I'm not
just talking
about
that.
That makes
you different.
Use that
to your
advantage.
Just because
you think
you may
not have
gotten
100 out
of 100
on your
project
doesn't
make your
project
bad.
But it
doesn't mean
if you're
not getting
100 out
of 100,
your project
is not
good.
So always
remember that.
The work
you're doing
is difficult
but it's
also in
your benefit
and making
you look
unique.
Any
other
questions
or
readings?
Last
one?
Okay.
All
right.
So
let's
move on
to the
more
fun part
of the
class,
which is
performance.
So
which
algorithms did
we take a
look at
last time?
Anybody
remember?
Or did
everybody
forget?
Scan?
Okay.
Reduction?
Radix sort?
Some
area
table?
Compaction?
Yeah.
That's
about right.
Okay.
So today
we're going
to take a
look at
a bunch
of these
algorithms
and performance
trade-offs
and how
they help
improve
the algorithm.
And while
we may
talk about
specific
algorithms
at specific
times,
all these
apply to
all the
algorithms
in
the
world.
You
optimize it
for the
architecture
and you
get maximum
performance out
of it.
If you
remove this
yellow box
here,
this is a
key component
of deriving
maximum
performance.
So let's
revisit
parallel
reduction.
Okay?
So in
parallel
reduction,
what we
did was
we took
this array
of eight
elements,
we added
them two
at a
time.
What did
we do
next?
Add them
again and
add them
again.
Everybody
follow?
on board
with parallel
reduction?
Hopefully
all of you
implemented
this in
project 2
already.
Fingers
crossed.
The only
thing is
which index
we are
writing into.
But they
read the
same data.
Completely
the same
thing.
This is
kind of
the code
for this
kind of
indexing
where you
have this
thread,
this
stride,
which dictates
what the
difference in
indexing is.
If you're
reading from
one to
four,
you see
how
stride is
less than
block time
and you're
multiplying
stride times
two.
In multiple
blocks you
want to be
loading that
into shared
memory so
you're not
always reading
from global
memory every
time you
operate in
shared memory.
I don't
know why
my clicker
is doing
this.
Where
were we?
I think
we were
here.
So
the stride
you get
one to
four until
it's less
than block
time.
Why do
we need
signals?
How is
that wrong
information
coming up?
Let's
say you
have a
thread
and you
want to
load
that into
shared
memory.
You
want to
load
that into
shared
memory.
You
want to
load
that into
shared
memory.
You
want to
load
that into
shared
memory.
Let's
say you
have a
thread that
is
writing
here and
automatically
jumping here.
This is
all
computing.
Now you're
reading bad
data.
Every time
you write
to shared
memory without
fail, every
time you
write to
shared
memory,
put a
new thread
into
shared
memory.
So here's
a question
for you.
As
time increases,
what do
more and
more threads
do?
Yeah?
The
idle?
Yeah.
Because
they're not
doing any
work.
If we
come back
and look at
this,
if we
get to
the last
level,
8 elements,
even
like in
the first
thing,
you're going
to see
four threads
are not
doing any
addition at
all.
Only four
threads are.
In the
next iteration,
only two
threads are.
In the
next iteration,
only one
thread is
doing
something.
So what
does that
mean?
In
general,
the number
of threads
you use is
half.
By the time
you get to
the last
iteration,
most of
your threads
are not
tweaking.
So what if
we tweak
this algorithm?
And how
should we
tweak it?
So we
have,
how should
we tweak
this algorithm
to make
it a little
better?
What's an
alternate way
to do
that?
The same
algorithm.
add two
elements and
so on.
Right?
Like,
naively,
right?
Like,
dense them
all.
So,
like,
instead of
one and
then idle
five,
idle nine,
idle 18,
put all
those together
and the
next time it
will be
systems pointing
at each
other.
I like your
idea.
Tell me
what happens
with the
arrows.
Arrows,
fade.
So let's
say zero.
Let's start
from zero.
What should
we add to
zero in
your idea?
We should
add one.
Okay.
Then we
should make
two and
what should
we add to
two?
But we
are doing
the same
thing.
So what
should we
add to
zero?
You're
saying bunch
them
up.
What if
we did
like,
zero and
seven?
Zero and
seven.
Okay.
And then
like,
one and
six.
Okay.
And
then
one and
six.
Okay.
And
then five
and four.
I like
that idea
better.
But flip
it around.
What if
we do
zero and
four,
one and
five,
two and
six,
three and
seven?
So let's
take a look
at that.
So we
have this,
right?
This is
our input
array.
What if
we do
this?
How
about this
now?
What is
this doing?
Isolating
the thread.
You're
isolating the
thread.
What's the
next step
for me?
So you
take those
two
threads,
right?
And
you
take the
next
thread,
right?
And
you
isolate
the
next
thread,
right?
So you
take those
two and
add it.
The last
step is
likely going
to be the
same.
So now
what that
allows us
to do is
a few
things.
I want you
to pay
attention.
I'll go
back and
show you
one thing
in our
code that
we have.
So this
is our
thread.
So
I want you
to pay
attention.
See how
big this
condition
is.
T
modulo
two times
prime.
Where are
we doing
two times
prime?
We're
doing it
again.
When we
go up in
the
column,
we're
doing it
again.
We do
it there
and
we're
doing it
again.
Modulo
is
extremely
bad.
I can't
tell you
how bad
it is.
It is
like
compared
to a
floating
point
addition,
it is
probably
20 to
40 times
lower than
a
multiplication
because it
is not in
hardware.
So
remember
those two.
I will
fast forward
a little
bit and
see the
code for
this.
So
we are
not changing
any of
that.
But now
look at
this.
We start
with
this.
So if
we look
at
this
example
here,
the smaller
version,
our
stride in
this case
in the
first level
is 4.
You go
from 0
to 4,
1 to
5,
2 to
6,
3 to
7,
and
stride is
4.
So we
want the
stride to
go from
4 to
1.
So we
start
there.
Our
condition is
very simple.
We
have our
same
strides,
but now
look at
this
condition.
So
simple.
T less
than
stride.
We
add.
So now
this
operation
remains the
same,
but
our
condition is
simpler.
Our
modular
is lower
and
our
stride is
also
simpler.
So
thinking
we
haven't
even
optimized it
completely yet.
We
just went
from
addressing
to
stride
addressing.
And
thinking
about that
will probably
make our
algorithm
40%
faster
on a
GPU.
Any
questions?
So
we
actually
haven't
changed the
number of
threads we
launched yet.
We will get
to that.
But in
this we
haven't changed
it.
So if I go
back there, we
still launch
eight threads.
And
eight threads
load eight
values into
ShedMap.
But when
you get to
the addition
part, you
will see
how to
optimize
that.
Any
other
questions on
this?
So
next
Wednesday we
are going
to have
what I
essentially
call
next
Wednesday's
presentation.
At some
point on
the calendar
I forget
the exact
date, we
will have
what I
call
performance
optimization.
I will
run all
of this
code.
I will
run this
version and
we will see
with each
version how
much it
improved.
I will send
out instructions
for you to
bring your
laptops to
class and
you can run
it with
me.
We will
see how
much better
it gets
with simple
modifications
like this.
Okay.
So
visually,
what is this
going to
do?
What happens
in iteration
1?
What happens
in iteration
1 to
our threads?
Which threads
are going to
do the
work and
which threads
are not?
So before
iteration 1
they are all
doing work
by loading
things into
memory.
At iteration
1 only
four threads
are doing
the work.
So four threads
are already
kind of useless.
Then in
iteration 2,
two more
threads are
doing the
work.
Iteration 3,
only one
thread is
actually doing
anything.
So now
if you look
at this
side by
side,
again,
I told
side by
side is
good,
I am
using
side by
side.
And
we have
spoken about
all of
this.
So I
just want
to make
sure the
memory is
all there
for all
of you.
Indexing is
cleaner.
The other
thing we
haven't spoken
about yet
is memory
coalescing.
You are
reading
continuous
values here.
These four
read the
same value
here.
The
for loop
is simpler.
Lots of
benefits.
If you look
at the
code,
I have
highlighted
this already,
but this
if statement
is so much
simpler than
this.
If we
just make
this change
on a
GPU
algorithm,
let's say
for 10
million elements,
we are
probably going
to see
this.
That's
how much
overhead that
kind of
condition has
every single
time you do
it.
Any other
questions so
far?
This is
value reduction
revisited.
Any other
questions?
Is there
any way
to
reuse
that?
Not in
this
algorithm,
but in a
moment I'm
going to
get to
why you
may actually
want them
to become
useless.
If they
become useless
like this
left side,
that's not
good because
now you are
wasting time.
Whereas
here it
could be
strategically
valuable.
Yeah,
absolutely.
For
example,
if you
were launching
only half
of the
threads,
it would
still work
the same.
You would
just have
to load
memory twice
for each
thread.
Also,
if you
are still
trying to
make the
first four
threads,
then can't
you just
add
offsets
to each
thread?
So it's
not like
the interleaving
threads are
useless,
but the
calculation
is still
that one,
but you are
just adding
offsets to
each.
Wouldn't
that be
the same
as this?
Wouldn't
that be
the same
as this?
Yeah,
in my
mind it was
the same
as this.
So if
you are
making the
offset block
them by
two,
you are
suggesting
why don't
we just
make it
16 at
a time
and it
would still
be
interleaved
and then
we would
add them
up.
Yeah,
the addition
is still
interleaved
instead of
doing it
this way
.
Is there
any reason
why you are
saying this
kind of
addition?
Yeah,
and that's
the key
point.
If we are
drawing a
tree,
we are
not going
to draw
it like that,
but the
amount of
computation
that happens
is exactly
the same.
Here you
are probably
doing index
plus one,
index plus
two,
and you
are doing
it as a
simple
condition.
Any other
questions on
value
deductions so
far?
So let's
take it a
step further
and look at
warp partitioning.
Warp
partitioning
is how
strands
from a
block
are
divided into
warps.
So we
said if
we go back
to warps
five years
ago, we
said that
block size
is defined
by U,
and then
the threads
in a
block are
subdivided
into warps
at the
hardware level.
You don't
control that.
Each warp
has 32
threads,
and that's
divided at
the hardware
level.
Warp
partitioning
is about
how you
use the
threads in
a
warp.
You can
strategically
define your
algorithm so
that it's
taking
advantage of
that.
So there
are two
things that
we'll cover
today.
Minimizing
branch
divergence.
Why do
we want to
minimize
branch
divergence
within a
warp?
Why do
we want to
minimize
branch
divergence
within a
warp?
If you have
branch
divergence
within a
warp,
you're going
to do
double the
warp.
In
worst case
you're doing
n times
the warp,
even though
you're not
actually doing
that.
So you
want to
do that
and you
want to
retire
warp
partitioning
within
a
warp.
Let's
take a look
at examples
of how
warps are
structured.
In a
1D
block,
1024 is
the maximum
block size
you can
have.
And
warp n
will start
at 32n
and end
plus 1
minus 1.
Very
simple,
very
straightforward.
So
1D
warp
structure.
No
questions?
Okay.
So let's
look at a
2D
block.
So in
a 2D
block,
increasing
thread
IDX means
increasing
thread IDX
dot X
plus and
start with
thread IDX
dot Y
equals 0.
And only
when you
hit the
maximum
of X
you
get
32 to
63 in
X
and still
0 in
Y.
But at
63 you
hit the
maximum
of X.
So in
warp 2,
X resets
to go
0 to
31 and
Y increases.
Then you
go to
warp 3 and
it's 32
63 on
X and
warp Y
is the
maximum
of X.
What
happens in
warp 4?
Y increases,
X resets.
Okay?
So these
threads in
a warp will
always be
continuous.
Okay?
Any
questions on
this?
So if
you have a
block of
64 by
8, how
many warps
are we
getting?
16.
All
right.
The other
thing to
pay attention
to is
essentially
how we
got from
here to
here.
Just remember
that.
In a 3D
block you do
the exact
same thing
as we did
with 2D
but now
you have a
Z component.
You will
rarely use
3D blocks.
I certainly
don't recommend
it.
But if
you ever do,
that's how
it will
work.
You will
be doing
double the
work.
If not
N times
the work
based on
how your
branches
diverge.
Branch
divergence
within a
block is
bad.
You don't
want branches
to diverge
within a
block.
Not
entirely
true.
Ideally,
yes.
But it
is probably
not okay
for a
branch in
a block.
So let's
take a look
at an
example.
So for
what size
people
certainly
do,
which
works have
divergence
or does
any work
have
divergence
for this
condition?
The first
work,
okay.
What
else?
Or no
other
work?
Divergence?
So it
depends.
Let me
come back
to you.
Exactly.
Remember
our 2D
work, how
y increases
and x
resets?
Every time
thread
IDH.x,
any book
that has
thread
IDH.x in
this book
will
have
2D
work.
So
2D
works
in
this
condition,
you will
have a
branch
divergence.
It's not
just the
first work.
It is
any work
that has
this
condition.
Okay?
What
about
this?
Does
this
diverge?
You're
not
shaking
your head.
Why
does this
work?
This
will
never be
true.
Like,
it may
be true,
so in
the first
work,
let's
take 1D
example.
In the
first work,
0 to
31.
Work
sizes,
32.
Minus
1 is
31.
Can
any value
between 0
and 31
be greater
than 31?
In work
0,
it's not
divergent.
Let's go
to work
1.
What are
the values
in work
1 in
a 1D
case?
32 to
64.
Now what
happens?
32 to
64,
greater than
31.
All
true.
No
divergence.
There's a
diff condition,
but no
divergence.
No branch
divergence
here.
Now let's
say,
let's say
I have
this.
What
happens now?
So,
work
0,
there won't
be divergence.
Okay?
In work
0,
you go from
0 to
31,
greater than
32.
Right?
All false,
it's fine.
In work
1,
what happens?
32 to
64,
compared to
greater than
31.
Not greater than
equals,
greater than
31.
Is there
divergence now?
Yes,
on the first
thread,
there is
divergence.
So you
want to be
paying attention
to that.
Those
things matter,
plus 1,
minus 1,
always
matters.
So now,
given what
we know
about
divergence,
let's take
it visually.
So pretend
our work
size is 2.
Okay?
What can we
say about
this?
What can
we say
about the
left and
the right?
How many
diverging
works do
we have?
On the
left,
4,
and on
the right,
1.
On the
4,
we have
4.
On the
left,
we have
4.
On the
right,
we have
0.
No branches
diverge.
Second
pass,
we have
two branches
diverging
here.
0 on
the right.
And on
the last
one,
how many
will we
have?
One on
the left,
one on
the right.
There is
no other
way around
it.
But what
we've
essentially
done is
minimized
how many
divergent
works we
have.
So if
we take a
look at
this once
again,
what we
also get
from this
is not
just less
diverging,
but we
can also
get shorter
time.
So let's
take a look
at this.
We can
pretend a
warp size
is 2.
In this
case,
no warps
are there
because all
the warps
are doing
something or
sticking around.
Or at
least one
thread in
the warp
is doing
something.
So this
thread,
this thread,
this thread
is doing
something.
So you
can't
get rid
of
this.
You
can get
rid of
this.
So the
scheduler can
get rid
of this.
The
scheduler can
be like,
okay,
you have
no more
useful
code to
execute,
bye-bye,
return,
that's it.
And just
these two
warps will
actually do
work,
which is
good.
But
once the
waiting will
come and
fill it up
in the
code,
hardware,
they will
actually do
something instead
of making
half the
threads wait
like there
is here.
Does
everybody get
that?
Okay?
In the
next step,
now we
see two
warps
retired because
these two
are
working.
And then
in the
final step,
yeah,
no warps are
retired,
but now
the third
warp is
here.
So
after a
full
iteration.
Okay?
So
everybody
clear on
how this
works,
how
changing
our
indexing
system is
helping
warps
retire.
In this
case,
in our
right case
where the
warps are
retiring,
the same
block or
other block
can fill
it up.
Whereas in
this,
even though
you're using
the same
number of
threads,
the number
of individual
threads doesn't
change.
Remember
that.
But the
number of
threads and
individual
threads
doesn't
change.
So
essentially
construct your
algorithms.
When you're
thinking about
your
algorithms,
you always
want to
think about
what is
easy versus
how the
GPU and
even your
CPU is
going to be
using that.
You always
want to keep
that in
mind.
What is
the easy
versus how
the GPU and
even your
CPU is
going to be
using that.
Questions
around warp
partition?
Yeah.
Right.
So what
you said,
I'll put it
in another
way.
When you
retire warp,
you're retiring
threads.
Okay?
You're retiring
their context.
their memory.
So you're
freeing up
hardware
resources.
So what
happens is
there are
blocks waiting.
So let's
say you
launch 10
million elements.
You can't
fit 10
million elements
on 4,000
ports,
right?
So when
you retire
those
warps,
those ports
free up
and new
threads will
fill them in.
So it's
not like
you're using
the same
threads.
You have
the hardware
executing
those threads.
So the
hardware frees
up and
new threads
will come
and execute
on that
hardware.
So think
about threads
as a
software
content.
If you
retire those
warps,
the GPU
can be
like,
threads,
you're done,
go back,
I don't
need you
in the
scheduler,
you're done.
So
that's
essentially
what happens.
Yep?
So even
if they
are not
being
used,
since the
scheduler has
less
warp
advantage,
so there
will be
less
overhead.
So we
will still
make the
algorithm
run
the best.
So when
you are
returning
threads early,
when you
call return
inside a
kernel,
which you
absolutely
can,
and all
consecutive
threads
are hit
return,
it will
retire the
warp.
The scheduler
will get
rid of it.
So that's
what happens.
So hitting
return is
important.
And
then we
have another
task that
would require
like 50
blocks.
So
they will
say like
the first
one, the
second one,
the main
one.
So
initially
they will
require
a block
which
was part
of the
doctrine
that
we
were
talking
about.
And
then now
we have
three
top
blocks.
So
will
the
scheduler
do
okay?
So I
wouldn't
put it
that way.
So let's
say you're
launching a
million
elements,
okay, of
10, 24
blocks each.
How many
blocks do
you have?
You have
1,000
blocks.
Can your
1,000 blocks
fit on the
GPU?
Yeah, they
probably can.
Doesn't mean
they're executing
at the same
time in the
GPU.
Probably not.
Okay.
Just because
they can be
launched at
once doesn't
mean they're
executing at
once.
They can be
hitting stalls.
Remember how we
saw the stalls
chart?
They can be
hitting the
stalls which
doesn't
mean they're
executing at
once.
So if
you have a
warp that
is not
going to be
doing any
work, come
in and fill
it.
It's just
wasting our
time.
So that's
why we
will retire
those
warps and
if we
retire them
we can
bring in
the warps
that are
going to
be doing
the work.
You don't
want people
who don't
have any
work to be
coming and
sitting at
the bank
counter.
You want
people who
are going to
be withdrawing
money and
making
transactions
to be doing
that.
If you
tell people
to go
away, you
can take
new people.
If you
just keep
people filling
the form
and
letting
them
do the
work,
you can
do that.
What
are the
questions?
Everybody
understand?
No more
questions?
All right.
So before
we start
memory
coalescing I
think we
can take a
break.
Let's come
back at
6.40.
Thank
you.