All right.
Let's get started with the intro to Kuta Patil.
So we'll continue what we were doing yesterday about introducing Kuta, but go one level deeper
in that.
All right.
So here are a few things we're going to cover today.
So we'll cover a bunch of Kuta things before we get into matrix multiply.
So if you remember, there were a few things that we assumed are limited about our matrix
multiply example last week, we'll see how to expand that and do it properly today.
So let's start with a bunch of built-in functions that we'll see.
So firstly, the first one is global.
Of course, all of you are probably well aware of that by now.
That is executed on the device and called from the host.
Then we have two more like that.
We have a device which is telling the compiler that this is a regular function.
It's not a kernel.
It's a regular function that gets executed on the device.
And then the host is telling the compiler that this is the host function and it will
only execute on the host.
So just differences of global will always return a word.
Like we discussed last week, global a kernel will never return anything, whereas a device
can return and is in line by default.
What do you think these do?
The first device and host on a function.
What do you think that does?
Yes, exactly, you're spot on there.
So let's say you have a very simple function called add.
Maybe you're adding two vectors, for example, you can write a helper function that does
that and call it from both the host and the device.
On the compiler side, there are just two copies of that function, one on the host and one
on the device.
But you won't need to maintain two copies of the code.
So that's the advantage.
What about the second one, global host?
So global is a kernel, host is running on CPU, what do you think that does?
You're probably thinking the right thing to say.
You think that is something logical?
The first question you have to ask is, does this make sense?
I never said this was a valid statement, I just asked what do you think it does?
This is completely invalid.
You can't do that because a global is creating kernels and host is creating a helper function
on the host that won't be allowed.
I'll have many trick questions like that, don't worry about it.
So yeah, that's that.
So just function declaration, so global and device functions, recursion is allowed.
On the first version of CUDA, on the first versions of GPUs that supported CUDA, you
couldn't even do recursion, you couldn't call device functions from device function.
So we've come a long way in how easy it is to program CUDA these days.
Dynamic parallelism where you can call kernels from kernels is something that became possible
around 2013, 2014.
It's a neat feature that I've never seen used, like I've never seen anybody actually use
it in production code where somebody's calling a kernel from a kernel.
I'm sure it's being used somewhere, I've just never seen it.
We can't do static variables.
Anybody guess why?
Why are there no static variables in CUDA, especially on the device?
Static variables are generally stored in the host, but they can be, let's say they
can be put in constant memory as well.
But why no static variables?
What does static do on the host?
Static specifier essentially tells the program that this memory is for the life of the program.
Not conflicts, but because kernels have a certain life, they start and they end, creating
a static variable inside a kernel makes no sense because it won't live the life of the
entire program and stuff like that.
And lastly, no mallocs.
You can't dynamically allocate inside a kernel.
Edward, go ahead.
So when you use device, you are operating within a kernel that has multiple grids and
blocks inside of it.
You're never calling a device function directly from host.
When you define it, when it is being used, when it is being called, what is it running
on the inside?
It's always running on the GP.
So if you think of the functions back, you call the kernel first and the kernel calls
the device function.
And each thread executes its own version of the device.
So in that case, since each thread is using its own version of the device, those threads
are in different blocks.
No, no, but they could be because if they were on different ones, then they can't.
No, I mean, we'll get to that a little later.
What you're asking is something about scheduling and how threads operate together.
And we'll get to that a little later in the lecture.
So just in terms of other hyper functions and stuff, so we have the same data types
as we have in C. So you get double and float and unsigned, you know, all of those things
in kernels as well.
You also get a bunch of math and functions that CUDA has built in.
A lot of these work on integers, floats and doubles as well.
Some of them are called intrinsics.
So you'll see that they come with this underscore, underscore thing.
What they do is they operate on floats and doubles, usually on floats.
But they only operate on 24 bits.
So if you think of a float being 32 bits, it has the mantissa and the exponent.
And the exponent bits, if you cut off like 8 bits, you can kind of work faster with it
because it's only 24 bits.
So what that produces is a slightly inaccurate result, but in a much faster way.
And we see that with a lot of you who are doing machine learning when half got introduced.
Half is actually half precision.
So float is single floating point precision, double is double floating point precision.
Half is half floating point precision.
And the reason to chop it down to 16 bits was for performance because you don't need,
in most machine learning use cases, you don't need that 32 bits of precision.
So they chopped it down to 16 bits.
And that's why you have all the half values as well.
So in addition to those functions, we also have some built-in vector types
that help with SIMD and other vector instructions.
So just like we have VEC3, VEC4, etc. in GMM, you get a bunch of those here in CUDA as well.
So to create something like that, there's this make function here.
Again, because there's no object-oriented program in CUDA.
You can't do a new VEC3 of something.
You have to use this function, make underscore,
where you create those vector types and store them as vectors.
Finally, you access those vectors with the .xyzw components.
Unlike GLSL, there's no RGBA, it's only .xyzw, which is completely fine.
Most of us are used to that anyway.
So that's pretty much for the built-in function and stuff.
This is mostly for your information as you get used to it.
You can always refer to the slides or even better refer to the CUDA programming guide.
That's going to give you much more comprehensive, much more updated information as well.
Any questions before we jump into the next part?
So the next part is essentially going to be your guide for the entire semester.
And that is how scheduling thread works.
Scheduling threads both affects how you run the kernel, how you program it,
as well as what performance bottlenecks you might run into later on.
So just in terms of how the GPU architecture is arranged,
this is the GeForce 8, which is the first CUDA GPU.
When I say G80, this is what the logical diagram essentially looks like.
First, you're going to see this.
Again, these are all logical, so understand that these have evolved
and I'll show you some images of how they look for modern GPUs.
For modern GPUs, this is called a streaming multiprocessor, an SM.
In some of your project zeros, you were asking what's SM3 or SM86 and stuff.
That stands for streaming multiprocessor.
Each of the green ones here, those are your compute units, are called streaming processors.
And a bunch of those are called streaming processors.
And when you are buying an NVIDIA GPU and you see 4,000 cores or whatever it might be,
this is what they're talking about.
They're talking about the number of streaming processors in the GPU.
So for a G80, that had 16 SMs, 16 streaming multiprocessors,
and each had eight streaming processors.
So a total of 128 cores back then.
Now, if you think about it, we're going to do a lot of mind math here
in the first part of this course.
So each SM could host.
Remember, this host is different from our CPU host, but what this host means is
it can run up to 768 threads at a time.
It has eight cores, but it can run up to 768 threads at a time,
and we'll get to how in a little bit.
But just in terms of this, so what this means is each SM can host six blocks of 128 threads,
three blocks of 256 threads, or one block of 512 threads.
You can't go over that limit.
If you want to go over that limit, it'll just put that block onto the next SM.
So when we were discussing it in the last class,
what happens if we go over overflow like this happens,
where it just puts it onto other hardware.
So in-flight, if each SM has 768 threads,
16 SMs can have 12,000 threads in-flight.
That means running at a time, not maybe actively processing at the time,
but you could call 12,000 threads, a kernel with 12,000 threads on a G80.
This was back in 2008 or something like that.
So you can certainly see where the scale comes from,
that you're able to launch that many threads.
So after the G80 came the GT200.
So this had 30 SMs, 30 streaming multiprocessors, each with eight streaming processors.
So 240 SPs total.
Each of those could host eight blocks or 1024 threads.
And again, doing some different permutations and combinations,
it could host eight blocks of 128 threads,
four blocks of 256, or one block of 1024.
And in-flight, each SM could have 1024 threads.
So that essentially means if you launch a block of 1024 threads,
only that block will live on one SM.
And then with 30 streaming multiprocessors, you get to 30,000 threads.
So we went from 12,000 in a G80 to 30,000 threads on a GT200 in about a couple of years.
So after the GT200 came the Fermi architecture.
This was probably around 2011 when I was essentially at Penn as a student.
So you can start seeing how the architecture has changed,
and I'll get to that in a little bit.
So if you just want to keep a mind picture of this and then see this,
not just in the way NVIDIA portrays it,
but there are architectural differences as well.
And I'll point a few of those out.
So the Fermi GF110 architecture, that came with 16 SMs.
So the SM count went down, but the core SM count went up.
So now we are up to 32 cores per SM.
And each SM could host 48 warps.
Warps is a new term.
We've never said that in this class before.
And we'll get to that, what warps means, for 1536 threads per SM.
So what that means is you could have, I believe, six blocks of 256 threads,
12 blocks of 128 threads, or one block of 1024 threads.
You can't have two blocks of 1024 threads per SM.
You can have it across the GPU, but not in a single SM.
So the architecture differences itself.
So with Fermi, NVIDIA introduced this new concept of a giga-thread engine,
which added this graphics processing cluster, as it's known,
and it's still valid to this day.
Where what they did was they took a bunch of SMs,
grouped them together, and then created a raster engine for those.
A raster engine is essentially what is used in games to render the scenes and stuff.
And this raster engine is essentially working for all of these streaming multi-processors.
So now you can have, for example, in this architecture,
you have four different raster engines for that GPU instead of one single raster engine.
So if we come back here, you're going to see you have a geometry shader,
vertex shader, set of raster pixel shaders.
This is essentially what one raster engine would look like.
But now we have four raster engines with a Fermi GPU.
After Fermi came Kepler. Kepler has been one of the most widely used NVIDIA architectures.
So you see a very similar architecture.
You see the number of SMs increase.
You see the number of the amount of L2 cache increase.
This is when you start getting better double-precision support.
In SM 3.5, you start seeing dynamic parallelism and things like that.
In Kepler, now they started changing the terminology for SM to SMX,
because it refers to the new next-generation SMs that they started creating.
Each of these had 192 CUDA cores.
And remember, I say single-precision here.
Because the way the transistors are essentially laid out,
they are designed more for single-precision.
And then you have special units for double-precision.
So if you were to run very high precision scientific simulations on the graphics card,
you would see lower performance compared to single-precision floating point.
After Kepler came Maxwell.
Maxwell, I believe, if my memory serves me correctly, is the 980 GPU series.
And you start seeing very higher transistor counts now, really improved memory,
lots of CUDA cores, geometry units, and stuff like that.
You don't have to memorize any of this.
I'm just showing you how the GPUs have evolved.
Maxwell SM, so now you see how they've kind of divided the GPUs.
They divided this into two parts, where you have multiple Watt-schedulars.
So this was new in Maxwell, where they started breaking out Watt-schedulars and dispatch units,
and breaking out the SM into smaller parts, essentially.
Then came Pascal.
You have widely increasing the number of cores and performance here.
Added, I believe, DDR5X, which increased the bandwidth as well for global memory.
Turing was the first RTX GPU that was announced in 2018.
Again, changing the architecture and stuff.
They added TensorCodes for all of you who are doing machine learning.
You know this very well.
And then each of these, if you compare Pascal to Turing,
you start seeing the RTX core down here.
And that's what's used for hardware-based ray tracing.
So instead of just doing floating point compute here,
you're actually doing bounding-volume hierarchies, ray-triangle intersection, and things like that.
And finally, to modern, like the latest architecture, that's the Ampere one.
I won't read through all the stats, but essentially you can start seeing how much bigger the chips are
getting, how many more transistors they're trying to fit in the cores, how many tensor cores,
RTX cores that they're trying to fit on these GPUs.
Compare that to G80 about 12, 14 years ago, where they were fitting in 16 SMs, 8 SPs.
Now we have 10,500 cores on this, possibly.
This is an architecture of what a single Ampere architecture looks like.
Again, these are all for your reference, not expecting you to memorize any of this.
But just to understand about how the evolution has happened.
Now, there was one term that we saw that I said that was new.
Anybody remember what that was?
So that's what we are going to look at.
Warps are very, very critical to how performance is improved in GPUs.
So let's take a look at that.
A warp is a group of threads from a block.
It has always been and will always likely be, although Nvidia never guarantees it,
32 threads, a group of 32 sequential threads in a block is a warp.
They make a few guarantees to you.
They always run on the same SM.
There's a guarantee that a block makes as well.
All the threads of a block run on the same SM.
So it's valid for warp.
There are a unit of thread scheduling.
What that means is all the threads in a warp always do the same command at the same time.
So the scheduler in CUDA is never executing one thread at a time.
It's never saying thread one, do that, thread two, do this.
It's always executing schedules based on warps at the warp level.
And if you ever need it, you can use the warp size to check what the warp size on your GPU is.
Any questions on warp?
I will dive deeper into how they work and stuff, but on a conceptual level, are there any questions?
This essentially is also why whenever I say block size, I will generally say multiples of 32,
not just in multiples of two, but in multiples of 32, because this becomes important.
Why is it called warp?
Why is it called warp? That's a good question.
Sorry, I didn't catch your name.
I don't know.
I'm assuming it has something to do with wrapping trends into one,
but I don't know why it's called a warp.
But to be completely honest, I've never looked.
So maybe you can find something on the history of CUDA and bring it to class next week.
Any other questions on warp?
No, it's always been the same.
It's always been 32.
Any other questions?
Why is it included so much?
Yeah, so we'll get to that.
But to answer your question, so why not make it one?
The answer is because the scheduler will have too much work to do.
So that's on the low end.
Why not make it 256?
Because then you'll see what we are going to come to in a few slides.
Any other questions?
I can call it warp because of text reference.
Interesting.
All right, now we know.
Okay.
No, as long as you're doing CUDA programming and CUDA kernels, they're always the same.
Yeah, but if you're writing a traditional CUDA program like we are going to be writing in this
course, those aren't generally getting executed on the ray tracing code.
Only if you call specific APIs like DirectX and Welcome,
then go run on the RTX ports.
Only then you're using those.
But otherwise, regular CUDA programs are not using the RTX ports.
Any other questions?
Okay.
So this is kind of the view of how three blocks or blocks from three blocks essentially can run on
the same SM.
So you have block one, block two, block three, and you have threads T0 to T31,
maybe 32 to 63 in the background, and they can essentially all run on the same SM.
So there's things we want to optimize for this.
The reason we have worked.
So you know how in some of the early architecture slides I was saying
a GAD can have 12,000 threads running even though it doesn't have that many cores to run on?
That's because we always try to saturate a GPU with performance, with actual execution.
That's why we call it high-density compute.
So what happens is, even on the CPU, whenever you read memory or you're waiting for something,
it's called a stall.
So in the case of GPUs, let's assume our website is 8 just for simplicity.
Whenever you try to read global memory, it actually takes time.
It takes drop cycles to go to the memory, fetch that memory, and bring it back into the registers.
So that's called a stall here.
So if our first work executes and, for example, is doing
int A equals gory global memory of matrix A, that's a stall.
But on the GPU, we don't want to be waiting.
We always want to be executing something.
So what the scheduler does is, hey, work one, stop.
You know, I'll get your memory for you, but hold on.
Work two, get started.
It will run through the same instructions, and then it will hit that same memory point
where it has to be.
So you hit that stall.
Then you get to work three.
Same instructions.
It wants to read global memory.
It's a stall.
Same thing with four.
It's that stall.
And by the time this hits a stall, we realize that work one is ready to run.
So it's read the memory.
Now it's ready to go to the next instruction.
So we say, okay, work one, continue executing.
So you see how in this diagram, even though we're executing four times the amount,
they essentially run in two stages, all in parallel.
If they were all executing at the same time as well,
you'd kind of get a similar performance.
Whereas if you never had the stall and never had this change of work,
what you would see is work one would run, hit a stall, and then it would finish.
Then this would start here.
Hit a stall, wait for it to finish, then run.
And it would essentially become sequential.
Whereas with work, you can swap them out at no cost.
It's called zero cross switching.
And that's what allows you to saturate the GPU with execution.
Any questions on this?
Almost anything that's related to memory, except for registers, I believe.
So any global memory reads, I think global memory reads have like hundreds of cycles worth of stall.
Any places where you have to synchronize,
even shared memory reads have like two or three cycles of stall.
So most of those kind of cases, you can hit stalls on.
Anything that's essentially not compute?
That's a good question.
If you have, let's say, hundreds of blocks, your question is whether they run on the same SM.
And that essentially gets to where I was talking about how many threads can be in a block.
If let's say you're launching blocks of 256 threads and an SM can host 1024 threads,
then most likely, depending on other factors as well, it could host up to four blocks per SM.
And then other blocks would get assigned other SMs.
Basically, they're like,
rather than the SM choose, they get assigned. You can think of it that way.
Basically, we're bundling threads.
Or, yeah, and why don't we just, like, all the threads separate, and if a group and stall the
thread. So, I mean, like if we're using warp, if this thread and continue to execute,
but since we're using warp, we have to wait for other threads inside the same one.
So, there are two reasons for that. The first reason is, if we were to individualize
at every single thread, we would be wasting transistors on making the scheduler bigger.
Right, the scheduler would have to do more work. So, more, you only have so many transistors in a
chip, and you have to pick and choose what you're proposing them for. So, if you purpose more for
the scheduler, you get less compute. So, that's one reason. The second reason actually has to do
with memory and bandwidth. So, for us, again, you know, coming from very traditional CPU programming,
we think when we do int i equals a, whatever it might be, that we read how many bits we want
from one place to the other. It doesn't always work like that, especially on GPUs. On GPUs,
what happens is you read a bunch of memory at once. That is the minimum. Usually, it's 128 bits
or 256 bits. So, that no matter if you're reading one float or eight floats, you're reading the same
amount of memory. So, why not optimize for that? So, that becomes another reason. I'm sure there
are other reasons as well, but these are the two main ones to get started with. Yeah.
And there's only one more time exactly the same.
Not at all. So, this is only for representation. So, for example, if you have an SM with,
you know, 192 threads, for example, you could have six walks running at a time. At any given
clock cycle, you could have six walk executing. You can have more walks waiting, but at any given
clock cycle, you'd have six walks executing. Yeah, for SM or a global. For SM.
All right. So, let's dive deeper into this. This is not the only slide I have. So,
SMs essentially implement that zero overhead walk scheduling. So, whenever you write code,
you don't have to worry about what's being switched in and out. As long as there are enough
walks on an SM, it's going to be saturated. It's going to be doing useful work. So, you
don't have to worry about if I'm reading memory over my walk might be waiting or something like
that. That's not an area you have to worry about. So, what happens if a branch happens in a
or what happens if a branch in a walk diverges? So, you have an if-else condition, for example,
that's a branch. What do you think happens?
So, what was the first thing we said about a walk? That there are 32 threads
that execute the same thing at the same time. What does an if-else condition do?
Yeah, it could execute different things. So, what happens if different threads in a walk
do different things? What do you think happens?
Some empty steps. Okay.
Might stall multiple times. Okay. What else? I think both of you are. So, let's take this
for an example. Let's say we have a walk of eight and we have three threads that are true and five
threads that are false. What actually happens on a clock level is in the first three clock cycles,
the crews will execute. If they have any stalls and stuff, those will also have to get to me.
And then after that, the else part will also execute. So, even though each thread might be
doing only some work, all the threads are doing all like they take all the time essentially. Even
though they're not working, they do take all the time. So, this is where you have to start thinking
about branch divergence and you don't want too many if-else conditions. Of course, you will always
need to have some level of if-else condition. That's a whole part of programming, but you always
want to be mindful of where the divergence happens. What's the worst case scenario?
What's the worst case scenario in something like this?
You get a branch divergence of two then. So, one thread does one thing or 31 threads do
another thing. You only get branch divergence of two. What's the worst case scenario?
They all have different conditions. Every single thing is trying to do a different part of the core
and all the threads will have to wait for every single other thread. Not the thing you want.
So, best case scenario, all the threads do the same thing. Even if it's an if-else,
you can try to make them do the same part of the core. Sometimes you can't avoid a branch
divergence. So, it's okay. It's not the worst thing in the world, but you don't want to be
getting to those worst case scenario type of things.
So, let's do a couple of exercises. An SM on a GT200 can host up to 1024 threads.
How many warps is that? Easy question.
It's 32 warps. 32 threads in a warp, 1024 threads, 32 by 10 or 1024 by 32 is 32 again.
So, 32 warps. If three blocks are assigned to an SM, each block has 256 threads. How many warps is
that? Loudly. So, we have a total of 768 threads, 32 threads in a warp, divide 768 by 32
by 32, that's 24. So, you'll have 24 warps in total.
So, in a G80, there are 32 threads in a warp, but only eight streaming processors.
In modern-day architecture, there's a lot more. Modern-day architectures, you have 192 or 256
cores or sometimes 128, but in a G80, you only had eight. So, we said warp runs always together,
but there are only eight cores. How can a warp run of 32 threads run only with eight cores?
So, to do that, this is what we do. An SM scheduler essentially used a clock cycle
to schedule eight threads at a time. So, it did eight threads in the first cycle, eight more in
the second cycle, eight more in the third and fourth cycle. So, four cycles were used to dispatch
a warp. It wasn't just one cycle. Modern-day, it's one cycle, but back in the day, it was four cycles.
So, another exercise. A kernel has one global memory. So, about 200 cycles
and it has four non-dependent multipliers and arrays. How many warps are required to hide that
memory? So, this is getting into how we want to hide latency by using more warps. So, we have a
latency of memory reads. How can we launch enough warps so that memory latency is hidden? So,
you remember that step diagram that we had before? How many warps do we need to hide that
latency? It's a question. Anybody want to take a guess? 50? You're ignoring one part of that
equation. You're on the right track, but you're ignoring something. No. So, 200 by 4 is certainly
part of the equation, but there's one more part to it. How many? So, we said four non-dependent
multipliers and ads. That takes time, right? Even if it's not 200 cycles, that takes time.
So, if we assume that four multipliers and ads take 16 cycles, then to cover 200 cycles, we divide
200 divided by the number of cycles that we need for the four multipliers and ads. So, instead of
counting four multipliers and ads as one clock cycle each, we have to count them as 16 clock cycles
and that will give us 12.5 and we want one more than that, so it'll be 13. So, we need to launch
13 warps to make sure that we are hiding that latency. So, these are just exercises, but the
core point overall is to make sure that warps execute together to reduce branch divergence in
them and try to make sure that they are all executing the same thing at the same time.
Any questions on warps before I start moving into other parts of today's agenda?
Yeah, so to launch enough warps, you have to see how your kernel is running and then make sure
your block size is optimized for that. That's why sometimes you may want to pick a block of 128,
sometimes you may want to pick a block of 1024. So, again, it depends on a lot of factors that
we cover through the entire course, but for now, think of it as how many threads you're launching,
how much memory read you're doing, and stuff like that. That's a thing, like we define that
by the code or it can be another run back. No, that's why you do the block dim and grid dim,
like when you're setting up the kernel, before calling the kernel, you're defining how many
threads per block, right? So, that would be defined by you, unless you go over the resources and the
hardware does other things. Any other questions on warps?
Okay, there's a lot more to learn about warps, but we'll slowly go over it.
No, so each multiply, each multiply and add, it's called an FMA, floating multiply and add,
takes about four cycles by itself. So, if you do four of those, that's 16 cycles. It's not about
waiting for memory of it. The operation, the floating point operation, it just takes the cycles.
Because if you have 12, then at some point, all the 12 warps are going to wait for the
for memory and there'll be some level of waiting before the first warp becomes ready to execute
again. So, that's why we want one more, so that it's always computing. It's fine as warps are
waiting. We're not worried about warps waiting. What we're worried about is not having something
to execute. So, we can launch 15 blocks or 15 warps, we can launch 20 warps, not a problem.
What we want to make sure is that you're not launching less warps and having the GPU wait for
memory. Any other questions on this? So, warps are not something you necessarily
ever write in a program. You'll never use the term warp in a program. What you'll essentially do is
make sure that your branching conditions and other things are aligned to 32. So, it's more
of a hardware concept and a debugging concept as you've seen in the debugging lab.
So, let's look at memory. So, we touched on it a little bit last class, but let's dive a little
bit deeper into it today. So, you saw this diagram of course, there are five types of memory,
registers, local memory, shared memory, global memory, and constant memory. And then the host
can read and write to global memory. So, let's look at each one of them. Registers are the fastest
kind of memory. They are on a per thread basis. So, one thread's registers cannot be accessed by
another thread. They are fast, they're on chip. So, they're very close to the compute CUDA cores
essentially. So, they're basically instant. I believe they're probably one or two blocks high
for me. Increasing the number of registers used by a kernel has what effect then?
So, I think this was asked in the last class probably by somebody. If you have all registers
in a kernel, how is that going to affect your kernel? It'll be faster? Maybe? What else?
We don't have infinite number of registers. So, what could it affect?
The number of threads that can be executed at the same time. Is that what you said?
Fewer. Fewer threads can be executed at the same time.
Yes, you are along the right lines, but tell that to me in another way.
That's like slower memory. So, we can like store the unused registers.
But that's not what I'm trying to get at. What I'm trying to get at is
on a GPU, you only have so many transistors. And like we've seen, most of them are assigned
to CUDA cores. Some of them are assigned to memory and some of them are assigned to registers.
So, you only have so many registers on a GPU. There is a numerical limit on it. What happens
if you use so many registers in a kernel that you surpass those limits? For example, just for quick
numbers, let's say you have a thousand registers on an SM. And your work, maybe not a thousand,
let's say you have 20,000. And you launch a block of 1,000 threads.
You can at most have, on average, you can have 20 registers per thread.
20,000 registers total on an SM. 1,000 threads per block. You can have 20 registers per thread.
What happens if you use 25? That's my question. What happens then is essentially
the blocks get broken apart or the number of watts executing at the same time has to reduce.
So, let's take this example. On a GID, we can have 768 threads. We have 8,000 registers.
How many registers per thread is that?
It's about 10 registers. So, let's say if we go to 11 or 12 or 13 registers,
what happens is, let's say in the example of 11 registers and each block has 256 threads,
how many registers is that? 2,560 or 2,560 plus 256, whatever that number is.
But what does it mean for how many threads the SM can host?
So, each block has 256 threads. If we were under the 10 registers limit,
how many blocks can we host? If we are under the 10 registers limit,
how many blocks can we host per SM?
We can host three blocks because the limit is defined by the number of threads.
3 times 256 is 768. So, if we are under the register limit, we can launch three blocks.
But if we are over that limit, if we have let's say 11, 12 or 13 registers,
then maybe we can only launch two blocks because the third block will not have enough registers
to store memory. So, if we were to go to 11 registers, we only launch two blocks.
So, that's essentially what it means for overloading resources. So, it's not just
the number of threads that dictate how many blocks execute on an SM. It also is determined
by how many registers, how much shared memory and all those kind of things that you're using.
Any questions on this?
What if one thread uses like 10,000 more than eight?
There's no, I mean, at some point you're going to run into an error where
CUDA is going to complain that it's going to give you a runtime error essentially,
saying that I can't launch this kernel.
Any other questions on this register memory?
Okay. So, there are a few special registers, so thread IDX, block IDX, block IDX,
block IDX, and print them. They're all special registers so they don't count towards
your register allocation and usage. So, the next type of memory is called local memory.
Technically, this is not a physical memory. What it means is when we allocate too many registers,
some of those get spilled over and get stored in global memory and are cached so that they are
faster for use. Then no one's going to be close to how fast a register is. It's local because
it's in the private scope of the thread itself, but not on the physical registers that we have.
So, that's essentially like spillover memory.
So, it hurts performance in two ways. First, it increases memory traffic because now, if you're
going into local memory, you're not just increasing the number of clock cycles you need to
cover for because it's slower than registers, but you're also decreasing how many other things
can use global memory because it's taking up bandwidth. It's taking up that read-write resource
because it's stored in global memory. Sometimes, that spilling may not always be bad. In very,
very rare cases, you ideally want to avoid it, but sometimes it may not be bad because it
gets stored in the L1 cache. Any questions on local memory? Most of the time, again, you wouldn't
know if you're using it. If you're doing something bad, the profiler will complain about it.
If you're doing something bad, the profiler will complain about it, but by itself, you're not going
to see this as something that you're going to... There's no create local memory for me kind of
thing. It's a very inbuilt concept when you use too many resources. All right. The next type of
memory is shared memory. This is something we're going to use today as we go into matrix multiply.
So, shared memory is per block. It is also per SM because, remember, a block will always execute
on the same SM. So, shared memory has a certain limit per block and there's a scope per block
and there's a hardware limit on an SM. It's fast, maybe not as fast as registers,
but it is fast enough that you shouldn't worry about using shared memory. It is still very much
an optimization and it has full random access. So, you can read, write as you want.
So, let's see this. I mentioned that there's a block limit and a SM limit. So, let's say per SM,
you would host eight blocks and each SM has 16 KB of shared memory. How many kilobytes per block
can we allocate on average? So, you have 16 kilobytes and you want to allocate up to eight
blocks. On average, how much shared memory can we give to each block? Two. Then give two. Now,
similar to the previous example, what if we gave each block five kilobytes? Then how many blocks
can an SM host? Three, because you'll hit that limit at 15 and then the other blocks will have
to go on to other SMs. Any questions? So, I haven't dived deeper into shared memory. I just
want to show how it's conceptual. When we get into magics multiplied, that's when we'll talk
a little bit more about shared memory. Any questions on this?
Okay. So, global memory, which by now you're all probably used to, is hundreds of cycles. It's off
chip. So, it doesn't actually live on the chip itself. If you see any picture of a GPU, you'll
see that there's a central chip in there and then you'll have these black dyes all around it. Those
black dyes are the global memory. So, that's why there's a bus and a bandwidth on it. It is still
actually very, very much faster than your CPU RAM. So, if you have 16 or 32 GB RAM on your laptop
or desktop, the global memory on a GPU is still way faster than your CPU RAM. It's just way slower
than registers or shared memory and that matters when you're doing parallel compute. So, reads and
writes can do it. Complete random access can have performances because, as I was mentioning earlier,
when you do reads from global memory, they happen in chunks. They don't happen
one float or one intact time. They happen in a group and it's really fun. These are some very
old numbers for GT200 and G80, but some of the modern GPUs can hit 300, 400, 500 gigabytes per
second. Compare that to a CPU RAM, which can probably hit about 30, 40, maybe gigabytes per second.
The last memory is constant memory. So, constant memory is essentially a special global memory
that is cached and it's only read-only for the GPU. It's read-only for the GPU,
so only the host can write to constant memory. Once you write it and you launch your kernel,
it's read-only. Kernels cannot write to constant memory and it's up to 64 kilobytes because it's
mostly going to store information that is valid across the entire GPU kernel's lifetime.
So, just some terms here for how we're going to define these. So, registers and threads,
registers you do int x or float x. That's how you define it. It's both for a thread and this
for the kernel's life. Local are automatic array variables or anything that spills over.
To define shared memory, you're going to use undersponders for shared. To define a global
variable, you're going to use undersponders to device. Same as you use for function,
you could potentially use it for this. And then the last one is constant,
which you can use for defining constant variables on the host.
So, quickly to see how we can read-write constant memory. You don't use CUDA mencopy for constant
memory. You do symbols. So, get CUDA symbol address is essentially like CUDA mallet,
except you're getting the memory address for where your value is going to be stored.
CUDA gets symbol sizes, how much memory you're allocating in CUDA global memory for constant.
Mencopy to symbol and mencopy from symbol is similar to CUDA mencopy except we are
specifically saying symbol here. So, that's an example of how you're going to use our constant memory.
This line here, very important, has to be in global scope. It can't be inside main or any other
function. It has to be defined on the global scope because the compiler needs to know how much memory
needs to be allocated. So, that's a very important thing. So, with that, I think let's take a break
now. Let's come back at 6.40. We'll have Wayne's recitation and then we'll come back to Moore's
intro to CUDA stuff.
Okay.
All right. Is everyone ready for recitation?
Okay. So, I hope everyone's hopefully at least looked through project one. It's a
relatively gentle introduction to CUDA, but it's a very fun project. I really enjoyed it. So,
hopefully you guys will enjoy this one. So, Boyd's flocking on a GPU.
So, let me make sure this works. All right. So, what's a Boyd?
So, a Boyd actually stands for bird-Boyd object. So, basically it's just like a... So, the term Boyd
came from Craig Reynolds and it's basically... He did like a simulation to simulate how birds
keep flocking. And so, he basically crowned the term Boyd. So, it's essentially simulating
flocking. And if you've taken a CIS 562 computer animation... So, Craig Reynolds is also the guy
who came up with a lot of behavioral animation. So, you'll probably be familiar with that.
But really, flocking is only like a small part of what he's doing. So, it's kind of like a
particle simulation. We have particle, or void, however you want to call it. And they have position
and velocity data. And we store them in two separate buffers. So, in the PLC, the position
velocity buffer on the GPU. And those are four defaults. And yeah.
So, what I want to do is actually show you guys what the...
Just to make sure that you guys know what flocking looks like. So, if we go to...
So, your results should look something like this. So, you can see...
So, basically, each point is like the void. And then they're flying, they're flocking. So,
they'll start to group together. And they're going to fly together. And we've color-coded
each void group by colors. So, as they kind of join together, they're going to become the
same color. And that's kind of a way that you can identify that they're indeed going towards each
other. Okay. So, let me go back to the presentation.
So, the way flocking works is basically around its neighbor,
based on some radius. And we look at what the velocity of the neighbor is. And then
based on that, depending on whether I should go, you know, avoid it or
follow the velocity. So, there's basically three types of sources that kind of affects
how the board moves. One is cohesion, one is separation, one is alignment. And you don't
actually need... For this project, you don't actually need to know what... How the voids
actually work. So, if you go to... If you go to instructions, so there we give you like the
pseudocode for... Okay, rule one, this one is cohesion. Rule two, this one is to keep a small
distance away. So, this is separation and finding there's alignment. So, if you follow this pseudocode,
you should be able to get the basic result for the voids flocking. And we've provided all the
parameters for you. So, like the scaling factors, the search distance, and you shouldn't have to
change those, but feel free to play around with them to see... To get different behaviors.
But yeah, so that's flocking. Now, let's go back to slides again.
So, you start the project by doing the naive method. And the naive method is basically you
loop over every single void and then you... So, when you do voids, you need to look at their
neighbors. And the naive method of doing that is you look at... You look through all voids and to
see if certain void is within the radius. And doing that is super slow, but that's the first
step. So, you want to make sure that you actually get that working first before you
move on to the second or third... The second and third parts. Okay.
Okay. So, to actually do a simulation. So, it's again, it's kind of like a particle simulation.
So, you have time steps and for each time step, the void was just going to first look at
neighboring voids to determine the new velocities. And then it's going to update the position based
on the velocity and the time. So, that's pretty straightforward. The one thing to note here is
ping pong buffers. So, does anyone know what a ping pong thing means for this case?
Okay. So, yes, it's switching buffer, but why do you want to do ping pong buffer?
Yeah, that's right. So, you're reading and writing concurrently and that's why
we want to switch it so that we're not overwriting what we're currently reading.
When you read your neighboring voids, you're looking at voids, but at the same time, you're
writing. So, you want to make sure... And that's happening in parallel. So, you don't want to make
sure you're not overwriting what you're reading. And so, for this, if you look at the code...
So, we provide you dev. So, dev means device. Hopefully everyone knows by now.
Device position, device velocity 1, velocity 2. And if you wonder why we need velocity 1, velocity 2,
it's because we need ping pong buffers. And so, once you've
write your new velocities and you do your ping pong buffers, then you update your positions.
So, after you've done the naive method and hopefully you'll see the flocking behavior,
you can start up with some small number. But if you really want to crank it up to, say,
like 100,000 to even millions, it's going to be super slow. And this is when you need
some sort of spatial data structure to optimize it. And this is very...
It's very common in lots of graphics applications where they just introduce spatial data structure
to accelerate things. So, for this project, we want you to implement a uniform grid. So,
you're basically spatially dividing the space into a grid with uniform cell width.
And then, so, each void here, for example, here you have some voids and they may lie
in certain cells, but not in others. And that way you're essentially calling out what are needed
to be searched. So, for this project, you don't really have to worry about sort of defining
what the grid size width are and then the kind of the individual cell width. We have that defined
for you. So, if you look at the code here in initialized simulations, you'll see that this is
where we set up the grid parameters for you. But you have to make sure that you know,
because later on you're going to need some of these variables to calculate, for example,
where which grid certain void is in. So, this is where you should kind of look at.
And so, for this project, we have defined
the grid width. The search way is the grid width is 15 times
and only have to search through 8 to 8 cells or 2D is 4. So, you can see that
because 9, there is culture of exception to these things.
Okay. So, you're going to need to calculate where, which grid cell
you want. So, to do that, you have to know sort of the low position of the grid. And by that,
you have to know, okay, where is the minimum, where is the very minimum point of the grid
for the world space. And based on that, based on that, so you're given the forward position,
you have to find which cells. So, for example, here, we want to find 42. And
the way we do that is so we can say 42 is at 2.4 and negative 5. So, there.
And then divide that by the cell. And then once you know that, it's going to give you
an Ix. So, the cell of the x direction and the cell number in the y direction.
And because the grid, even though it's the ultimate representation,
it's still like the 1D array. So, we want to find that into this one index.
It's sort of like the threaded index with x plus resolution. Sorry, 10 percent.
And for 3D, it's very similar.
Any questions up to this point?
Yeah, it cannot be greater than an egg, but yes, you have to consider the edge cases where
it's at the corners. Or at the edge, then it's also like, like might be in between.
So, in this logic that you're talking about, there was a problem in the scenes. But in this case,
we're also given indices, which is supposed to like store the like index. So, like my understanding
is like index of zero. But indices of zero gives you the index for the zero point that would get
you its corresponding position and velocity. But how is that different from just,
because in assigning this, right, like what we call the current computer disease,
you are just going through all of the voids one by one and calculating, computing their grid cell
index, right? So, I guess in the first pass, do these all in order? I'm confused as to like what
to assign the values of indices, because if we are accessing the position, we are accessing,
so yeah, we're accessing the positions in order to have the grid index, then doesn't that index
already like tell us, like don't we already have that index? So, if you don't sort anything, then
yes, you do have that index. But because we're sorting, then your index no longer aligns anymore.
And that's why we need to keep track of an extra array of the actual index of the indices of the
voids so that when you sort it, and I'm going to go into why we're sorting actually just right now
in a bit. But you're right. So, one of the biggest challenge for this assignment is really
understanding those buffers and like what goes into them.
Yeah, the reason
one model is built more, and because of the randomness, when I was talking about
real memory, they said random access is bad. So, more we want that access to be
fluorescent as we say, you'll get to that more in future class, but we want as much as possible to
be accessible at the same time. So, then the question is, how do we get all the voids
in a certain cell once we have the uniform grid defined?
So, the answer is that we use a key value sort, and this is when we actually need that extra
buffer to keep our indices under the voids. So, a key value sort is when you have,
for example, like a dictionary key value, but then basically when you sort the key,
the value has to fall with it. And this is very important for this project. So, we are,
yeah, so we are, when you do compute indices, we are sorting saying, okay, which cell the
void belongs to, and we store that into grid cell index. So, you should see that as a buffer.
And then we're sorting that, we're sorting grid cell index as well as the voids indices
based on the grid cell index. And I'm going to, so this image here actually is going to be
visualized. So, at the top, you have, so right now, we have, for example, we have at the top,
we have the 15 cell for grids. And the first step, we go through each void, we assign it.
Is there a laser producer? This step here, the first step we do is we build through the voids,
we're like, okay, which cell will be the one? So, 0, 5, grid cell 5, 5 as well. And then,
at the same time, which is whatever you're wondering, it's like we're keeping another array
at the start, it's 0, this is 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, which is just the sequential order.
But when things start to get tricky is in order to find, to represent this grid and to be able to
find, to know, to get, basically to access them, which voids are in the cell, you need to sort,
this is when you start sorting. And so, the key essentially is this part and the balance.
And so, once we sort it, we get this sorted. So, now your array is not squinted.
And so, what happens here is because whenever you're doing the computation or whatever you're
doing in the neighbor search, you're always accessing all the voids of that cell. So,
having it in continuous form like this essentially helps with that and allows me to access
continuous memory. The reason we don't access, don't sort the voids and position and velocity
vectors is because we don't need to access those in continuous fashion. So, it's fun to keep them
that way and then we can use the releases to access them using that. Any questions about
like this part, like the sorting, how we walk over. So, sorry. So, another part of this is that you
need to, so these parts, this part is in the compute indices function. So,
here you have the kernel compute indices. So, that's the part you sorted the grid indices.
And then, after you've sorted it, you need to identify the cell start and end.
And this is, if I go back to slides.
So, this is where this is sort of representing is that, okay, now I need to figure out based on this,
what is the start and end cells that would point to,
the points basically point to the starting point of this buffer that contains, okay, what's
what word are they? These are like dictionaries.
You can think of it as a dictionary, but they are, it's just like index, I mean,
index. So, this is, there are two separate arrays, right, but like for instance, what I do,
I do, I look for the first element in the grid index, void index, right. Those refer to the same
void, right. That tells us that void number eight is in grid cell zero. And if I were to
find the eight index of the position where the velocity vector is going to be finding that,
So, these are the main buffers that you need to work with. So,
again, I just want to stress that it's really important to understand what each buffer is for
and then like whether like, and specifically like what the indices represent and what their
values represent. So, just having that understanding will be really helpful for this product. So,
the particle grid indices, this one stores which grid the void belongs to. And then this array
indices, it's like, it contains the pointer to your actual like position and velocity.
And these two will get sorted. So, yes. So, in that case, first off, we need to
balance by our symbols, right. Second, the particle array indices that will be initialized to just
like zero equals zero, like zero, zero, one, one. So, then that will get messed up.
And the cell start indices, great. So, these are, once you start to get to that grid,
then these are representing actual grids. So, the size is actually great. So, for particles,
the size is number of voids. For grid variables, the size is great count.
Yeah, great research.
Okay. So, any questions up to this point? Yes, sir.
So,
x times like the numbers of rows and the y. So, if you look at this here, exactly like that.
Any other questions? Okay. So, the last part of the project, and it's not as big of a
modification. So, the last part you need to do is, so, so far we are, okay, we're sorting
the array and then we have, we are doing coalescing for, I guess, for the grid part.
Okay. So, we're doing, for the grid cell index, this is, we're doing coalescing. And the last
part, we just, we're just sort of like optimizing one step further by saying that, okay, since we
are, we, so right now we're, we have, say we have a grid cell index points to eight, we still have
to go to eight in another array that tells, another buffer that tells us, okay, what position
the blocks are. So, the last step is essentially removing this, sorry, essentially removing this
extra step. And the way you do that is that you would, as you rearrange this, this point index,
you would, at the same time, rearrange the position of blocks. Yeah. So, if you look at here,
um, now you're, we're sort of rearranging position blocks until it matches the x of,
of what the array index is, how the array index is sorted. And this will optimize further. So,
any questions on this? Yes. My, if that's the case, then what is the point of even having the
point of the x in?
Guesses for iteration? You have to remember that those, those buffers, you know, there's
code as a table that they're actually able to buffers. Yeah. Like we're not using that for
accessing anything. I don't think that's entirely true. We still use it for, um, the understanding
when we move things based on how the volumes move around the sense that, um,
we need to keep that around.
Okay. So, we're basically at the end here, but some tips for you guys. So, first of all, um,
we didn't define all the kernels that you need. And we also didn't define,
you may need some extra buffers as you see fit. Um, definitely use the unit test to test some of
your kernels. Uh, it's very helpful. And also definitely make sure you watch the Cuda debugging
video.
Look at the variables and kernels. Um, so yeah, so between naive to semi-coherent,
basically after you finish naive and then, sorry, after you finish uniform grid,
that's a lot of change, but from uniform grid, naive uniform grid to semi-coherent uniform grid,
uh, it should look very similar. And then, so a lot of copy and pasting, that means you're
doing the right thing. And finally, uh, something to consider is when we're doing a index 3D to 1D,
we're flattening, um, the 3D index in this fashion. And something you want to think about is when
you're traversing the grid cells. Uh, so say you're using, if you're using a for loop,
so it's because some people might hard code it, but if you do a for loop, um, you want to think
about how, which order, like do I look through X first, Y first, or Z first, which one will get me
the most optimal result considering like memory contiguous access. And we're not going to give you
the answer, but just think about that, um, how do you optimize that? Does that make sense?
So just make sure you're memory, you're accessing memory,
but coalescing. And again, Shazam's going to go into more why you want to do this and how you do
that. They don't. This is good for me, you know, this project has been the first project in the
class for a while. So while you may seem daunting and you're like, oh my God, well,
these buffers are really, as you start getting used to it, as you do the first nine
two grid, uh, implementation of it, that's when you start getting into the buffer names.
And then that's when you start going to uniform it, you start getting more used to it. So
programming, I'm sure you've all, have all been in classes that have been said projects where
you're starting to write some code, you're getting used to it. So don't be afraid.
Our discussion, we'll always try to respond quickly.
In terms of the visual reward, this is already going to be one of the best projects in terms
of performance, and you can talk about it. So it'll be really fun, especially as we start
getting up to those many other points, you'll start seeing how much better it is than, uh,
than you see people want you today. I think if anyone else has a question, feel free to
present it out. Not that we can go back and forth.
Okay.
All right. So
looking, I'm obviously looking forward to all of your projects. We get some really cool gifts in
the readings at all times. So make sure you're putting enough time into it. Don't wait until
the last minute. You'll get into trouble for that. Not for me, for yourself. So, you know,
be sure to start early. So coming back to threads and warps and stuff. So let's look at how
synchronizing thresholds. We said warps execute, you know, at the same time. So let's dive a little
bit deeper into that. So let's take this example. Very simple. Something we should all be used to
in terms of code now, where we have, where we calculate some thread index. That is...
Okay. We calculate some thread index using this very common equation by now,
using blocks and grids to compute the global index. We do... No idea why this is not working.
We do some read from global memory. We do some function on it and then write it to some global
memory. Everybody should be like, this is the bread and butter of this course now.
So threads in a block can synchronize. We use a function called sync threads,
underscore underscore sync threads to create a barrier essentially. What that means is,
a thread called waits until all threads in the block hit the sync threads function.
Okay. So let's take this code as an example. It doesn't really matter what that code is
doing, but let's see how that executes.
So look at the time here. Okay. That's going to be important. Look at the arrows. And for this
example, only for this example, we're going to assume a warp time. So I put that out there.
Okay. So our first two threads are warp zero. Our bottom two threads are warp one. Okay.
So at time zero, we are going to execute warp one and we are going to execute the first line of that
and they're going to execute it together. Okay. So time zero. So at time one, we've executed those
and we've hit the same threads. What happens now? These warps are in the same block. So what happens
now once these hit sync threads? So now warp zero is like, oh, I can't execute any further
because I've hit sync threads and I need to wait for all of my co-block threads essentially to
finish hitting that sync threads as well. So this, it's a stall. Okay. This is a stall here.
So thread zero and one are blocked at the barrier. So the scheduler is going to be like, okay, warp zero
you're paused. Let me bring in another warp. So it's going to bring in this warp, execute that line
and now it executes sync threads. Now what happens?
The end block. Yes. Because now all the threads have hit sync threads, right?
So now the threads can move forward. Which one executes next?
So we are, our warp, this warp is active. It's syncing threads. All the threads are
syncing threads. What executes next? This one or this one? This one executes because it's already
active. Even though we have zero cost warp switching, because this is already active,
this is going to continue into the next line. So once this is done, we go back into the previous
warp, finish executing that and we're done. So any questions on how this is executed for sync threads?
This executes inside a block. You can't do sync threads across many blocks. Each block
can do its own sync threads, but if you're trying to do one thread from block to one and another
thread from block two, they can't synchronize. So any questions on sync threads so far?
Everybody gets it? Okay. So now we saw this a little bit earlier,
but why is it important that execution time be similar among threads?
We scheduled by warp. And if we scheduled by warp and some threads take more time than others,
then some threads are going to be waiting longer than others, which means our GPU is
possibly. So just as we don't want branch divergence to be costing us more time,
we don't want sync threads to be costing us more time either. So that's important.
Why does it only synchronize within a block? Why can't we synchronize across blocks?
Sure, but sync threads doesn't work using shared memory. It uses some other mechanism.
But you may be on the right track. Think about what's one step lower than that.
Not in terms of memory. What is the other condition on blocks?
Remember how I said blocks execute on the same SM? All threads of a single block always execute
on the same SM, which means they execute on the same part of the chip. There's no way for different
blocks to talk across SMs on a hardware level, except maybe global memory, but that's more newer
controlling it rather than the hardware controlling it. There's no way to synchronize across blocks
because they could be executing on different SMs. And we don't have a way to synchronize that.
And it would be too costly on a hardware level to synchronize that. So
sync threads only works within a block. Any other questions?
There is no guarantee on which blocks run on which SM. No guarantee at all. The other thing
you should think about is if you're doing something like that, can you change the algorithm to make it
different? And I don't know if it's the next class or after that. We will look at a few algorithms
and how we synchronize using that. But essentially you don't take traditional CPU algorithms and just
put them on GPUs. You see how you can change them to parallelize them and optimize them as well.
Any other questions on sync threads?
Okay, let's look at it a little bit more. So in this example here, each block can execute in,
like I just said, there's no guarantee on which blocks execute where. If you have
different types of devices, different types of architectures, they can execute anywhere. So there
is no guarantee on which block executes where. So the only guarantee you have is all the threads in
a block execute on the same SM. That's the only guarantee that CUDA gives you.
So with sync threads, can we cause it to hang? And what may cause it to hang?
As a reminder, sync threads is a barrier on a block network that doesn't allow threads to
progress until all threads are hit back. So what are potential scenarios in which a sync threads
can cause a block to hang? Thread crashes, that's certainly one of them. So what happens here?
Does this cause a hang?
So what about this?
What happens now?
So let's say half threads are here, half threads are there.
So they're essentially waiting for, both of them are waiting for, let's see if we have a thread,
both of them are waiting for A, but they all only get four. So
So these two sync threads are not the same. It's almost a cardinal sin in GPU programming
to put a sync thread inside a condition. You may do it in very, very, very special circumstances
where you know all the threads in a block are going to hit that and those conditions are very,
very bad. So if you are putting a sync thread inside an if condition, try to think about why
you're doing that. So don't put sync threads inside an if condition or it will cause a turn on your hand.
So my next slide is going back into matrix multiply. So any questions so far today?
So you're asking for the variables that are getting passed into the kernel?
If they're in global, then yeah, you could come. Yeah, it's essentially a copy.
You'll have a CPU version of it and a GPU version of it.
Any other questions on what we've discussed so far?
Okay, let's look at how all of what we've learned today is going to come into play
in matrix multiply. So let's revisit it. So CPU implementation, you know, you're
iterating through i and j. Again, i and j are of the output matrix. You come in, you do a dot product
on each vector as a row and as a column. I assume no questions so far. We've discussed
in detail in the last class. On the CUDA side, let's look at the CUDA kernel once again before we
try to optimize it. So we have the global to specify the kernel, the void to specify that
nothing is returned from a kernel, and then constant types for which are read buffers and
which are write buffers. We calculate the indices for the output matrix. There are no for loops here
because the for loop is implicit in our multi-threading. You allocate the allocator.
Which memory are we allocating this in? What memory are we storing p-value in?
It's in registers because it's a regular declaration that we are doing.
We do a for loop so that we are now doing the dot product. We read the memory. We do the dot
product and accumulate and then write it into global memory once. So what are some of the
problems here? We discussed some of these in the last class. What are some of the problems?
Matrix size is limited, yes. What else?
Matrix shape, we can only do squares. Edward?
What's one more? What's the last one? We discussed this in the last class.
What about memory?
Maybe, but more simply, we are doing global memory reads inside a for loop.
And maybe all the threads, a lot of threads are trying to read the same memory over and over again.
So our problems are it's limited matrix size. So maximum is a square. We can do 32 by 32 because
it's one block and then it has a lot of global memory access. So let's see how we optimize this
and scale it because we don't just want to optimize it for one block. We also want to scale it for any
size. So let's see how to do. What we're going to do is a kind of a sliding window approach
combined with shared memory. So first, to remove the size limitation, what we are going to do is
break our matrix, especially our output matrix into blocks. I use the term blocks because
essentially that put up blocks. So each part of this PD matrix will execute in one block
and use thread IDX and block IDX to identify which part of the memory we are going to be writing.
Any questions on this? We'll see how to write the code for it, but just the idea of this. Does it
make sense? Another thing we are going to do. So the way to a very simple example of this is that
we have a four by four matrix and we divide it into two by two blocks. This is what it looks
like. We have block 00, 01, 00, 01 and 01. And again, remember the blocks represent the output
matrix and then we'll read the required memory to execute those. So this is what it looks like.
Tile width, I put it in red because anytime you see red or blue stuff that generally represents
code. So we're going to use that tile width variable. So now how does this actually work?
How do we do the dot product for this? So let's see block 00. For index 00, we need row 0 and
column Z and multiply that here. So do a dot product. For PD10, we need row 0 and column 1.
What are you noticing? Both of these PD00 and 10 are reading MD, row 0. So you're reading that
MD twice. Same thing for MD and this. Same thing for column and these two. Now imagine doing it
from the entire matrix. So PD00, 10, 20 and T0 are all reading row 0. So that's something we
cannot do. So let's look at this. So this is the kernel that we have. We are going to make
made a few modifications. First, we have a global index calculation. You guys are used to this.
I don't have to explain but I'll walk through it again. Calculate the the row index of PNM.
I may have that maybe a typo.
Yes, pointing to the wrong place. I should update that. I changed the template that I
used on the slide so it kind of pointed to the wrong place. So essentially between these two slides.
My clicker is not cooperating today. Between these two rows, you're calculating the row and column
of PMNM depending on which version you're using. So each thread computes one element of the P
submatrix. You have many blocks. Each thread in a block computes some part of the P output matrix.
We'll skip the for loop for now and we'll come back here and this again is very similar. You've
seen this before where we calculate the index where we should write and write the value.
Everybody clear on these two parts? How we calculate the global index and how we calculate
the output? Any questions so far? Okay, let's switch to the CPU side. One of the limitations
we had was we could only do 32 by 32 before. So now see how we're changing this. Each block,
we've got these blocks now. Dimension of block is tile width by tile width. Remember how I showed
you the 2 by 2 and the 4 by 4 matrix? That the tile width is going to dictate how big our blocks
are. So that's why tile width by tile width. The number of blocks we need are now the width of the
matrix divided by tile width and similarly width of the matrix divided by tile width.
Now of course there's some seal and stuff that we should do so that we are accommodating for
rectangles but for now let's assume this works. Then we'll launch the kernel
similar to before and using dim blocks and dim gates. Any questions on this?
Okay, so global memory access. So one theoretical slide here before we go back into matrix multiply.
On a G80, peak gigaflops is 346. This is 14-15 years ago. So on a modern RTX card or something
like that this is going to be many many teraflops. I don't even know what the latest number is. I
should probably check. The reason this number is here is because if you want to achieve that
many gigaflops you need 1386 gigabytes per second of memory bandwidth to make that possible.
Ignore the math behind it. We won't get into it but believe me that's the number.
So this number is probably still double of what is modern day bandwidth
and we're talking about something 15 years ago. So basically impossible to achieve. The real
world memory bandwidth of a G80 is 86. So we are talking almost 20 times that.
What that does is limit our matrix multiply implementation to about only 21 gigaflops.
So clearly not optimizing our GPU performance. Remember how I said we want to be scheduling
enough watts. How we want to always keep the GPU occupied. This is clearly not
executing the GPU in an optimal way. This is very subpar. So that's what we want to improve
about how we access global memory so that we are improving our performance.
So let's see how to do that. So we discussed before how there is enough duplication in how
we are reading them. So for example these two elements both read py. They both need that single
column and we can use shared memory to duplicate that. So let's see it on a block level.
Okay. So let's assume this. Let's take this block for example. We also don't have unlimited
shared memory. So we can't read the entire matrix into shared memory. We can only read parts of it.
So for this kind of block execution what we're going to do is we're going to read the blue part
into shared memory and we're going to read this blue part into shared memory and do a dot product
for that sub matrix essentially. Then you're going to read the orange part, the orange part
and read that. Do it. The reason is, the reason this works is when you read this orange part,
you don't need this blue part anymore. You're done with it. The dot product is sequential.
The values here don't need to get multiplied by the values there. They only need to get
multiplied. These values only need to get multiplied by the values there.
So you can override shared memory. So the amount of shared memory you need drastically reduces
because you use this sliding window. So if you do this, you slide. You do this, you slide.
So that's what allows you to do it much faster and maintain that data locality.
So for each thread, now we're getting closer to the programming side of it.
Each thread, because our blocks are these and the number of elements we bring here will be the same
or at least we want them to be the same, each thread in the block reads one element from here
and one element from up here. What that means is we are also reading memory in parallel into
shared memory. So each thread only needs one element instead of the entire matrix,
which we were doing before on the entire row and point. Now we are only reading one at a time.
So that's another optimization. So let's see how this looks in code.
The first thing you're going to see is two new lines. This is one way of declaring shared memory.
You say shared, float, and you give it the dimensions. This is going to get stored in
shared memory. The next thing you do is you break up your global memory computation. You know how
you were calculating index as block size times block dim plus thread x. You're breaking that out
and we'll get to why in a bit. The column and row kind of remains the same, but you're
using the temporary variables for that. See how this has changed now.
M defines the phase of our window. Remember how I said it would be a sliding window?
So M is going to be that window essentially. M by time width is the number of windows we need,
the number of times we need to move that window.
So now we're reading memory into shared memory. We are reading global memory into shared memory
and remember how I said we are doing it once for the time. So there's no
for loop k. The for loop k is down here. Here if we read this, each element is reading one element
and putting it into our shared memory sub-matrix and we do that by this. So this index M should
be pretty clear. SM and SM and see how we are mixing up the row times width plus this
and column times this plus row. Why are we doing that? Because we need row from one matrix and
column from the other matrix. So that's why we are changing the indexing. Then in the for loop k
matrix, we are no longer reading global memory inside this matrix like we were before.
All we are doing is taking the shared memory and reading it here and see how in these two lines
Tx and Ty are the same. But now Tx and Ty are on if this is our major, this is our minor.
That's because we need rows and columns. We're changing which one we need and that's why we
install it as the temporary way we would say. So once we do this, once we do the dot product
for the sub-matrix, let's say we are done with the sub-matrix, we go to the next window now.
So this k is not for the entire row, not for the entire column, it is for the sub-matrix only.
That's why we do k less than ty. Any questions so far on this?
So if we don't have any separation lines, not shared or global, any variable we define here
automatically they're all ready. So let's say you don't put the shared here,
this float SM, this will go into global memory.
Any other questions so far?
No questions. Everybody got this? I'd be surprised. I'm impressed.
Okay.
Once you get to the second same print, all that has happened on all of your friends and
friends so far is going to be the first element of the sub-matrix.
That one is inside of the...
Right. So let's iterate over this. So m equals zero means you are...
So this is m equals zero. Two is m equals zero. Red is m equals one. Okay.
When m equals zero, you're operating on this. When m equals one, you're operating on this.
When m equals three, you're operating on that. So essentially zero, if you think of this here,
that's when you're operating. Okay. So now...
Definitely not positive. Okay. So m equals zero, m equals one, we're doing that.
These two lines are essentially reading our blue and red part. Remember, there's the only
loop for this is m. So we're reading this once for the sliding window. We're reading two global
memory per thread per sliding window. Okay. Here, now we have to do the dot product for
the sub-matrix. That's why we have the k here. And this is our compute. This is addition,
multiplication of shared memory. All compute. It's all shared memory, so it's very fast.
So this is not a performance bottleneck anymore. Before it was because we were doing the global
memory read inside here. No longer a performance bottleneck. Now, if you could call it a bottleneck,
it's here, but it's already optimized. We are already reading it once per thread anyway.
So this is also correct. Any other questions on this?
Okay.
Run it. Run it on your computer and tell me. I have a number towards the end, but
run this on your computer and tell me how much it improves. Any other questions?
Okay. So like Constance asked,
why do we have, she asked first thing, but I'll go to the second thing. Why do we have the second
thing? Yeah, that's spot on. So let's get to the first thing. You're reading into shared memory,
right? All the threads in the block are reading into shared memory. Let's take it when m equals
zero. Okay. Nothing has happened. There was a first time you're reading into shared memory.
Why do you need the same threads?
The value of different area in the matrix for your data. So you want to make sure that the
whole sub-matrix is copy. And what determines that?
That all threads are run. So because that's the index of the sub-matrix.
So what she's getting at is we said all the threads in the block run on the same
method. We have that guarantee. What we don't have a guarantee of is when the warps run.
Right. So warp zero might have executed this and is ready to do this, but warp one may not have read
this. Warp one may have garbage, right? Warp one's part of the shared memory may have garbage.
So we can use this in threads to ensure that all the warps of the block have finished reading into
shared memory. Otherwise we'll get like part of blue and then everything else will be garbage
and that won't work. So we have the same threads here. Why do we need the same threads here?
Like Constance said, if we don't have the same threads here, let's say warp zero finishes this.
It's going to go here and it's going to override shared memory for the next window. Now in warp
zero, M becomes one and it overrides the shared memory before warp one executes this. So now warp
one is reading garbage. So we have to make sure that at all times shared memory has the correct
version of the sliding window. And that's why we have same threads so that no warp is left behind
and no warp is going forward without all the warps being the same.
So now you see how sync threads works with shared memory. So general rule of thumb is if you are
reading into shared memory or writing to shared memory, both of which have been here, you're
reading and you're writing, always put the sync threads around it. Or at least start with the
sync threads around it and then see if you can remove them. Any questions on this?
Okay. Sorry, it's covered by the watermark there, but that last line is essentially the
same as we've been doing before and we are writing to problem method.
So any questions on this kernel so far?
So let's see from the form. Before we had a kernel, when each thread was reading
two times the size of row and the size of column. So if you had a matrix that was 1024 by 1024,
so about a million elements, each thread was reading 248 values from global memory,
which is insane, like that's a lot. And a lot of threads are also reading duplicate
values because they're reading the same rows and the same columns. Now what we have is a structure
where each thread is reading m sliding window, the number of sliding windows we have that many
times of global memory, that's it. Instead of reading the matrix size, we're reading sliding
window size. So let's say we have a matrix that's 1024 by 1024, so a million elements,
right? And our target is 32 by 32, so 1024 threads per block.
So the number of sliding windows we get is 1024 divided by 32. So we are decreasing our memory
reads by a factor of 32. So now you can imagine how we've optimized from going from 2048 memory
reads to maybe like 64 memory reads. And that's where the performance comes in, multiply with
that by 200 cycles of a global memory read and boom, you've optimized your performance.
So that's how we have to start thinking about GPU programming. It's not just doing memory reads for
the sake of memory reading, but how do we optimize how we are reading so that we're doing more compute
and less waiting, okay? So let's take two questions quickly before we end the class.
How do we pick tile width and how can it be too large? So any thoughts here? How can we pick a tile width?
Maybe, maybe not, not necessarily. Like although the code I've shown ignored some parts of it,
but yes, you can do it on rectangular matrices, you can do it on non-multiples as well.
You would have to write if-else conditions that ignore those threads, but you can absolutely do it.
So what about tile width has a limit?
Yeah, or total threads in a block. So your tile width can't be greater than 32 by 32 essentially.
And how can it be too large? If you try to pick a tile width that's 64 by 64,
then it's going to be more than your SM or your blocks can handle. So that will be another
limit there. The other limit can be based on shared memory. So depending on your GPU,
most modern GPUs may or may not run into this problem. If you have too many blocks for SM
and you're allocating a lot of shared memory, that can lead to an overflow and then you get
less number of blocks per SM. You're not going to run into an error, but you're going to get less
number of blocks per SM. So you'll get something like this kind of calculation.
So the benefits of shared memory tiling are depending on how big your tile width is,
you're reducing the number of memory reads per thread by that much of a factor. So if you if
you're tied with the 16, you're optimizing your memory reads by a factor of 16. If it's 32,
you're optimizing it by a factor of 32. So based on this, if we use a factor of 16, remember how we
said our old kernel was only like 21 gigaflops. Multiply that by 16, you almost get 245,
345, 360 gigaflops. So it's all because we optimized how we are doing our memory reads.
So that's when I was asked, how do we know the performance is going to increase?
That's how we know. Just by understanding that we're decreasing our memory reads,
we'll increase our performance. It's plain and simple.
So to put that in again, put that in math. If our tile width is 16 by 16, that gives us 256 threads
per block. In a kernel that or in a matrix that's 1024 by 1024, so a million LEDs,
this gives 64 by 64 blocks of total of 4000 blocks in total. Everybody clear so far
about this math? So 1024 by 16 is 64. So each thread performs two times 256
loads. Loads are essentially reading from global memory. So you're doing 512 loads
from global memory. And in total, you're doing 8000 by 192 multiply max. This is from our dot
product operation. So why am I saying this? Remember how we went back to that example where
we had four floating point operations and 200 cycles of global memory read? This is exactly
that problem. You have 500 memory reads. You have 8192 multiply and add operation.
How do you hide all of those memory reads that you're doing that you have to do? We optimize them,
but they still have a latency, right? Even though you're doing one read per thread,
that still has a latency that still makes the GPU wait. So what we're essentially doing here is
you have that memory read. How can we hide it even more? We're like, go sit in the closet while
the other warp executes. And then when you're ready, come out and do your work. So this is how
we're optimizing it so that it's no longer a memory bandwidth problem. It just means
if one warp is hitting a stall, to quote Hydra from the Marvel movies,
if one warp hits a stall, there are two more to take its place.
So that's how we are optimizing it. The memory reads essentially get hidden,
the latency gets hidden away, and we are always doing compute.
So any questions on this? So that's the end of today's lecture. I'm more than happy to take
any questions. And just a reminder for anybody, I may have email to stay back to stay back because
I would have forgotten if I didn't put that there. So happy to take any questions if anybody has.
I think Wayne might be able to take, let's divide in content.