And if we can get started whenever you're ready, I'll do an introduction before you
go with your slides.
Okay.
Yeah, I'm sort of trying to just get one thing in here.
That'd be nice to have.
Yeah, I guess.
I already have the PDF form up so you guys can look at that.
And put that in a...
Let's see what we know.
How's it going to use the slides here?
Huh.
Ah, the mystery slide.
Let's zoom in here.
Let's see.
Hmm.
Ah.
Okay, hold on.
Yeah, one more minute.
Ah, I just have to email it.
I figured out everything in the world, like when you have this sort of minimized zoom,
how to actually email it.
If you want to email it to the class post.
I saw that Patrick joined as well.
All right, thanks Eric.
Okay.
Eric, can you hear me?
What?
I can't hear you.
Yeah, yeah, I can hear you.
I think this should be okay now.
I have to switch the microphone.
All right.
All right, welcome everybody to our first guest lecture of the year.
Guest lectures have always been a big part of the class.
Back when I was a student, we had a few back then as well,
so it's been a growing tradition and it presents a really good opportunity
for students like yourselves to get insights from the industry
about what the leading cutting-edge technology is,
and some of which you might be working on when you take full-time jobs
at some of these companies.
I'm sure NVIDIA is going to be a big hire again this year,
so certainly some of you might be working on exactly what Eric talks about today.
So our first guest lecture, and first guest lecture for quite a few years nowadays,
through the years, has been Eric Haynes.
This is Eric's fifth consecutive year guest lecturing in the class
and has been an amazing friend of the course in both his advice
and research that he does and shares it with the class,
joins our final projects and all that.
So Eric's background is incredible.
He started with a degree at Cornell back in 1986.
I wasn't born then.
I'm pretty sure most of you probably weren't born then either,
if not all of you.
So that's essentially when the Cornell box was created at Cornell University,
and Eric was around for that.
And through the years, Eric has done so much for the graphics community.
He's really been a pioneer of it.
Some of his major accomplishments have been while he was at Autodesk.
He spent almost two decades there, so a lot of the software you use today,
Maya, 3ds Max, and others have a lot of his work in real-time rendering built in.
About five years ago, in 2018, Eric Haynes joined NVIDIA
as a distinguished researcher working on real-time ray tracing,
a lot of which he's going to be talking about today.
His hobbies, if I can call it, include Minecraft,
and Eric was pivotal in introducing real-time ray tracing into Minecraft
using DXR, DirectX Ray Tracing.
And yeah, he's a curator of real-time rendering resources.
He's an author of real-time rendering and has also contributed to ray tracing gems.
I could be here and speak for an hour, and I wouldn't list all his accomplishments.
So Eric, thank you once again for sharing your time with us,
and we look forward to another amazing guest lecture over the next few minutes.
All right, thanks for the lecture, Son.
Yeah, so right, I've given this lecture each year, and each year it changes.
But luckily, the basics of ray tracing don't change.
So I'm just going to run through.
I've got way too many slides because there's sort of a lot of new, cool stuff
that's just come up in the past few weeks, and I sort of want to stuff that in there.
But I hate getting rid of the old stuff, so I'm going to just talk very rapidly.
But the good news is that I have put the PDF of all these slides,
which also includes in the notes a lot of pointers to resources and so on
for the various things I'll talk about.
So if I talk about something for 10 seconds and you're like,
what the heck was that, you can always go back and look.
So anyway, ray tracing, very basic idea, very simple idea of, gee, I want to form an image.
Well, okay, think of basically if you look through any little pixel,
what you're looking at is, you know, what's the closest object to the eye?
And so we've done that in the past with rasterization,
where we're sort of throwing all the triangles of a scene against the image plane
and figuring out which pixel, you know, which triangle goes where.
And, you know, if there's five or six triangles that overlap,
which one's the closest one for each pixel?
Here, for ray tracing, we kind of reverse the process.
We go pixel by pixel and look at the scene and basically shoot a ray,
compare it to all the objects, and say which one's the closest.
So that gives us what's at that pixel.
And then we can continue to shoot rays to do other things.
So the simplest one is just to say, well, I want to see if that surface that I've hit is lit or not.
And so I shoot a ray at the light, and if nothing blocks it, then I'm illuminated by that light source.
And that goes way back to 1968, this guy at IBM, Arthur Apple.
And anyway, so it's sort of an old idea, but, you know, a nice simple way to get shadows on things.
In 1980, the seminal paper really was Turner Whitted at Bell Labs at the time,
and he came up with the idea of, hey, gee, now we're sort of reversing the process.
Instead of looking at things from the light's point of view,
let's look at things from the eye's, you know, point of view and shoot out rays.
And we got this idea of transparency that, in fact, was sort of around for about a year before Whitted came up with this.
Like, in fact, I'll claim, you know, Cornell actually had one person who wrote a paper about, you know,
using it for transparency and so on.
But Whitted made the really important mental leap of going, hey, you know,
we could start reflecting and refracting rays through and start making a tree of rays and evaluate that.
And so that's a pretty simple idea.
It's basically you're sort of assuming everything is either not reflective or it's highly reflective,
like it's mirror-like or it's glass and very, you know, very well-polished glass kind of thing.
And so at its simplest, let's say you're looking at a piece of glass.
You shoot a ray out from, you know, through some pixel and you hit the piece of glass.
From there, you spawn maybe a shadow ray to see what's going on on the glass's surface.
Is it lit or not?
But more importantly, the glass is mostly transparent and so on, a bit reflective.
And so you shoot two more rays, one that's a reflection ray going down below
and then another one that's going through that's a refraction ray.
And then from there, you might again shoot a shadow ray and then continue on.
And there's another refraction ray and a reflection ray and so on, you know,
test those for shadowing and decide whether they're lit or not.
And then you basically have this big bushy tree of rays and you kind of evaluate them from the bottom up
and eventually you figure out some color of, you know, whatever's coming to your eye.
So that's sort of basically what's called classical ray tracing.
And about four years later, Rob Cook and a number of other people at Pixar came up with this idea
that they called distribution ray tracing, which is still a term that they use at Pixar
but pretty much nowhere else in the world.
Everyone else calls it like stochastic or something else other than distribution
because distribution makes you think of distributed computing, which is not at all what this is.
His idea, though, is a great one, which is basically so you may have a glossy surface,
something that's kind of polished but not quite totally reflective.
He said, well, why don't I shoot a burst of rays out from that and sort of add those up,
you know, over that for that ray instead of just trying to get a single reflection direction.
And he said, well, I could apply this to other ideas.
I could apply it to shadows or I could apply it to motion, motion blur.
So the idea is that you may be shooting rays where, you know, each ray is sort of over a bit of time.
Like you can say, OK, well, from 0 to 0.01 seconds or something,
I'll shoot a ray at 0.01, 0.02 or whatever, you know,
basically in that little span of time and add those up essentially.
And that way you can get these sort of blurry objects because at each point of time, the objects are moving.
And so you evaluate them differently each time.
But to just make that a simple example is one for shadow rays where, so I've shot my ray,
I've hit my object, and then I basically shoot more and more rays at the area light.
And the more rays you shoot, the more expensive it is,
but the better approximation you get as to how much of the area light you see.
Is it fully illuminated, partially illuminated, sort of in a penumbra like shadow?
Or is it fully in the umbra, fully shadowed?
And so with that kind of approach, you get, you know, these nice images.
And so the next step then is about two years later,
Jim Kejia came up with this idea of diffuse interreflection where instead of sort of following glossy surfaces
and sort of saying, well, let's shoot a burst of rays in the direction that the glossy surface likes,
he says, well, for a diffuse surface, what do you do?
Well, you kind of shoot rays in all directions.
And the idea is that you sort of follow each ray that you're shooting
and you just follow it and keep shooting it.
And you sort of hit some new surface and shoot another ray and just keep bouncing around.
And the idea is that eventually that ray will hopefully hit a light source.
And that's the catch is that there's sort of this apple limit.
In other words, you may have to do a very high number of bouncing of these rays.
And so we tend to have shortcuts for some of this path tracing stuff where we try to figure out good ways to shoot those rays
or else we just say at a certain point we call it quits and say, okay, well, just tell me how the light sources are affecting me along the path.
Anyway, there's a lot of tricks, but at its limit, you have this idea of path tracing where you're just kind of taking a ray
and saying, okay, from my eye I'm going to shoot a ray.
I hit this diffuse box.
Diffuse just means like a matte surface isn't reflective, like maybe concrete or something like that.
And then I shoot a secondary ray in some direction and I just keep doing that.
So this next ray happened to hit a light.
Well, that's great.
That's going to get a big contribution of direct illumination from that.
But you have these other rays that are sort of bouncing around and they're picking up light.
And hopefully they get to some light source basically and pick up some light.
But basically the idea is you're just shooting more and more rays.
And eventually you add up all the past contributions and get a color for the pixel.
And this is what's commonly done for computer graphics and films is they have the luxury of not having to be interactive.
So they can take 20 minutes a frame or two hours a frame or whatever they like.
And so they will typically shoot anywhere from 1,000 to 5,000, you know, you name it.
Sky's the limit.
You know, sort of number of rays per pixel, number of these path rays per pixel.
So that obviously is a little bit pricier than interactive.
But anyway, the whole point of this is that ray tracing is great because it's so simple.
So Paul Heckbert had part of this for graphics gems.
He basically had this little contest of, hey, write a little ray tracer.
Try to make it as small as possible.
But it's still doing something interesting.
And so here we have this, you know, 1,607-byte ray tracer, which basically it's just super compressed and kind of crazy and so on.
But what it basically does is it ray traces a bunch of spheres because a ray is a very simple object.
It's just a point and a direction.
And a sphere is a very simple object.
It's just a point and a radius.
So combining those two, it makes for a simple quadratic equation that you solve.
And you can get this sort of nice, you know, reflections and refractions in this case and shadows and whatnot.
Here's another business card that's even smaller and has a lot more spheres.
And anyway, you get the idea.
So your first quiz question here, and this is my chance to take a little gulp of water, is which one of these is the real photo?
And I don't know.
I have to look at my course notes each time.
And it's the one on the left, it turns out.
And this was an experiment done in sort of mid to late 80s where we had this idea of this Cornell box, this sort of simple box scene.
And we said, well, let's make a real one at Cornell.
And let's, you know, actually compare it to what our simulations are giving us.
And we're in pretty good agreement.
And it turns out the answer is yes, so that was good.
So just to look at that Cornell box and to sort of go through some of the ray tracing things we've just seen.
So classical ray tracing gives you these hard shadows.
And the hard shadows are done by, you know, that little tiny point light at the top here.
And then you have these rays that you just get a single ray that goes to that point light, and you see they're on or off, very binary.
For soft shadows, you have a nice area light.
So you might shoot a bunch of rays at that area light, and that gives you these nice soft penumbras.
And then there's interreflection, or called indirect lighting, or color bleeding, or global illumination,
or the sort of old-fashioned Cornell thing was called, we solved it with this thing called radiosity,
which is just sort of a heat transfer kind of a system.
But anyway, the whole point here is that you're essentially doing, nowadays, you're doing a path trace.
And you, you know, shoot from the, you're basically shooting paths from some point on your surface.
And you go, okay, we'll just start bouncing rays out.
Okay, I bounced one out here.
Oh, great, it hit a green wall.
But then I bounced it again, and oh, look, it hit the light.
And okay, so that means some, you know, this wall over here, it got some green.
So that's why this area in shadow is a bit green, and this area of shadow on the other side is a bit red,
is because it's bouncing light around.
What's good to keep in mind here is sort of the reason we're shooting rays from the eye as opposed to the light,
is if you think about it, if you shoot them all from the light, you have lots of rays bouncing around,
and they're depositing, you know, they're sort of hitting things and warming up, you know,
various surfaces and having some physical effects and so on.
But the amount of light that actually gets to your eye is really,
really tiny compared to how much light's bouncing around the environment.
So that's one way to think about why we kind of reverse that process.
And, oh, finally, there's just glossy reflections, which is, again,
you get these sort of softer reflections here.
And, again, you're just sort of shooting up in more of a quick fashion.
You can just think of it as shooting out a burst of rays.
And so here's just another example of a ray trace, which is just varying the glossiness of the surface
and showing how that varies.
Just another ray trace.
And here's, I think this is another quiz question.
Which ray tracing effects are you sort of seeing or are you seeing in this environment, in this picture,
as opposed to if you just tried to make, like, a rasterization version of this thing?
And so that's my chance to go up water.
So, yeah, here's the three things that I see, at least, are soft shadows.
So you're getting the softer shadow because you're shooting a number of rays towards the sun.
And here's the glossy reflections where it's not a perfect mirror reflection,
but rather you're, again, sort of shooting and getting more of a glossy kind of a thing by shooting more rays.
And you also get inner reflection, which is basically, if you think about it,
the light in this scene is just where the sunlight is.
And maybe you could say that some of the light is bouncing off of this ceiling here.
But, really, the whole area is lit because of path trace kind of thing,
that you're actually picking up light from bouncing rays around and picking it up from other surfaces and other areas.
There's one other place where you might see ray tracing get used.
And it's almost more of a ray casting thing.
And it's kind of a fake global illumination effect.
There's no actual lights in this scene.
All this scene is being lit by is a thing called ambient occlusion.
And the idea there is that it's kind of in the name.
Like ambient light is one where we sort of say, well, just add a fudge factor to the scene so that nothing's totally dark.
So people do that by typically, you know, you put a light at the eye in the scene so it doesn't cast any shadows.
It's just giving a little light to everything.
Or maybe you just color everything 10% brighter or whatever.
But with ambient occlusion, what you're doing is trying to get something that's at least sort of physically based.
And the idea there is simple enough.
It's just saying, well, given some point, think of a hemisphere above that point.
And shoot out rays in kind of a random stochastic pattern in that hemisphere.
And just see is anything within three feet of me or not.
And if something's within three feet and I hit it, then I'm probably dark in that area.
I'm in a darker spot in the scene.
And if I don't see anything, so like, for example, this other sample point here, I shoot out a bunch of rays.
And most of them don't hit anything.
So that's more well lit.
That's kind of another interesting use of ray tracing, where it's not really truly a global illumination algorithm.
But it's a popular one for games and so on.
There's a bunch of variants on this.
There's other faster ones, but they're less reliable.
So using ray tracing gives you a more consistent result.
Another thing you can do with ray tracing is depth of field or background blur, where you're basically focusing the camera.
And there you're kind of changing where the ray starts on the lens, essentially, or on the lens system.
And so you can imagine the lens is kind of focused on those characters.
So they're nice and sharp, but everything else gets a bit blurry because the rays are kind of coming from different angles and adding up to give this kind of blurry effect.
And you can change the, you know, change where that depth of field is by changing the focus distance.
So the character in the back is in focus, and you get this foreground blur.
And this is one that, again, you can do a lot of faking as far as rasterization goes.
Like games have had this kind of depth of field stuff, you know, in them.
But you kind of have to do a lot of fakey filtering and sort of kludgy stuff.
What's nice about ray tracing is it just kind of falls out.
You know, you just make a little variation in what you're doing, and you get these cool effects.
And as I mentioned, you can get this motion blur effect, which is just basically kind of time slicing,
but trying to do it in a semi-random way so that you don't get, so that it doesn't just look like, you know, five separate images added up together,
which would look kind of clunky and would look kind of, you know, jagged and so on.
Here you're trying to get sort of this smooth thing by doing this.
And this is used all the time for, you know, computer graphics and films, for sure.
Another one, you know, Shazan mentioned I like Mineways or Minecraft, and indeed this is a Minecraft scene.
And it's done in this renderer called Chunky.
And basically, you can get atmospheric effects by doing ray tracing, where instead of ray tracing where the ray just goes through the whole scene,
you instead kind of march along the ray and find out, you know, volumes, essentially volumes of space where,
okay, there's light here, there's some kind of medium, like there's dust or whatever in the air, water vapor, whatever.
And so you have a scattering function, basically.
And so you're able to sort of walk through that space and add up the scatters,
and that gives you that kind of occlusion, that atmospheric effect.
And one last effect that I'll mention is what's called caustics.
And here what's happening is this sort of, it's like a pool, like a swimming pool, where you have some waves on the top,
and you'll see, you know, if you're on an indoor pool at the YMCA or whatever, you get these, you know, sort of caustics on the walls.
It's a little more obvious under the water, you sort of see at the bottom of the tank, these caustics form.
And this is just kind of a clever real-time effect that was done in Ray Tracing Gems 1.
There's an article about how Guy did this.
There's also beams of light kind of thing going on here.
So the caustics normally are pretty tough to do because you're having to trace a lot of rays.
But you can get these really glorious effects.
You're sort of having to, if you're sort of tracing from the surface, you're kind of shooting a lot of rays towards the glass
and seeing, you know, which ones get to the light, and that can be pretty pricey.
There's, in fact, like I say, there's 101 algorithms for this kind of stuff.
You can also reverse the process and really do shoot light from the light and go through the glass and deposit what's called like a photon map
and sort of, you know, say, well, where did all the, you know, did the photons gather anywhere?
I shot a whole bunch through the glass from the light.
You know, where's the hot spot and so on.
But this is kind of done the right way, as it were, kind of doing with path tracing.
You get these really nice effects.
And, yeah, with that, I want to point out one danger.
Don't be me.
That's basically the story here is that, and I've seen a lot of other ray tracing people rendering.
So you'll gather little artifacts.
You'll gather like, oh, here's this cool piece of glass or here's this, you know, piece of marble or piece of copper or piece of wood.
And, you know, see how do these materials work and what's going on with them.
You tend to gather these goofy little things.
And I've been gathering, you know, so I had this little crystal ball thing for a few years.
And I moved from one office to another.
And then I was moving to yet another office.
And I kind of looked closely finally and was like, hey, wait a second.
What are those marks at the bottom?
And, yes, they are indeed burn marks.
You know, here's I'm showing it sort of in the sun.
It's, you know, focusing some burn here.
Luckily it did not step out of the office on fire or anything like this.
So just be aware.
Don't put your shiny or your glass objects in your window basically.
In fact, if you Google, it's not so funny.
Because, like, if you Google, you know, snow globe fire, you know, about once a year there will be somebody whose house catches on fire because they put their, you know, snow globe out during, you know, before Christmas in their window.
And it focused like a lens.
So anyway, those are sort of the basic ray tracing techniques out there.
And they do get used in different kinds of games.
You know, there's reflections, global illumination, shadows, and so on.
So those are kind of the big ones.
So I'm going to move now to hardware.
So ray tracing is one of these things that's called embarrassingly parallel.
Because it's kind of obvious how to make it faster.
You know, we're going pixel by pixel.
So, hey, I've got an idea.
And in fact, Turner Witt is sort of the first I heard of this idea, which was he talks about, like, you know, people asked him, well, hey, gee, how can we speed this up?
How can we make ray tracing fast?
And he said, well, I'll tell you what, what you do is you get a Cray, which at the time was the fastest supercomputer.
It's now nothing at all.
But at the time it was the supercomputer that could, you know, compute a bunch of rays per second.
And he said, well, just get a football field full of those.
And on the top of each Cray you put a red, a green, and a blue light bulb.
And you basically have each Cray feed its pixel result and turn on those red, green, blue bulbs accordingly.
And then you fly the Goodyear blimp overhead and, you know, you can see your picture lit up.
You know, very, very simple system.
But the point is, is that, you know, basically if you put a processor on each pixel, you can get a pretty darn fast system.
That's a little more, you know, more transistors than we really have the ability to do.
I mean, you know, if there's a million or two million or however many pixels per, you know, monitor, cheap monitor, nowadays you can't quite do that.
But the idea is sound, that you can do a lot of this stuff in parallel and there's not a lot of crosstalk between the pixels.
They're all pretty much independent.
And one of the things that, it's funny actually, like, because our CEO, Jensen Huang, gave this keynote talk a few weeks ago at GTC,
which is a conference we have every few months or so, just saying, you know, here's what's going on with NVIDIA.
And here's how much other, you know, cool talks and so on.
He said, oh, you know, Moore's Law is ending.
And that made the press, which is like, I'm like, how did that make the press?
He's been saying that ever since I joined the company in, you know, 2018.
So they're finally starting to pay attention to, wait, wait, wait, the same Moore's Law is ending.
And it's sort of the strict version of Moore's Law, which is the idea that, you know, as we go along in time,
the number I like to use is that every five years, processors get 10 times faster.
Or another way you could say it is every five years, processors get 10 times cheaper.
So the same processing power is a lot less cost.
And his basic point is, is that processing power, you know, we're able to stuff more and more transistors in the space.
And we're able to sort of scale them down to a certain extent.
But that process is becoming more and more expensive.
And we're sort of losing that percentage kind of a thing.
And so this slide is actually from Google.
So it's not just NVIDIA saying Moore's Law is ending.
Anyway, so NVIDIA's kind of answer is to say, well, with GPU computing,
you can try to focus on various tasks that we really want to accelerate and try to still keep them competitive as far as cost.
But we need to have specialized hardware.
I mean, if you think about when you're designing a chip, a microprocessor, you basically have three ways you can use your transistors.
You can make a couple of transistor and a capacitor, and that gives you a little memory, one bit of memory.
Or you can make a general purpose processor.
Or you can make special purpose hardware that does special things, basically.
And that's really about the three ways.
And so NVIDIA's thrust is, well, we put in special purpose hardware for rasterization.
Gee, is there other special purpose hardware?
What kinds of things are coming down the pike?
And what should we try to accelerate?
And so NVIDIA's answer in 2018 was to have this idea of, well, we'll add some more things.
And this is just kind of schematic.
This is a marketing slide.
It's not how much of the footprint actually gets these things.
But the idea is that we added tensor cores, which are for artificial intelligence, deep learning, evaluation of neural nets.
And we added these RT cores, ray tracing cores.
And the ray tracing cores, as well, focus on in the next bit.
But basically, we added special purpose hardware with the idea of speeding up things that we saw as common to various processes.
And so, yeah, just a week and some ago, I guess, kind of lost track of when exactly that was out.
But anyway, this new thing, Ampere, is this next generation.
And, you know, it's sort of new, new, new.
It's sort of new, various kinds of shaders, RT core, tensor cores.
There's also this sort of optical flow accelerator, video engine.
So there's other goodies that are basically getting put on the chip and so on.
And just trying to, and that's sort of how NVIDIA works to a good extent is, you know, we have a large research group.
Some of it's for software.
You know, we actually have a bunch of software that we try to get out to the world, you know, in various forms so that people can take advantage of GPUs.
But there's also, well, we actually, you know, what looks good and promising for hardware.
So, if you know rasterization at all, or even if you don't, the basic rasterization just goes through this idea of you emit a draw call.
You say, I want to draw this triangle or this mesh or whatever.
And a bunch of vertex shading occurs, vertices get moved around possibly or whatever.
And then you rasterize, you basically form triangles out of those vertices, throw those at the screen.
You pixel shade, and then you blend whatever that does shading, you know, determines what lights are hitting the surface and so on.
And then you finally output that triangle as needed to the screen, if it's visible or not.
Ray tracing is kind of the same thing in a sense, but you're generating rays instead of throwing triangles at the screen.
And the important difference really is that you're going through this traversal idea.
So, you're going to traverse the scene, you're going to find out what the ray hits, and then you're going to shade what the ray hits.
But you also, by shading something, as we saw, you have a sort of tree of rays, like you're possibly emitting more rays.
You're making maybe a shadow ray or a reflection ray or whatever.
And so, that means there's sort of this recursive thing where the shading can emit more rays.
It can go and throw another ray into the pile.
It's basically, you know, there's sort of a whole bunch of rays coming in, and they're kind of grouped up and set up to figure out.
They're not all done simultaneously, since we have less processors than pixels.
So, this part's, yeah, sort of the RTX part, NVIDIA's part.
The other trend that's going on is just more and more memory is getting available.
Like, if you think about how much memory you need to save, you know, even a 4K image, it's only a few megabytes.
And there's not, you know, there's red and there's green, there's blue, and there's a whole bunch of pixels, and that's how many bytes you need.
Even if it's high definition, you may only need twice as many bytes.
But, you know, the number of bytes is in the, you know, 10 million at most kind of thing.
So, what all the other bytes are for is basically putting model data or any other kinds of structures you need that'll help you out.
And so, or textures, things like that.
So, this has gone up over time.
And so, a single processor, a single GPU might have, like, 24 gigabytes at the higher end.
But you can also have these really crazy processors where you have, like, 16 GPUs tied together over a fast bus.
So, they're all sharing each other's memory.
And that can get you up to, you know, 512 gigabytes.
And those things cost, like, you know, I forget, $300,000 on up or whatever for a serious machine.
But, you know, if you think about it, like, film, for example, I know as of a few years ago, I don't know what the average is now.
But when they sort of polled a few years ago, the number was, like, oh, for a complicated scene, it was 50 gigabytes of data for a single scene, for a single render.
You know, lots of texturing, lots of detail, all that kind of stuff, crazy amounts.
And so, you know, it's nice if you can get into that spot where you can fit all the data into the machine and just have it crunch on that image.
So, talking about assets, there's sort of an interesting thing in software.
This is from Unreal Engine, which is from Epic, you know, just a game engine commonly used.
And one of their big things in the past year or so has been Nanite, which is just they've really tried to get a hold on, well, how do I deal with, you know, some city that has, you know, 7 million instance assets?
In other words, 7 million separate objects.
And each of those may have millions of polygons in them.
How do I deal with this level of detail?
And so, they have a software version or a software system, which I'll talk about a little bit later.
But if you think about it, even if you're at sort of far away from things, you may still have just a ton of models out there.
And, you know, you shoot one ray into that.
Well, you know, what are you going to do?
I mean, you don't really want to shoot a ray against, you know, 5 million triangles.
That would be shooting a ray against, well, is it hitting triangle one?
No.
Two?
Three?
No.
So, the way ray chasing speeds this up is the one we've chosen, at least, is the bounding volume hierarchy.
And it's the one that's kind of won out in the data structure, as I think of it, as in the 80s and 90s.
There were lots and lots of ideas, grids and octrees and all kinds of things.
But the one that sort of won out as most flexible and efficient overall is the bounding volume hierarchy.
And sometimes you'll see other ones just because they fit, like, if your voxel rendering might be much more suited to just have a grid that you're walking or things like that.
But, anyway, bounding volume hierarchy, very simple idea.
So, imagine you have a ray coming from, say, the left, and it kind of skims over the top of this sphere and hits this red object at the top.
So, what you're doing is you'll test that ray against the root node, which is this big circle here.
And you say, well, okay, I hit the root.
All right, so that means now I have to test against the two circles inside.
Well, the rays up here, it hits this circle on the top, but it misses this circle.
So that means all these objects to the right side of the hierarchy can all get thrown away.
I don't have to look at any of those.
So that's where the savings comes, basically.
And here the ray continues.
It maybe hits the spheres here and finally hits the object.
It's tested against the object itself.
But as you get more and more objects in a scene, you get this sort of order log n kind of behavior.
And obviously logarithm of n is much smaller than n, which is the number of objects.
And here's what the algorithm sort of looks like more realistically.
We have these things called AABBs that are axis-aligned bounding boxes.
And they're basically just a ray bounding box operation is a nice, fast operation.
And you can test against a bunch of boxes.
And then you kind of go down the hierarchy until, you know, you may miss a bunch of triangles and finally hit a triangle.
Okay, great, you're done.
But again, you've, you know, instead of having to shoot against all the bunnies triangles, you just maybe shot against a small subset.
So these ray tracing cores are focused on three things.
Basically trying to do this bounding volume hierarchy as quickly as possible.
So that just stays local to the bounding volume hierarchy.
The bounding volume hierarchy just kind of goes and says, okay, you know, I'm walking this ray through this hierarchy.
Did I hit anything? You know, okay, did I, do I go deeper in the tree and so on?
And it just keeps track of all that.
The other thing that accelerates is ray triangle intersection.
So again, it can all be local to this little ray tracing core.
It doesn't have to go out, leave the ray tracing core at all and go, you know, go to some other processing unit.
And triangles are very popular, basically.
Everything sort of gets made of triangles eventually in most systems.
You know, you can, ray tracing is very flexible and that you could, you know, shoot.
If you have a ray that can go against some other object and have some equation or some algorithm to solve it, sure, use that other object.
You know, we showed spheres earlier, they're nice and simple.
Subdivision surfaces, you know, whatever you like, implicit surfaces.
There's a bunch of object intersections out, you know, that you could do.
But realistically, like for games, which NVIDIA certainly points at, they've traditionally used triangles for everything.
You know, you turn it all into triangles eventually.
And so, indeed, we have a particular ray intersection triangle, ray triangle intersection rather, that's just super fast and optimized for hardware.
And then there's just this idea of instancing, that you can make lots of copies of the money and it can keep track of that, essentially.
It can understand how those objects get shared so that they're not taking up so much memory.
And then you come back to the shaders, which NVIDIA calls stream multiprocessors, SMs, if you ever look at NVIDIA literature.
And those are more like general processors.
And so they do other things like instancing or intersection or, you know, like they can do ray sphere or whatever, and traditional shading and so on.
So just to give you a flavor, there's five kinds of ray tracing shaders.
So if you start actually trying to write a ray tracer or look at ray tracing code written for Vulkan or any kind of other API DirectX, you'll see these kinds of five shaders.
There's the ray generation shader, which is just sort of, it's called trace ray.
It's the one that's kind of in control of the ray.
It starts the ray out and sort of says what do you want to do with the ray and so on.
There's intersection shaders, which, like I say, you have the built-in one that's for triangles or you have the, you know, make your own, roll your own.
And then there's these last three, which are sort of a group.
And I'll just show the groups, in fact.
There's miss shaders, which is like, well, if the ray goes through the whole intersection structure and misses everything, what do you do?
Closest hit shaders, in other words, you hit something with your ray, what do you do?
And then there's any hit shaders, which I'll talk about more in a minute.
That's a special kind.
So how do these fit together?
Well, there's sort of this whole, you can look at this complicated flowchart kind of thing.
But here's an easier one, just to get a flavor.
And it's really just sort of saying what I said before, but just at least you can kind of look at this without getting too distracted by bounded boxes and whatnot.
Which is just simply, you have a ray, starts on the left.
You say, okay, shoot that ray into the scene.
So that's going to go through that acceleration traversal, ray tracing core.
And, you know, if the ray basically gets down to a box and says, oh, okay, there's something in this box.
You know, if it's a triangle, we can stay in hardware that's specific in that RT core.
But one way or the other, we're basically doing an intersection shader.
We're saying, well, did I hit that object or not?
And then maybe we use this thing called the any hit shader, which, again, is mysterious at this moment, but won't be in a minute or two.
But, you know, we go through this loop, basically, continuing to say, oh, no, no, I missed.
Okay, next object.
Okay, I missed.
Next, next, next.
And either I hit an object or I get through the whole traversal.
If I hit an object, I do a closest hit shader.
If I miss, I do a miss shader.
And then I return from trace ray.
But this closest hit shader can also spawn rays, which then go and, you know, go back to this process again, the acceleration traversal.
And that's it in a nutshell, basically.
That's how the hardware works.
So what's the deal with the any hit shader?
Well, there's this idea of cutouts.
And these actually turn out to be fairly significant.
Like I was reading a thing a year or two ago from Call of Duty guys, the guys who were doing Call of Duty.
And they said, boy, if we can just feed up one thing, it would be, you know, for rays hitting vegetation.
So like in this scene, there's some vegetation.
This is a pretty elaborate scene, but it can be done in real time.
And, you know, if there was lots of vegetation, though, it could slow down.
The trick with vegetation is we use a trick, you know, at least in the games industry, they use this trick a lot, which is instead of actually making a, you know, you could make this thing, this leaf out of maybe hundreds of triangles to make sure you got the nice leaf shape and all that kind of stuff.
But instead, we usually make it out of two triangles.
Out of two triangles.
And we basically apply a texture to it that has an alpha channel, a transparency channel.
So either a pixel's visible or it's not visible.
So these areas out here are just where it's actually transparent.
So what the anti-edge shader does is you're going through your acceleration structure and you hit something.
You say, oh, I hit this leaf.
And the intersector says, oh, leaf.
Oh, oh, wait.
Yeah, I've looked up.
I've hit the leaf.
I've hit one of these two triangles.
But I don't know if I've actually hit the leaf or if the ratio continued.
So that's where the anti-edge shader comes into play.
And what the anti-edge shader does is it basically goes, oh, okay, just a minute.
Let me flick through the book here.
Oh, here's the texture.
Okay, let me look up the pixel.
Oh, oh, you hit, you know, congratulations, you hit a leaf.
Or, oh, you missed.
Oh, the ratio continued.
And that process turns out to be rather slow because this anti-edge shader is done outside of the hardware.
It's done out of, well, I shouldn't say, everything's in the hardware, right?
It's all in the GPU.
It's done outside of these ray-tracing cores.
The ray-tracing cores kind of do this intersection and acceleration traversal.
But the anti-edge is actually in this sort of SM, in that streaming multiprocessor in the general shader.
And so there's sort of this whole communication thing where it has to go to the shader.
The shader does its thing.
It comes back eventually.
And it says, oh, start up the ray again, you know.
So that's a very slow process.
So one thing that we've addressed just, you know, announced in these past few weeks is this idea of opacity masks where we don't, we can do it down, I think, to the, I don't know, maybe do it down to the pixel level.
But basically what we do is we have a very tight encoding compressed version of that texture that our ray-tracing cores now understand.
That basically you say, hey, instead of going to the any hit shader and having to slow down, we have this sort of very, you know, tightly compressed, not quite binary.
I think there's three states or four, depending on how you configure things, that basically say, you know, either when I hit something, I can just immediately look up, is it transparent or is it opaque or is it somewhere in between?
In which case, at some point, you may have to go to the end hit shader anyway.
But you can see there's sort of vast areas that are either opaque or, you know, something, you know, empty.
And so that can speed this up considerably.
So that's one area where we've thrown a little more hardware, basically, to try to speed up that process because that turned out to be a pain point for a lot of AAA games.
Another thing is, so Unreal Engine has this whole nanite idea of level of detail that as you get closer to things, they pull in new level of detail and try to, you know, quietly merge it so you don't really notice the difference in detail.
But you can see here, like on the left in particular, there's sort of just still a ton of little triangles.
There's, you know, at some point, you've got maybe, you know, little lion's heads or whatever, you know, you've got some very detailed content that you want to try to keep at some kind of level of detail.
And so one thing we've added this time around is this idea of a micromesh, which is basically saying, given a triangle, you can make a bunch of little triangles.
So you could have something like this crab, where, you know, you may have a bunch of crabs and you have, you know, 16k micromeshes, in other words, 16,000 triangles expand to 2 million microtriangles.
And there's hardware that's just there to, you know, very rapidly shoot rays at these microtriangles and also to keep them nice and compressed, like, so that it's not taking up a ton of room.
So anyway, that's another thing that's just come out, just announced in the past few weeks.
And the last one I won't really go deeply into, but it's this interesting idea that it's called shader execution reordering.
And it kind of just happens, it's now a new unit of the ray tracing core, because the realization is that, like I say, I won't get into it.
But basically, those streaming multiprocessors, those shaders, the way they kind of work is they're not like a single processor per ray.
It's really a single processor per what's called a warp, which is like 32 rays at once.
And so you're sort of evaluating 32 rays at once.
And what they found is that if you can bunch these nicely, they work well.
So like you're just shooting rays from the eye, no problem.
But typically, games are kind of doing that by using rasterization for that.
And then they're shooting like shadow rays or reflection rays or whatever.
And the rays kind of diverge.
They kind of go off in different directions.
They, you know, they're basically quite different.
And that kind of, that can create a slowdown as far as these 32 rays at once works.
And so there's sort of this, now this sorting unit, basically.
It says, oh, let's try to order those as best we can.
Let's try to group things.
And so the sorting can give you higher performance, sometimes much higher performance.
And it's just kind of in the chip now, basically, is the idea.
You know, in software, you can sort of try to do some of this ordering if you're clever about things.
But, you know, it now has some hardware support for that.
So back in 1987, I had been out of school.
And I was working for a company.
And I put out a little database of like this fractal sphere thing on the right, which I call SphereFlake.
And I put it out about two weeks before SIGGRAPH.
I'm like, yeah, I'll just put the code out there for free.
You know, maybe someone will use it.
And so I was surprised and happy to go to SIGGRAPH and see this thing called AT&T Pixel Machine announced.
It was sort of the first real-time ray tracer.
And it couldn't do this SphereFlake in real time.
It took, you know, for 512 by 512 pixels, about 7,000 spheres, it took about 30 seconds.
But still, like, super impressive because it would take me hours on my, you know, workstation at the time, my high-end workstation.
And they actually had an interactive thing where you can move the mouse around.
And there'd be this one ray-traced sphere on a plane.
And you'd be like, oh, my gosh, this is amazing.
You know, now you can do this on your phone, no problem.
But at the time, it was just magic.
Anyway, so, you know, fast forward a bunch of years.
And when I first joined NVIDIA, one of the first things I did was like, oh, man, give me one of them cards, you know.
And, you know, give me some code to do some ray tracing.
And so I did the SphereFlake at 48 million spheres, you know, higher resolution.
And was, you know, pretty easily getting 60 frames per second.
You know, it was just like, and I could probably have kicked it further by doing instancing so I'd touch less memory.
But I never bothered.
You know, that was plenty good enough for me.
48 million is more than you can possibly see.
You know, that's way more than the 2 million pixels I'm seeing.
So anyway, that's, you know, that's not even accelerated spheres.
The spheres are special custom intersectors.
So that's the slow path.
And what's cool, anyway, for me about ray tracing was I realized when I had that demo, it was like, oh, yeah.
Like, I want to add soft shadows.
Well, if you add soft shadows and rasterizers, that can be really slow.
Like, oh, okay, well, do this sort of funky thing with my shadow map.
And, you know, yeah, I'll do some tricky filtering kinds of things.
But ray tracing, you just go, well, just, you know, shoot the shadow rays over, you know, half a degree or whatever.
And, you know, add them up.
You could, you know, keep it a softer shadow like here.
You can get a hemisphere kind of a pattern by just shooting them all over the whole hemisphere.
And that was like, you know, 20 minutes of coding, literally.
You know, the hardest part was going, oh, yeah, how do I shoot rays randomly over an atmosphere?
I've got to look that up.
But once I had that, it's like, you know, 20 lines, 10 lines of code, and boom.
You basically have a new shading algorithm.
And you could add depth of field very easily and so on.
These are all just easy things.
So that's one thing I really like about ray tracing is that since it has sort of a basis on, like, here's how light kind of actually works.
You know, you can quickly add and play with new ideas fairly rapidly without having to sort of force hardware to do weird things.
So one thing I'm going to talk about for about 28 seconds is the rendering equation.
Like, it's the kiss of death to, like, show an equation in any lecture I found.
But I'm going to risk it, give this one a very quick one.
And it's not a rendering equation.
This is the rendering equation, which is that one from Kajiya back in 1986.
And the idea is very simple and worth mentioning.
It's just because it's kind of what path tracing is all about.
It's why we kind of, you know, came up with path tracing is that you say, well, how much light do I have given some position x and given some direction?
Well, okay, that would be the incoming light.
Like, you can just say, well, you know, given if there's an emitted light right at, if I'm staring at a light, okay, I know how much light I'm getting.
I'm getting the light from the emitter.
But what you usually have to do is, you know, have some material looking at here.
And what you want to do is you have this, you know, sort of sum of this, integrate all the light coming in from all the different directions.
And then you have this sort of geometric term because sort of light coming in directly overhead from a surface versus light coming in from an angle.
Well, there's sort of just geometrically, there's kind of less light, you know, shining at an angle.
Like if you hold a flashlight at an angle to a surface, it will not be as bright as if you hold it way overhead, as we know.
And so that's all this lab return is.
And then you have basically this material, which just says, given an incoming amount of light, what's the outgoing amount of light?
In other words, how much does it reflect in, you know, per wavelength kind of thing.
And so you basically just do an integration and, you know, voila, you have the answer.
But, of course, this incoming light, well, that just depends on where the light came from.
And the light may have come from some other surface.
So, again, when you go to that other surface, you shot a ray and, oh, I hit another surface.
Well, you, again, have to do this equation again for that other surface.
And that's basically the path trace idea is that you're kind of, you know, recursively solving this equation again and again and again as you go down the path.
But it's sort of, you know, it's just that simple.
And really a lot of work is just based on a lot of ray tracing research is, you know, how do we speed this up?
Like, what's significant as far as incoming light?
What's significant when we know the material?
And so on and so forth.
So one path trace game, in fact, is Quake 2.
It's kind of fun. It's old by now.
But anyway, it's kind of cool to take Quake 2.
And they just said, hey, let's just make it path traced.
You know, we're going to add this cool thing.
You know, the initial implementation is open source.
I think NVIDIA has a cooler, faster implementation.
But it's kind of fun to just walk through and see some of the effects.
And so if you think about that rendering equation, like I said, you can sort of pay attention to the material.
So if you have, if you know, like, you've got a, you know, classic mirror, you know, classical ray tracing, the only important direction to that mirror is the mirror direction.
You know, if you have a light overhead, I don't care.
I'm not seeing that light in my mirror.
You know, the light's not reflecting back towards my eye.
It's only, you know, it's the light's directly overhead.
It's reflecting directly back up from the mirror.
So it doesn't affect what the eye sees.
But if the surface is glossy, well, now I'm going to have to start shooting, you know, a bunch of rays, a burst of rays.
And then if it's diffuse, now I'm sort of shooting in all kinds of different directions.
And I don't really, you know, know what good direction is what as far as the material goes.
So there's this idea called MIS, multiple importance sampling.
And what the idea there is, is you sort of say, well, you know, it's all very well that the diffuse surface, we don't know which direction is important.
But we do know lights are really important.
You know, if you directly see a light, that's going to have a big influence, most likely on the scene.
So what you do is you tend to shoot more rays, essentially shoot shadow rays towards the lights in the scene.
And so this is an old technique.
It's from 1995.
But it's really a good one to sort of, if you want to think about sampling and the rendering equation and what works and so on.
I like just kind of staring at this thing for 10 or 15 or however many minutes it makes sense to you.
Like, you know, well, okay, here I'm sampling light source.
And it's looking pretty good on the left here for, you know, this diffuse surface where I indeed know that, you know, sampling on the light is going to be really important.
But I know that over here at the top is a shiny surface.
And, gee, that's not so great just, you know, trying to sample light source is kind of weird.
This isn't even totally reflected at the top here.
It's just glossy.
Anyway, the point is, you know, if you sort of stare at each one of these and think about what's it mean, that you realize that, oh, yeah, trying to do a mix of these two where the light matters and the material matters to get a good image.
But the point of all this in a way is that you can see in that previous slide that there were a lot of, there's a lot of noise, you know, a lot of this kind of speckly stuff going on.
So if you shoot just one sample per pixel, you get this very speckly kind of stuff where it's like sometimes, oh, I hit and I hit a light, you know, sometimes, no, you know, I didn't get much light, whatever.
And so you get this very noisy kind of thing.
If you shoot more rays, you get better and better and better.
But the trick is, like many things in life, like many kinds of sampling, is a diminished return, a diminishing return where basically the square root of the number of samples is how much quality kind of improves.
That's kind of the rule.
So, you know, four samples per pixel took me four times longer, but it's only sort of twice as good.
And so this diminishing return really is not a good thing.
You know, we wish it was just one for one, every ray we shot was, you know, made it, you know, that much better.
But that's not the case.
So that kind of puts an upper limit on, you know, how much you can kind of get out of rays in a real time environment.
And so, or even in a film environment, sometimes they'll have this problem too, where they just don't have enough samples, even with a, you know, 3000 per pixel, you can still get noisy results.
So the thing we've looked at is how to reconstruct, basically, given a noisy result, you know, how do you get a nice image like here on the right?
And the cheat is to use deep learning to do image denoising.
Image denoising is an old idea.
You know, it's basically there's sort of a lot of heuristic rules that humans can apply.
But at this point, I think the machines are winning, essentially, like, you know, human made denoisers, you can try to glue up raised denoisers, and sometimes they'll work and sometimes they won't.
But really, now we just sort of brute force it, we throw lots of images at the neural net, essentially, and we train this neural net by saying, well, here's the noisy image.
And here's the result that I really want.
I have now a really nice image here, and a crummy image here.
And there's even tricks for doing that very rapidly generate those images.
But you put those both in and basically try to train, you know, here neural net, if you see this noise, you see this high frequency jump, we probably don't want that, you know, come up with something else.
And we train to have that happen, essentially.
And so this works surprisingly well.
Like, so here's one sample per pixel they trace.
Here's a denoise. And the reason it's so noisy here is that, you know, you have a bunch of rays, they're going towards the sun, which has a maybe a half a degree angle in the sky.
So they're going to different points because they want to get a soft shadow.
But they're also sometimes hitting leaves, sometimes not hitting leaves, and so that causes a lot of noise.
And so the denoise looks pretty good.
And it also compares quite nicely, actually, with the ground truth.
This is one where they shot lots of rays per pixel and got the, you know, the essentially correct answer.
And you can compare that to like traditional methods of rasterization called shadow mapping, this sort of common one used in a lot of games, still used.
But there you get sort of a very sharp kind of a shadow just because it's not really based on physical principles.
They're just kind of doing buffer hacks, basically, you can't get the same effect.
Here again, you have this sort of one sample per pixel, which you bounce around, retrace reflections, denoising looks pretty good.
Here there's sort of a fair bit of difference between the ground truth and the one sample.
But, you know, comparable, you know, you might see like on the left hand here, it's a little sharper, maybe with the ground truth.
But anyway, but, you know, given that it's only one sample, it's pretty nice.
And that compares quite favorably with the stochastic screen space reflections, which is sort of the way that people did it before having ray tracing,
is that you have this sort of, you take the image and you kind of reflect it off the plane in this kind of funky algorithm, basically,
where you're using the image and you're reflecting.
And you can see like, at the bottoms of these little objects, we don't have any reflection there.
So it just sort of turns kind of weird.
But anyway, so the point is, is that, yeah, this works better.
Again, one more example is that scene we saw earlier.
One sample ray trace global illumination.
Here's the denoise version.
And again, compares favorably with the ground truth.
Between the two, you can sort of see in the upper left, you know, we're losing some of the detail by having this sort of simplified things.
But, you know, a lot cheaper.
We can also have this idea of just, it's called deep learning supersampling, where supersampling is just saying, I want more samples in the pixel.
And this can be used for ray tracing or for rasterization or for, you know, really anything where you're not getting as much detail as you'd like in a pixel.
And, you know, again, what you've done is basically said, well, I've gotten these samples.
And, you know, I've only got one sample per pixel here.
I wasn't able to get more than that.
What can you do for me?
And if you turn on DLSS, it often will just rebuild it, you know, amazingly well, actually.
You know, occasionally you'll see errors and so on.
But for the most part, it looks pretty good.
Because it's just trying to sort of, you know, say, well, I've seen lots and lots of other images.
And this is sort of what, you know, when I've seen this, it really means this.
And so the thing we've come up with in the past few weeks was just announced was this supersampling three, which I won't really get into.
It's sort of the piece that we've added is this chunk down here using optical flow.
And basically the idea is it's sort of a funky idea.
It's like saying, well, I want more frames per second because I want a smoother user experience.
You know, people love, you know, 30 frames per second.
A lot of people object to even 60 frames a second.
People don't like so much.
If you can get higher than that, you know, it just looks smoother.
It just feels better to them.
And so this actually is a way to sort of kick up the frame rate.
It's funny, though.
I won't get into it.
But it doesn't really decrease the latency per se.
But there's another thing called NVIDIA Reflex, if you're interested, that does decrease the latency.
And so this is actually kind of  it's basically just creating intermediate frames with not using any kind of renderer or anything.
It's just sort of saying I've got this frame at time A.
I've got this frame at time B.
I want to create a frame in between at time, you know, half between A and B that I can throw up on the screen really quick.
I can, you know, I can generate quick and I can throw on quick so that I'm not losing much frame rate.
But because of that, you know, generation time, that I'm able to get, you know, twice as many frames essentially on the screen.
So this is sort of the marketing slide is that you can turn this on, get comparable frames, and you get a lot more frames per second.
So the other thing, like I say, that NVIDIA works on is software that we release as SDKs.
And so there's things like RTXVI, which is direct illumination, which is, you know, the research name is called ReSTIR.
And basically the idea is you're just trying to find the important lights in the scene and use them to shade things.
So here we have these tiny little, you know, little lights and not much effect really on the scene.
Here we're sort of seeing, you know, hey, gee, these lights are significant.
And the idea is you're sort of trying to track what lights are significant for various pixels and try to, you know,
try to gain information from both the neighboring pixels and from the frames that have happened previously
to try to zero in on the useful lights to render, you know, shoot rays towards.
And you can also do like ReSTIR plus denoise. So you can get these sort of, you know, good ReSTIR effects.
But if you add, you know, denoising to them, you get, you know, nicer effects.
So these things tend to have, you know, sort of a synergy to them.
And the other one that I'll mention just again, again, extremely briefly, get the slides if you want to look up.
I've got URLs of some of the research involved.
But it's this idea of having probes, which are just sort of areas.
You think of them as little, think of a box in space.
And you say, in this box in space, you know, what light's getting to me?
And so, well, there's an area, you know, there's a directional dependence, you know, and so on.
And there's an occlusion dependence. If something's blocking you within the box, that could be problematic.
But basically, there's sort of this idea. You can see some games for a long time with this idea of probes.
And we're kind of elaborating on that, making these probes sort of more, yeah, more full flame, more full featured.
And also the ability that you can update them. Like it used to be you just made a bunch of probes.
You'd bake overnight, make a bunch of probes.
And you had a global illumination system, but it was just kind of baked in and you couldn't change it over time.
This allows changing, allows objects to move around the scene and affect the global illumination solution and so on.
Anyway, that's just one more SDK that's kind of interesting to look at, or if you want to look at the research for that.
Another area, which I, again, will only spend a few seconds on, but I think it's super interesting because there's also just,
and I'm not the only one, there are literally hundreds of papers in this area now in the past few years,
is the sort of neural radiance caching, where you're kind of using, again, neural nets to try to figure out,
you know, not so much a denoise in some ways, but to sort of figure out, well, where's the useful light, you know, in the scene?
Where should I be looking? What should I be using?
I can't go further than that because, frankly, I can only go a little bit further than that, and we don't have time anyway.
The thing I have been playing with lately, actually, and added one little feature a few weeks ago,
was this thing called Nerfs, which, again, is a super hot topic in the past two years.
And this is a fun thing to play with.
Honestly, you know, if you have an RTX card available, it's actually fun to go grab this stuff, you know, compile it,
which actually compiled, you know, amazingly quickly.
Like, usually whenever I see one of these things, now you just compiled the code.
I go, well, that'll be five hours of my life.
And this one took me, I don't know, 20 minutes or something to get it all compiled and running.
Anyway, it's kind of a fun thing.
The idea of a Nerf is that you're essentially, it's kind of like stereo, it's like photogrammetry,
where you've got lots and lots of views of an object.
But instead of trying to rebuild the mesh and try to get a 3D mesh out of the object that's all textured,
you're both getting a representation of the object, which isn't necessarily a mesh.
And that's, in fact, the whole research topic, is do we do a mesh, or do we do an implicit surface,
or do we do, you know, some kind of voxel implicit surface, or do we do something else?
Or what, you know, what's the best representation for objects in this kind of method?
So the idea is basically, you're throwing this data through a multi-level perceptron,
which is just trying to figure out, you know, given this view, what do I, you know,
given this view and given this location, what would I see in that direction?
And at what opacity?
And so ray tracing is used to rebuild these kinds of images,
and is used to sort of generate some of this data and so on as to analyze this data.
So basically, you just have this idea of a light field, where, you know,
a light field is just saying, given some point in space, and I'm looking in one direction,
what do I see, and how, but it's kind of more of a limited light field,
where it's just like, how, what do I see, and how opaque am I seeing it?
In other words, is there something solid in front of me, or is it kind of fuzzy,
and then I should continue the ray?
Anyway, long and short is, it's a very interesting system.
This system's kind of fun, this particular piece of software.
It's because it resolves very quickly, like this fox head just takes like a minute or less
on a computer to sort of figure out from ground zero from just a bunch of images,
this thing, and, you know, you get these cool images.
It's just, it's tantalizing because it also captures how the light's actually interacting
with the surface, so it's capturing both the material and the material glossiness
and reflection and so on, as opposed to just capturing the model, the mesh.
So it'll be interesting.
Right now it's research, though.
It's not, you know, nobody's commercially doing a lot with this so far.
One thing I had to mention real quick, just because I saw it just today,
was like this thing, Dream Fusion, which is by Google and Berkeley.
They just put this out, I think, a paper on archive on, let's see, September 29th,
so just last week.
And it's this kind of idea where instead of generating 3D models,
you're just using a text-to-3D system like they have this one called Imogen,
which basically you just give it some text, it comes up with a 3D image,
and they say, well, okay, given these 3D images, is there a way that we can kind of
backpropagate, if you know Deep Dream, same kind of idea where you sort of say,
well, here's the image I wanted.
Here's the image I got from just random noise.
How can I sort of influence that random noise to look more and more like the image
that I really want?
And now I do that from a bunch of different angles.
So it's this really weird idea of like, okay, I'm just going to say text,
and I'm going to say what I want, and I will get images from various angles
and so on, and then I'll try to solve to get the underlying earth.
Anyway, it's just this crazy thing, but I love that it's literally like every week
there's a new paper, if not every day, it seems, in this area.
It's just fascinating.
So anyway, just to sort of wrap up what we've gone through.
One is LaFon's Law.
He's Aaron LaFon, was at Intel, now at NVIDIA.
He's been there a bunch of years, one of the heads of research.
And I really like this sort of idea of, you know, well, nowadays we're, you know,
especially with real-time rendering, we're not so much trying to make the picture
with the rendering.
You know, we're not trying to sample the living daylights out of it.
It's to try to get enough samples that the AI can figure out, you know,
how to put it together to make the picture.
And there's sort of a corollary, which is, you know, if your rays are coherent,
you're probably shooting too many rays.
You know, try to make all your rays matter.
So, you know, cherish your samples.
Try to do the most that you can with what you've got.
And then there's sort of finally, you know, the ray-tracing creed
or the rendering creed in general.
It just has to look right, right?
So for rendering, it just has to look right.
You know, we don't have to necessarily, like, physically-based
and physics help us inform us as to how to make things look right.
But, you know, ambient occlusion, for example, looks right,
even though it's not exactly a physical process.
So for rendering, you know, we can get away with this and that.
What I'm going to now really rapidly do, because I've already run out of time,
is just go through some things that I think are interesting ray-tracing uses
beyond rendering.
So ray-tracing, we know it from media and entertainment.
You know, for architectural design, we have, you know, say, dots.
You know, the one on the right in this case is the real one.
But, you know, we can make, you know, quite realistic images.
We can do it for industrial design.
We make pretty cars, you know, shiny cars.
You know, but what happens when, you know, how do I put this?
What happens when buildings fight cars?
Well, the buildings win.
You've probably heard of this one, the fry scraper.
It's also called the walkie-talkie, where the design firm,
I think they came up with the design in, like, 2014,
and they didn't really pursue the idea of, gee,
maybe we should do a really good lighting study of, you know,
what the light's going to do.
And the gist is that, well, what the light does is it melts Porsches,
I think is the deal, or I forget.
No, I think it's a Jaguar, actually.
But anyway, it actually melted a car, you know, sitting on the street
because the thing acts like a concave mirror.
And to be honest, as an architect,
101 would be never design things with concave mirrors,
or B, if you're going to design something with a concave mirror,
don't have it face south if you're in the northern hemisphere,
or, you know, vice versa if you're in the southern hemisphere,
because it's just going to focus the rays, you know,
if you've looked at this at all.
But nonetheless, anyway, it's an interesting thing.
So we've been able to, you know, as a sort of a demo,
we have iRay, which is a physically-based renderer
that we could also use for determining how many, you know,
basically how much illumination, you know,
illuminance is hitting a spot, and you can see,
yeah, that's a red spot, don't park your car there.
But you can use, you know, ray tracing for all kinds of other things.
Here we have millions of spheres, which is really nothing.
You know, I could do 48 million spheres.
This only has 1.7 million atoms.
That's nothing.
But, you know, we can do this interactively.
This is the SARS, you know, COVID thing.
So, you know, but SARS COVID, you know, 20 million spheres and so on.
And this is the kind of thing that's, you know,
oh, ray tracing loves this.
Hey, we can do spheres, great, you know.
And there's other kinds of visualization where, like,
if you're doing volume rendering, you know, ray tracing wins.
Rasterization is just not really good for it.
Same with, you know, here's stellar radiation,
same kind of things where you want to do volume render stuff.
Rasterization is just really bad at volume.
In general, you have to do a lot of hacks,
and often it doesn't quite work and whatnot.
So, anyway.
And finally, you can actually start using ray tracing in actual physical simulations.
So for telescope design, there's obvious uses.
You know, you're tracing rays through optics.
You know, you can do it per wavelength.
You can get all kinds of information out.
And, indeed, that's how people design, you know, lenses now.
And they have for years.
And we talk about photons.
And whenever we talk about photons as a rendering person,
I always think, oh, it's just the visible light.
You know, it's the spectrum kind of thing.
But there's tons of photons out there, you know.
They go from gamma and x-ray all the way down to, you know,
sort of this, you know, longwave radio and whatnot, microwaves, all the rest.
So those are photons, and they're perfectly traceable.
And so you'll see simulations like what's called digital twinning,
where you kind of make a version of the city that you're, you know,
wanting to put things in.
And then you just put things in and see how they work.
So, you know, here's like, oh, if I put a 5G, you know, tower here,
how's that going to work?
You know, how will it work with cars?
You know, will they use signal, dah, dah, dah, dah, that kind of thing.
So you can simulate that.
You can get to really, you know,
other kinds of things like synthetic aperture radar.
That's a huge deal for sort of intelligence gathering,
both by governments and by like open source intelligence.
They use, you know, you can basically look through the roofs of buildings
and all kinds of things with synthetic aperture radar.
So it's got a lot going for it.
And indeed, you can use ray tracing to do stuff with that.
Heat transfer, you know, sort of obvious one.
Audio simulation, which is interesting in that audio is partly direct line,
but also as it goes, you know, if you hit like a,
if you shout through a door, you know, people can hear you because the,
you know, there's sort of a large edge diffraction effect essentially is how
they're thinking about it in this research paper.
But this kind of thing gets used.
I mean, like Dolby uses it to sort of figure out, you know, okay,
how is sound traveling in the system?
You know, where do we put the alarms?
Where do we put whatever?
And yeah, just other things like seismology.
There's sort of an interesting dead zone on the earth.
So when there's an earthquake in a spot, you won't pick up any waves from the,
you know, from the earthquake because they have this sort of refraction effect
through various parts of the core.
And that's, you know,
a good part of why we know sort of how we have these inner cores of, you know,
liquid steel or liquid metal and stuff like that, liquid iron and so on,
is because of how we find these waves.
And finally, you can do things like train, like robots.
Well, not finally, but this is yet another application where on the left is a virtual world
where you're teaching the robot, you know, here's the vision.
What are you doing, robot?
Where do you want to put your feet and so on?
So you can train it in the virtual world without having to, you know,
run over pedestrians or block off a corridor or anything like that.
And then, you know, apply that training to the real world.
And finally, Ikea simulation for driving cars, realistic imagery for the cars, for one.
And also just, yeah, you can get different array shapes and so on.
And so that's just, you know, you don't want more.
And finally, yeah, we have like collision detection and response.
You know, there are ways to do collision detection that don't necessarily involve rays.
You can do other geometric sort of surface, you know, does this object overlap that object?
But rays are handy if you want to get things faster and have more prediction and better response.
And so anyway, so there's the old joke that goes ray tracing is the technology of the future and it always will be.
Well, what's particularly funny for me about this was that I looked it up.
Oh, you know, David Kirk made this joke in 2008.
And it turns out, well, soon thereafter, he actually started the project at NVIDIA to, you know,
well, what can we put into hardware?
What makes sense to put into hardware to commit to actually have ray tracing be faster,
ray tracing itself be faster?
And, you know, it sort of started right about this time.
And it took about 10 years to, you know, finally come out the other end of like, okay,
these are what things we figured out that are actually worth committing to hardware.
But now that that process has started, it's now just, you know, sort of every release of the hardware is like, oh, we can add, you know,
let's see if we can dedicate, oh, we found this cool technique, this cool one, that one.
Okay, we'll dedicate some hardware to that to make it fast because there's a good payoff.
So, yeah, now it's sort of simple enough to fit on a business card, complicated enough to consume an entire career.
I'd actually put consume an entire many careers because there's just a ton to know in the area.
But, you know, it's knowable.
Like I say, it's a simple enough thing to start with.
So that's my talk.
But Shazan said, oh, can you give some quick advice about, you know, things, you know, as far as career advice kind of thing.
And I'm not sure if I'm the best person to look at, but, you know, I feel I've been successful for what I wanted to do,
which is the thing that motivates me.
I think that's probably number one is what motivates you, you know.
What motivates me is I really like to share information.
Like I do some research and I do some development and I do a lot of writing or sometimes write.
I shouldn't say a lot of writing, sort of periodically I'll do a lot of writing.
But what I most like to do is try to make connections between people and try to get information out, which is one reason I like giving this lecture.
One reason I talk too long is because I really want to throw a lot at you guys to have you think about, oh, what was interesting there?
Or, gee, I want to go look that up and just try to expose you to, you know, to know what you don't know kind of thing.
Anyway, so I liked this from back from Pax East pre-COVID.
Rand Miller, who's a sort of famous old game designer, made this classic video game Myst.
You know, success has a lot to do with luck.
But if you work hard, you get more dice rolls, which I think is true.
You know, you sort of have more opportunities the more things you go out and get involved in or do.
I mean, you don't want to overcommit or anything, but, you know, really sort of follow your passion or, you know, find the things that are interesting to you and go, you know, give that bit of effort to them.
And I felt that that pays off.
So these are my pro-ish tips. It's kind of a long list.
Like I say, I made the slides available. Just go look at them.
But the gist is, is go do something you want to do.
I mean, you know, you can put in the minimum. You can get a, you know, a reasonable grade in a class and then go, well, I've done that. Check that off the list.
But, you know, if you're if you're into the subject, there's it's such a wonderful world out there.
Really, if you want to do something more in an area, you have that opportunity and there's tons of ways to do it.
The one I do recommend, no matter what, even if you are like, I don't want to do any of those crazy things he's talking about on this list, is just make your own website for your own stuff.
You know, just say, here's, you know, like you can have, you know, as a minimum, you always should have your LinkedIn page or whatever.
That's kind of your your online resume. But having a resume of like, oh, here's, you know, here's projects I've worked on.
Here's screenshots from them. Here's my GitHub. Here's the stuff I've done. Here's whatever.
That stuff is just, you know, that sort of follows you through life.
That's your online, you know, sort of metaverse, you know, kind of thing is that, you know, that's that's where you're living in the virtual world.
And, you know, really, it's worth your while to do that. And don't just rely on, oh, well, my school has a site and my work has a site.
Well, guess what? You probably won't have the same job forever anyway.
Or even if you even if you do have the same job forever, when you retire, you might still want to have that website.
But anyway, yeah, it's just these are sort of all the things you can do, you know, volunteer.
If you really are interested in a topic, you know, don't feel shy to ask the author a question.
They may be too busy. They may not get back to you.
But, you know, most authors I know, if you're like interested and ask sort of sensible questions,
and I really, you know, really do care about contacting them and understanding, they're like, oh, wow, somebody's using my work.
Cool. Here, let me see if I can explain quickly or point you at some other resources or stuff like that.
Anyway, just get out there. Don't be shy. Don't don't feel like, well, the classroom is all I can learn.
This is this is all there is to the world. You know, there's a much wider world out there.
Anyway, so that's just a bunch of kinds of things you can do.
And my pet peeve is to if you know, I'm happy to say hello to anybody and say, sure, you know, thumbs up.
I'll link to you on LinkedIn or I'll accept the LinkedIn connection.
But only if you actually say something to me, you know, or if I've actually met you in person and I know who you are.
But, you know, I'll often get these just random people from nowhere, you know, saying I want to connect.
And, you know, they put in two seconds of effort as opposed to, you know, hey, take the whole minute of effort to say, hey, I read your paper on such and so.
I thought it was cool. Or, you know, hey, I have some questions on such and so.
You know, in other words, don't don't do it just to be like, oh, I've got to network with people and build up my list.
That's it's just not it's not so impressive. You know, what's better really is to actually say, oh, I want to connect with you because I really want to connect with you.
I want to talk to you and see what's going on.
Anyway, talking about sort of just things things to get involved in something I realized after SIGGRAPH, I went to this sort of thought.
Well, basically, this whole thing about USD, which is the universal scene description, which is a big deal in both like the film industry and it's becoming a big deal for the metaverse.
It's basically trying to describe scenes in a very full featured kind of way. It's coming out of Pixar, but it's getting picked up by a lot of film industry.
And like I say, metaverse interest. And so I realized, like they said, oh, you know what, there's a working group and we have an assets group and you can just join it.
You know, there's no like, oh, no, no, no. It has to be, you know, vetted by everybody.
Just show up for the meetings. And so I showed up for a meeting and I was like, oh, you know, I should actually make something.
So I had this Minecraft exporter and I had these really cool, you know, sort of a highly processed kind of physically based rendering materials that someone else made in Creative Commons.
And thank heaven for that. And as I said, hey, I'll make this little scene using USD, go test it out.
And now they're like, oh, yeah, yeah, contribute that, you know, put it on our GitHub repo and so on.
So, you know, it didn't take me much time to do this. And also I sort of focused on one particular scene here where I realized that a lot of viewers out there don't get this very simple scene correct.
And I was like, yeah, it should just make a simple test scene so that anybody writing a viewer, you know, can go and test and see, oh, oops, yeah, whoops, I didn't look at bias and scaling.
And that turns out to be really important. So I should go fix my viewer, you know, make my shader better.
And so this kind of stuff is like, you know, I'm not like, oh, I'm such a saint, I'm doing it. I just think it's just like, here, here's this cool thing.
A, I get to contribute to the community. B, it really, it helps NVIDIA. It helps, you know, we're really interested in USD.
We're using it in our own products a lot. And it helps the community as a whole.
Anybody using USD can now just say, oh, does my viewer do it? Or, gee, I want to just understand the file format.
Here's the simple file format. I can just go look at the code. It's all in English, you know, I can read the words, and so on.
Or I can point out to the spec writers, hey, you guys might want to tighten your spec a bit or whatever.
Anyway, it's just, it's just good for us all, basically.
And so it's nice to see other people contributing to the same kind of thing that it didn't take much.
I mean, this was maybe, this turned out to be a rabbit hole, the whole normals testing thing.
I learned a heck of a lot about how normal maps are formed, way more than I thought I'd need to learn.
But all in all, this was, you know, maybe 10, 20 hours of work.
And most of it was just writing it up, you know, coming up with the test scenes was actually pretty easy.
The hard part was sort of explaining it all. But anyway, it's not a ton of work.
And it's the kind of thing you can do. Take my word for it.
Pixar, this USD working assets group, they only have maybe eight or 10 sort of unit tests.
And they could use a lot more, in my opinion. There's a lot of features that need testing.
So, you know, if you're looking for a spare time thing where you want to get involved, this is a nice easy one.
It's not high tech. You know, they have the viewer right there that you can just use.
Anyway, so just to wrap it up, at work, ask questions when you don't know things.
Get over looking ignorant. You know, you don't want to always look ignorant.
You don't want to be constantly that person with their hand in the air going,
well, I don't, you just said a sentence, I don't know what you're talking about.
But, you know, ask that person afterwards.
So if you don't want to slow down the flow of a meeting or whatever.
But everybody's ignorant about everything, pretty much.
You know, I mean, that's as a species. That's how we survived.
Is that, you know, we you know, we don't all question like, gee, do you think that mushrooms poisonous?
I don't know. Those five other people tested it and they all died.
But I could be the lucky one. We have lots and lots received wisdom.
And there's just tons we just don't know anything about and just kind of go along with the flow.
But, you know, if you really want to understand something, go and ask.
Go and ask and it's OK to not, you know, not know everything.
That's kind of what science is about, right?
You don't know everything and you're supposed to be trying to figure this stuff out.
Anyway, feeling solo is fine, but feeling with others and work with others.
So, yeah, we're all experts in our own little niches.
Everyone sitting in this room, in the room where I'm talking to, knows something that I don't.
Knows probably a bunch of some things that I don't.
And so, yeah, you know, we can be experts, but you have something to learn from, you know,
everybody else in the world knows something you don't.
So, you know, keep learning.
And also, I sort of like this. I'm not religious, but I really, you know, the Bible nailed it on this one,
which is, you know, let someone else praise you and not your own mouth.
Or the short version is, you know, self-praise is no recommendation.
You know, don't be all like, yeah, I did this cool thing.
Like, yeah, OK, great, you know, just whatever.
And that's about it.
So, yeah, there's lots of free resources on ray tracing.
You could, well, you know, again, you can look up the notes.
But, again, I have this first website.
I list them all.
And the second one is where you can get two free books on ray tracing called Ray Tracing Jobs.
So, OK, thanks for listening.
That's where I am.
If you have any questions or whatever.
Thank you, Eric.
That was really good.
I especially enjoyed the part where you were describing the real world use case of software ray tracing.
A lot of which, at least in the graphics world, we tend to ignore a little bit
because we are so focused on the rendering and the animation
that we forget that there's so many other use cases outside of it.
And for me, working at Cesium, of course, that's very near and dear to my heart and work.
So I'll pass it off to students to ask questions.
Who wants to go first?
Just make sure you say your name as well.
Hello.
Thank you for this wonderful talk.
My name is Edward.
I am an undergrad senior.
And my question is, you talked in the beginning of all of.
Oops, you cut out.
Hello?
You cut out there.
The type of material that we went through, I'm still not hearing it.
Hello?
How about now?
There we go.
Okay.
You talked about the types of materials.
The types of materials that were the first to be implemented,
going from glass to diffuse to mirror, and then eventually caustics.
Is there anything else that we don't know how to do yet?
That's a good question, actually.
At some level, yeah, it's funny.
I think that's something, usually, not by a letter, perhaps.
But, yeah, I think people are kind of satisfied in a certain sense.
They go, okay, I've got fuzzy, I've got this, I've got that.
I've got fur, I've got feathers, I've got whatever.
And there will be some studies sometimes of like, oh, wait,
this is a kind of interesting phenomenon that we haven't seen before.
So the film guys will go, oh, how can we do this kind of cool glaze
over pottery or whatever it is, something.
But, yeah, I don't know.
It's kind of interesting because, yeah,
I don't really follow the latest and greatest as far as materials go.
And what was interesting to me was actually going to a talk a few years
ago where the person there was a biologist and she was studying the wings
of these like morpho butterflies or whatever.
And there's a certain breed that has like, you know,
like you've probably seen the phantom black where it's really black.
Like, you know, you shine light on it and just about nothing comes off of it.
And they were saying, oh,
these butterfly wings are actually even more black than those.
And she actually did a whole like micro analysis, you know,
and did a lot of optical ray tracing simulations to figure out, you know,
what the geometric structure of that was, you know,
why does light go into these things and never come out basically.
So there's, you know, there's actually interesting materials work and so on.
I think on a different level, like, you know, a real practical,
like we're, you know, we're looking at material science kind of level.
But I frankly don't follow it very much.
I mean, you know, I'm kind of like, well, yeah, good.
We got here, we got clear codes for, you know, cars, we've got this, that.
But yeah, I don't know.
That's interesting.
I'll have to quiz the materials guy at a video that I know and see if he has anything.
It's like, yeah, if only we could do so-and-so.
But I don't think so.
I mean, I think there's, like I say, most people just have, you know,
are trying to figure out something that's, you know, it just has to look right.
So if we can figure out something that's a reasonable approximation,
it's like, yeah, okay, great.
Thank you.
Hello, professor.
I'm Shu Tong.
I'm a first-year CET student.
I have a question.
So back when 10 years ago, like,
computer game graphics aren't as realistic as what we have today.
So what do you think the future, like, after 10 years ago,
after 10 years, like, what will the graphics be in computer games and in the industry?
The motor's a lot slowing down, but, you know, we're certainly trying to boost it.
And we're not the only ones.
I mean, like, you know, ray tracing is certainly seeing its use, you know,
and AMD and Intel, they're all, you know,
coming out with things that are ray tracing oriented.
So it's sort of a new tool in the toolbox, basically.
And it's one that, you know, in some ways, yeah, it's basically, it's just being born.
You know, we're sort of finding out, like, denoising in particular is one where we're finding,
gee, we don't really have to be shooting all those sensors.
So I think that, yeah, you know, it's sort of, you know,
we've never gotten to the point where we're like, well, that's it.
We're done.
You know, we have all the detail we want in the scene.
Everything's moving fast.
You know, we can do all kinds, you know, get all these nice motion blur effects.
We, you know, we can deal with hundreds or thousands of moving objects.
You know, we're done.
And so, you know, I think it's just continuing to be sort of upwards and onwards on that front
is that, you know, people are trying to figure out more and more techniques,
both in software and hardware.
You know, how can we get things faster?
Because going from something that's kind of clunky, like, oh, once every five seconds,
I get an update to, you know, once every one second, I get an update,
to something that's actually interactive where it's like at least six frames per second,
you know, starts to feel, you know, slower than that,
and you feel like you're kind of moving through molasses.
But if you start getting some kind of frame rate, it's like, ooh,
this actually is qualitatively different.
You know, it helps artists do their jobs.
It helps CAD designers do their jobs, you know, beyond just graphics for games and so on.
But I think that, yeah, that's going to continue to be a thing that people are just going to be like,
yeah, keep pushing on that.
We found that useful.
So I don't know.
You know, in one way, it's like, yeah, we're just done.
But, yeah, I don't know.
I don't know what the exact things are that will get better.
There's also sort of interesting things, obviously, with VR and virtual reality and augmented reality,
where like seeing like the PlayStation's new VR headset, that looks pretty cool.
Like they've got all kinds of things going on with eye tracking and just, you know,
a bunch of sort of newer technologies.
And so I think there's a lot of sort of interesting things perceptually that will go on there of like, you know,
what do we need to render at high res?
What can we get by with low res if our eyes aren't looking directly at something we can get away with
and sort of cheaper along the periphery?
So that's sort of another area.
Yeah, I don't know.
I look forward to it, frankly.
You know, like I really didn't know.
Like when I first saw denoising, like maybe in 2017, I was like, well, that's magic, you know.
But that turned out to be a real thing that, you know, really could be evaluated very quickly
and give, you know, a reasonable image very rapidly and save a lifetime.
So, yeah, I look forward to what surprises there are.
I mean, personally, I'm not sure.
But, you know, it seems like people haven't just sort of washed their hands of it
and said, well, we're done now.
You know, it's just rendering solved.
Yeah, we're at the point where game graphics are kind of realistic.
But I'm not sure.
So there's sort of a whole bunch of other things, like physics and so on,
where, you know, actual simulation processes, again, making those fast and iterative, you know,
that we can iterate and look at, oh, that animation didn't work.
Okay, let me try this, you know, that iteration cycle.
If you can make that fast, that's the sweet spot.
That's the, you know, point where you get a lot more out of animation or animators doing your work
and so on, as opposed to, you know, oh, I said it and I came back five minutes later
to look at the animation and, nah, it looked terrible.
And now I change, I'll tweak one little thing.
You know, that's a terrible kind of development cycle.
So, anyway.
Yeah, I think simulation has to do a lot of work.
Eric, I had a follow-up to that question.
Do you think we'll see drastic seismic shifts in rendering like we had with RTX?
Or do you think denoising will just help the incremental updates that we're going to see?
Yeah, I don't know.
I mean, right, you know, I don't want to be one of those old guys that's like,
oh, I think we've got all the problems solved now.
And then five years from now, some amazing thing comes up that's like, oh, wait.
You know, that's the limits of my imagination, right?
Yeah, I don't know.
I mean, you know, what's funny is to, like, look at things like nerfs,
which two years ago, you know, no one was looking at this nerf technology.
And now it's sort of like, well, maybe that's actually useful for online shopping.
You know, you want to look at an object, and sure, you can look at 3D images of the object.
But what if you could just rotate the object around and know that what you're seeing is, you know,
pretty detailed and is actually capturing the feel of the, you know, the object itself, the actual look?
You know, you're buying, I don't know, a purse or something, and you rotate it around,
and you can see, oh, that's how the light's going to reflect and so on,
and that's how it's going to look in the scene and stuff like that.
You know, that's pretty interesting.
But right now, it's, you know, just a little baby research tech that kind of came out of nowhere, you know.
It was one of these, like, oh, why don't we hook, you know, multilayer perceptrons to, you know,
like just determining if these views correlate and what's that,
where the two views are looking and so on and see how that works.
And suddenly, oh, wait, we're getting 3D models out of this.
Oh, this is cool.
So, yeah, I don't know.
I think there's a lot of interesting rendering stuff to be done
just because there are so many different representations of data,
and some of them surprisingly fast.
I mean, the NERF stuff is, you know, it's pretty fast to make images,
and they look pretty convincing.
So, anyway.
Hello, and how are you doing?
Yeah, okay.
I'm Gita Joshi.
I'm currently in the second year of CGJT.
And during your talk, you mentioned that we should, right now,
we are at a point where we just need to cast enough rays to make every ray worth it.
So I was wondering if you could elaborate on how could we find out,
like, how do we determine what part of the scene requires more details
or more rays have to be cast in that particular direction
or towards that part of the scene to get more details there,
and then cast probably lesser rays because we don't need them on those parts of the scene,
which are simple.
Yeah, it's an interesting question because it's, you know, well, right,
could you do sort of a low-res pass and then say, oh, okay, you know,
here I think is what's going on.
The trick is you don't want to miss any, like, high-frequency details.
You know, you can sort of, that's the catch, right, is you sort of say, well, okay,
I'm just going to shoot a few rays here.
And, oh, look, they all hit this black object that I'm holding up.
Well, the black object happened to be a comb, and you just happened to hit four spots on it.
And so maybe you fill it in as a rectangle because you say, well,
all four of those spots were a rectangle.
But, in fact, the comb has a bunch of teeth, and so, you know,
you really should have shot more rays to make sure you got the fact that there's some high-frequency going on there.
So there's always a chance, like, if you're under-sampling.
And we saw that in that one image where, you know, we didn't capture that fine shadow because,
well, we just didn't shoot enough rays to really know, oh, yeah, there's a shadow here.
Let's put, you know, put a shadow there.
But there is, like, for example, in the first ray-tracing gems, there's an article by,
I don't know, I think it's, I want to say Bob Sansky or something.
There's one about anti-racing where he kind of does a simple, hey, I'm just going to do a ray per pixel,
and then I'm going to go back and sort of see where the high-frequency areas are.
Like, oh, look, something's changing over here.
You know, I went from one object to another.
So go back and shoot more rays at those locations, you know, that kind of thing.
And I think that's an interesting approach of, you know, instead of trying to do a denoise kind of thing,
you just say, no, no, no, you know, I'd really like to shoot more rays where I think they're important.
So I think, you know, there are ideas like that, where can we shoot more rays.
That's what a lot of the sort of ReSTIR stuff is about.
Like, well, you know, you've got a thousand light sources in the scene.
You know, how do I find those useful lights?
But on the other hand, you don't want to just get stuck and say, well, that's the useful light,
and there's no other useful lights.
So how often do you shoot other rays out to sort of say, oh,
are there any other useful lights that have come into play in this scene?
So there's just a lot of, yeah, there's tons to be done in a certain way,
and it kind of depends on the application of what you're trying to solve.
Is there a lot of stuff moving around in the scene?
Are there lights moving around in the scene?
What's sort of happening?
There's so many parameters that it's, you know, you push one of those parameters to one end or the other,
and it becomes like, hmm, okay, how do I solve that problem?
My technique is falling apart because, you know, classic things like, oh, my door is just a crack open.
I'm in a dark room, and the only light coming in is through that door.
That's a famous problem with what's called a metropolis light transport,
where you are trying to figure out, well, where's the light coming from?
Well, it's only from that little slit in the door where the door is just slightly ajar.
Well, how do we find that light and use it as opposed to just shooting samples everywhere
and always getting whack as our answer?
So, anyway, that's it in a nutshell.
There's lots of, well, how do we sample things better?
That's it in a nutshell.
You're talking about almost all ray tracing research as far as speeding things up is, you know,
what should I do with my rays?
Thank you.
Hi, Eric, can you hear me?
Hi, thanks for coming today.
It's a truly inspiring talk.
So my name is Leo.
I'm a second-year graphics master's student.
My question is, so over the recent years, NVIDIA is kind of like switching the direction.
Instead of just purely pursuing more raw power on the graphics card,
NVIDIA is kind of like switching to accelerated computing,
so adding more specialized cores, doing like DLSS.
So as a graphics student, I have this concern.
So I worry in the near future people might think that we don't really need that many graphics engineers anymore.
We just need some basic graphics and let AI do all the work.
So what's your opinion on this?
Yeah, I would not think so.
I'd like to stay employed.
But no, there's plenty of graphics work to be done for sure.
One project that I've been working on, me and, I don't know, a thousand other people at NVIDIA, is Omniverse.
It's this one thing called Omniverse where we're basically just trying to make a platform that's kind of,
it's not really meant as a modeling thing.
It's more meant as a simulation and rendering where we can bring in all kinds of different data sources
and work out, you know, put them in particular in a sim and animate them or simulate,
you know, do simulations on them or whatever.
And so there's tons of work just from a pure, like, work to be done kind of standpoint.
But I love that product.
It's a free product.
It's just a free download.
But it's, you know, sort of like looking at the future.
Because I'm like, yeah, anybody that thinks, oh, we're done, you know, we've got all the graphics we need.
Like that system has a really nice, it has like actually three main renderers in it.
One's like a real-time renderer, which is, has a little bit of ray tracing in it.
There's one that's a path tracer, which is a little slower, but a little more, a little nicer.
And there's iRay, which is the more sort of professional, like serious ray tracer that takes longer,
but you get a better image over the long run.
And so there's sort of these different levels of like, well, what do you want in rendering?
Do you want that super fast interactive where I just need something on the screen and show it to me?
Or do you want the, oh, I'm wanting to wait a half a second to see, you know, a nice render of my thing.
Or do I want to wait five seconds to get a good render, that kind of thing.
And so even, you know, so that's, again, another sliding scale, which, you know, you may have not one, not two, but three renderers.
Plus there's all these other kinds of renderers you can plug in that are called Hydra Delegates for rendering,
which is a universal scene description kind of thing.
So, you know, and those renderers that we have are like super fast, and, you know, they're focused on NVIDIA.
You have to have NVIDIA hardware to use, that kind of thing.
And so anybody in the rest of the world, outside of NVIDIA, that's like wanting to take advantage of that,
has to sort of do that rendering, you know, kind of thing.
So from just a development standpoint, I think there's just a ton of work.
For that alone, you know, it's not maybe the most glamorous work on one level, but on another level,
it's like, no, you're solving real problems of, you know, it's not research per se, but it's more development.
Like what actually works? You know, how do I make this fast?
And there's always quality speed tradeoffs. You know, what's the default here?
You know, we argue internally about, you know, well, you know, turn that flag on by default.
No, no, off, because it slows it way down when you do this.
So anyway, there's, you know, there's a lot of sort of interesting work there, basically.
That's just from a development side.
So, yeah, I don't know. And like I say, there's sort of, you know, on the research side,
we do have these new ideas that come in, and they're like, oh, yeah, that's really good.
Okay, let's expose that as software, or maybe that'll influence future hardware.
Yeah, I don't know. I don't feel like, you know, we may be done.
I feel like we're semi-done, but that's probably my ignorance at work as far as, you know, materials and so on.
Like I feel like we've got a fairly good grip on a lot of materials.
You know, we can make a lot of, you know, tiles or wood or stuff like that, you know, but even then, you know, carved wood.
I know a few companies that have good carved wood, but we're not one of them.
Anyway, or I don't think so, but I don't really look at it per se, but there's some really elaborate wood models as far as how things are flying and so on.
I don't think we're at that level yet, but, you know, we're moving onwards with that kind of thing.
But there's, you know, tons of materials in the world. There's tons of lighting situations, and, you know, each has its own niche.
You know, how much do you spend on that niche? I don't know.
Yeah, I just feel like, you know, there's not like, oh, well, once we've got the renderer, we're done.
Like, film companies, they kind of have the renderer in a certain sense, you know, their final frame renderer.
They're not going to, you know, throw it all away and make a new one overnight, but they'll constantly be adding new features.
You know, this will speed this up. This will make this material better. This will work better in animation.
This will do this simulation, you know, that kind of thing.
You know, every film is usually adding one or two new effects to their library of things they can do.
So, yeah, I don't know. I don't feel like anyone's like, yep, we're done, you know, just wash our hands and we'll all figure it out.
You know, yeah, sure, maybe for, I don't know, games like films or something, we don't have, you know, too much more processing power and that might be it.
But, I don't know, phones are still getting faster and so on, so.
I think there's more than that.
Thank you.
Hello, Eric. My name is Alex.
And talking about AI, neural rendering is really a hot topic now.
So, my question is, how soon do you think will neural rendering find it useful in the game industry?
Yeah, it, let's see, it sort of depends.
I mean, it's sort of, it's like a, it's almost like a bell curve, you know.
It's one of these things where you'll have a few early adopters, you know, like sort of AAA titles, you know,
and they'll devote some time to like, oh, you know, if you want to have the coolest graphics, you know, get this new card or, you know, whatever.
And, you know, you'll get this feature and, you know, we're cooler.
And it'll be faster, it's a good one.
You know, you just get the new card and it's faster, but that's not very interesting.
But, you know, you'll get new effects and so on.
And, you know, what happens over time is that sort of, you know, as old cards go away, you know, as they die off,
and, you know, if you're using a GPU from 10 years ago, you're probably not playing very many games, you know.
There's very few games that you can play that are sort of serious AAA titles or that push, you know, push things at all.
You pretty much have to have, you know, a relatively decent card the past few years.
I don't know what the drop-off is at all, but, you know, it's the kind of thing you can look at.
I think Steam has, you know, stats about who's using what cards and, you know,
what are the cards that get used for Steam games and so on.
And that's pretty interesting to look at right now.
But, yeah, so, you know, GPUs are always phasing out.
And so as the new GPUs come in, you start to be able to, you know, use these features more widely as they're just like,
oh, everybody has ray tracing, you know.
It used to be, you know, way back in the day, like, you know, you could do a bit of rendering on the screen and that was it.
And that sort of locked in, you know, you had very little choice as far as shading models or anything.
And then we had programmable shaders and that opened up a lot of ideas.
And people then realized, oh, look, we can do multi-pass, we can do a bunch of images and combine them, you know, in a single image.
We can do special effects that way, we can do coder tricks, basically, like shadows and stuff.
So there's sort of a bunch of, yeah, I don't know, you know, technology basically, I find it fascinating, basically, because there is a lag.
You know, it's not like, oh, there's new features in hardware.
So, you know, forget all those old users.
The only way you can play this game is this.
Well, you're probably not going to do so well.
But if you have the, oh, wait, you know, if we detect you have one of these cool ones, we can do this nice effect.
That can be, you know, a definite selling point for games.
You know, there's a lot of enthusiasm for the game because, hey, it looks cool, you know.
So anyway, yeah, there's sort of a funny dynamic.
I don't really know the whole, you know, how long it takes for a feature to become just part of the workflow and so on.
But, you know, and there's also just, yeah, tooling on the side of games developers.
You know, it's not like, oh, we have a new feature, you know, Unreal Engine, somebody says, or Unity says, hey, we have this new ray tracing feature.
It's not like developers just turn it on and go, hey, I've got ray tracing.
And I know there's, you know, a definite lag time with them having to look at the technology.
For the artists to sort of take advantage of the technology, find out what works, what doesn't work, and so on.
So it's, you know, it's, and a game can have multiple years before it comes out.
And sometimes an embarrassing load of years before it comes out.
But, you know, hopefully in a few years, from beginning to end, their new features get put in, but it takes a lot of photos to pull it out.
So, yeah, there's definitely a lag.
But, you know, it's definitely an outwards and outwards.
I've never seen it go backwards.
I've never seen people go, well, yeah, I'm done.
You know, let's just make it cheaper.
You can always get a cheaper GPU.
You can always get a crumblier one.
It's just kind of the nature of the beast.
Thank you.
But my opinion is, with the real-time rendering and...
I can't really hear.
But my opinion is, regarding the neural rendering, my opinion is, with the real-time ray tracing and the 4K textures come to real.
So we can have very promising graphics for games now.
So I think the main bottleneck preventing pursuing super-realistic now is actually the physics.
So do you think where the physics become the hot topic again in the coming years?
I would guess.
I haven't really followed trends carefully as far as simulations and so on.
But certainly, yeah, just doing more collision detection, it's something that's just part of various libraries now.
It's various collision detection libraries and so on.
And how to use CUDA or to use other kinds of GPU processing to speed up that.
And to allow you to do things like interactively drop a whole bunch of junk in a scene and have it interact properly.
Yeah, that's certainly a big deal.
Things like water actually flowing properly, that's a tough one.
That would be interesting and difficult, I think.
If you constrain it, you can do some interesting things interactively.
Yeah, like I said, there's sort of the rendering side, there's the animation side, there's the simulation side,
and there's probably some other side of it from now on, there are two other things.
But yeah, there's a lot of interesting things I think you can do with GPUs.
In part, we've sort of figured out some of the stuff.
But what I like actually is the fact that when you come up with a new feature,
and you say, oh, here's a new feature, this is kind of cool.
Like for the ray tracing cores, they definitely have a purpose in mind.
But for the deep learning cores, the tensor cores, those are just big.
Those are just big, and essentially the integer matrix multiplies,
and that's kind of the core feature that you use to essentially run a neural net.
So you give it inputs, and then you say, okay, go.
And basically you're evaluating how much it multiplies to get what the neural net says to do, essentially.
And so that's one where we didn't have the idea of, oh, that would be good for denoising.
Which is like, oh, that's just a thing we use all the time for neural nets, so let's just put it in there.
And so it's great to just sort of see these new technologies where, oh, okay, we're doing denoising.
That's nice.
But people are using them for all kinds of crazy neural net stuff that you never predicted, stuff that seems unlikely to work.
But like, wow, really? That kind of works.
Like the one that I saw just the past week or two, is this one where text to video.
I want to see a dog flying through a jungle or whatever.
It'll attempt to actually make a realistic little film of a dog flying through a jungle or whatever.
It's really in baby steps right now, but it's just interesting to see.
It's sort of a funny thing.
People sort of joke about, well, yeah, at some point we'll just have deep learning,
where we'll just describe the scene and it'll just appear that way.
I'm not laughing as much as I used to about that.
It's sort of like, gee, how much can we shove into these neural nets as far as geometry and ornamentation and so on.
And try to make them much cheaper to have a very minimal description of something that's actually quite elaborate when you render it.
So anyway, I don't know.
There's a lot of fascinating stuff going on.
So I guess we'll see is the answer.
Thank you.
I saw a hand sticking up, but I don't want to hold you guys forever.
I really appreciate you all listening.
Hello.
Oh, my God.
But, yeah, I'll just say, give me questions.
I appreciate what you're doing.
I'll just be right on.
I don't mind you not hearing it.
It's perfectly fine.
Thank you for your time.
I appreciate you listening to all that stuff.
I'm focused on the discussion.
OK.
Hello.
Hi, I'm David.
I'll preface this question by saying that the answer is probably I don't know.
But you talked about different other ways that path tracing can be used, like modeling sound or collisions or getting some poor architect fired for designing a bad skyscraper.
I was wondering if you know any work that's done where ray tracing and path tracing is used to model radar waves.
I'm sure it does.
I'm betting if you Google ray trace radar right now, you'll find a few thousand things, no doubt.
Just because, like I say, if it's something that you have something where you're trying to go from point to point and either determine between these two points, is there anything or I want to look in this direction and see something.
If that's used at all, then go for it.
So I'm looking here, you know, just Google a realistic radar ray tracing simulator for, you know, for the radar basically.
For large MIMO arrays.
I have no idea what a MIMO array is in automotive environments.
I'm assuming that's for self-driving cars or something, but I don't really know.
Yeah, there are, you know, people figure out ways.
What's interesting is that, you know, on one level, photons, if you think about them, yeah, sure, they're going straight and so on, you know, for the most part, but there is also this whole problem with diffraction, you know, especially with sound and so on going around corners and so on.
So, but there's a lot of work on well how can we simulate diffraction and often it comes down to shoot more rays, you know, so.
So really the ray is just a tool, it's not meant, you know, it's not like well if it's not going point to point, then I can't use rays. It's more just, this is just a way of sampling.
It's just a way of sort of saying, you know, what's going on between these two points, or what's going on in this volume of space and what's, you know, going on from this point to this area or whatever.
One way that you can do that is shoot lots of rays. So, so I will always guess that the answer is yes. Yeah, so Googling right there's 1.4 million results.
So, yeah, I'll say yes. Ray tracing and radar get along.
All right. Thank you.
Just to add to that, I think in addition to what you said very generally about anything that is point to point, you can do it with ray tracing.
In specific case of radar, I think it goes the opposite way as well when you're trying to design stealth hardware that you don't want things to bounce and you don't want that radiation to be coming out.
So you can do, you can use ray tracing to find black objects essentially.
So it goes the other way.
Any other questions?
I had a few, but I'll let the students go first.
Let me pick mine out.
So, Eric, you spoke about Dream Fusion, kind of reminded me of DALI for images, of course, where text gets converted to images.
Do you think we'll get to a point, and I know there's a lot of discussion around metaverse for this, is about how easy it becomes to generate 3D models using AI.
Do you think it'll be as simple as text to 3D or do you think there'll be some level of artistry involved?
Yeah, let's see, I know, well, the text to 3D, I know, that's sort of a hot topic right now, right?
Are all artists going to be out of business, you know, because hey, gee, I can just, you know, say what I want and I get some kind of funky image.
Yeah, it's, you know, it's interesting. Yeah, like the Dream Fusion thing was, I found just fascinating, like, oh, okay, wow, someone's really going for it and, you know, seeing if they could get something reasonable coming out of it.
But, let's see, I just want to see if I could find the link real quick.
Yeah, but, yeah, no, the Dream Fusion site's definitely worth looking at.
That they, you know, they're basically, their method is just, you know, baby steps kind of a method, but it's interesting to, like, see, you know, if you actually go to that site, there's things like, you know, here, let's share screen again, just because it's kind of fun to look at.
Yeah, so they just have this thing where it's like, okay, you know, let's start with this photo of a squirrel, but you can pick your variant of the squirrel.
I think these are all, possibly all canned, but anyway, like, you know, so he has this little wooden carving of a squirrel.
All I wanted to have it wearing a kimono, you know, now I have this model with it wearing a kimono or wearing an elegant ball gown.
And at the same time, I want to have it, you know, waving a sword around, or I want to have it, you know, on a pottery wheel or whatever, where they just, you know, you just change the, you know, your attributes.
And these things I think in real life, I think they've just blown through and made all these objects and then made little films of them so you can do every permutation.
It takes, I think, a few hours.
Although one of the people who worked on the paper is actually an intern at NVIDIA right now, I believe.
But anyway, so yeah, so, you know, they're getting these kind of cool models out of, you know, this sort of, well, I'll just do a text thing, and I'll get these sort of 2D images, and then I'll have it kind of try to figure out what the 3D NERF model is from those 2D images.
It's pretty interesting, you know, I don't know, you know, the question is really, you know, how much control do you have over that?
You know, it all depends on your training set, right?
Like, if you, you know, if you don't have, like, yeah, there's a lot of questions as far as, you know, well, okay, I have this model.
Well, that doesn't tell me anything about how to rig it, how to, you know, animate it, how to do anything with it.
You know, there's tons of other stuff that's not done by this, but it's still nonetheless a very interesting, you know, sort of use of deep learning.
Yeah, you know, I'm not sure how far I can go.
I think, I mean, it's probably, you know, we'll hit limits, and, you know, we'll, you know, there's just, it's hard to imagine sort of like, I don't know, if you play with some of these, you know, stable diffusion systems and so on, after a while, it's like, oh, things kind of fall into certain categories.
You know, you can pick up artistic styles and so on.
But there's sort of a sameness to them after a certain point.
And here, like, I think they're doing like a 64 by 64 by 64 sort of voxel thing and rebuilding images, you know, rebuilding surfaces at that resolution.
So they're not super high res kind of stuff, as I recall.
Anyway, so I don't know, is the sort of, you know, kind of answer.
But yeah, that was interesting.
Oops.
Oh, I never did share.
Sorry. Yeah, so this is, you know, this is sort of it.
I was clicking through all these things talking and you're all quietly saying what the heck is he talking about.
Now I actually see what I'm sharing.
You know, so you can just pick these various things, you know, a squirrel, wearing a purple hoodie, chopping vegetables, you know, so there's a model that does that.
It's all just based on deploying that images and, you know, making that into a 2D diffusion system.
So there's no 3D models underneath the hood.
It's all just sort of 2D and sort of, you know, interpolating a 3D model from that.
Thanks, Eric.
My next question was, I think real time rendering edition four came out a few years ago.
Do you think we'll see an addendum that talks more to the machine learning side of things?
Or do you think we'll see that in edition five at some point?
I don't plan an addendum personally.
Yeah, the Thomas and I and the other authors, you know, we liked, you know, we like sharing.
You know, we definitely like going, OK, here's the book, you know, that here's all the stuff we didn't know.
You know, here's the book we wish we had when we started out to try to say here, you know, here's just the techniques, you know, try to explain them simply and point to lots of references and let you go figure stuff out.
But, man, that takes a lot of work.
You know, it's, yeah, it's just a ton of labor.
And, and also the books sort of at the cracking point, like it's larger than it can really fit in a single volume.
And you kind of like, you know, it's hard to like kill your darlings or, you know, that's the famous phrase of like, you know, you do all this work on something in a novel or a film or something.
And sometimes you just have to cut it out.
And if you go at, that's a nice piece.
But, you know, we just got to cut that scene or we're going to cut that character or whatever.
And it's difficult to say, well, what do you, what do you, you know, abandon real time rendering?
Should I throw away texture mapping?
No, I don't think so.
You know, so, so there's sort of too many topics and too many interesting things going on.
But also, it's just a matter of, you know, each, each edition has gotten a number of larger number of years between each edition.
Like the first edition, we felt like, well, it's about two thirds complete.
The second edition, we felt like, oh, good.
We kind of covered all the things we wanted to cover.
You know, we've seen some kind of coverage.
The third edition, we're like, oh, my gosh, a lot's happened.
You know, there's all this programmable stuff going on.
Okay, we've got to talk about all these new techniques.
The fourth, you know, yet more stuff we've got to talk about.
And each edition became, like, I think it was, you know, two years between the first two, maybe, you know, five years between the next.
And then, like, about ten years between the last two.
And, you know, it's like, okay, that means maybe 20 years.
Because it's just a ton of work.
You know, it's hard to, like, you know, keep a, you know, sort of go over the whole book.
The difference between the third and the fourth edition, I think, I calculated by doing diffs.
And it's, like, about 40% different.
You know, that's how much of the text actually changed between the two editions.
So it's just like, oh, my gosh, that's a treadmill that really is sort of a joke of, like, when we'll do the next edition is when we forgot how much pain we went through doing the previous edition.
So I don't think any of us has forgotten the pain yet.
So it's going to be a while, I think.
So here's your chance.
If you want to write a new, you know, a new book, a real-time rendering, go for it.
I'll give you my full support.
Eric's putting out a call for authors.
So, you know, please, please respond.
Eric, my...
I think people are just going to keep learning to think that you just erased the whole text.
That would be good.
Yeah.
Only 10% of the text would probably be total wrong.
But, you know, other than that, we'll do that.
Eric, my last question for today is if you're looking for contributions to MacUSD, if that's something the students should look to contribute to, like in their final projects, or are there other hobby projects you want to give a shout out to that would be good for the students to look at?
Yeah, MacUSD, that one's more just, I would say that's really minor.
Like that's one that's sort of, you know, it's sort of bread and butter rendering stuff that's not...
I don't really think it's a great final project in some ways.
But maybe, I don't know.
You know, you might find something in the USD space that's like, oh, okay, well, you know, USD view works, but it's really simple.
Maybe I'll add something to USD view.
I don't know.
The only reason I mentioned MacUSD is I just was thinking, you know, what have I contributed to the community lately?
And I'm like, oh, yeah, I did this, you know, three weeks ago.
So sure, I'll pop that on the screen.
Yeah, I don't know.
I mean, there's, there really is just a ton out there.
It's, you know, I don't, unfortunately, I'm not sort of set up that I go, oh, yeah, what, you know, what project would I give somebody like you guys, you know, to work on?
Yeah, I'm sure I'll reach out to you before the final project starts to give the students ideas.
So I can pick your brain then again as well.
Yeah, yeah.
I'm trying to think about that.
Maybe I'll put a little call for ideas slide around here and see if anybody has any sort of, you know, not big enough for an intern.
It's, you know, hired by a first semester kind of thing.
That's sort of one level.
Yeah.
Like NIC USB is really, it's not a ton of work.
It's more just, you know, it would be like, okay, I'm going to learn the USB material description, and I'm going to see what I can do to, you know, test it.
And so that's, you know, that's, that's all that really is.
It's nothing, nothing deep there.
It's more just saying, hey, you know, it's good to contribute.
But it is nice.
On the other hand, if you had something where you were like, I'll take a week and just try to see if I can, you know, I see nobody has tested this feature.
Well, I'm going to go learn about that feature, test it, and make a little, you know, a little simple model.
And that's all it is.
There's no programming.
It's just making a model and then trying it on USD view and saying, okay, oh, that worked or that didn't work or trying it on a few viewers and saying, hey, this is one, you know, you guys might want to add to your working group assets.
You know, that's pretty doable and makes a huge difference, frankly, because there's a lot sort of writing on USD, but there's not as much as I would like with, you know, sort of unit tests or models that are in that format.
But anyway.
Yeah, I think a lot of the standards organizations are trying to change that and get USD to build more foundations there.
So thank you once again for sharing your time.
It's over two hours, so really appreciate it.
Students, if you want to wave hi to Eric, you can stand up and look at the camera behind.
But otherwise, thank you so much once again.
I'm sure the students appreciate it.
And we will see you for final projects and other things.
I'll be sending out those invites.
So, you know, always appreciate the advice you share with the students.
Yeah, I look forward to what you guys come up with.
Honestly, year after year, you guys have done above and beyond on some of the projects.
I would want to take that on.
That looks hard.
So, yeah, it's very impressive what you guys are up to.
So, yeah, keep on doing it.
All right.
Thanks, Eric.
Have a good night and see you next time.
Bye.
See you.