Let's make sure I'm not on mute, okay.
All right, so with today's class,
we essentially move into what I'll call loosely
the last trimester of our semester.
So for me, when I'm teaching this class,
the first trimester is getting you guys up to speed
on CUDA, leading up to project three.
Then I would say the second trimester
is project three and project four and project five.
You've got that experience
with hands-on computer GPU programming.
And now I'm only like teaching that one stuff
and the guest lectures I've started.
And now we go into the final trimester,
which is probably the most exciting part for me.
So in this class today, what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna be sharing really more
about the motivation behind final projects,
what to expect, what the grading looks like,
because that matters to you.
For me, it's more about the work
and what you guys should be looking for
when doing these projects.
And feel free to stop me at any time.
I'm more than happy to take any questions at any point.
I know I don't need to say that again,
given that we've been in probably 20 lectures by now,
but feel free to pause me at any time and ask questions.
Why are you not working?
All right, that should work.
Okay, so the first thing is what are final projects?
What is expected of final projects?
Final projects in 5.635 are gonna be large,
and I really mean large, path traces, not large.
GPU programming projects of your choice, okay?
They can be graphics, computing, machine learning,
whatever you may want,
as long as they have a GPU component in them.
And this doesn't mean you're writing CUDA necessarily.
It could be using any type of API that you want.
It will be two to three times harder
than the hardest project,
or it is expected to be two to three times harder
than your hardest project, which is generally path tracer.
But you also get to work in teams,
so it's not like you're necessarily overworking yourselves.
The best projects require about 100 hours of time commitment
based on the feedback we've received.
But if you think about it, it's not 100 hours in a week,
it's 100 hours spread over four and a half,
I think it's five weeks at this point.
So you're giving 20 hours a week,
which is probably generally what you've given
to this class for the most part.
Okay, so final projects themselves,
must be some combination of this.
It can't be just one, it doesn't have to be all of them,
but it has to be some combination of this.
It needs to serve a real need in the community.
And I'll keep giving examples, okay?
A need in a community, for example,
is you do an amazing project for WebGPU
that has driver adoption.
You make amazing samples for WebGPU,
and that's now the de facto,
okay, if you want to learn WebGPU, you go to that project.
So that's like serving a need in the community.
Exploring a new API.
CUDA at this point is not a new API to you, okay?
You may want to explore metal, right?
You may want to explore one API from Intel.
So that again is encouraged.
It can be recent research,
like graph papers, graph Asia papers,
high performance graphics,
you know, anything that you find interesting.
It could be extensions to existing work.
This could be, you know,
improving the performance significantly,
or adding, combining two different techniques
to bring something new to the table.
Or it could be something completely original.
You have an idea that you're coming up with,
and you're like,
hey, I'm interested in the super niche thing.
Maybe you're researching that in your PhD,
but you want to test it out on the GPU in the first,
more than happy to accept that as well.
So some combination of all these, okay?
We're not saying it has to be two out of five,
and we're not saying it has to be three out of five.
It depends on what your idea is,
that it has to pick some of these boxes,
and that is generally accepted.
Any questions on this?
Okay.
Either I'm doing a really good job,
or I've scared all of you already.
No questions?
Okay.
So, like I said,
you'd be working in teams of two or three.
That's the recommended approach, okay?
All of you will receive the same grade, okay?
Teams of four, I've never had a team of four,
but if you are trying to do a team of four,
the level of work that is required is extremely high.
And yes, please get pre-approval.
If you're trying to do something alone,
that is discouraged,
because the amount of work you're able to do
as a single person team is not gonna be as big
as something that two to three people will do.
That's not necessarily a detriment to you,
like the amount of work you might put together
is probably equivalent,
but the impact you're creating as a single contributor
versus working in a team of two or three
is gonna be a lot less,
because you're gonna be putting in less time.
So, it is in your favor,
it is for your betterment that you work
in a team of people.
So, if you absolutely want to work alone
and you have good reason for it,
you can get pre-approval,
but it's not guaranteed that we will approve it, okay?
So, if you're thinking about it,
please reach out early,
don't wait until last minute to ask,
hey, can I work alone kind of thing, okay?
Any questions here?
No?
I do not control how you form things at all,
it's completely up to you.
If you want to use that discussions
that's absolutely available,
you can be like, hey, I have these ideas,
if is anybody interested, please do that.
You can use private messages to reply if you want,
I think that's enabled.
But yeah, I don't play any part in how teams are formed,
because I don't want to get into those dynamics.
Any other questions?
Okay.
The other thing you can do to form teams is,
I'll come to it in a bit,
but as teams are being formed,
they're gonna put their names on a spreadsheet.
If you are interested in an idea,
you can be like, hey, can I join your team as well?
That's fine with me,
but it's up to the team itself to say yes or no,
that's not under my control.
Okay.
So, other guidelines, use GitHub, I think,
that's generally worked well for everybody.
You may use private repos,
but it's not encouraged or required.
Again, like I said before,
the programming language, graphics, whatever you want,
the platforms completely up to you.
Okay.
Again, I'm giving you the freedom to pick your interests,
but I'm expecting good work out of it.
Okay.
I want you to be able to pay that back
for what you are interested in.
To be completely honest,
this is work you may be doing in the class,
but you're not doing it for me,
you're doing it for yourselves, right?
This is like your highlight of your time at Penn almost,
and you have the freedom to do pretty much anything you want
as long as it's related to the GPU.
So, you get to pick what you want.
Like other projects,
you are allowed to use existing libraries.
So, for example,
you use TinyOBJ or TinyGLTF for PathTracer.
You can use similar libraries here as well.
The key thing is that they must not be solving the problem
that you are trying to implement itself.
Like in PathTracer,
you are trying to implement a PathTracer,
you're not trying to read an OBJ,
so it's fine to use a library for that.
So, in similar way, that is fine here as well.
So, any questions so far?
No?
Okay.
So, here's what the tentative schedule looks like, okay?
And pay attention here.
So, what you're going to get started with
is what I'll call a pitch.
And I will use here in final projects
are essentially what people do in the industry, okay?
If you want to,
if you are looking for something new that can change
how your company operates in the future
or build a new product,
you are going to have to write a document or some idea,
formulate your idea and communicate that to your manager
so that you get approval.
That's gonna be your pitch, okay?
You're gonna be doing that.
So, that's you on, I believe it's a Sunday, November 6th.
On November 7th, you'll pitch it.
You'll pitch it to me and a few others, including the TAs,
about why you want to do this idea,
you know, what's important,
what are the different components of it
and why it should be accepted as a final project.
November 12th is shadow team selection.
And I'll come back to shadow teams in a little bit.
And then we have three milestones
before the final presentations.
These milestones are key checkpoints
for when you will show your progress in the class
with demos, videos, whatever it might be.
So, these will be presentations,
but generally very short.
And I'll give you guidelines for these as well.
So, we'll have three of those on November 16th,
November 28th, which is after Thanksgiving
and December 5th.
December 11th, I didn't change the year, did I?
I should be changing the year.
I changed the dates.
I didn't change the year.
December 11th will be your court submission, essentially.
That's when your code is done, your readme is done.
You don't touch GitHub after that.
On December 12th at 4 p.m.,
that's when your final presentations are due.
That means your slides are due at that time.
And then at 5.30 approximately
is when we'll do the presentations themselves.
And these will be live.
And I'll share details on each one of these with you.
But any questions on this other than the year?
Does anyone have any feedback?
We'll do, we'll ask you to make changes
and give you feedback.
And depending on how much changes are required,
you may either be able to just resubmit the document
with those edits,
or if it's completely out of the park
and we need you to submit a new idea,
then we'll do a follow-up that Wednesday.
Edward?
Are the pitches with pre-formed groups
or do you just do that with a new idea?
No, you'd be pitching as a team.
You'd be forming your team and then pitching it as a team.
Yes.
So essentially you don't touch GitHub after this.
And no late days.
If you save late days, use it for final project
or project five, use all the extra credit.
You don't have any late days for final projects.
Any other questions here?
No?
We already have teams for final project pitching as well.
I'll get to that.
So this is just an overview.
I'll confirm all of,
I'll get into the details of all of this.
But any questions here on an overview?
Okay.
All right.
So final project pitches itself.
The first thing you're gonna want to do
because it's first come first serve
is put your team name in this document.
It's an Excel spreadsheet.
I'll bring it up here so that all of you can see it.
So what you're gonna do for the first thing,
like even right away,
if you know who your team is,
who you want to be teaming up with, put your names.
You don't even have to put your idea.
Just put your name on the time that works for you.
And the time may change.
Like if we get enough teams,
we may have to start around like 4.30 or something.
So the time may change,
but essentially put your names on there
because if once a team puts their name,
that's their slot, okay?
The time is essentially when you're gonna be pitching.
And I'll come to this in a little bit,
but essentially your team is gonna come,
you're gonna sit down.
We would have already read your pitch,
but we'll ask a few questions.
We'll ask for your motivation and stuff.
And it's about 20 minutes per team.
So yeah, that's...
And then once you put your names there
and you're working through your ideas,
eventually you're gonna create a pitch document,
which again, I'll get to,
and you're gonna link it here in this column, okay?
So those are the first two steps you need to do
before the pitches.
Any questions on this?
Okay, so again, we'll have a special office hours
next Monday to help answer your questions and stuff.
You don't come with like 50 ideas
because I almost never say,
hey, do this exact project.
I will say, if you are interested in this,
here are the things to think about.
And if you're interested, go forward.
I'm gonna give you guidelines
around how to think about these projects, okay?
So come with like three at most.
If you're coming with five,
then you need to narrow it down yourself first
about why you want to do all of the five, okay?
Narrow it down to two to three,
and then we can have more discussions.
The pitches themselves,
this year is gonna be really special
because I'm gonna be hosting these
in the brand new CGU office.
And I say brand new
because we are literally gonna move into it on Tuesday.
So we're gonna move into it Tuesday
and the following Monday,
you guys are gonna come in there.
And I'm doing this because I wanna give a feel for,
again, the motivation is to work,
how it's like to work in the industry.
I've said that from day one.
I wanna give you guys that feel.
And we'll make a great environment that we'll have pizza,
we'll have some drinks, cookies, and those kinds of things.
You're free to come at any time,
depending on like your pitch time may be one thing,
but you are free to come in at any time.
You're free to hang out, eat.
And we also have a really good arcade,
including an NES, a Nintendo Switch, a PlayStation 1,
a Super NES, and a bunch of arcade games there.
I think that's Ridge Racer, Pac-Man,
and a digital Marvel.
You can play Spider-Man pinball and all that.
It's brilliant, trust me.
That's where I'm coming from today.
So yeah, we'll be doing these.
You are free to take whatever transport you want.
I'm not taking care of that, but it's not too bad.
You take the subway from like 34th street to 5th street,
and then it's a block from there.
So it's pretty convenient.
Any questions on this?
No?
How many of you are excited to play that arcade?
All right, good.
Come early.
I'm telling you, you can come early.
Don't make it that tight.
That's my recommendation.
You are free to select those times.
I'm not giving you those times.
You're free to select those times.
So if you have a class that ends at 5 p.m.,
don't pick the 5.30 slot.
Pick the 6 p.m. slot.
So that's my recommendation around that.
Any questions?
Okay.
All right, grading which I know all of you care about.
Your project, this final project is worth 50%
of all the grade in the class.
Imagine all the work you've done so far.
Voids, stream compaction, path tracer,
denoiser, and now you're either doing Vulkan or WebGL.
You've done all of that work and that is only worth half.
This is what the other half.
It may not be as much work
as all of those five projects combined,
but it's still like very, very important, okay?
So that's 50% of your grade.
It'll be divided into four parts.
Each of the milestones will account for,
or five parts technically.
Each of the progress you make,
that is the core progress you make in the milestones
will be about 20% each, okay?
And then the final submission that you do is additional 20%.
And then the presentations that you give
for each of the milestones and the final presentation
will be worth 20%.
So it's not just the code that counts,
which I've always said, you know,
in your projects it's the readme,
here it's gonna be the presentations.
Those are going to count for 20% too.
Any questions around this grading?
And a reminder that everybody,
the entire team receives the same grade.
If any of you have a questions about,
hey, my class disappeared and I don't know what to do.
Don't wait till the final submission,
tell me when that happens, okay?
So that we can help resolve it.
Ideally that situation never,
if it happens, you know, please communicate early.
Don't wait for the last minute.
Any other questions here?
Okay.
Nobody cares about grades anymore?
That's a good thing.
All right.
So the project pitches themselves.
Okay, here's the do's and don'ts.
You want to either write a one page document
or five slides.
It is up to you.
You can do a Google Doc,
you can do Word,
or you can do PowerPoint or Google Sites.
Completely up to you.
Submit a PDF for all it's worth.
Conciseness is best, you know?
Give the key information that's useful.
Have clear goals and outcomes.
Talk about why you want to do the project,
what is expected out of the project,
what each of the milestones should be
and what you wish to accomplish.
Include any programming languages,
APIs, platforms that you wish to use,
game engines that you might want to use,
references to any papers, inspiration,
those kinds of things,
and any third party code.
Now, what you shouldn't do,
don't include math equations.
I won't understand them, nobody will understand them.
Okay?
Don't include it, they're not useful.
Don't exceed two pages and five slides
and or five slides.
Because again, if it's more than two pages,
I'm not going to read.
That means you're not writing it concisely.
You can,
don't bring repeat ideas.
For example, we had a WebGPU based GLTF viewer last year.
Don't do the same thing.
That's done.
You're not doing anything new.
You're a year ahead.
You should be moving the class forward.
Okay?
And lastly, don't come unprepared.
Understand why you want to do this project.
I'm telling you the questions that I'm going to ask.
If you come unprepared, then it's going to look sloppy
and I'm going to be like, okay, go rework that.
And while you're reworking it
between the Monday and the Wednesday,
other teams have already gotten started on the projects.
So it's going to put you at a disadvantage.
Any questions about these pitches?
Wayne, any recommendations from your pitch last year?
Yeah.
If you remember.
Your pitch was probably one of the easy ones last year.
Yeah.
Yours, Matt's, and Ashley's.
The project wasn't easy.
The pitch was well done.
Wait, were you saying my project?
Your pitch.
Okay, yeah, yeah.
It was well done, yes.
Yeah.
But any recommendations you have
as a student who's written a pitch?
Yeah, I think that's a stupid short.
Say you're implementing a paper,
you don't really have to talk a lot about the paper,
but really focus on what's novel about your project.
I think that's the most important thing.
Yeah.
So again, I'm coming from the industry.
I understand things would move.
When I ask you to write a schedule
for milestone one to three on the final,
I am asking based on what is your expectation.
If let's say one feature as part of one of these milestones
is like, hey, we spend more time on this,
so we are not able to accomplish it, it's fine.
Don't worry about it.
I want to make sure that you understand
what the requirements are and how much time it takes.
And if I don't see that to be realistic,
I will tell you, hey, this is not realistic,
move these things around.
Again, I want to help you do amazing things, okay?
This is not a test, okay?
So be very conscious, be very pragmatic
about what you're taking on
and you're understanding the problem
that you want to implement.
And what I'm asking you to do here
is essentially a sanity check that you understand it
and I can confirm it from my side.
I'm not gonna understand all the problems you come up with.
You may come up with,
hey, I want to do machine learning
that understands when it'll rain in not great weather.
Sure, like write a machine learning algorithm.
Do I know much about machine learning?
Probably not.
Can I connect you with Liam
who knows a lot about machine learning?
Yes.
Can I connect you with industry people?
Absolutely.
But the fact is I want to make sure
that you understand what you're doing, okay?
Anything else here?
Yeah.
Are you asking about the milestone date
or the amount of progress to make in the milestone?
Again, they should be reasonably set.
Like again, if you plan to do three things in milestone two
and you do two and a half, fine, I don't really care.
You're not gonna get dark points for that.
Again, I live in a realistic world.
I see deadlines slipping every day.
So that's not the worst thing.
Now, if you come from milestone one to milestone two
and you're like, I haven't made any progress.
Yes, that is a problem, okay?
So I will be as reasonable as I can be.
I'm here to guide you,
but ultimately you have to do the work, okay?
You are free to change it if you have good reason.
Let's say you do milestone one and you're like,
hey, we did made a lot of progress,
but while making the progress,
we realized like all of these things
that completely throw a plan out of the window
and here's a new plan and you've thought about it.
Fine, no problem, okay?
But being able to articulate what happened
and what your new plan is and doing that well,
that is the important part.
Make sure you're not coming into the class
and saying I have no progress, okay?
If you're running into problems,
communicate that so that when we come into the milestones,
we know what to expect and we are just there to see,
okay, you've thought about it
and you know what the way forward is.
Any other questions on the pitches?
Okay, all right.
Coming to the milestone presentations,
this is when you're gonna be up here
and you're gonna talk.
So I'm gonna be sitting there pretty much the entire class.
You will have time limits, okay?
We will, before the presentations,
a few days, at least a few days before the presentations,
we'll tell you how many minutes you have
and this is gonna be generally between five and eight.
It's not gonna be very long.
You're not gonna be giving a 20 minute presentation.
I don't think we'd be able to sit through
that many presentations.
So if I say the limit is five minutes, it is five minutes.
You go over, you get doc points, okay?
Again, I am not looking for you to tell me
the entire history of your week.
Tell me the main points.
That's the key thing.
Show me the progress that you've made since last milestone.
These can be videos, images, demos, including live demos.
And then tell me what your goals for the next milestone are,
if they're consistent with your pitch
or you're planning to change them a little bit.
Again, perfectly fine.
The audience here now,
from when you start doing these milestones
is not just gonna be me and the TAs.
Don't look at us when you're talking.
You're sharing this with the entire class.
Your class is there to understand what you're doing
and be inspired by it, okay?
So the audience is all of us
and you wanna take that into account.
And then once you're done with the milestone,
add that presentation to your GitHub repo, okay?
Other do's, use social media.
I've seen some of you use social media, props for it.
I've liked it, I've shared it.
Use social media more and more, okay?
Get in touch with the authors.
Eric Haynes shared this before.
Brandon asked you to reach out if you're doing WebGPU.
Reach out to the authors.
They love it if people are trying to replicate their work
and advance their work.
None of the people whose work you will try to recreate
or advance will have even a sense of ego or jealousy
that, hey, why is this person doing my work?
No, they will in fact take pride that,
hey, I've done something that is inspiring other people
to do the same thing, okay?
There are presentation guides.
Again, this is also guides.
So please watch that and prepare for the presentations.
Don't come in sloppily.
How the quality of your presentation
determines that final 20% of your grade.
Remember that, okay?
I'll take questions after I do the don'ts part.
Now, don't.
Don't exceed the time.
Again, reiterating that happens every year.
Don't do it.
Please try not to do it.
Don't include code and math equations in your presentation.
It's not useful.
You're gonna be presenting for five minutes, right?
To read five lines of code,
I'm gonna take more time than that, okay?
Include a math equation that shows how,
let's say the rendering equation works.
You're gonna need way more time to explain
what the math equation is than you have time.
So don't include them unless there is something
very, very, very exceptional about it.
Sharing that equation is a required part
of explaining what happens next, okay?
You don't need to open Visual Studio.
You don't need to walk through the code.
You want to do demos?
Awesome, do demos.
But have it ready.
Compile it, have it ready.
Don't compile in front of it
because that's using up your time, okay?
You don't get free,
you don't get additional 30 seconds for compiling time.
That's five minutes, if I say five minutes, okay?
So any questions on the milestone presentations?
No?
I'm sure there'll be some.
Okay, I'll move on.
So final presentations are a bit special.
So you have milestone one, two, three,
which will be the milestone presentations.
Then we'll have the final presentations.
And they're gonna be special
because I'm going to invite
not just guest speakers from this year.
I'm gonna be inviting guest speakers from last year,
friends of the course,
and anybody who takes an interest
in the final projects in this class.
And trust me, there are a lot of people.
I think last year we had at least 25 people join.
And this is all people like Brandon Jones
who are joining, and Eric Haynes joins every year.
So these are people who take an active interest
in the final projects of this class
because, and this is important,
they know the final projects in this class are amazing, okay?
So there is a bar that has been set
by the former students of this class
that has put up a standard
that people take an interest on what this class does.
And that directly leads to interviews and jobs.
And it has happened and happens continuously.
I expect it to happen this year too.
So because we have people coming from the outside,
your audience then becomes the entire world, right?
The people from different fields, different technologies,
they're all gonna be watching.
So first of all,
your presentation should be a lot more polished,
practice it more.
Again, that's why the submission is on the Sunday.
And then you have the Monday
to practice your presentations if needed.
Don't include information about our logistics.
Our milestones are logistics.
Our pitches are logistics, right?
It's a way for me to keep a check on you saying,
hey guys, I've given you five weeks.
What have you come up with?
You know, that'll be dangerous if I try to do that.
So the milestones are kind of like a checkpoint for us.
But when you are showing this to the world,
show it as one complete thing.
You've done this project and here's the outcome of it.
So that's what we wanna show.
Most likely five minutes,
but I'll let you know what the exact time is for that.
And pretty much the same,
otherwise it's the same do's and don'ts
as the milestone presentations.
What you should expect to do in the final presentation.
Give an overview of the problem,
use one to two slides of the technical approach.
Absolutely show a demo if you can, a live demo.
And I will give you extra time
if you want to do a live demo.
I will add information about this
as we lead up to final presentations.
But if you plan to do a live demo, I will give you more time.
If you wanna include videos, again, well-recommended.
Include some performance analysis
about what the performance is,
what was expected, what you came up with.
And then any shortcomings of future work
that you may not have been able to achieve
or expect to do in the future.
You can do this as slides with the demo video
or prepare a video for the entire presentation.
But it's important that when you come up here,
you are talking.
You can have the presentation run as a video,
but you will have to speak.
You can't just record yourself talking
and just play the video.
So again, final project submissions are due
on December 11th.
And then final presentations would be Monday evening.
And between that,
I recommend that you take the time to sleep.
I know this is not the only class
and you'll have other classes,
but try to take the time to sleep.
Practice your presentations.
That'll be important.
And then work on any demo videos.
Again, the demo videos don't have to be submitted
to GitHub, so you're free to work on those.
Make changes to GitHub only if you find a serious bug
and let us know if you're doing that, okay?
So those are my notes for presentations, milestone,
and the final project presentation.
So any questions on this?
No?
You guys are awfully silent today.
All right, I'm sure there'll be something
and we'll come back.
All right.
Shadow teams.
So shadow teams was an idea I started in 2020,
I think, when the pandemic hit,
or it may have been 2019, I can't remember.
Essentially, the goal of a shadow team
is to be able to have a paired team.
So you are a team and there'll be your shadow team
who you can either bounce ideas off of,
you can be like, hey guys, you're trying to do this,
do you have any other suggestions?
And then you can practice your presentations with them.
Okay, so both of you should be like,
hey, let's practice our presentation.
Okay, you do your presentation.
The limit is five minutes, you go to eight minutes
and you're asking your shadow team,
okay, what should we cut down?
What is not important?
What went over your head that makes no sense
to put in this presentation?
Those kinds of things have become very, very important.
We recommend that you meet once a week,
at least for 30 to 60 minutes.
And if for nothing else to practice your presentation.
Okay.
Generally, you will be allowed to select your shadow team.
So once you do your pitches,
you will know what the other teams are doing.
So for example, if there are two teams doing web GPU,
you'll be shadow teams.
If there are two teams doing machine learning,
you'll likely be shadow teams, okay?
So the shadow teams should generally be relevant
to your topic.
And in the past years when we've done this,
shadow teams have always helped make presentations better.
And this is extremely clear.
Teams who come up here and do a sloppy presentation
will have never practiced with their shadow team.
The teams who come up here and do an amazing job
of the presentations, practice with their shadow teams.
And it has nothing to do with
whether you're an English native speaker
or how confident you are about speaking.
It is about the information you share
and bouncing it off of somebody
who is not doing what you're doing.
When you're doing these final projects,
you're gonna be knee deep in them.
Okay.
You're gonna be debugging them.
You're gonna be reading the papers.
And at some point what happens is
you forget what the basics are, right?
You forget that the things you understand,
the person in front of you doesn't understand
because they haven't read those same papers.
So the shadow teams will help you bring it up to a context
that other people will understand.
So it's absolutely vital that you meet
with their shadow teams and practice with them.
Now, again, it's not a free hand.
I will be checking in.
And the way I check in is through the shadow team surveys.
All of you filled out my pre-class survey, right?
When I asked for your information and your interest.
This is gonna be similar to that,
but it's gonna be very short.
It will take no more than three minutes for you to fill out.
The information I'm looking for is when you met,
how was your interaction?
What were some of the highlights?
And that's about it.
Okay.
So not filling these is a penalty.
It will go off your milestone points.
And sadly, I've had to do this in the past.
Again, it takes no more than three minutes.
While you're meeting with your shadow team,
you're ending your meeting, just type it out.
Okay.
And so any questions on, what did we do?
We did final presentations was done on shadow teams.
Any questions on shadow teams?
No.
I do deserve the right to change the shadow teams,
by the way.
Because there are times when just a group of friends
want to be each other's shadow teams
and have no sense of relations and topics.
So I will keep an eye on that,
but otherwise you are generally free to choose
as long as you're making conscious decisions.
Any other questions?
No.
Okay.
So shadow team service is done.
So what do you need to deliver?
So there are a few things.
The project pitch is due on November 6th.
So that's the first deliverable.
Your three milestone presentations are deliverable
on the day of the milestone,
and then you add them to GitHub.
Your final presentation,
your final code submission on GitHub,
and then four shadow team surveys, one for each week.
Okay.
You missed shadow team surveys.
I take no pride in docking points,
but please just finish it.
It's, you know, it's not a complex problem.
Just add the information there.
So any questions here?
Yeah.
All right.
So for your reference,
I've put in a bunch of final projects
for you to take a look at.
And this is, these can be good
because they did something technically amazing.
They can be good because they captured a really nice video
from the work they've done.
They could have written a great readme.
So these are all really, really good final projects.
This one up left is Wayne's.
This is Rachel's team.
That is Shubham's team who did Voxels and ReSTIR.
So, you know, again, really good projects.
These are not the only great projects.
So please visit previous year's websites
to actually see what was done.
I'm not gonna be walking through each of these,
but these are for your inspiration
when you go back home and start thinking about projects
to take a look at for inspiration of what is expected
and how students have gone on in the past
and done their projects.
Okay.
So let me skip through these.
This was the first DXR project in the class, by the way.
So a bunch of them.
And then there are links for you to reference
really good pitches, milestone, final project presentation.
So these are all like, again,
references for you to understand what is expected.
Any questions on this?
Nope.
No?
Okay.
So let's get into project ideas.
And these are, I will be very clear, only some ideas.
I ask for recommendations from people in the industry.
I come up with some of my ideas of my own,
but these are only some.
You are free to explore the world
and come up with your own ideas, okay?
So denoising is very big.
I think Eric Haynes shared that with us.
You guys saw the project poll.
If you want to do a denoising with Path Tracer and or DXR,
please, I think it's a wonderful topic.
It's definitely taking a lot of headway in the world.
So definitely recommend it.
I won't read all of this, but this is an idea from Nvidia.
So when Eric Haynes came in, I asked him,
hey, do you have ideas for final projects?
And he asked in basically Nvidia's research Slack channel
about what are good ideas for students.
And this is one of those.
So I won't read this.
This is for your reference to read at home.
DXR, I think, is an amazing topic.
And I write DXR, but it's really,
if you want to do welcome ray tracing,
that's perfectly fine with me too.
Again, in this case, so if you remember the second slide
that I showed you, it was that your project
must be a combination of things, right?
So in this case, DXR is one part of that.
And then you come up with, what do you want to do with DXR?
There are so many things you can do.
What do you want to apply DXR to?
So that's something you have to come up with.
Replicating papers from advances in real-time rendering.
I think it's an amazing course at SIGGRAPH.
Please check out the papers from there.
Both of these links are really good for that.
Check them out if that's what you want to re-implement.
Very well recommended.
Another idea coming from NVIDIA
is this Voxel space GitHub repo.
Again, I won't read the full text.
This is as it's coming from NVIDIA,
but another thing that you can think about
how to improve with the GPU.
ReSTIR, so we've had all the last two years,
we've probably had like four or five ReSTIR projects.
ReSTIR is spatial temporal sampling.
I forget the entire form,
but it's essentially a technique
for making ray tracing faster
because of improving denoising and stuff.
So if you try to do the seminal ReSTIR paper,
you'll get a no.
But if you try to do an advanced ReSTIR paper
with improvements and stuff that are coming every year,
sure, I'm very much open to that.
So this is one of those ideas coming from NVIDIA.
You can do a lot of machine learning projects,
both with graphics output and not graphics output.
These are some with graphical outputs,
you know, CNNL, STM, transformers.
Again, I may or may not understand all of these,
but I'm more than happy to connect you with Liam
and others who are interested in this
and have a lot of expertise here.
And Liam will be coming to the milestones and stuff
if any of you are doing machine learning projects.
And then there's machine learning on the compute side.
So this is object detections, speech to text.
Speech to text is a big hobby for Liam.
He does NLP, right?
So a bunch of things here, again,
very much of interest for this class
as well as for the industry.
Advanced projects in Vulkan, DirectX, Metal.
Again, these are APIs.
How you apply them is up to you, okay?
I think Metal is certainly very interesting.
Vulkan and DirectX, probably a little bit more common,
but definitely try to explore these if you want to.
WebGPU, I don't think I need to say much more
than what Brandon has already shared with us.
We had three WebGPU projects last year.
I'm looking to build on that.
I think that momentum is great.
People took notice.
The entire Chrome GPU team
joined the final project presentations last year.
And maybe, Wayne, if I'm putting you on the spot,
you were in touch with the Chrome GPU team
and maybe why don't you share
some of how your communication with them went
and how it's like, in complete honesty,
how it's like to interact with them.
Yeah, I think they are very,
definitely open to the WebGPU team.
I mean, I'm sure you guys heard from Brandon.
The whole team, they're very open to project ideas
and they really want to make the API better.
So whenever you have questions,
you can really just reach out to them directly
during your project.
So I'd say, don't be scared.
If it's like WebGPU is such a new thing,
you can definitely get a ton of support from the team.
Yeah, it was way more complex when you were doing it.
We are a year ahead of that
and there's been so much progress made.
It's very, very close to standardization.
So it should be a lot better experience
for you guys as well.
Okay, again, this is an API.
How you apply it is up to you.
This next one is pretty close to me.
So for geospatial, so you can essentially
take the entire globe and stream it into Unreal Engine
or on WebGL using Cesium JS.
If you have ideas that you want to work on,
for example, I think back in like 2017,
one team did like a snow simulation
inside Cesium JS using WebGL.
If you have ideas that would help with something like this,
again, if you think of ideas in the metaverse
or digital twins, those kinds of things,
if you want to improve some of this,
I will certainly help you.
I will get you connected with developers at Cesium
and would strongly encourage
if there's anything you want to do here.
Similarly, that's going to come November 14,
but even before that,
NVIDIA Omniverse is a fantastic platform.
We've been playing around with it a little bit.
If you want to use NVIDIA Omniverse
to help build an amazing project
based on some of your interests,
again, that is very open.
I'm more than happy to get you connected.
For those of you who love Python,
the NVIDIA Omniverse API is written in Python,
so that'll be a good opportunity
for you to work with that as well.
Again, Omniverse provides the platform.
It's up to you what you want to do with it.
Other general ideas using game engines,
you can use Unity or Unreal Engine
and add a key feature on top of that
that takes advantage of the GPU.
This could be compute shaders
or anything like that that you're using
to help advance a certain feature.
Similarly for O3D,
some of you may or may not have heard of this,
but O3D is formerly Crytek,
used for Crysis, of course,
that became Amazon Lumberyard,
and then Lumberyard became O3D
through a collaboration
between Linux Foundation and Amazon.
So O3D is a very new game engine
from that point of view.
It was made open source last year, last summer,
and there's a lot of momentum behind it,
especially with Amazon's backing
on having a AAA-grade open source game engine.
So there's a lot of good stuff that is available
that you can do within O3D,
so I would certainly recommend that as well.
Mesh shading is a great idea as well.
We had Manuel Cramer give a guest lecture in 2020.
Very, very interesting topic,
having mesh shaders,
so if that's something you're interested in,
again, wonderful, wonderful topic to explore.
3D mesh classification and segmentation
is really good as well,
where you're taking data from the real world,
3D models and stuff,
and trying to classify,
this is a window, this is a door,
the door opens this way,
and adding semantic information to 3D models.
They are complex topics,
but certainly well worth exploring as well.
Some other topics,
Three.js, Babylon.js,
again, just like the game engines I mentioned before,
using Three.js and Babylon.js is certainly an option.
Take a look at the GitHub issues that they have
and what they may want to explore.
NVIDIA Optics is great too,
although I would recommend doing something
with Omniverse first before you consider Optics,
but Optics is great too.
And then any people from machine learning conferences,
SIGGRAPH, all of that,
so I've added a link here as well.
Couple of other topics that came from NVIDIA,
massively parallel collision detection.
Again, I'm just giving you four words,
what it actually means is up to you.
And then in general,
trying to improve performance or memory
without affecting any existing algorithms.
So trying to make significant improvements
to existing algorithms is really good as well
and valued a lot by the industry.
Okay, so I've given you ideas,
now let me give you anti-ideas,
things that I don't want to see.
Don't use Vulkan Compute Shader.
You're doing that as part of project five,
I don't really want to see that, okay?
You want to come up with a better idea.
Multi-GPU was a thing back in 2013.
It's not really a thing now,
the GPUs are far more powerful.
Simulation, depending on the algorithm
and the goal it's trying to accomplish,
can, may or may not be good.
So if you're thinking of doing a simulation,
what a simulation, plot simulation or stuff like that,
please run it by me next Monday
when we have those office hours.
If you are trying to extend your CUDA pathways,
I have a very, very strong idea behind it.
If you come to me with the idea that,
okay, I'm going to take my path tracer
and all the features that I didn't do in project three time,
I'm going to do now, not worth it.
Like, absolutely do it,
just not part of the final project, okay?
I strongly recommend all of you do
because it's a great project,
you can keep improving on it,
just not as part of the path tracer.
I mentioned ReSTIR, we have had four in the last two years.
Again, try the newer papers,
don't try to re-implement it.
So this quote again came from NVIDIA.
And this is from somebody who teaches a class like I do,
they work at NVIDIA and they teach a class.
If the goal is to go implement a paper
from the last five years with no improvement,
that'll get you a B-plus
and that's kind of what will happen in this class as well.
Okay?
So the work that we expect is that you do something unique
from either 2021 or 2022
and or make significant improvements to it.
So those are anti-ideas.
And generally my goal behind anti-ideas,
the why is again, so that you are doing amazing work.
Okay?
If you are taking, let's say this one,
this CUDA path tracer idea,
you're not making improvements,
this has been done in 2016, right?
We are in 2022, we want to do the latest and greatest stuff
and you have the opportunity to do that.
If you do make improvements to the CUDA path tracer,
you're falling behind.
There are students who are doing more advanced things.
So the goal is for you to do more advanced things
rather than me saying,
hey, I don't like this, don't do this.
I love the path tracer.
There's a reason why it stayed as a project
for over 10 years.
Continue to improve on it,
just don't do it as a final project.
Okay.
So I'll pause there and take questions.
And I've gone through a bunch of topics.
Again, those topics are not what you're limited to.
You can come up with your own ideas.
Those are just suggestions from me.
Okay.
I mean, you have to come up with that, right?
Like you have from this Monday until next Monday
to come up with that plan.
Like you may have,
I want to make every tree in the world render really nice.
Sure.
Great idea.
How you want to go about doing that is up to you.
And that's the part you are going to figure out
in the next two weeks.
If it was just, hey, here are 15 papers, pick one,
then I'm going to give you two days for it, right?
You guys kind of see it in 660 and stuff.
I love 660 too.
I think it's a fantastic class
that gets you to implement papers.
But here, I want to give you that time and space
to really think about what you're doing.
Edward.
Yes.
So this comes up every year.
If you're trying to do a machine learning project
that requires you to do training,
either understand the requirements
and have the data available.
Again, these two weeks are there for you to research that.
There are data sets available in most places.
If you're trying to re-implement a paper
that needs some training data, go contact the author.
Maybe they'll just give it to you, right?
Don't come to me at the end of milestone two
and be like, hey guys, we have no training data.
Our project's dead in the water.
Please don't do that.
It's not good for you, okay?
So think about this problem early.
If you are planning to do any kind of project,
not just machine learning that requires a dependency
that you don't have access to, think about it early.
If you don't think there's a solution to that,
leave the problem, okay?
You can do it in the future.
What are the questions?
Any other questions?
All right, by now I would have covered most of the FAQs,
but let's go through them, okay.
Very commonly asked.
I want to do a project on a topic
that has been done in the past.
Is that allowed?
Again, the goal of the final projects
is to move you forward,
allow you to do industry relevant topics.
If you do something from previous years,
you're just falling behind.
You're not on the cutting edge.
So can you take inspiration from something
that was done in past years?
Absolutely, please do, okay?
Even projects that were done in previous years
were cutting edge for their time.
Take inspiration, but come to me with
what are the advances that you're making to that, okay?
What changes are you making
that is making it relevant to 2022?
Generic question.
I want to work on a topic or technology
that I have no experience with.
My response to that is always to be brave.
You guys, most of you, if not all of you took this class
knowing nothing about CUDA.
And now you can pretty much walk into any CUDA job
and ace it, right?
So no, I'm being very serious about it.
So there'll be enough time for you to learn
and implement during the final projects, okay?
It's not two weeks deadline every single time.
So be brave.
If the topic and technology is relevant to you,
you are interested in it,
you think you want to work in that field in the future,
do it.
I highly encourage you to do that.
Okay.
I don't think this is so much of a problem these days,
but was in the past.
Let's say you want to do a DXR project
and you need one of the modern GPUs
and you don't have access to one.
Well, firstly, I think most of the Moodle app computers
now have at least a fallback capable DXR GPU.
If that doesn't work,
all of you receive credits from Azure, AWS or Google Cloud
where they have GPUs that are capable,
Tesla T4s and others.
You can take advantage of those,
use those for your DXR projects.
And if you're planning to do this,
let us know as soon as possible.
Okay.
You may or may not be doing something
that's graphics or visual.
Perfectly fine.
We've had so many projects do that in the past.
You should, if in that case,
you may or may not have videos and images,
but what you will have is performance analysis
and some kind of results.
You want to be focusing on that.
Another common question, you're from CIS.
You don't really have a graphics background.
You don't want to do a graphics related project,
projects that you can work on.
Again, I've shared a bunch of those projects already,
but essentially the core piece of advice is
take something that's of interest to you
and put it to the GPU.
Whether that's machine learning, deep learning,
autonomous driving, Tegras, Apple Metal, anything
that's relevant to you and you are interested in
that will generally be okay with me.
I've generally covered this, I think.
So I won't go over it again.
If you're working on a long-term research or PhD project,
and this has happened in the past,
where you've been working on a problem,
mostly on the CPU and maybe multi-threaded on the GPU,
and now you want to move it to the GPU
and take performance advantage of that.
This is okay, this is acceptable,
if, under these conditions,
and all of these must be satisfied.
There's no double dipping.
You're not getting grades in two different courses
for the same work, okay?
The goals are clearly laid out.
What is in the research that you're doing
and what is required for the class are clearly laid out.
And if necessary, I'll request faculty or researcher
also approve the work, okay?
And other conditions based on your research and stuff
may be taken up case by case.
Any questions on this?
Those of you who may be involved in research
and maybe thinking about this?
No?
Okay.
Missing milestones is not okay.
I'll be very, very clear about that.
The only exception under which I will allow you
to miss a milestone and forgive you for it
is if you are going on site for an interview and stuff,
which is a lot less common these days.
It was a lot more common before the pandemic
that people would fly to Google or Nvidia
or anywhere and do in-person interviews.
Doesn't really happen much these days.
So the only circumstance under which you miss a milestone
is, again, the goal of this class
to prepare you for the industry.
If you're doing an interview that helps you get a job,
okay, fine, acceptable.
But otherwise, not okay to miss.
Now, if you have to miss,
make sure that the rest of your team is presenting.
And before you leave to go wherever you have to
or miss the milestone,
schedule a time with the TAs,
AT or multiple TAs prior to the milestone,
not after the milestone,
prior to the milestone and discuss the progress you've made.
Okay?
So again, the importance is on communication.
Don't hide.
If there is a problem,
if you're not able to make a milestone,
whether you have a job interview or you fall sick,
communicate it before.
If you communicate it after, there's not much I can do.
Okay?
This is not really relevant anymore.
It was more when we were remote and stuff
that people were studying from India and Australia
and China and Japan and New Zealand and stuff.
And the times were really, really odd, right?
So that's not a problem,
but just in case I'm leaving this in here.
For shadow teams,
if there are an odd number of teams that come up,
again, because I don't pick the teams
that are 30 students in the class.
If everybody tries to pick a team of three,
that's 10 teams.
But if some of you do two or one,
you're going to have more teams.
And sometimes you may end up with odd teams.
In that case,
we'll just make one or two groups of three,
three teams are shadow teams.
And this has worked generally well in the past.
Okay?
That's it for final projects overview.
Now, the floor is open for you to ask questions
about what's important to you
and what you think should matter for final projects.
Again, this is half your grade.
So ask all the questions you want right now.
Of course, our discussion is open,
but here I'll be able to answer in much more detail.
Yeah?
So if you're going to do an XR related project,
do you have any resources at that time?
Sorry, what related?
XR related project.
XR?
Yes.
And what kind of resources do you want from me?
I was like, you know,
now we are in the past,
we are in the industry.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
I mean, Steve Lane is probably the number one resource.
Steve Lane is amazing.
But if you want to get connected to, for example,
the people at Oculus,
yeah, I'll get you connected.
What else?
You guys have been surprisingly quiet today.
Deep?
What if I'm just really bad at coming up with ideas?
You can join other people's ideas.
That's the goal, right?
It's not that every person comes up with an idea,
you put it in a bowl and pick one out of that.
Please don't do that.
Pick something that you think is worth working on.
Again, you're not going to be able to do it
if you don't have a team.
You're not going to be able to do it
It's worth working on.
Again, you're going to be spending significant time
on this and frustration on it.
So pick a topic that you'll actually want to come
on the other side of and be proud of what you've done.
What are the questions?
Wayne, did I miss anything?
Wayne, Shubham, did I miss anything?
Yeah, don't pick up projects that are too hard.
Don't pick up projects that are too easy.
Find a good, reasonable balance.
And if the project's too hard, I'll tell you it's too hard.
Although I will say, I will encourage you to take it on,
but I will say, hey, I think this is too hard.
And I'll be honest about it.
Again, I will reiterate, it gives me no pride
or no ego to either give the entire class an A-plus
or the entire class an F.
These grades, I'm here to teach you.
I'm here to encourage all of you to do amazing work.
If all of you deserve an A-plus,
I will give all of you an A-plus.
So the goal for me is to facilitate
the projects you want to do.
Let's say, I think you sort of addressed this
while you were sliding to be more clear.
What are the stipulations of re-skilling a project
if you take it on, you make good progress,
and then something happens and now it's impossible?
Shubham, do you want to share your experience from last year?
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Maybe, again, you guys have done it, so you share.
Yeah, so when I was in, I think it was impossible for us.
If you have to redo the project, that's kind of what we did.
Like, we didn't change our project,
but we had to make everything from ground up again.
That's because the project was actually fairly hard,
and that's what Shehzad told us.
I think it was our first pitch also
that this project is going to be really hard to do,
but if you guys want to do it, then do it.
So, yeah, like, but I would say,
even if you have faced a situation like that,
let everybody know, but don't change it.
I think just, like, when you are deciding on,
keep everything in mind and then start from there.
Yeah, you'll be able to do it at the end.
So, I think Shubham laid it out well.
There can be different reasons
your project falls off the rails, right?
And the goal is to, how do we pick back up?
The project may be behind because you underestimated
the task of milestone one, for example,
but you reasonably understand what's required
and you think you'll catch up.
Sure, no problem.
That just means you move a few features around
and or you may want to drop a few features.
Again, communicating early and often
is the key thing that I have to share.
So, that's one.
The second thing might be, you may realize,
oh my God, what kind of project have you picked up?
Again, it's not unheard of, it's happened.
That's why I'm giving you this information.
First, try to, again, try to reach out to the authors.
As soon as you pick the project, reach out to the authors.
That's the first thing you do.
Hey, I'm thinking about doing this.
Do you have any recommendations for me?
And people will love to give you those, okay?
And then if you still find yourself in a tough spot
where you don't know the way forward,
again, reach out to them and be like,
hey guys, you're stuck here.
I think it was in pretty much the first class
where I was like, the students were doing a shallow water,
they were stuck, they reached out to the authors
and the author was like, hey, just change this.
And it worked.
And usually that fixes it.
If everything given, you still need to pivot
and you need to change your project.
Again, communicate that off as early as possible
with good reason, with good reason
and a good plan with that.
If you come to me with, hey Shahzan,
we are really struggling with this.
My first question is, okay,
have you reached out to the authors?
Have you tried a bunch of things, right?
Make sure you've done all of that before you come to me.
And then even when you come to me, be like,
hey, this is the problem we are having.
Here's why we think it's insurmountable
and we won't have a good final presentation.
Here's the pivot we wanna make,
here's the projects we wanna change or stuff like that.
Whatever it may be, okay?
You had a question, sorry.
So suppose we're trying to create a research
and the original product got screwed up
and if I were to use the research in metals
and does that count as a viable option?
Yeah, generally I would say generally yes,
but it also depends.
So for example, if you're taking a paper from 2013
and trying to do it in metal, I'd say probably not.
Unless you're making significant changes.
If you're taking a paper from 2022 GTC,
NVIDIA's GPU technology conference
and you wanna do that in metal, sure, absolutely.
Yeah.
Is there any potential budget allocation
to buy data sets if needed?
I don't know how I fund that.
I don't even know what the university process or anything,
but if it comes up, at least let me know
if there's something that I can help with.
Even if I don't know, I'll probably ask DeepLane
to see if there's something like that.
What else?
Yeah.
Off the top of your head,
is anything relating to state of the fusion
or generation viable in the scope of your project?
Yeah, why not?
Again, ask Liam what better ideas might be.
You have his email, feel free to email him
and get suggestions from what will be good ideas.
Again, the goal is not that,
A, I don't know much about machine learning,
but I can at least give advice,
but my advice could be dangerous.
Liam's advice is gonna be very industry-derived.
Just like I can tell you what Cesium does
and anything related to Cesium,
Liam can tell you the world's end
about natural language processing
or machine learning in general.
So that's my recommendation there.
You may reach out to other professors as well
to understand what might be required,
but it's up to you ultimately.
What are the questions?
Anybody already have the project ideas?
It's okay to say yes.
It'll only help you find good teammates.
No?
Okay.
I don't know if anyone wants to do this with me.
No, no, no.
If you wanna share them.
Okay.
Why not?
Well,
two ideas, right?
One is
pose estimation
to drive a 2D body sprite.
So currently there's motion capture
and there's camera-based motion capture.
A motion capture retargets poses
into rigs of 3D
models.
I was thinking that if we take,
combine like the existing
pose estimation from camera,
like monocular camera view
onto
a rig
with like 2D body
that can be novel.
That's one of the other things.
Although I think that's been done quite a few times.
I think that's being done quite a few times.
You may want to look into that.
Yeah, again, it depends on the combination,
but that idea itself,
I think there's a lot of research being done on it.
Yeah.
I know that pose estimation is big.
It's the mesh deformation of like a 2D.
Oh yeah.
If you want to do mesh deformation as well.
Okay.
If you're just doing the skeleton,
then that's kind of.
No, no, no.
Because like the skeleton is like the output, right?
It's the idea of like retargeting that skeleton
onto a,
because like with 3D mesh, it's a mesh.
Yeah.
And that's driven by like a rig.
But with 2D, the rules are different.
So like, I feel like that could be parallelized
in terms of how those calculations are done.
And then it will like real time
and camera to output sort of thing.
The other thing, which is the machine learning thing
is that
there is a fundamental difference between face,
like in non-photorealistic rendering of faces,
lots of models are scripted to break facial planes
based on camera perspective,
because the 2D aesthetic is not geometrically,
like geospatially like consistent based on camera angles.
And I was thinking potentially doing
the machine learning thing to see if you can just,
given like two branches off of that,
this is just me talking.
One is give a head-on perspective
and you try and get like a three-fourths perspective,
or it's you are given a three-fourths perspective
of like a 3D model,
that you like, you perturb it
to make it look more like a 3D style.
And like, that's, I know like there are a bunch of papers.
Yeah, what you're saying,
and I'm extrapolating here,
is take the entire history of Japanese anime
and create a 3D world out of it.
Yeah, because if that happens,
if that happens, right,
CG in anime is solved.
Yeah.
But I mean, piecemeal.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Anybody have any other ideas?
Okay.
David?
I was thinking of doing like a radar tracer.
So it would be similar to like a path tracer,
but instead you're like simulating radar waves
instead of light.
So if you do that,
you would take like an airframe of like a fighter jet
or like a boat,
and you could check the radar signature.
And basically it's how like stealth hardware is built,
like trying to minimize the radar signature of the kid.
And also like thought about different ways
that you could even manipulate the airframe
or the ship hull to make it,
you would have a smaller radar signature.
Yeah, I think that could be very interesting.
And other, Eric Cain's in his presentation
also brought up something like that.
If RF and 5G propagation is really big,
so all of those ideas could be very, very good
where you're taking ray tracing
and applying it to non-visual stuff as well.
Okay, last call for any other ideas.
Uta.
I think the reason for Facebook is that it's a big company.
I thought that Facebook was a big one,
so I was thinking of using it to get able to,
I've never seen a middle in AI.
If I can play some digital,
that's something I'm doing with Facebook.
Of course, there's some limitations that it should do.
Yeah, you may want to think about
what are the applications of that,
and maybe you would talk to Steve Blain
about what he thinks about that idea.
I know he takes a lot of interest in AR, so talk about it.
Yeah, I was reading about it,
and I think it will have the same implications.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think it's something that can behave like-
Yeah, okay.
But I'm not sure how.
No, it's-
I think it's like an idea of, again,
to learn AR, but it's also like generating something
that's used to be in AR,
so as you're, and all of this with a normal phone,
some individual device, so if you can,
as you move along, let's say,
there are things or problems going,
but you really want to play,
so it's basically detecting various areas of time
and generating something.
Yeah, that could be very cool too.
Okay.
Last call, anything else?
All right, I'm super excited hearing just those ideas
about what you guys will come up with.
So as a reminder, go sign up for the sheet.
Again, first come, first serve,
so if you book a slot, it's yours.
I do reserve the right to change the times,
but generally, I won't change your team itself.
But yeah, do that as soon as possible
so that I know at least how many teams there are
and I can organize the pitches on November 7th and all that.
I will follow up with more details around the plan
on November 7th about when you'll come
into the CSUMB office and stuff like that.
I'll post that all to a discussion.
But otherwise, I'll hang out here.
If you want to come ask any questions,
ideally, you would have asked it in the class
and I would have clarified it,
but if there's something very, very personal to you
that you want to ask, sure, come up.
But otherwise, if you're coming up here
and asking a question that applies
to pretty much the entire class,
I'll be like, go ask that on that discussion now
and I'll answer it, okay?
That's all I have, thank you.