All right, so we are getting into the second half
of the semester, right?
And we have some really good stuff lined up.
So first of all, today's lecture will be a couple
of more graphics pipeline stuff following
from last time around.
We'd also have the Project 4 recitation,
which you may or may not choose to build
upon your Project 3.
If you don't choose to build upon it,
we have a base code that you can get started with.
On October 12th, we'll do likely a last CUDA-specific
lecture, which will be advanced topics
where I'll be talking about streams and other things.
October 17th and 19th will be really good,
especially for those of you who are interested
in machine learning.
Liam Duggan, who was a student in 2018,
did the first DXR project, DirectX Ray Tracing Project
as final projects.
He was part of that team.
Went to NVIDIA, came back to Penn to do machine learning PhD
in natural language processing, interned at Roblox
over the summer with Morgan McGuire.
And he did two lectures in the class last year
on machine learning and CUDA, and he's coming back
to do those two lectures again.
So both of those will happen next week.
Simultaneously, we'll have an introduction to WebGL,
which will set up one part of project five,
and then we'll do an intro to Vulkan
that will be pre-recorded and shared with you
from last year, so we'll re-share that.
But both of those will be introductions for APIs
that you may use for project five.
On Wednesday, we'll actually have the recitation
for project five, which will be an option
between a WebGL project or a Vulkan project.
It's up to you to choose which one.
They're both graded equally, so there's no difference
in picking one or the other.
It's really up to you to choose what you want.
The only thing that we say to think about
is whether you want to do a Web-based final project
or a Vulkan-based final project,
or CUDA you already know, so CUDA will obviously be there,
but it really depends on which path you may want to go on.
So that's setting up next week.
And then project four will be due at the end of that.
October 24th is an amazing guest lecture by Brandon Jones.
Brandon Jones has been involved in web graphics standards
since before I got into graphics.
He's part of the Chrome GPU team.
He's worked extensively on the WebGL standard
and its implementation, and for the past few years
has been working on the WebGPU standard
and its implementations.
And he'll be coming in person.
He'll be spending the day with us.
And then in the evening, he'll be giving the guest lecture.
And I'll be opening that invite up to the broader
CGI Penn community as well,
so that if anybody outside wants to join,
and please feel free to advertise it to your friends as well
who may be interested in this.
WebGL, if a simple comparison between WebGL and WebGPU
is kind of like OpenGL and Vulkan,
WebGPU gives you a lot more power,
and it's an up-and-coming standard.
We had three final projects on WebGPU last year,
which was great.
Hope to have similar, if not more, this year.
So Brandon Jones is going to do
an amazing guest lecture on that.
October 26th, we'll do the final projects overview.
So that class will just be talking about final projects,
answering your questions, giving you some ideas and stuff.
So we'll do that on October 26th.
October 31st is TBD.
I'm not completely sure what I'm going to do then,
but on November 2nd, we'll have Jim Jeffers,
who is a principal engineer
and director of advanced rendering at Intel.
He's worked extensively with Intel's ArcGPUs and OneAPI.
So kind of like how NVIDIA has CUDA,
AMD has their open pipelines,
and then Intel has the OneAPI.
So he's going to be coming to, again, in-person
and talking about how they're working on rendering here.
November 7th will be the final project pitches.
I'll talk more about what exactly those are
in my final projects overview.
November 9th is Gabe Dagani.
So this was, after a few years,
you're having a proper mobile GPU lecture
going to be happening in this class.
Very excited about that.
He's going to be great.
He's also interviewing.
I did post a job post on a discussion for it.
If you're interested, you know,
please feel free to reach out.
October 14th, this was just confirmed Thursday or Friday.
Rev Lebredian.
Those of you who may not know the name,
Rev is the vice president of NVIDIA Omniverse.
To give you a sense of how big that is,
he manages a team of, or a group of,
over 200 plus people at NVIDIA.
And if you paid, if you watched the SIGGRAPH keynote,
the NVIDIA keynote at SIGGRAPH,
Rev was there beside Jensen talking about NVIDIA's vision
for Omniverse, Metaverse, and things like that.
He's coming in person to talk to you.
Like Rev could be a keynote speaker
at any graphics conference you want,
literally any graphics conference you want.
And he's coming here.
He'd be standing here in this classroom
and giving a guest lecture.
So I'm super excited for that.
It's going to be a great guest lecture on USD,
NVIDIA, Omniverse, those kinds of things.
If you are interested in talking to him
about career opportunities and stuff,
he's very well known in the industry.
His background comes from rendering.
He was, he wrote a rendering pipeline.
He started his own company, sold that pipeline,
joined NVIDIA, did a bunch of stuff at NVIDIA,
and now is leading the Omniverse team.
So that is likely our final guest lecture.
The only one that I'm figuring out is one from Epic Games.
I'm trying to organize who it might be.
The issue is I'm trying to get the Nanite team,
but the Nanite team is busy.
So they always have like a fall release,
so they get busy around that.
So it doesn't always work out for me
to get somebody from Nanite,
but fingers crossed we'll get somebody good.
So yeah, that's about it.
I'm super excited.
All of these four guest lectures that we have coming up
are like A plus in their fields.
They're literally leading the charge
in innovating standards and stuff.
So yeah, I'm super excited about those.
Any questions on the schedule?
Okay.
And a reminder, because I know some of you have asked me,
there are no extra days for final projects.
So don't save up on them.
If you haven't used them for project three,
use them for project four and project five.
Do the extra credits and stuff.
There's no point saving it.
Don't come to me and be like,
hey, I have two extra days left.
Can I get an A minus from a B plus or whatever?
No, I don't reward extra days being left over.
Use them and work towards your page for that.
Okay.
And like,
Yes.
So that's these milestone things here.
We'll have three milestones.
I'll explain all of that in the final project overview.
There's no late days on any final project things.
Any other questions?
All right.
So with that, let's get into our lecture today.
So last time around,
we spoke about the graphics pipeline, right?
About how we go from taking points,
making them into triangles,
projecting them and then eventually rendering them, right?
With vertex shaders, fragment shaders and stuff like that.
Today, what we're going to talk about is
how do you take that pipeline and change it up
so that you can add more performance to it?
Okay.
So the first of those is called a deferred shading pipeline.
And we look at that today.
So the basics are that you want to design a rendering engine
that renders a lot of different materials,
a lot of lights and a lot of different types of lights.
And this is true about any game you see
or pretty much any 3D application you see,
where you have different materials, different objects,
lots of lights going on.
Even if you think of like GPA, for example, right?
You have a city environment, you have street lights,
you have people wearing different clothes,
you have hair, you have rigid body physics,
you have gravity that goes crazy.
So all of these things need to be taken into account
and be done cleanly and efficiently
in a way that the game can be maintained.
You can provide upgrades and stuff like that.
So the most common way of doing this
was with multi-pass shading.
Multi-pass shading is in a way very simple
where you take that graphics pipeline you have
and you do it multiple times per frame.
So essentially what you do is for each light that you have,
then you choose every visible object you have,
you render that object, accumulate it in the frame buffer
and then keep doing that, okay?
Now it's pretty obvious what's wrong with this, right?
Or what's good about it or not.
What's something good about this?
Yeah, sorry?
Yeah, you won't miss an object, that's for sure.
What else?
Yeah.
What else is good about this?
You're covering the major sources of light, okay.
What's bad about this?
Sorry, I'm just curious.
It's like every colorless is affected to this.
Yeah.
So that's going probably two levels deeper.
But if you come back, your question is,
do materials matter, right?
If you come two levels higher,
do materials and light matter?
Yes, absolutely.
If you have three different types of light,
one point light, one direction light, one ambient light,
and you are trying to see how one material gets lit up
or a hundred materials lit up,
every one of them is gonna act differently
with different types of light.
So in this case, one of the pros is that
you can have one shader that is handling all material,
that is handling one material and light combination, okay?
So for every type of light,
you will have one shader for every material.
So it's like N times N.
So imagine as a game engine writer,
you have to manage all of that.
You'll go crazy.
I mean, even in this room, see how many lights we have.
Right, so that becomes very, very complicated.
What else is the problem with this?
I think you had your hand raised.
Yeah, absolutely.
You're wasting time on occluded objects.
If something's super in the background
and you're pretty sure not to be able to see it,
you're gonna be wasting time
rendering this in this double form.
What else?
So here are some more, okay?
We covered one shader per material and light type.
I discovered occluded fragments are shaded.
This one is important as well.
Not all lights affect all the objects.
A light in that corner of that room
is not really going to affect me
when I have a light right above me, right?
So the significance of any light in the room
doesn't count the same for all the objects.
And then you have to do the rasterization.
You have to do the entire pipeline for each object
for every light.
And that means more pipeline stages
doing the same thing over and over again.
So those are some issues.
Now, if you change that to a single pass,
then you get something like this.
For each visible object,
you try to find all the lights that actually affect.
Okay, so I'm standing in this corner.
I'll probably get affected by that light
and maybe that light.
Not getting affected by that light in the last row.
So that reduces how many passes you have to do,
but then it has its own cons as well.
Some of those cons,
and now you need one shader per light combination
like before.
It's hard to create all of those shaders
because now you have to write complex code
for which light is affecting what type of light
and all that.
It may require runtime compilation
because let's say objects are moving through the scene,
they're gonna be interacting with different things.
Sometimes you have to create long over shaders
for managing a lot of different materials.
So not the best thing.
And you still get the same issues as before
where you are still rendering occluded objects
and still have light issues, okay?
And so because there are so many
of these different combinations,
you can have different lights, different materials.
Some of these are being compiled at runtime.
And this is something that happens in every game engine.
Not all game engines come with pre-compiled shaders.
Some of those are actually happening at runtime,
but because they happen fast enough,
they get hidden.
So still not great.
We still have quite a few issues here.
So what we, and I say we collectively
in the broader community,
people a lot smarter than myself,
especially in the games industry,
have come up with what is known
as a deferred rendering pipeline, okay?
In this pipeline, there are two stages essentially.
In the first stage,
you're computing all the visible objects.
And these visible objects then get written
to what is known as a G-buffer
or more commonly as a geometry buffer.
The geometry buffer essentially stores
the visible part of the scene.
And we'll see how that works.
And then what you do is you break that up.
And then in stage two, for each light,
you only work on the G-buffer.
So only on the visible part of the scene.
That way you don't render anything
that's occluded, for example.
So let's take a look at how this works.
Starting with the pros and cons.
So the first thing is you're decoupling lights
from the scene complexity.
So no matter how many triangles you have in your scene,
no matter how many materials you have in your scene,
the lighting is decoupled from that.
You are rendering the visible part first
and then the lighting will only work on the visible part.
You reduce the number of shaders.
So now you have one per material and one per light type.
And because we store the G-buffer,
you're transforming and rasterizing only once.
The G-buffer comes after rasterization.
And finally, as I said before,
you're not rendering occluded objects.
So all the lights are working only on visible parts.
Possible downsides.
It could lead into memory bandwidth issues.
And we'll talk about this in a little bit.
Essentially because you're reading the G-buffer
again and again.
You're calculating full lighting equations still per light.
So that's gonna be an additional cost.
And then some of the additional good looking features
like MSAA translucency blending become a lot difficult.
Okay, so let's take a look.
So this is the G-buffer layout in LUDEworks 1.1.
Some of these images should be now pretty familiar to you
as debug images from your path tracer, for example.
So some components, not necessarily all the components
of a G-buffer are the ambidextrous RGB color,
the depth buffer, which comes second,
the normal buffer, and then the specular filter.
These four combined can give you a diffuse lighting
situation and a specular lighting situation,
which if combined, give you the final image, okay?
So what we're essentially doing is from the Python
that we saw last time, okay?
We're not rendering the frame buffer to the screen,
but really rendering frame buffer to textures.
One of those textures is an RGB texture,
but we don't do any lighting.
We just take the RGB and store it.
So you get the RGB colors
for the visible parts of the scene only.
There may be a lot of stuff in the background.
Don't really care about this after this point.
Similarly, we get the depth buffer, store it in a texture,
take all the normal, store it in a texture,
and then specular factor and store it in texture.
Now, if you think about diffuse lighting,
what was the diffuse lighting equation roughly?
It was something like direction of light,
normal, do a dot product, right?
So if you take the albedo, you take the normal,
and you know where the lights are, you get diffuse lighting.
You can take albedo, normal, specular factor,
you get specular reflection, right?
So that's the kind of process where you're not necessarily
doing it in a single pass,
but you're storing this information
so that along with the lighting,
you can generate the lighting components of the scenes.
Let's dive in a little bit more.
So this is how you would essentially store your buffers.
And I want you to pay attention to this part
because this is something you're gonna do in project four,
not necessarily in real-time rendering,
but in path tracer denoising.
So these images essentially get stored like this.
The RGB color gets stored as an RGBA value.
That is a 24-bit component.
Again, you don't need 32 bits.
You don't need that much precision.
So 24 bits is good enough.
And we'll see how we may or may not use the eight bits
out of this later on.
And then you may store the normal,
which can be either 32 or 64 bit,
depending on the precision you want.
Look at this.
We also store a specular factor here.
We pack it up essentially.
Instead of just having three values that add up to 24 bits,
we also throw in a specular factor
that can pack it up nicely into 32 bits.
Remember how we said caching is important
and reading in 32 bits will be important
and 128 bits will be important?
This is why you have packing here
because even though you can store three numbers, no problem.
Storing it as four numbers is just better
because you'll use the specular factor anyway,
multiple times, and it kind of comes for free.
Okay.
So let's take an example from Killzone 2.
So this is the target image you want, right?
What are some of the lighting effects
or material effects that we see in this?
You guys should be pros at this by now.
Okay.
So I'm sure there's something called mapping and texture.
Textures serve as the albedo
on which the loose lighting is applied.
Let's see, a lot of specular stuff.
There's shadow as well.
Yeah, shadow is good.
So, and there's a motion blur.
There's definitely motion blur here on this guy.
Maybe a little bit on the gun too.
What else?
Amplitude, yes.
If you look at like that, that is amplitude.
What else?
Sorry?
Depth of view, yeah.
Depth of view, yeah, depth of view.
Depth of view.
Yeah, so probably this part is all normal map.
What else?
I mean, some of the basics,
we have to count some of the basic stuff, right?
Walls are probably all diffused,
even if we don't count it.
What is this here?
On the bullets.
Specular.
That's all the buttons here.
I don't think we have any soft surface scattering,
not required for real-time rendering.
Some reflections going on here.
Yeah, shoulder pad is the perfect specular, right?
I don't see too much transparency or translucency here.
But yeah, okay, let's figure it out.
So we figured out all the effects we need, right?
We need our motion blur, we need depth of field,
we need the specular diffused,
we need some normal mapping and bump mapping,
some, you know, amplitude and textures in the background.
So let's take a look at how the scene is now built up
using deferred shading pipeline.
All right.
The first thing we do in the scene,
or pretty much any pipeline,
is generate the depth map, okay?
So this is the depth map for the scene.
You can kind of make out that that is the back wall,
that is something in front of it, and so on, right?
And then this is the closest.
Remember, depth map has zeros the closest to the camera,
and one is the furthest away from the camera.
That's why whites are further away and blacks are closer.
Okay?
The next thing we do is do view space normals, okay?
Why do we do view space normals?
These are not world space normals.
Why are we doing view space normals?
Yeah, reflections and specular will use view space normals.
They don't need to use world space normals,
because then if we have view space normals,
we can do it in the fragment shader, or in screen space.
We don't have to do it in world space,
saving ourselves some transformations.
Okay.
Then we have specular.
Now you see how much specular there is in the scene.
We counted the bullets, so the bullets are here.
We definitely counted that,
but look at how much more specular there is
that we didn't necessarily see.
We said shoulder pads were partially specular.
His glasses are specular.
Look at the eyes.
Eyes definitely seem to be specular in real-time rendering.
So yeah, a lot more specular than we realized.
Then we have a specular roughness factor, or a power,
where the whites essentially are non-specular,
and then this applies a power to how to increase that,
essentially, that specular component.
Then we have a motion vector.
So again, this is in screen space.
It's not in world space.
So we said that the gun has some motion blur,
and this guy has some motion blur, right?
So we're generating an image for that.
This is like optical flow.
What do you mean by optical flow?
Optical flow is usually you capture the real world,
and then you try to visualize it, right?
It's not like in computer vision,
like optical flow is like within two images, right?
You identify two-
Points.
T-shirts, and then like the directional vector of that.
This, or is this something that looks the other way?
This is what you're doing in your projects.
This is literally knowing the velocity of this guy
that we are generating,
how much this person is gonna move between two frames.
So that's how you get the motion.
Okay.
So we generate the 2D motion vector, okay?
So that's gonna give us the motion blur part of it.
Then one of the most basic things,
we generate the albedo.
So now you see without any lighting effects,
what that color looks like.
The window almost looked like a grill, right?
It didn't look like there were windows in there.
If I go to the other side and see.
All right.
So look at this.
There's no reflection here whatsoever, right?
It just looks like bars.
But if we look at the specular map,
the specular map,
look at how the windows are highlighted
as being specular, right?
And then if we go to the albedo without lighting,
now we see the windows come out.
So this is the albedo, right?
So this is the albedo.
Now we see the windows come out.
The glass of the windows come out.
So that's why albedo becomes important
because it gives you a sense of what the scene is like
without any lighting.
Also look at the bullets.
No specular there, it's just yellow.
It's almost flat shaded, right?
And the scene also looks a lot more lit up.
The background is a lot more visible.
There seems to be a lot more light in the scene
because technically we are not using light.
It's all albedo.
All right.
But we get the deferred composition
where we are bringing in some of those lighting things.
You take the albedo, you take the normal maps,
the specular maps,
and now you're building the scene from that.
No motion blur in this.
We haven't put that in yet.
Now, if we add the motion blur, the depth of field,
again, this is all post-processing.
Post-processing is in screen space.
So everything that we spoke about was screen space
now gets added on.
So we have depth of field, bloom, motion blur,
colorization, all into this.
So that's why when I say doing something in screen space,
that's what allows you to do it in post-processing
as a fragment shader.
You don't have to run a full pass for it.
You can just do it in a fragment shader.
So any questions on how the scene got built
using the different passes?
So what's happening in each of these frames,
so I'll come back to albedo,
is you're not in the rasterization pipeline.
The pipeline itself isn't necessarily changing.
The single pass pipeline that we have isn't changing.
What we are changing is that in each pass,
we output one of these debug images
or intermediate images as a texture.
And then we run the lighting pass,
which takes all the lights into account
and these textures, doesn't take geometry into account.
Okay, the geometry is gone at that point.
It only takes the depth buffer, the albedo texture,
the normals, the screen space texture,
all of those into account and build the lighting from that.
So that's how you separate the lighting from the geometry.
So now the lighting only works
on what's visible in your scene.
So any questions on this?
Any questions on how we got here?
Because this is kind of what you're gonna do
in the denoiser as well.
You're gonna take your G buffer
and then run that through a bunch of things.
Yeah, Ed?
So with the, we can think of the depth map
as sort of like a geometric hole, I guess, right?
In terms of just how far, how close everything is to it.
So that instead of doing like a break intersect, right?
We just sample screen space for the distance.
Yeah, exactly.
So if you had to answer the question for each pixel,
what is the depth of that pixel in the 3D world?
Your depth map answers that question.
So it's the closest point to what's visible to you.
So from my point of view,
if I wanted something over there that's closer,
this is gonna be the back wall.
If I'm looking down here, it's gonna be the stable, right?
So you're only looking for the closest point
in the depth buffer.
You would get this depth buffer
by basically getting all the per pixel T values
of the frame pass from the camera?
No, not at all.
You would rasterize the scene
and store it in the depth buffer.
You're not doing ray casting at all.
You're doing only rasterization.
This is real-time rendering.
So if you think about our last lecture,
when we do the rasterization pipeline,
one of the goals of rasterization
is to figure out what's visible.
What's the first thing that is visible?
Remember that two triangles that we had
when we tried to figure it out
through flood fill or scanline algorithms
about how we figured out which triangle
is ahead of which triangle?
That is kind of what the rasterization pipeline is doing.
And one of the outputs of rasterization pipeline
is the depth buffer.
Any other questions on this?
Okay, so let's take a look at how...
Now, we have all of these images, right?
We've got so many textures.
We have to store them somewhere
because you're not gonna store a texture
and run the lighting pass.
You have to run all of these textures.
You have to have all of those textures saved
before you can run the lighting pass.
So to save that,
we store it in what we call the geometry buffer.
And this is what the geometry buffer
for Killzone 2 looks like, okay?
So let's go through it.
So first, you had...
First see that these are all 32 bits, okay?
That's the first thing I want you to notice.
So the first thing we have in our first buffer
is the 24-bit per pixel floating point depth.
We don't need 32 bits, 24-bit is good enough.
So we'll store 24 bits.
Now, we have eight bits left.
So we'll store a boolean for the stencil.
You know, we can have different textures, right?
And not every texture has to cover everything.
So we store the stencil as an alpha or a boolean.
We'll store a lighting accumulation RGB
along with its intensity.
We only store two normals at 16 bits each.
Why?
Why are we storing normal XYZ?
Oh, this is for normal.
Why don't we store normal Z?
Normal Z can be computed by normal X and normal Y
using a cross pattern.
So we need to store a normal Z.
And a cross pattern.
So we don't need to store that.
Then we have a few other vectors.
So we have motion vector X and Y.
So in both directions,
because it's screen-based, you only need X and Y.
We have specular power and specular intensity,
two things that we saw above before.
The last one is the diffuse albedos RGB.
And then you have some occlusion
from the sun lighting or the ambient lighting.
So that allows you to build what is known as the G-buffer.
And you take all of these vectors
and then run the lighting computation
for how you're going to build a scene.
And I haven't told you how to do the lighting.
I've only showed you how to do the G-buffer so far.
Lighting will come next.
I want to make sure that all of you understand
how the G-buffer is coming about
and what it's going to be useful.
Any questions on this?
Okay.
So let's take a look at how we take the G-buffer
and then compute the lighting from it.
The one thing I want to highlight is the sun occlusion
is used for shadows here.
That's one thing I forgot to mention.
Okay.
So final call for questions on this.
All right.
So let's see how the G-buffer then gets used in light.
So one of the things we want to do
is understand the geometry for each light.
Okay.
We said before that not every light
affects every object in the scene, even if it's visible.
Not every light is going to affect every object.
So we construct a volume around the light
depending on its power and intensity
about which objects it's going to affect.
And that can be done using a scissor or stencil test.
And if it's a full screen, then you apply the whole thing.
If you want to do it in 3D, you do it as a sphere or a cone
depending on what kind of a light you have.
Okay.
So this example here to our bottom right,
it shows the light, which is in purple
and its field of influence, essentially.
Its sphere of influence.
Let's take this point here.
If our object is in this black space,
this point isn't going to affect that
because it's not powerful enough.
So that's why we say we only need to do every light,
process every light within its sphere of influence only.
So that's the first thing I'm going to do.
This essentially reduces your workload
and improves performance.
From there, you can do additive blending.
So for example, we have these here, right?
And these are just the points that we have.
If you do some overlap on this using additive blending,
you'll see that the bright red parts
are where more lights affect an object
and the darker parts are where no lights affect an object.
So using that, we can accelerate the pipeline as well.
Because now what you can do is,
if you know that this sphere, for example,
only affects this light,
you don't have to render the full scene, right?
You don't have to render like 1920 by 1080,
for example, if that's your scene size.
You only have to pick what's the bounding area for this
in pixel space, in window space,
and you only work on that.
So now you can do that.
You only work on that.
So now you can create parallelism there as well,
where you can run multiple light passes at the same time
in the GPU.
Any questions on this?
So let's take a look at this demo here,
which shows off how that works.
So I'm gonna play this video.
So now you can see how there are lights going around
and this purple light doesn't affect everything.
It just affects, oh, look at the green light there.
It only affects the part that's closed,
but not necessarily this wall on the side.
That's being affected by a different light.
So that's where you can pick and choose
which area of the scene you want to render.
And that's where you can have so many more lights.
If you want to have these many lights
with a simple forward pass rendering,
it would just run too slowly
because you're trying to compute too much at the same time.
So there's a WebGL drop buffers API in WebGL,
and that can also have with the GBuffer.
So when using WebGL drop buffers performance
with this kind of a scene with 25 Stanford dragons,
with the extension, with the drop buffers extension,
you get significantly better performance.
Remember, this is FPS here.
Then you do without that extension.
Okay, there are gonna be graphics extension.
You're gonna come across that will significantly
improve the performance you get or may decrease it.
Similarly, with 25 Stanford dragons,
you're gonna see similar issues as well.
Essentially what it's doing is the drop buffers pass
is helping your fragment shader write multiple textures.
For example, after you do your rasterization,
think about all the textures you can write.
In just one pass, you do the rasterization.
What information do you have at that point?
You have the depth, you have the albedo.
Let's say you have the specular lighting, right?
You can compute all of those and store it in a texture.
So instead of having three different rasterization passes
for each of those,
you can just do all of those in one pass and store it.
So you significantly reduce how many single passes you do
for each one of those intermediate buffers.
So that's what this is trying to explain
that you have to, when using these graphics APIs,
you should always look for extensions and stuff
that can help improve your performance.
So in default shading,
there's a few good parts and a few bad parts.
The good parts are that light management becomes trivial
because light is only working on screen space
in the G-buffer.
You can manage as many lights as you want
without too much complexity.
The shader management is simple,
again, because you're working only on the G-buffer
from a lighting perspective.
There's no overdraw.
There's single pass geometry.
You're not rendering on occluded aspects.
And you can reuse the shadow map for different things.
Now the bad part,
because everything happens through this G-buffer
in screen space, there's no transparency, right?
Those windows weren't transparent when we saw them.
Because if you wanted to do transparency,
now you have to do multi-pass on the objects
and figure out different depths.
Like the depth buffer, for example,
can have only one value.
You can't have two values.
You can't say, I have a window
and I have something behind it.
There's no transparency in the first shading
for that reason.
You have very large frame buffer
because you need to store all of that G-buffer data.
If you need MSA, you need to like four times
or eight times your frame buffer as well.
You can have multiple shading.
If you want to do multiple shading models
with different types of shading,
let's say toon shading and physically-based shading,
that becomes very, very difficult
because you don't have that pipeline anymore.
And you use a lot of bandwidth
because you're reading and writing
through those textures quite a bit.
So you have to make sure that all of your GPU bandwidth
is being used effectively
and you're not hurting yourself because of that.
Any questions on the pros and cons of this?
Okay.
So let's take a look at how do we improve this further?
So we have different shading.
It's good, but not perfect.
How do we improve it further?
The first thing you do is,
the first thing you do is you kind of borrow
from matrix multiply.
Remember how in matrix multiply we created tiles
to do one block each and then do other blocks, right?
We're going to divide our screen into two big blocks.
For example, of 16 by 16 pixels.
Okay.
In those, we'll only pick the lights that affect that tile.
So now not all lights are affecting every tile.
You can optimize it.
To do that, you can do it in the compute chain
or you can do it on the CPU,
but compute shader is going to be faster
to compute which lights affect which tiles.
And then you can do a light accumulation pass
to read on the GBuffer only once
and then all use the light tile info
to find which light is affecting which pixel.
So let's dive into this a little.
So we have the scene here, right?
This would be how the tiles look.
So I'll switch back and forth.
So you see how there's a big empty area here.
So that's kind of seen here.
But what I want you to notice is these squares.
This is not a low resolution image.
It's the same resolution image
that is showing the different tiles in the image, right?
We said 16 by 16 tiles.
We are taking this image here and creating those tiles
just like we did in matrix multiply.
So each one of these is a tile within the image
that you are using to compute how many lights there are.
So in this particular image, going from here to here,
here, the white, this is not a depth buffer, by the way.
In this, white is representing more lights
and black is representing less lights.
So pay attention to this.
Which is the white?
Maybe this, this line here,
black area that goes inside, right?
So let's switch back.
Pay attention.
Does it match?
So we did this, this has more lights
and there's lights here, right?
Now we'll switch back.
You can see that, right?
So that's what this image is showing
is how many lights are covering each tile.
And based on that, now you can choose which tiles
have which lights and then render those together
to improve performance.
So to look at this, again,
performance matters everywhere.
We take this scene with number of lights
and see how, when you go from a very small number of lights
to a very large number of lights,
using tile-based shading
significantly improves your performance.
Why is that?
Because when you have like, let's say a thousand lights,
if you did non-tile-based shading,
you're trying to compute the effect of any light
in a given area to the entire image, right?
Whereas in tile-based shading,
you're computing which part of the image
is affected by that light.
And only those tiles are computed for each of them.
So it significantly improves the performance.
Similarly, for tile science,
the smaller your tile, the more tiles you have.
So you may not get adequate work done
if your tile is too big.
Then too many lights are affecting your each tile
and you won't get the performance.
So choosing a 16 by 16 or 32 by 32 tile
usually gives you good performance.
And this is something you've seen in,
let's say your reduction and scans
where you've chosen different block size, right?
So this is exactly similar to that,
except in a rendering concept
rather than in a compute concept.
Any questions on this slide?
Okay.
So there are a bunch of references here
that we've used for these slides.
Feel free to check them out.
There's a bunch of demos as well
that you can play around with
to understand deferred rendering a lot more.
Okay.
The other thing I want to show
is optimizing how we do backfaces and stuff.
So if you flip the depth stress to greater,
so I said zero is close to the camera
and one is further away from the camera, right?
If you flip that,
now you can get what's backface essentially.
So it's kind of like front face color.
So you hide the front faces
and you see what the backfaces are.
So you can optimize that further as well.
So let me open a demo for this.
So look at this, lots of lights, right?
All the spheres roaming around our lights.
We have 50 lights in the scene.
I'm going to increase it to a hundred.
Okay.
And see how,
while this is the final image,
let's go through each of these stages.
So I'm only going to do color.
Now, why did the spheres change into these cone type things?
So let me go back to the final.
So these spheres are around
and then we have some cones around it, right?
So those are the cones that we see here in the color.
So white means there is some color,
black means there is no color or it's an object.
We see the normals much more clearly here, right?
We can do a depth buffer.
White is furthest away, black is closest.
So as these cones come close to the camera,
they'll become black.
Then we can do a deferred one.
So this is just plain deferred shading.
Then if we do deferred with light proxies,
now you get the lights coming in and floating around.
Then we can do lights here.
So this was used to generate that image
that you saw in the slides.
Is there a pause button here?
I don't think so.
But essentially you can see
as the lights are roaming around,
the spheres are floating with the two.
Maybe let me change it to one light.
And then we can see.
So see how the sphere is floating with the lights.
I can stop that.
So let me go back into 50 lights
and then I'll pause the animation.
So now we can see how all the lights overlap
and stuff within that image.
Now, from these light spheres, right?
Let me zoom out.
We can compute the light influence.
The light sphere is not the light influence, okay?
The light influence is how it's affecting geometry.
So I'm going to switch that.
So now it's affecting this in 2D, essentially.
It's not a sphere, but it's more in 2D,
giving you a flat view of which light is affecting
which part of your screen.
So sphere, influence.
And then if you do influence add,
now you see where, what are the hot areas of your screen?
Right?
All the bright reds are where
there's more lights having an influence.
The dark areas are where
the lights are not having an influence.
If we do crop,
we only see where at least two lights are affecting.
And now you can see that with the geometry.
So if I zoom in here,
you can see the geometry
and how the geometry is affecting it.
And notice how there's no back geometry to this.
This was, I stopped somewhere like this,
and now there's only the front-facing geometry.
There's nothing at the back.
Right?
And that's because we are in this deferred pipeline
where we have paused the animation
to only see what is front-facing,
what's in the G-buffer.
And then if we do a fall-off,
now you see where the lights have no influence.
So I'll go from crop to fall-off,
where now you see,
like if you pay attention to this cone here,
see how this light,
while it has an influence, right?
The same light has an influence from here to here,
but it doesn't mean that
the light has the same influence
across its entire radius.
The light is gonna have more influence
close to its center
and less influence close to its edges, right?
So that's what this fall-off means,
where those edges have less influence.
Then you do shading with those lights.
And then if you add albedo,
then you get your colors.
So that's essentially the different stages
of the deferred rendering pipeline.
Let's come back to our slides.
So that is essentially
for all the deferred shading that is,
at least as we have in the slides,
there have been a lot more advances
in deferred shading through SIGGRAPH and stuff.
If you're interested in doing final projects
of any of them,
I'd be more than happy to encourage you to do that.
Both the project fives,
Vulcan and WebGL
have come from former students' final projects,
and I'd love to update them.
So if you're looking to doing new rendering,
real-time rendering pipelines,
would certainly encourage that.
So that's the first part of my lecture,
which is deferred shading.
We're gonna take,
we'll do the recitation for project four.
We'll take a break,
and then we'll do the second part,
which is forward plus rendering,
which takes a different view
on how we can do even more lights,
even more materials,
and take a look at that after the recitation on the break.
So I'll pause there, Shubham, whenever you're ready.
So I have the instructions open here if you need them.
So I'll just look at it.
So, I'm getting a bit of a, I should just-
No, go ahead.
You get started, we'll get on the break after.
So smoking.
Okay.
Talk about something, which is denoising.
And so I hope all of you enjoyed your project,
the ray tracing project.
But all of you must have noticed
that when we are iterating through like samples per pixel,
initially the image is very grainy.
And that is something that we're trying to solve
with denoising images,
that we're trying to convert the images faster.
If you can't do it through some concepts of path tracing,
then we'll take a different approach
and we'll denoise those images.
So that's what I talked about right now.
And let's see what happens.
Like, how do we do that?
So, it says that it's especially true
for simple path traces,
like our basic version of project three.
Light paths, they terminate as black.
And that's why you see a lot of grainy grains
on your images.
And rays scatter randomly on diffuse surfaces.
That's why it takes a lot of time
for your image to be converged.
So, we have noise worse
when light paths are unlikely to hit light sources.
So, if you have, let's say one light source in your scene
and you send a lot of light rays into your scene,
many of them will never reach a light source.
So, it will just give you a black color
or the pixel light.
So, that's what we see in like our scenes,
which has a lot of geometry or a lack of lighting,
that your image is gonna take a lot of time to converge.
And that's where the denoising comes into play.
And we have this third point,
which says that noise reduction
usually doesn't scale linearly with more iterations.
What it means by that is that,
let's say you have an image
which has like 10 samples per pixel.
Yeah, you just started here.
You have one sample per pixel.
Your image is very green.
You denoise it.
You will have some effect.
Your image now has 500 iterations.
It's way more converged than the first image.
You denoise it.
You get some results.
But then when you reach 1000 iterations,
your image is, it's gonna be,
it's not gonna have that much of an effect
when you see from 10, going from 10 to 100,
going from 100 to 500.
And that's what we will see now.
And that's what it means by like,
the denoising doesn't scale linearly with more iterations.
So, let's see how it works.
So, we have this one sample per pixel image.
Then by 11, and then 99, and then 501.
You see that now the image is fairly acceptable,
but it still has a lot of greens, right?
Now, when I reach 1000 samples per pixels,
from 500 to 1000, you didn't see much of a difference.
And I'm not saying that it looks 2x better.
So, like from here to here, I can say,
yeah, it looks way better, right?
Yeah, it looks way better for going from 99 to 500,
but it's not that great from going from like 500 to 1000.
So, you can't quantify it, right?
It's just how your eyes see that.
So, that's how the noise denoising is gonna be.
Initially, it's gonna perform really good,
but as we go with more iterations,
it's not gonna perform as good as it used to.
So, now this is like the fun part.
I don't know how many of you have taken the 460 class,
but all of us, we had that Gaussian blur
on Wahoo, the Mario thingy.
And when we did the Gaussian blur,
it just blurred out the image, right?
The whole image was blurred.
So, that's how we create like blurring
post-processing effects.
But what it does is it blurs the whole image, right?
And I want my blur to stop at certain point.
Let's say that you take a photo of me
and then you denoise it and you just blurred me out.
Like, I am like, you can't even see,
like differentiate me from the background.
But what if you stop at the edges?
Like if I have like my image
and you stop blurring me as soon as you found that,
okay, my like this, and that is different.
So, that's when your blurring is gonna be like really good.
It's gonna be effective.
It's gonna create a denoising effect, right?
So, let's see how it looks like.
So, for some scenes and materials,
as I told you about, it's gonna work great.
And we can control the blur with more per pixel info.
So, basic concept,
you just learned about G buffers, what they are.
So, let's say that I store the normals and the colors, right?
So, my normal, like at each of,
let's say like I have UVs and my normals,
like each point is gonna be different than this wall.
So, you can detect, okay,
I am a different object than this wall.
So, that means you can stop
when you're denoising me from that wall,
you can get that edge, right?
And the same thing goes for pixels.
Like it depends upon the scene,
but if this board is different than this board,
in terms of color, right?
So, when I'm denoising this image,
I will say, okay, stop here.
Like don't count in these pixels because this is an edge.
So, that's what we have here,
that we have an image, which is like this.
If you just apply a simple Gaussian blur,
it's too blurred out,
you can't make anything out of it.
So, we store positions inside our G buffer,
which looks like that.
And then you also store normals.
And if you add all of this up,
as I told you about,
if you stop blurring out
when you see difference in normals and positions,
you're gonna see something like that.
And this is what we're aiming for in this project,
that we wanna build a denoiser,
which performs really good when we detect some edges
and we blur out those pixels.
So, we are basing off our implementation
from this amazing paper, the 8Ru paper.
And the key take up,
like it's like, it has a lot of fancy terms inside the paper
when you read through it.
But the main idea is what I just talked about,
that we're gonna approximate blur filters like Gaussian blur
with fewer memory reads.
And that is like one thing,
if you want to blur the whole image,
you have a bunch of pixels and you start a kernel
and then every thread is just blurring one pixel out.
It's gonna be like way,
like it's not gonna be memory efficient
because every thread is reading a bunch of values
from the global memory pool, right?
So, we're gonna see how we optimize those memory reads.
And that's what we saw in this paper.
And now we move on to here.
So, I don't know if a lot of,
like, has anybody seen Gaussian kernel before?
Yeah.
So, like, don't worry about that.
So, a Gaussian core is like this.
So, it's maximum, the maximum value is at the center.
And when we go away,
like when we go away to like move from,
in like standard deviation, it just reduces down.
That's what's happening here.
So, maximum value.
And when we go in any direction,
which is like away from it, the value decreases.
And that's how the pixel blurring works, right?
Because the current pixel that I'm currently,
like the working on,
I'm gonna have the maximum value from that,
maximum data from that.
And when I move away from it,
I'm gonna take like less and less and less.
So, that's just like a Gaussian blur.
And yeah, so, this is the pseudocode for,
the pseudocode for the Gaussian blur for each pixel.
Being blurred, we sample every pixel in the blur radius.
And we multiply by a weight, which is from your kernel.
And let's say that the color and the,
this weight is just multiplying with every,
the colors or the pixels of your final image.
And you'll get the final color of the one pixel.
So, now Gaussian blurs, they usually,
they usually do blurring on like some filter,
which is of some size.
So, let's say that this previous one was,
I don't know how much,
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
It's seven by seven.
Oh, it's seven, it's a seven by seven filter.
But if I want to blur,
if I want to do this blurring with a 16 by 16 filter,
which is, it's going to be like huge.
Because for every pixel, I'm going to read like,
what is 16 into 16?
256?
Yeah, 256, oh, it's a dimension.
Yes.
So, it's, so I'm going to read like 256 pixels
for every pixel.
Like, so it's going to be, I don't know,
like how much, 19, 20 to 10, 80 pixels.
Each of them doing 256 calculation every time.
So, it's like too much, right?
So, I have to find a way to optimize this.
So, how it's done in, like,
how A2A explained that,
how we found a good way to optimize this thing is that,
instead of doing a 16 by 16 curtail,
instead of using that, I use five by five curtail.
And what I do is, I first use the five by five curtail weights
to find the color for this pixel,
which is like center.
And next slide, in next iteration,
I'm going to use the same five by five filter.
And instead of taking these pixels for the values,
I'm going to take these pixels.
So, there's like a bunch of pixels here
that I'm not taking into consideration,
and I expanded my filter.
So, that's what I'm doing.
Every iteration, I expand my filter,
and I add, so these are like,
are going to be like a bunch of pixels
that I don't care about,
and every time I get more pixels.
So, I'm doing the same effect.
I'm having the same 16 by 16 effect
by using a five by five curtail.
So, that's what we have here for a five by five filter.
And I want to do 16 by 16 blur.
So, what I do is,
I'm going to just do 25 pixel reads every iteration,
and I'm going to do it three times.
Why? Because like five into three
and five into three is approximately that same value.
So, we have 75 pixel reads per pixel blur
instead of two pixel reads for Gaussian.
And then the total number of pixel reads
gets more slowly when increasing blur size,
because now we just have like a small blur kernel,
and then we just like expand it.
So, it's going to expand like way more less,
like it's going to be way more efficient
when we slowly increase the blur size.
So, the G-Buffer,
we'd store per pixel information for surfaces
seen beyond the ray trace color.
What we store in G-Buffer is the position
and just the normals.
I think that will be enough for us.
We'll also add color, but let's see how it scales.
So, that's what it says.
What else might be useful for edge detection
and detail preservation?
Color. Color will definitely,
because the surface is different color than that surface.
So, we can know that these two surfaces
are different.
Sometimes these things might not come into play
because let's say that this and this surface
is like different, it's of a different material,
like the normal mapping is different,
but they are of the same color,
but I still wanted to preserve that edge.
That edge will be lost.
So, that's why we will make all of these factors somehow.
Well, this might have different normals than that.
So, sometimes normal will be more come into play,
sometimes position will come into play, sometimes color.
And we'll have to like squeeze all of these factors,
you know, like in one equation to find out
a perfect equation which works for the edge detection.
So, we'll also see how it works,
how this scaling will work,
this edge detection and everything will work
with reflective, refractive and translucent material.
I'm not gonna talk about it,
but I think in your readme slide,
you have to write about it.
So, write good answers.
So, yeah.
So, now let's look at the paper.
The paper, yeah, it looks kind of daunting,
like it's too much to read,
but I'm just gonna make it like,
it's actually a simpler way
and then you can read it on your own.
But what it tells is that,
so, just like think about this thing for now,
which is like, I want to calculate the color of my pixel
using my Gaussian kernel
and some of the ways that I calculated, right?
So, coming here,
this weight is based on some normal,
some position and some input image, right?
So, they're using a normal buffer,
a position buffer and the weighted input image.
And what we do is,
how do we tell that one value is too different,
too much different than the other, right?
I just calculate the distance between them.
It might be like anything,
like let's say I have a normal value,
it has some x, y, z coordinates.
I have another normal, which has some x, y, z coordinates.
Calculating the distance between two normals
doesn't make any sense.
But if I just do this,
like the same distance calculation
to calculate the distance between these x, y and z values,
it will tell me how it's different there, right?
So, first thing is that,
so, there's like this way to calculate
how much different the two things are.
And then the second thing is,
if something is like different,
if it's more different,
I want to scale it,
like I want to weigh less.
So, that's why this equation tells you something,
like if this is like an exponential equation,
which tells me if this is like E minus D upon two,
if the distance is like,
so, it's gonna be like one upon E D by two.
So, it tells me that if distance increase,
I should decrease the weightage I'm giving to that.
So, like, if this is a normal for this surface
and that is a normal,
which is like two different for two surfaces
and the distance is large,
that means I don't want this thing to weigh more
because these things are too much there.
That's why we have this one upon exponential of some,
because that's like that function right there.
So, one thing we conquered.
Second thing is this weight.
So, this weight is actually a combination of three things.
So, you calculate the difference between the normal,
like how different they are.
You have a weight for position.
So, it's like the things are two different,
like two different positions
that I know that they are too far apart.
There might be a length there.
And then I think we also have the range-range input image
which we might be using for color or something.
So, finally, what this image is doing is that it says,
for a pixel P, which is my current pixel,
and for the pixel Q,
which are like all the pixels inside my kernel.
So, if I'm using a five by five kernel,
it's gonna be five by five pixels around me.
Five by five minus five pixels around me.
I'm just gonna do the weight calculation for all of them.
I have my color.
I have like a weighted value for all of the other pixels.
And I think this is like the Gaussian kernel value.
So, I use the weights, the Gaussian kernel,
and the color of that pixel,
that is like my surrounding pixel.
And I like add those up and average that out
which is the sum of all these weights.
I average that out and that's gonna be my value.
So, now, coming on to here,
this code is exactly doing that.
It just calculates the force, which is I think.
So, we store the color value, the normal, the P value.
We calculate the weighting factor from there,
which is like the color weight, the normal weight,
the position weight.
And then at the end,
I'm just averaging a bunch of these values, five by five.
And this equation works perfectly.
It's really good in detecting edges
and stopping blurring whenever there's an edge.
And, okay, I think I explained all of this.
So, what is this in this code?
So, this is like, I think, a fragment shader code
that is mentioned in the paper.
And we are gonna implement this in our CUDA kernels.
So, the kernel is our Gaussian kernel.
The offsets are these things.
So, initially, there's no offset.
So, we start off, let's check on the first iteration.
There's like, let me show you.
So, here.
So, you see that two to the power i minus one factor there.
So, like my first iteration, there is like,
so, that tells me how many zeros are there
between two values.
So, if I,
so, here, there's like no.
So, if I come here to here,
you will see that there's no zero between two values.
Like, this is the lowest kernel.
Then, the next iteration,
I have one zero between every bit.
So, that's my offset.
So, I just keep on increasing this offset.
Every iteration, I increase the offset.
And then, like, how much I want to blur my image.
How much I want my blur, the kernel to be.
So, yeah.
So, at the end, what we have is,
here, for all the values in the kernel,
I'm just like, going through all the pixels now,
and applying this same formula.
So, for pragmashifter, it's a perfection program.
Pragmashifter is for what's for each
in relation to the exceeding separate.
So, it's same.
So, I start with my original Gaussian kernel.
I calculate the final result for every pixel.
Now, the next iteration, I'm going to have this kernel.
This kernel instead of that, which has some separate,
because I'm, like, stepping my way by, like,
some, let's say, from one unit value.
I'm going to do that again,
and I'm going to do it a one more time.
And at the end, I will have a final result.
So, for loop handles gathering neighboring pixels
based on the A2 filter, which is like my bottom picture,
which is 515256, and I keep expanding it.
So, I think, yeah, this slide has also these
color coding patterns, which are telling you
where this thing, where, like, each of this value
is inside this random variable.
So, there's, like, purple.
This HI is, like, your kernel.
Then, there'll be this CIMA, your color.
So, it's helping you to understand
where the paper is fitting inside the fragmented code.
And, yeah, I think that's it for this paper.
It's not going to be really hard to understand.
I think you might have gotten a pretty good idea
about how we are doing it.
We have a bunch of weights.
These weights depend upon how much distance
is between the current value, like, anything,
normal, further, anything, right?
And then, it scales, depending upon exponential,
so that if two values are too far apart,
we're going to be in that.
If the values are close, we're going to be in more.
That means, like, they are the same thing.
And, yeah, the deadline for this project is 21st, yeah.
So, does that mean, like, that, like, iterative,
you know, go to look at it and apply,
you know, parse the kernel.
That's, like, that's just independent
of the actual parentheses on the weights,
like, the kernel, like, the, you know,
the normal and the cognitive position.
Is that correct?
Maybe you can give me that question again.
So, like, when you're, when you're,
when you are doing the iterative blurring
with the sparser and sparser matrices,
that's just an optimization on Gaussian blur, right?
That is just, like, we can do this denoising
with a regular Gaussian blur, too.
Yeah, right, yeah.
The middle values are just too insignificant to care about.
The what?
The values in the middle,
as you make your portions go larger and larger.
Yeah.
The values in the middle are too insignificant,
like, 0.003 or something.
So, why waste memory on those?
Yeah.
Yeah, I think what Atra might have done was, like,
use the original 5x5 pixels,
and then kept on increasing it,
and then, until it,
and then, it was largely 16x16,
and then use the original 16x16 Gaussian blur kernel,
and see if that,
and he found that the results were not too different,
that we, that we can go about just using lesser memory,
then that's the optimization that we do.
Does anybody else?
Yes.
So, I'm doing this on your,
these reflections,
I don't,
So, let's, let's think about, like,
what a mirror specular material would be.
Let's say that there's a specular ball inside,
or, like, in your scene somewhere,
and then behind that is the wall,
as, like, I'm just imagining my corner box scene.
We have a sphere, we have balls.
So, when, let's say that there's an edge for the sphere,
and then there's a wall behind it,
I just want to know that I don't blur
the values of the sphere,
like the reflective values inside the sphere with the wall,
because if I blur them, that's going to be a problem.
So, I am going to stop as soon as I find
that the normal of the sphere is too different
from the normal of the wall.
Yeah.
So, yeah, the reflections will be blurred.
Oh.
The reflection, the scene, or the goal of denoising
is to denoise the whole scene.
So, even if you have a very defective sphere,
doesn't mean that you're not going to have a draining wall.
So, the goal is to get rid of the draining.
But, as you'll see in project four,
this is just an introduction to getting started
with denoising.
It's not anybody else's great at denoising either.
So, what it's going to do is it's going to help your scene,
it's going to help your scene dissolve a lot faster,
but it will introduce some amount of blur.
But, ideally, it shouldn't be too bad.
What, if you run denoising on the first image,
compared to the hundredth image,
you're going to get different amounts of blur.
So, it depends where you balance it out.
Yeah, so like a perfect example would be,
yeah, so you see, there's grain here,
and then there's also graininess on the reflective material.
It's the same, right?
If I blur my, let's say, the ground,
I should also blur this,
because the reflection should be the same, right?
Like, it should show me the same image,
where I'm like the same values that I'm seeing here,
like for the color.
If I blur this out, then that should also be blurred, right?
So, yeah, that's why we should blur the whole image.
I'm not saying that the results are going to be great.
It's going to be like a very bad result.
Let me show you.
Yeah, you see, it's not that good.
Like now the reflection, it's all blurred out of the sphere.
Yeah, you can't see it clearly right now.
It doesn't look that bad.
So I think this was, yeah, this paper is like for us
to understand how denoising actually works,
like how it started off.
Now there's like, now we also have like neural networks,
and that's what will do the denoising of the sphere.
So what I understand, basically we identify the portion.
Is this done in screen space, or is this done?
We like using the g-buffer.
Yeah, so in the g-buffer, right?
Like per pixel, we know something,
we know its position, we know it's normal,
we know its color.
And based on this screen space information,
we are segmenting the image into discrete elements
that would apply a specific color to the image.
So this is a big Gaussian blur at the end.
Yeah, so like, you know,
because instead of applying it to the entire screen,
okay, this is a wall, that wall is like that wall,
but not other parts.
And then if you get to an edge, like what happens?
Like if you're on-
No, it's exactly like, let's say that.
So this is the blur that we see in the glossy blur,
randomly, like an image.
This is not what we're gonna get.
But if you do it with the edge of it,
what's gonna do it, it's gonna stop.
So let's say that this is the pixel that I'm operating on,
like this whole thing, this whole patch.
So I found that the normals of this wall
was like really different, and even the color.
So when I was weighing this pixel inside my Gaussian,
which I'm applying with formula,
I weighed it down, like the weight is like two less now
for the Gaussian blur to come into effect,
because these two values are too far apart.
Oh, so literally like,
because we have a, what, like a 16 by 16 window, right?
So let's say we have the pic,
we're trying to calculate, you know, the value,
the RGB value of, you know, a pixel that's right on the edge.
When we do our weird Gaussian blur,
when we do the pyramid,
we will evaluate a pixel that's on like a different wall.
But because that wall has a different normal value
and different color and like a different position,
we're gonna squish,
like it already has like a Gaussian kernel weight.
We also have another thing that we like,
because it's so different from our current thing,
we squish it down and therefore, yeah.
And I'm just gonna like,
for you guys to understand it better,
I'm just gonna do some calculation here really quick.
So let's say that this is the pixel of the red wall
that I'm trying to find out.
So, and my formula, it's like a formula,
which is gonna, let's say my filter is like five by five,
right?
So I'm gonna do like a four I equals to zero,
and which is like I less than 25,
because this is my five by five thing.
And this is,
this is my Gaussian kernel,
which is like some values here.
And then this is my center value.
So this is gonna be the largest.
I don't know what the value is.
Like let's say it's 0.02.
And all the values are smaller than that.
So my color value, I started like zero.
And then color is just like an additive thing
in this for loop.
So plus equal to my function.
This function is just gonna return me this A true value,
which is like some weights multiplied.
So this function is weight multiplied
by the Gaussian kernel,
multiplied by the color of my current pixel, right?
Yeah.
So Gaussian blur, we divide by K,
being the number of weights that are being emitted.
But if we do divide by K,
that assumes like equal weight
from each participating, like neighbor.
Like if our weight squeezes down different pixels
down to like zero,
but we're still giving people weight when they agree.
No, so what's happening essentially is,
when you have the edge between the red and the white.
In screen space, you're gonna be working
on both the red and the white pixels.
Yeah.
But because of the weights,
the reds are gonna have more weight than the whites.
Yeah.
So you don't darken your image in that sense.
The intensity doesn't decrease the intensity.
You may get a little bit of blur,
but not decrease in intensity.
My main concern is just like,
so all that's being affected actually
is the kernel weight, right?
Not the intensity.
No, I get your question.
So I'll explain that why that wouldn't happen.
So let me go through this.
So yeah.
So let's say that the weight for,
Yeah.
So when I calculated the weight for,
let's say this is my pixel that I'm trying to find in,
the weight for this one is like, let's say 0.9.
Nice weight, very high weight, right?
So, and when I added this value inside this color,
it's gonna be like huge,
because I know that it's like closer.
When I calculated the weight for this white wall,
it came out to be 0.001.
So that's why this color never get blended in,
inside my pixel.
So that's how the edge detection works,
because I didn't blur this value,
like this red will never have a white blurred into it.
So that's why, that's how it stopped.
Now to come back to your question,
where you were saying that if I didn't end up
taking some of the pixel values,
that means when I'm dividing everything.
So this pixel, because it took all of the pixels
surrounding it, then density will be higher,
because I'm dividing by like, let's say K.
But this one, it never took these pixels.
And for this one, it ended up taking all the 25 values
by the size of it.
This one never took all the values, right?
It just took, let's say, 15.
And all the values on the right side,
this white wall never came into play for the final color.
That means that the final color value will be less,
and that's what I don't want.
So when we see the formula, yeah.
So the K value here, which is like the mean of my thing,
is this thing, which is like HI and then the W.
So if I'm dividing by,
so if I'm adding something like 0.01,
which is like two less,
but then I'm also like dividing it by some value,
which is like lower,
then the whole thing is going to go up.
K is not constant.
Yeah, K is not constant, K is same.
Does anybody understand that?
We'll go to the third for the moment.
Oh, I see it.
That's happening at the last part,
so I'm dividing by the sum of the cells.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, we're not even.
We're scaling.
Oh.
Just kidding.
Who's name do you have?
It's like, if he doesn't, he would.
Yeah.
It's kernel, like kernel is the Gaussian.
So we're just scaling, also scaling the kernel values.
Yeah, so this is like one equation.
Don't think about this like, this is one equation.
It's like 425 by 25.
I haven't expanded my kernel here.
So the formula there, like for I go to zero to become 25,
I take in 25 pixels surrounding me and I do that.
There's going to be next iteration of the same code,
which is going to do this 25 again,
but now the options will be different,
for like the pixel position that I'm in.
So offsets, so it's uniform deck two,
it's an array of 25 deck twos, correct?
Yeah.
So for the corner ones, it would be like plus one,
plus one, plus one, minus one.
Yeah.
It depends on the power of the iteration, I think.
Two power n minus one, right?
So yeah, n minus one.
So what's written in the paper is like this,
like line minus, it can be very confusing,
but so it says that at each level,
i is greater than zero,
the filter doubles its extent by filling in
two to the power i minus one zero
between the initial entry.
So what it's doing is like,
so for the first iteration,
like so what we have is two to the power of one minus one,
zero, one, so one, one, one, one, one.
So everything we have like between every pixel
there's like one.
And that's like, yeah.
And do we have like two,
yeah.
And then between these two,
there's like two, and two, and two,
between every pixel.
Or is it like three, but it doesn't matter.
Oh.
So you're drawing like a problem.
Yeah.
Or I might be wrong,
because I checked the paper exactly,
because it's like some problem,
you just increase your step with every iteration
by a certain amount,
which is really depends upon
two to the power of five minus one.
That's what the paper tells.
Yeah.
And then you just apply with that.
And how many times you're going to do that same iteration
with like increasing step rate,
is like for you to find out,
like just see.
I think there's a value that's given in the paper.
I'm not entirely sure what I used,
but there's like,
I was going through my comments
and there was like this line that
I found this value to be perfect.
Now I don't remember
how I reached to that value.
Was it like this file in there?
I don't know.
I found it somewhere.
I just played around with it.
But yeah, just like that.
So does anybody else have any questions
regarding this project, the implementation?
Everybody got a good idea?
My work is done, I think.
Let's do, let's take a break.
We'll get some lunch at 7 p.m. sharp
and we'll get started with all the topics.
Okay.
Do we have to talk about the extra thing now?
The extra credits?
Like-
No, it's all there.
Yeah, it's all there.
Yeah.
We can take a look at it.
Okay.
Thank you, Professor Shehlan.
That's so good.
Okay.
I have,
I reached out to my client.
So it's like this.
Yeah.
I want to talk about it.
I agree.
Oh, thanks to you, because I haven't created it.
Oh, okay.
And I thought you forgot, I read your email.
Thank you for that.
Okay.
I'm going to
That was it.
All right, so we saw deferred rendering in the first part of the lecture, right, where
what we did was we separated the geometry and the material from the lighting computation.
Essentially, we stored all the rasterization outputs, and then we ran all the lighting
stuff.
So it kind of broke it into two parts.
What we're going to see with ForwardPlus and Clustered is another way to optimize our
standard rendering pipeline, but doing it in a different way.
So let's take a look at that.
So as a reminder, deferred shading has a few limitations.
It has a very high memory bandwidth because of reading that GBuffer over and over again.
You can't do too many materials, for example, you can't do translucency.
You can't do MS or you can't easily do MSA because as soon as you want to do multi-sample
are quadrupling, if not more, the size of your GBuffer.
And there's still some redundant lighting computation where there are lighting overlaps
or towards the edge of the influence, you have very low weights and stuff like that.
So how do we optimize this further?
So just as a recap, the deferred shading is for each light, you're computing the visibility,
storing it in a GBuffer, and then all of these have to be read again and again, right?
So that's where you have the overdraw essentially for each light.
And then at the bottom, so that's the traditional deferred, and this is the tile deferred at
the bottom where we are changing it into, okay, we only do it per tile and see which
lights are influencing which tile and then do it that way.
So another way to look at this is in 3D as one, okay?
So can everybody see this camera here?
Think of this as a virtual camera, okay?
These blue are tiles, right?
In 2D when you have like your screen here, these are tiles and they're starting from
the first point of intersection, there's a tree here by the way.
First point of intersection going all the way back.
Let me turn down the lights.
What we get is you see that where there's no intersections, it's hitting the wall and
you see the checker pattern back there.
And wherever it's hitting, it's going through these spheres of influence of light.
These spheres represent the lights as going through that.
So what you get is the tree in the front, so this tree here is actually doing a lot
of occlusion, okay?
It's blocking a lot of the lights.
None of these lights are actually affecting this tree here.
But the 2D tiling, so in deferred we had that 2D tiling, right?
Which I showed you in the sponsor scene.
It doesn't take that into account.
It doesn't take into account that all the lights are behind the tree here and a lot
of it is occluded.
So it's not taking that z value into space.
Another way to look at it is like this.
So these lights are the spheres of influence of the light and then we have this tree here,
okay?
And like only like two tiles affect like all six of them.
So only some of the pixels are from the tree, which are not influenced by any light.
But the tile, these two tiles here, these two blue tiles, they intersect with all six
lights.
And likewise, the pixels in the times are at the very back of the scene are only influenced
by two lights.
And that is this back here, okay?
So that's kind of the problem with deferred rendering is that it doesn't take all of this
3D space into account.
So let's see how what we call ForwardPlus helps solve that.
So ForwardPlus does light culling for screen space tiles and it's designed for modern day
GPUs.
It understands how, just like we've learned in this class about how CUDA has helped optimize
GPUs and the various things we should be taking into account.
It takes those kinds of things into account to help optimize the rendering pipeline.
And two of those things are a high computer memory ratio, which means computers free,
memory is expensive, and compute shaders.
So essentially what you've done in CUDA, translate that into a rendering pipeline and you get
compute shaders.
So ForwardPlus has three passes.
It has first a depth pass or a Z pre-pass as it's called, it has light culling, and
then it has a final shading.
How many passes did deferred have?
How many phases did deferred have?
Two, right?
It had generate the G-buffer, do the lighting calculations.
So in time we have three.
So let's see how this works.
So in the first step, in the first phase, we want to have the depth buffer, okay?
So what we're going to have is essentially what is called a pass-through fragment shader
where you're getting the depth buffer from the rasterizer, the fragment shader doesn't
do anything except write the depth buffer to a texture.
That's what a pass-through fragment shader is.
Very simple, no lighting evaluator.
If a fragment shader discards during the light accumulation, that still needs to be
accounted for.
So what we are essentially doing is a very standard depth pass and part of the input
to the light culling pass.
So this is one of the inputs that will be used in the light culling, which is phase
two.
So in this part, what we're going to do is we're going to have a fragment shader, which
in this part, what we're going to do is compute the lights that overlap each time.
Just like we had tiles in deferred rendering, in the deferred shading pipeline, we still
have those tiles in Power+.
We're not getting rid of those.
So that's why this image and this image, both appear very blocky.
The white parts of these images are more lights, the darker parts are less lights.
The red parts in this image are more overlapping lights, and the black parts are less overlapping
lights.
OK, everybody clear on this?
So what we are essentially trying to do is figure out where there is more light computation
when there's no light computation needed per tile.
So let's take an example.
We have this very simple scene here that is tiled.
OK, again, very simple, only for representation.
And let's say we have these three lights.
For this tile here, only light one has an influence, and even that is very fleeting.
For this box here, one, two, and three all have a strong influence on that light.
And then for this box here, two and three have not even to the center, but maybe like
a quarter of the tile is influenced.
So what we want to figure out is which tiles, and all of these are the tiles, by the way,
which are not covered by the orange, are not affected by these lights.
So what we want to do in our scene is figure out the exact points at which the light influence
starts and stops.
So the way to do that is this.
We do this in a compute shader.
So the easiest way to think of a compute shader is imagine a CUDA kernel inside a rendering
pipeline.
So you can do different types of computation in.
So now what we are going to do is, if this is our scene where our camera is down here
and it's expanding that way, so camera down here, depth max here, we're going to input
the Z-buffer, which we computed in our first path, the depth buffer, and we're going to
pass a light buffer, which is a shader object.
And then the output is going to be another list.
So this is what we're going to do.
This, where 9 is going like this, that's coming from the depth buffer.
That's showing you a top-down view of what the depth buffer might be looking like in
a cross-section, not in 3D, this is in 2D.
So instead of having a tile represent this entire thing, which we were doing before in
default shading, where the light started here or the tile started at minimum and went to
maximum, we're going to change that a little bit.
We are going to do it using the depth buffer and compute the minimum and maximum in each
tile in the depth buffer itself.
So each one of these is a top-down view of a tile, each one of these tiles.
So the light coming list here, the output for this tile will start from here and end
here.
For this tile, it will start here and end here.
For the third one, it will start here, or technically start here because there's a gap.
So you can have different objects forward and back.
So it will start here and end here, and so on and so on.
Is this clear to everybody?
Because this part is important about how we are creating this.
We are using a compute shader to figure out the minimum depth and the maximum depth in
each tile.
That's essentially the crux of it.
In 3D, this would be squares, squares and you're going to get volumes in the back.
But the depth stuff will remain.
The depth is still minimum z and maximum z.
That doesn't change.
Any questions on this?
So the way to do this is you do one-third per pixel.
Again, it's easy to think of compute shaders in almost like CUDA terms.
One-third per pixel, and one workgroup per tile.
One workgroup is a term derived from compute shaders and OpenCL.
It's essentially what a block is in CUDA.
So what it's saying is one block per tile and one-third per pixel.
Again, very, very easy for us to understand.
And you get a total of n compares with atomics.
We haven't covered atomics yet.
I'll cover it on Wednesday.
But what that means is you can do atomic comparisons in a parallel way.
Of course, it becomes serial, but you'll have n comparisons per block.
So that way you get the result per block in a tile.
And then you do the light and frustum overlap.
So essentially, if I go back here, the first page,
so this 2A here is computing the minimum length of the red line.
Forget the blocks.
Forget the light, red, volume.
It's just computing the minimum maximum per tile, 2A.
2B is what is computing the volumes.
And for that, you're going to do, again, one block per tile,
one-third per light now, not per pixel.
And this will require multiple passes for many times, if you have a lot of them.
Because this here, this volume here is not just one light.
It can have many lights across this entire thing for the influence.
So you have to compute them for each object.
And then you do one compute shader for this and one compute shader for this.
And you'll end up with something like this.
Any questions here?
So let me see if...
Now, the third part is actually accumulating all the lights per tile
for the lights that affect that tile.
Remember, I'll say that once again.
You accumulate the lights in a per tile fashion
for the lights that only affect that tile.
So material IDs can be used to look up the material information from that.
And then you can render that into the scene.
So I'll play a few videos here to show how this works.
And this is done by students.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to slow this down a little so you can absorb it.
So see how forward plus is much lower than...
Or forward is much lower than forward plus.
And you can see all the lights moving around
and how even changing the light stops influencing other parts,
but doesn't necessarily drop the frame rate.
You can see the frame rate up here when it was captured.
But now you'll start seeing a few debug views from this.
So this is how many lights are influencing each part of the scene.
That is the depth buffer.
That I believe is...
I forget.
That's normals.
And that's the final run.
So look at how many lights there are in the scene.
You'd find it almost impossible to do this with a regular forward rendering pipeline.
And I'll play another video.
That was a few debug views as well.
I'll let that play. You guys can absorb it.
So the thing to remember is the actual pipeline from going from primitives to rendering
isn't actually changing on the GPU.
The GPU hardware pipeline still remains the same.
What we're essentially doing is changing the way
we go from primitives and vertices all the way to the final image.
Instead of doing it in one pass or multiple passes of the whole pipeline over and over again,
we change how we store intermediate objects
and then come back for doing more computation that allows us to do more lights and stuff.
Otherwise, I'll move on from these videos.
So in this scene, you can also kind of see the spheres of influences and how they grow.
This is a very popular model, right?
Sponsor.
It's a very, very popular model to use when doing real-time rendering and showing the effects.
Yeah.
The way you have to think about it is the trade-off between compute and memory, right?
And that's what we said when I was introducing the Power+.
The computation to actually compute the minimum maximum within a tile is very, very low
because you're doing it within a block.
You're not doing it.
It's like doing a reduction within the block.
Minimum and maximum is a reduction operation, right?
You're comparing A greater than or less than B.
And you're doing it for, let's say, 16 by 16 to 256 elements.
You can do it in shared memory.
So it's very easy to do and it's very fast.
But if you have, let's say, thousands of lines, then that starts affecting you.
There may be lines that are in the background or the foreground that don't
affect the minimum and maximum.
So you can cull them away and remove them.
It's from the diagram I showed you.
It's a very, very simple diagram.
Real geometry can be much more complex because it also goes into 3D then.
Any other questions?
All right.
So those were some videos.
You'll have access to these, obviously.
So now let's see why Power Plus is faster than before.
In some ways, it's faster.
In some ways, it's slower.
But overall, it becomes faster.
The first thing is in the pre-pass, writing the gbuffer takes a lot more time
than writing a depth buffer.
In fact, depth buffer is just one part of the gbuffer.
So that's more information that you're going to be writing compared to just the depth buffer.
So Power Plus is faster so far.
In the lighting diagram, you're reading depth and light geometry.
Very simple.
Depth is one floating point value.
Light geometry is probably a few values in position and radius.
Then you're computing color and writing a light list.
All of these are way faster than the lighting accumulation in deferred,
where you're doing a lot more reads.
You're doing a lot more computation.
And you're accumulating the buffer.
Now, Power Plus is slower.
It's in the shading part.
Because now, in Power Plus, you're reading the brightness and the light drop
and then computing all the lighting and shading.
Whereas in deferred rendering, all you're doing is
you already have the accumulated light buffer,
and you're probably computing some additional shading.
The accumulated light buffer is coming from depth.
So what you write here, you're reading here, and you're doing the compute now.
So if we look at this comparison here, the blues are not that red.
The reds are very different.
And then the greens are slightly different, but not as much as the reds.
And so overall, Power Plus becomes faster,
because it doesn't have that high memory bandwidth usage.
So Power Plus is much more designed to have more compute
and less memory bandwidth usage.
And that's why it becomes faster.
So two scenes here, Sponza and Runhole.
So Sponza is a quarter million triangles.
Runhole is almost six million triangles.
So let's see how Power Plus and Power perform.
And this is also right here.
So Sponza, for 10 lights, 10 lights is like,
you can recharge pretty much the power every 5 minutes.
Well, you still see almost 2x improvement.
Like Power Plus is almost twice as fast,
or a little bit more than twice as fast as just the Power.
200 lights is where you start seeing slowdown.
So this is in milliseconds, right?
So this is about 6 milliseconds.
Very much real time, right?
You have at least 16 milliseconds to get 60 frames per second.
So this, for 10 lights, even a regular Power Plus is real time.
As you get to 200 lights, now this is almost 10 times as fast.
And then if you get to 1,000 lights,
now you're almost 1,500 times faster, right?
Or 15 times faster.
So that kind of shows how, as you have more lights,
kind of like in your GTAs or anywhere, any other game,
that this becomes an exponential increase.
And that's where changing how the pipeline works
is affecting games and game engines to do a lot more.
And that's kind of the influence behind
Nanite and Lumen and Unreal Engine,
so that you can have these different pipelines
as your scene grows.
Similarly, comparing the number of lights
between Power and Power Plus.
Runhole, which is 6 million triangles now,
so this was for Sponza, this is for Runhole.
So now we see how this changes as well.
Notice how the yellow bars are generally consistent.
So the exponential increase is not there,
whereas in the green, which is Power,
that exponential increase changes quite fast.
And then comparing how light radius can affect this.
So this is all for Sponza, all having 1,000 lights.
This is 1,000 small lights, 1,000 medium lights,
and 1,000 large lights.
And when we mean large, we mean a larger radius.
So this goes from radius of two to five to 10.
And you can see how in Power, the radius doesn't matter,
because we don't care about the radius
in our Power to Engine pipeline.
We'll just do all the lights all the time.
So the Power is going to remain constant and slow.
With Power+, now because the radius has an influence
on how many lights you can build
and how much influence it has in the geometry per tile,
you're going to see some performance drop off
as the lights become larger.
But it's still going to be way faster
than any Power rendering pipeline.
And then similar to Deferred,
when you compare the pipe sizes,
again, you see this sort of inverted delta,
where if you have eight by eight, it's kind of slow,
128 by 128 kind of slow.
But as you pick a decent size between 16 and 64,
you're going to get generally good results.
And then time spent in each pass for different tile sizes.
So this is tile size 16 by 16 and 32 by 32.
And that changes based on your compute pass.
So 32 by 32, you're going to take longer
because it's a larger block.
You're going to take more time to compute the min and max.
But because you take more time and your tile is bigger,
your final stage pass is going to be longer.
Whereas in 16 by 16, your compute pass is longer,
but your final pass is shorter.
Okay.
So any questions on that so far on Power Plus?
Because next we are going to see
how do we optimize Power Plus even more.
All right.
So the next step of optimization,
again, if you know anything about Green by Now,
we'll always have slides that are,
okay, how do we take this and optimize it more, right?
Performance Lab is the number one example of that.
So let's say we don't want,
we're not satisfied with a thousand lights,
we want a million lights.
Office Power is one million.
Let's see how to do that.
What we'll call this is cluster trading essentially,
and this is used by some of the most modern games.
It has better worst case performance,
but with large depth discontinuities,
and I'll get to that in a little bit.
And let's see how that...
So in cluster trading,
the same that we found that we did in Power Plus,
but now instead of doing full volumes,
we'll do clusters, okay?
And I'll show you an image of that.
And we want to remove any empty space.
And then the light coming
is assigned only to the non-empty clusters.
And then the final shading is, again,
same as the Power Plus.
So let's take a look.
So this is actually the same as what we found in Power Plus.
So this is how the depth buffer looks from top down.
In Power Plus, we get this kind of range,
but now, say clusters,
we're not just dividing the tiles like this,
we're dividing the whole scene into this.
So we're not just getting the tiles here,
we're also dividing that by the depth, okay?
So what that does is it removes
coverage on the bottom volume that we have.
So this is a prime example of this.
Look at this, how this line is going from here to here.
But now, because this is divided like this as well,
we don't have to draw a full box here,
we can just draw small chunks.
That's min and max, both in depth for this,
and then the x, y, and z.
And then similarly, look at this bounding volume here,
where you have a little bit in the back
and a little bit in the foreground.
What we'll do here is we have one cluster there
and one cluster here, that's it.
All this empty space where there's nothing gets removed.
We don't have, in Power Plus,
this would have meant if a light was like here,
influencing here,
we still have to do the computation of all that.
But here, there's a light influencing here,
we don't do anything.
We just, we cut it out.
So this is essentially improving
how well lights get curled within our scenes,
even better than Power Plus.
So traditional tile depth range
is often much larger than needed,
because you're going to have gaps
like we see in this third one.
You're going to have something in the front
and then something in the back,
and you want to get rid of whatever is in the middle.
So clusters are essentially walk cells
in our 3D space for geometry and lights.
So now, pairing...
This is the simplest way.
So, green is the explicit.
So if you get the color,
if you're trying not to do the super compressed version,
you can do the green version.
But the blue version is going to be
the most explicit founding body
that you have for the coverage in each cluster.
So let's say we have,
we take this example, we have three lights.
So light one doesn't affect anything, right?
Everything can get rid of it.
Light two doesn't affect anything,
even though it's closer,
it doesn't affect anything
so we can completely get rid of it.
And these two happen in both Forward Plus
and Forward Plus clusters.
We don't have to use these lights, one and two.
But three is where the magic happens.
For three, this time,
and this time we'll be computing with it
along with time four, right?
In clustered, however,
none of these times have to interact with light three,
only these two times interact with light three, right?
So now you see how many clusters
you're getting rid of
that don't have to interact with light three at all.
And that means you're removing a bunch of geometry
that doesn't have to interact with light three.
So you're going from what was 2D into 3D clusters,
and you're helping optimize the lights even further.
And uniform is not the only way to divide clusters.
You can divide it in different strategies
depending on how you're seeing them.
So for example, you can have this divided
in uniform normalized device coordinates
or normalized display coordinates.
You can have uniform like we were showing in this,
these are all uniform.
Or you can have exponential
where it just increases as you go along.
So you can vary depending on what your scene looks like.
If your scene has a lot more information up close,
you may want more clusters up close
and less clusters in the back.
If you have fog that is hiding everything in the back,
use uniform NDC and get rid of everything in the back.
So you can choose your strategy for dividing it.
Another way to look at it is like this,
where you have exponential spacing
and you have special near clusters
where if you have a lot of geometry here,
you may come to know, okay,
it's not even worth dividing it
because all the clusters will interact with all the maps.
So if you have, let's say a line like this,
all the clusters, even if you're in the white area,
are going to interact with that, right?
So it's kind of pointless to divide it into clusters.
So you may be like, okay,
let me just get rid of clusters in that area
and then start my clusters there.
But there are different strategies you can use.
There's no one right answer.
You can choose the strategy that works best for your use.
Any questions so far on clusters?
Remember, this is all project five.
If you do the WebGL project, this is all project five.
You're going to be implementing these pipelines
in project five.
Okay, all right.
So for the culling part,
now again, looking at it from top down,
if you have a light like this,
you want to cull out different parts of it, right?
So the traditional approach is checking of six frustums.
Remember, this is in 3D.
If you have a sphere,
you need to check minimum, maximum along each dimension.
So the planes have a lot of false intersections.
That is, if you have...
What we are essentially saying,
even though these four are the boundary planes
that encompass the light,
even within these, you can have false betweens
where the light doesn't retract that cluster.
Okay, so AABB, like you may have seen in your path traces,
when you import a mesh,
you don't access align bounding box around it.
You can still hit the bounding box,
but miss the mesh space.
The mesh doesn't cover the entire bounding box.
Same thing happening here.
This is the bounding box for the light
in terms of the clusters,
but you get clusters that are not affected by the light.
So that's kind of what you want to improve
is don't intersect by the planes of the frustums,
but they need to access align bounding box for the lights.
So now if you look at this in an image that we saw before,
now we start seeing this kind of thing
where the tiles that interact with the tree
first start here and go all the way to the back.
But anything that doesn't start with the tree,
for example, these lines here are much smaller.
And then you have some clusters here
that are only the ones.
So you save a lot of space here
where nothing has to interact with the lights.
So if I show this in a different way,
where we show the end of endpoint of the clusters,
this is what it looks like.
Some of them are hitting the ground,
some of them are hitting the boundary,
some of them are hitting the tree.
So this, so let me, let me go back.
This is forward plus, right?
Where you have the starting and the end, okay?
And this is cluster.
Why?
Because sponsor has a lot of space in the middle.
So what power plus is showing here is empty space, right?
It's just air.
We don't have to do that in cluster.
In cluster, you just get rid of all of it.
So you are only left with places
where there's actual geometry.
So instead of having 2D tiles that have a min and max,
you work into clusters,
which are much more compact in their size.
Any questions on this?
Everybody ready for project five?
Maybe you'll send that out now.
Hey, Alex?
Yeah, it has to do with global illumination.
It also has to do with modern games.
Like there's, there's a axiom, right?
Rendering artists and game developers
will always improve the quality of their scenes
to fill up the GPU.
And when can AMD come up with a new GPU?
All the games are going to maximize to take advantage of.
No matter, even if you have five generations of GPU
today, imagine if you could do that.
Today's game developers are ready to take advantage of all.
There's no end to how much quality game developers
and artists want to add into your scenes.
If you give them the capability to add a million lights,
they will add a million lights.
They'll add a light on every single car,
on every single street lamp, wherever it might be.
So being able to allow the complex geometry,
the complex lighting and materials
that modern games and real-time rendering want,
and not just games and rendering,
but also simulation, like how Eric showed the other day,
that we are using this in industrial applications and stuff.
You want to have the ability to render
any type of scene that you want.
Any other questions here?
Okay.
So here's a video of cluster trading.
And this is captioned, so I'll let that play around.
And you can see how fast it's working.
So you see the tiles here, and that's what's blocking.
So that was with 2,500 lights, 5.6 milliseconds
for the worst case test.
So it's pretty fast.
So what we haven't covered?
So I showed deferred and forward plus and cluster forward.
There are other parallel approaches
that you can do for light culling.
That's certainly something we didn't cover.
There's plenty of SIGGRAPH tables around this.
If you look at the latest and advanced
in real-time rendering talk at SIGGRAPH,
you're going to find plenty of things every single year
that essentially improve how we do rendering for games.
We also didn't cover shadows.
Shadows are a big, complex part.
Right now, we have only focused on how do you
render the scene with lights.
We haven't done too many passes, alpha blending,
those kind of things.
And we've also not taken a look at various different types
of lights.
Forward plus, we focused more on the point light approach.
So there's a lot more both in GPU Pro,
real-time rendering, and others to check out
about newer pipelines that you may want to explore.
A bunch of resources here, both former student projects
as well as other courses from SIGGRAPH
and other conferences.
I haven't updated this list in a while,
so please feel free to recommend any courses you find
at SIGGRAPH or elsewhere that I should be adding here.
Some resources on Clustered that you can also check out.
And finally, a comparison of all the different approaches
we've used.
We started with Clustered Different,
Clustered Different, Clustered Forward.
Clustered Different wasn't something
we touched on in the beginning, but it is a way to do it.
And then we had time to start formulating it.
Of course, different pipelines have different advantages
and disadvantages.
It is up to the game you're developing
to choose which pipeline you want.
If you're developing your 2D with one light,
you probably don't care about anything else.
You don't care about any of them.
You can just do a simple forward rendering pipeline
and forget about all of this, because your compute requirement
is not going to be that much.
But if you are in the GTAs of the world,
where you have thousands of lights,
you're probably going to care about one of these,
if not a more advanced pipeline that you may want to run.
So yeah, that's all for today's lecture.
Again, reminder that Project 4 is out.
We've released it.
If you want 21st and then both deferred and forward plus
will be one part of, or one optional part of Project 5.
So if you have any questions,
please review the slides and bring your questions.
That's all for today.
21st, on the calendar.
I don't remember.
Might be.
And then you'll have a break between when Project 5 is due
and when final projects start.
So that's the break you get.
Before we had six projects.
And the sixth project would essentially run
from end of Project 5 to start of final projects.
And I got rid of that.
It was too much for students.